<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Philippines</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>622</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>372</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2006-09-09</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2008-12-11</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2008-12-11</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2023-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">PHL</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">PHL</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/philippine/epa0609/main.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/philippine/epa0609/index.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="598">
      <article article_identifier="28212">Preamble 

Japan and the Republic of the Philippines (hereinafterreferred to in this Agreement as “the Philippines”), 

Cognizant of their warm relations and strong economicand political ties, including shared perceptions on variousissues, that have developed through many years of fruitfuland mutually beneficial cooperation; 

Recognizing that a dynamic and rapidly changing globalenvironment brought about by globalization andtechnological progress presents many new economic andstrategic challenges and opportunities to the Parties; 

Acknowledging that encouraging innovation andcompetition and improving their attractiveness to capitaland human resources can enhance their ability to respond tosuch new challenges and opportunities; 

Recognizing that the economic partnership of theParties would create larger and new markets, and wouldimprove their economic efficiency and consumer welfare,enhancing the attractiveness and vibrancy of their markets,and expanding trade and investment not only between thembut also in the region; 

Reaffirming that such partnership will provide auseful framework for enhanced regulatory cooperationbetween the Parties to meet new challenges posed byemerging market developments and to improve their marketinfrastructure; 

Recognizing the importance of the implementation ofmeasures by the Governments of the Parties in accordancewith their respective laws and regulations; 

Bearing in mind their rights and obligations underother international agreements to which they are parties,in particular those of the Marrakesh Agreement Establishingthe World Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15,1994; 

Recalling Article XXIV of the General Agreement onTariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General Agreement on Trade in Services, respectively in Annex 1Aand Annex 1B to the above-mentioned Agreement; 

Reaffirming the importance of the multilateral tradingsystem embodied by the World Trade Organization; 

 Recognizing the catalytic role which regional andbilateral trade agreements that are consistent with therules of the World Trade Organization can play inaccelerating global and regional trade and investmentliberalization and rule-making; 

Realizing that enhancing economic ties between theParties would strengthen Japan’s involvement in SoutheastAsia; 

Observing in particular that such ties would helpcatalyze trade and investment liberalization in Asia-Pacific; 

Bearing in mind the Framework for ComprehensiveEconomic Partnership between Japan and the Association ofSoutheast Asian Nations, signed in Bali, Indonesia onOctober 8, 2003; 

Convinced that stronger economic linkages between theParties would provide greater opportunities, largereconomies of scale and a more predictable environment foreconomic activities not only for Japanese and Philippinebusinesses but also for other businesses in Asia; and 

Determined to create a legal framework for an economicpartnership between the Parties; 

HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="599">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="28213">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 


(a) liberalize and facilitate trade in goods andservices between the Parties; 


(b) facilitate the mutual recognition of the resultsof conformity assessment procedures for productsor processes; 


(c) increase investment opportunities and strengthenprotection for investments and investmentactivities in the Parties; 


(d) enhance protection of intellectual property andstrengthen cooperation in the field thereof topromote trade and investment between the Parties; 


(e) promote transparency in government procurement inthe Parties; 


(f) promote competition by addressing anticompetitive activities and cooperate in the fieldof competition; 


(g) 	establish a framework for further bilateral cooperation and improvement of businessenvironment; 


(h) promote transparency in the implementation oflaws and regulations respecting matters coveredby this Agreement; and 


(i) create effective procedures for theimplementation and operation of this Agreementand for the resolution of disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="28214">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwisespecified: 

(a) 	the term “Area” means: 

with respect to Japan, the territory of Japan, and theexclusive economic zone and the continental shelf with respect to which Japan exercises sovereign rights orjurisdiction in accordance with its laws andregulations and international law; and 

with respect to the Philippines, the nationalterritory as defined in Article I of its Constitution.The term “national territory” also includes theexclusive economic zone and the continental shelf to which the Philippines exercises sovereign rights orjurisdiction in accordance with its laws andregulations and international law; 

Note: 	Nothing in this subparagraph shall affectthe rights and obligations of the Partiesunder international law, including thoseunder the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. 


(b) the term “existing” means in effect on the dateof entry into force of this Agreement; 


(c) the term “GATS” means the General Agreement onTrade in Services in Annex 1B to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization; 


(d) 	the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization. For the purposes of this Agreement, references to articles in GATT 1994include the interpretative notes; 


(e) the term “Harmonized System (HS)” means theHarmonized Commodity Description and CodingSystem set out in the Annex to the InternationalConvention on the Harmonized CommodityDescription and Coding System and adopted andimplemented by the Parties in their respectivedomestic laws; 


(f) the term “juridical person” means any legalentity duly constituted or otherwise organizedunder applicable law, whether for profit orotherwise, and whether privately-owned orgovernmentally-owned, including any corporation,trust, partnership, joint venture, soleproprietorship or association; 


(g) the term “measure” means any measure by a Party,whether in the form of a law, regulation, rule,procedure, decision, administrative action or anyother form; 


(h) the term “person” means either a natural personor a juridical person; and 


(i) the term “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Transparency" article_identifier="28215">1. Each Party shall promptly publish, or otherwise makepublicly available, its laws, regulations, administrativeprocedures and administrative rulings and judicialdecisions of general application as well as internationalagreements to which the Party is a party, respecting anymatter covered by this Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall make publicly available the names andaddresses of competent authorities responsible for laws,regulations, administrative procedures and administrativerulings, referred to in paragraph 1 above (hereinafterreferred to in this Chapter as “the competentauthorities”). 


3. Each Party shall, upon request by the other Party,within a reasonable period of time, respond to specificquestions from, and provide information to, the otherParty, to the extent possible in English, with respect tomatters referred to in paragraph 1 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Review Of Laws And Regulations" article_identifier="28216">Each Party shall examine the possibility of amendingor repealing laws and regulations that pertain to or affectthe implementation and operation of this Agreement, if thecircumstances or objectives giving rise to their adoptionno longer exist or if such circumstances or objectives canbe addressed in a less trade-restrictive manner.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Public Comment Procedures" article_identifier="28217">The Government of each Party shall, in accordance withthe laws and regulations of the Party, endeavor to provide,except in cases of emergency or of purely minor nature, areasonable opportunity for comments by the public beforethe adoption, amendment or repeal of regulations of generalapplication that affect any matter covered by thisAgreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="28218">1. Where measures are to be adopted which pertain to oraffect the implementation and operation of this Agreement,the competent authorities of a Party shall, in accordancewith the laws and regulations of the Party: 


(a) inform the applicant within a reasonable periodof time of the decision concerning an applicationconsidered complete under the laws andregulations of the Party, taking into account theestablished standard period of time referred toin paragraph 3 below; and 


(b) provide, without undue delay, informationconcerning the status of the application, at therequest of the applicant. 
2. The competent authorities shall, in accordance withthe laws and regulations of the Party, establish standardsfor taking measures in response to submitted applications.The competent authorities shall: 


(a) make such standards as specific as possible; and 


(b) make such standards publicly available exceptwhen it would extraordinarily raiseadministrative difficulties for the Party. 
3. The competent authorities shall, in accordance withthe laws and regulations of the Party: 


(a) endeavor to establish standard periods of timebetween receipt of applications by the competentauthorities and measures taken in response tosubmitted applications; and 


(b) make such periods of time publicly available, ifit is established. 
4. Where measures are to be adopted by the competentauthorities which pertain to or affect the implementationand operation of this Agreement and which imposeobligations on or restrict rights of a person, suchcompetent authorities shall, prior to any final decision,when time, the nature of the measures and public interestpermit and in accordance with the laws and regulations ofthe Party, provide that person with: 


(a) a reasonable notice, including a description ofthe nature of the measure, specific provisionsupon which such measure will be based, and thefacts which may be a cause of taking suchmeasure; and 


(b) a reasonable opportunity to present facts andarguments in support of the position of suchperson.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="28219">1. Each Party shall ensure that judicial remedies areavailable under its laws and regulations for the impartialand independent review and, where warranted, correction ofactions taken by relevant authorities regarding matterscovered by this Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that the parties to any suchjudicial remedies are provided with the right to: 


(a) a reasonable opportunity to support or defendtheir respective positions; and 


(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions of record. 

3. Each Party shall ensure, subject to appeal or furtherreview as provided in its laws and regulations, thatdecisions referred to in paragraph 2(b) above with respectto the actions referred to in paragraph 1 above areimplemented by the competent authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Measures Against Corruption" article_identifier="28220">Each Party shall ensure that measures and efforts areundertaken to prevent and combat corruption regardingmatters covered by this Agreement in accordance with itslaws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="28221">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement,nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to require aParty to provide confidential information, the disclosureof which would impede law enforcement, or otherwise becontrary to the public interest, or which would prejudicelegitimate commercial interests of particular juridicalpersons, public or private. 


2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, maintain the confidentiality of informationprovided as confidential by the other Party pursuant tothis Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Taxation" article_identifier="28222">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,nothing in this Agreement shall apply to taxation measures. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights andobligations of either Party under any tax convention. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement andany such convention, that convention shall prevail to theextent of the inconsistency. 
Note: The term “tax convention” means a convention for the avoidance of double taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="28223">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligationsunder the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to whichboth Parties are parties. 


2. In the event of any inconsistency between thisAgreement and the WTO Agreement, the WTO Agreement shallprevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 


3. In the event of any inconsistency between thisAgreement and the Treaty of Amity, Commerce and Navigationbetween Japan and the Republic of the Philippines, thisAgreement shall prevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 


4. In the event of any inconsistency between thisAgreement and any agreements other than the WTO Agreementand the Treaty of Amity, Commerce and Navigation betweenJapan and the Republic of the Philippines, to which bothParties are parties, the Parties shall immediately consultwith each other with a view to finding a mutuallysatisfactory solution, taking into consideration generalprinciples of international law. 


5. In the event of an amendment of the agreements towhich both Parties are parties and which are referred to inthis Agreement, relevant principles of international law,including those in the Vienna Convention on the Law ofTreaties, shall apply. In the event of the amendment of the agreements referred to in this paragraph, the Partiesmay consult with each other as necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="28224">The Governments of the Parties shall conclude a separate agreement setting forth the details and proceduresfor the implementation of this Agreement (hereinafterreferred to in this Agreement as “the ImplementingAgreement”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="28225">1. The Joint Committee composed of representatives of theGovernments of the Parties shall be established under this Agreement. 


2. 	The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Agreement and, when necessary, makingappropriate recommendations to the Parties; 


(b) considering and recommending to the Parties anyamendments to this Agreement; 


(c) supervising and coordinating the work of all Sub-Committees established under this Agreement; 


(d) adopting; 

(i) the Operational Procedures on Trade in Goodsand Rules of Origin referred to in Article 25 and the Operational Procedures on MutualRecognition referred to in Article 65; 

(ii) 	the Rules of Procedure referred to in Article 159; and 

(iii) any necessary decisions; and 

(e) performing other functions as the Parties mayagree. 

3. 	The Joint Committee may: 


(a) establish Sub-Committees and delegate itsresponsibilities thereto; and 


(b) 	take such other action in the exercise of its functions as the Parties may agree. 

4. The following Sub-Committees shall be established onthe date of entry into force of this Agreement: 


(a) Sub-Committee on Trade in Goods 


(b) Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin 


(c) Sub-Committee on Customs Procedures 


(d) Sub-Committee on Mutual Recognition 


(e) Sub-Committee on Trade in Services 


(f) Sub-Committee on Investment 


(g) Sub-Committee on Movement of Natural Persons 


(h) Sub-Committee on Intellectual Property 


(i) Sub-Committee on Government Procurement 


(j) Sub-Committee on Improvement of the BusinessEnvironment 


(k) Sub-Committee on Cooperation 
Other Sub-Committees may be established as the Partiesmay agree. 


5. The details of the Sub-Committees may be specified inthe Implementing Agreement. 


6. The Joint Committee shall convene once a yearalternately in Japan and the Philippines, unless theParties agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Communications" article_identifier="28226">Each Party shall designate a contact point tofacilitate communications between the Parties on any matterrelating to this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="600">
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28227">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “customs value of goods” means the valueof goods for the purposes of levying ad valoremcustoms duties on imported goods; 


(b) the term “domestic industry” means the producersas a whole of the like or directly competitivegoods operating in a Party, or those whosecollective output of the like or directlycompetitive goods constitutes a major proportionof the total domestic production of those goods; 


(c) the term “emergency measure” means an emergencymeasure provided for in paragraph 1 of Article 22; 


(d) the term “originating goods” means goods whichqualify as originating goods under the provisionsof Chapter 3; 


(e) the term “other duties or charges” means thoseprovided for in subparagraph 1(b) of Article IIof the GATT 1994; 


(f) the term “provisional emergency measure” means aprovisional emergency measure provided for insubparagraph 4(a) of Article 22; 


(g) the term “serious injury” means a significantoverall impairment in the position of a domesticindustry; and 


(h) the term “threat of serious injury” means seriousinjury that, on the basis of facts and not merelyon allegation, conjecture or remote possibility,is clearly imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="28228">The classification of goods in trade between theParties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="28229">Each Party shall accord national treatment to thegoods of the other Party in accordance with Article III ofthe GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="28230">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,each Party shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties onoriginating goods of the other Party designated for suchpurposes in its Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with theterms and conditions set out in such Schedule. 


2. On the request of either Party, the Parties shallnegotiate on issues such as improving market accessconditions on originating goods designated for negotiationin the Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the termsand conditions set out in such Schedule. 


3. Each Party shall eliminate other duties or charges ofany kind imposed on or in connection with the importationof originating goods of the other Party, customs duties ofwhich shall be eliminated or reduced in accordance with paragraph 1 above, if any. Neither Party shall introduce other duties or charges of any kind imposed on or inconnection with the importation of those originating goodsof the other Party. 


4. Nothing in this Article shall prevent a Party fromimposing, at any time, on the importation of any goods ofthe other Party: 


(a) a charge equivalent to an internal tax imposedconsistently with the provisions of paragraph 2of Article III of the GATT 1994, in respect ofthe like domestic product or in respect of anarticle from which the imported product has beenmanufactured or produced in whole or in part; 


(b) any anti-dumping or countervailing duty appliedconsistently with the provisions of Article VI ofthe GATT 1994, the Agreement on Implementation ofArticle VI of the General Agreement on Tariffsand Trade 1994 and the Agreement on Subsidies andCountervailing Measures in Annex 1A to the WTOAgreement respectively; and 


(c) fees or other charges commensurate with the costof services rendered.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="28231">For the purposes of determining the customs value ofgoods traded between the Parties, provisions of Part I ofthe Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A tothe WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to in thisAgreement as “the Agreement on Customs Valuation”) shallapply mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Export Duties" article_identifier="28232">Each Party shall exert its best efforts to eliminateits duties on goods exported from the Party to the otherParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Non-Tariff Measures" article_identifier="28233">Each Party shall not introduce or maintain any non-tariff measures on the importation of any good of the otherParty or on the exportation or sale for export of any gooddestined for the other Party which are inconsistent withits obligations under the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Emergency Measures" article_identifier="28234">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, each Partymay, as an emergency measure, to the minimum extentnecessary to prevent or remedy the serious injury to adomestic industry of that Party and to facilitateadjustment: 


(a) suspend the further reduction of any rate ofcustoms duty on the originating good provided forin this Chapter; or 


(b) increase the rate of customs duty on theoriginating good to a level not to exceed thelesser of: 
(i) the most-favored-nation applied rate ofcustoms duty in effect on the day when theemergency measure is taken; and 

(ii) the most-favored-nation applied rate ofcustoms duty in effect on the dayimmediately preceding the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement; 

if an originating good of the other Party, as a result ofthe elimination or reduction of a customs duty inaccordance with Article 18, is being imported into theformer Party in such increased quantities, in absoluteterms or relative to domestic production, and under suchconditions that the imports of that originating goodconstitute a substantial cause of serious injury, or threatthereof, to a domestic industry of the former Party. 


2. Each Party shall not apply emergency measures on anoriginating good imported up to the limit of quotaquantities granted under tariff rate quotas applied inaccordance with Schedule in Annex 1. 


3. 	(a) A Party may take an emergency measure only after an investigation has been carried out by thecompetent authorities of that Party in accordancewith the procedures provided for in each Party’srelevant domestic laws and regulations that areconsistent with Article 3 and paragraph 2 ofArticle 4 of the Agreement on Safeguards in Annex1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred toin this Chapter as “the Agreement onSafeguards”). 

(b) The investigation referred to in subparagraph (a)above shall in all cases be completed within one

(1) year following its date of initiation. 

4. 	(a) In critical circumstances, where delay would cause damage which it would be difficult torepair, a Party may take a provisional emergencymeasure, which shall take the form of the measureset out in subparagraph 1(a) or (b) above,pursuant to a preliminary determination thatthere is clear evidence that increased imports ofan originating good have caused or arethreatening to cause serious injury to a domesticindustry. 


(b) The Party shall deliver a written notice to theother Party prior to applying a provisionalemergency measure. Consultations between the Parties on the application of the provisionalemergency measure shall be initiated immediatelyafter the provisional emergency measure is taken. 


(c) The duration of the provisional emergency measureshall not exceed two hundred (200) days. During that period, the pertinent requirements ofparagraph 3 above shall be met. The duration of the provisional emergency measure shall becounted as a part of the period referred to insubparagraph 5(e) below. 


(d) Paragraph 2 and subparagraph 5(g) of this Articleshall be applied mutatis mutandis to the provisional emergency measure. The customs duty imposed as a result of the provisional emergencymeasure shall be refunded if the subsequentinvestigation referred to in subparagraph 3(a)above does not determine that increased importsof the originating good have caused or threatenedto cause serious injury to a domestic industry. 

5. The following conditions and limitations shall applywith regard to an emergency measure: 


(a) A Party shall immediately deliver a writtennotice to the other Party upon: 

(i) initiating an investigation referred to insubparagraph 3(a) above relating to seriousinjury, or threat thereof, and the reasonsfor it; and 

(ii) taking a decision to apply or extend anemergency measure. 

(b) The Party making the written notice referred toin subparagraph (a) above shall provide the otherParty with all pertinent information, which shallinclude: 

(i) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraph (a)(i) above, the reason forthe initiation of the investigation, aprecise description of the originating goodsubject to the investigation and itssubheading of the Harmonized System, theperiod subject to the investigation and thedate of initiation of the investigation; and 

(ii) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraph (a)(ii) above, evidence ofserious injury or threat thereof caused bythe increased imports of an originatinggood, a precise description of theoriginating good subject to the proposedemergency measure and its subheading of theHarmonized System, a precise description ofthe emergency measure, the proposed date ofits introduction and its expected duration. 

(c) When the Party provides the other Party withpertinent information that includes confidentialinformation, the other Party may only disclosenon-confidential part, summary or version thereofto the public. 


(d) A Party proposing to apply or extend an emergencymeasure shall provide adequate opportunity forprior consultations with the other Party with aview to reviewing the information arising fromthe investigation referred to in subparagraph3(a) above, exchanging views on the emergencymeasure and reaching an agreement on compensationset out in paragraph 6 below. 


(e) No emergency measure shall be maintained exceptto the extent and for such period as may benecessary to prevent or remedy serious injury andto facilitate adjustment, provided that suchperiod shall not exceed three (3) years.However, in very exceptional circumstances, anemergency measure may be maintained for up to atotal maximum period of four (4) years. In order to facilitate adjustment in a situation where theexpected duration of an emergency measure is overone (1) year, the Party maintaining the emergencymeasure shall progressively liberalize theemergency measure at regular intervals during theperiod of application. 


(f) No emergency measure shall be applied again tothe import of a particular originating good whichhas been subject to such an emergency measure,for a period of time equal to the duration of theprevious emergency measure or one (1) year,whichever is longer. 


(g) Upon the termination of an emergency measure, therate of customs duty shall be the rate whichwould have been in effect but for the emergencymeasure. 

6. 	(a) A Party proposing to apply or extend an emergency measure shall provide to the other Party mutuallyagreed adequate means of trade compensation inthe form of concessions of customs duties whose levels are substantially equivalent to the valueof the additional customs duties expected toresult from the emergency measure. 


(b) If the Parties are unable to agree on thecompensation within thirty (30) days after thecommencement of the consultations pursuant tosubparagraph 5(d) above, the Party against whoseoriginating good the emergency measure is takenshall be free to suspend the application ofconcessions of customs duties under this Agreement, which are substantially equivalent tothe emergency measure. The Party exercising the right of suspension may suspend the applicationof concessions of customs duties only for theminimum period necessary to achieve thesubstantially equivalent effects and only whilethe emergency measure is maintained. 


(c) The right of suspension provided for insubparagraph (b) above shall not be exercised forthe first twelve (12) months that an emergencymeasure is in effect, provided that the emergencymeasure has been taken as a result of an absolute increase in imports and that such an emergencymeasure conforms to the provisions of thisArticle. 

7. Written notice referred to in subparagraphs 4(b) and5(a) above and any other communication, including in theform of documents, between the Parties shall be made inEnglish. 


8. Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial andreasonable administration of its laws and regulationsrelating to the emergency measure and the provisionalemergency measure. 


9. Each Party shall ensure equitable, timely, transparentand effective procedures relating to the emergency measureand the provisional emergency measure. 


10. Notwithstanding subparagraph 1(b) and 4(a) above, if adecision to apply an emergency measure or a preliminarydetermination to apply a provisional emergency measure istaken by the last day of the seventh year, each Party mayincrease the rate of customs duty on the originating goodup to the level of the rate of customs duty which isapplied on a non-discriminatory basis to the members of theWorld Trade Organization in effect on the day when theemergency measure or the provisional emergency measure istaken, provided that such an emergency measure or such a provisional emergency measure shall satisfy the conditionset out in subparagraph 1(b) above at the latest as fromthe first day of the eighth year. 

Note: 	For the purpose of this paragraph, the term “year”means, with respect to the first year, the periodfrom the date of entry into force of this Agreementuntil the coming March 31 and, with respect to eachsubsequent year, the period of twelve (12) monthswhich starts on April 1 of that year. 

11. Each Party may take safeguard measures to theoriginating goods in accordance with: 


(a) Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement onSafeguards, provided that the originating good isthe subject of the concession of that Party underthe GATT 1994 and, by such a safeguard measure,that Party suspends the obligation of that Partyunder the GATT 1994 or withdraws or modifies the concession of that Party under the GATT 1994; or 


(b) Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafterreferred to in this Chapter as “the Agreement onAgriculture”), provided that the originating goodis the subject of the concession of that Partyunder the GATT 1994 and, by such a safeguardmeasure, that Party imposes the additional dutyunder Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture. 

12. The Parties shall review the provisions of thisArticle, if necessary, after ten (10) years of the date ofentry into force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="28235">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article XX and XXIof the GATT 1994 respectively, shall apply mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="28236">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to preventa Party from taking any measure for balance-of-paymentspurposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in accordance with the conditions established under Article XII and Section B of Article XVIII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Balance-of-Payments Provisions of theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A tothe WTO Agreement. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude the use by aParty of exchange controls or exchange restrictions inaccordance with the Articles of Agreement of theInternational Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Operational Procedures On Trade In Goods And Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="28237">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement,the Joint Committee shall adopt the Operational Procedureson Trade in Goods and Rules of Origin that provide detailedregulations pursuant to which the customs authorities, thecompetent governmental authorities defined in Article 28and the relevant authorities of the Parties shall implementtheir functions under this Chapter and Chapter 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Goods" article_identifier="28238">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Trade inGoods (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(b) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(c) performing other functions which may be delegatedby the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. 	(a) The Sub-Committee shall establish a Special Sub-Committee on Iron and Steel Products and a Special Sub-Committee on Automobile and theirParts. The Sub-Committee may establish any otherSpecial Sub-Committees, if necessary. 

(b) The functions of the Special Sub-Committee shallbe: 

(i) analyzing relevant matters on the relevantgoods and its sector, including trade insuch goods; 

(ii) reporting the findings of the Special Sub-Committees, through the Sub-Committee, tothe Joint Committee; 

(iii) with regard to the Special Sub-Committee onIron and Steel Products, reviewing theissues related to implementation of tariffelimination commitment on Iron and Steel Products; and 

(iv) with regard to the Special Sub-Committee onAutomobile and their Parts, reviewing theissues related to implementation of tariffelimination commitment on Automobile and their Parts. 

4. The Sub-Committee and the Special Sub-Committee shallbe composed of representatives of the Governments of theParties. The Sub-Committee and the Special Sub-Committeemay invite representatives of relevant entities other thanthe Governments of the Parties, including those fromprivate sectors, with the necessary expertise relevant tothe issues to be discussed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Cooperation In Relation To Export" article_identifier="28239">The Parties shall cooperate with each other on theutilization of appropriate mechanism on the conformancewith the importing Party’s safety and environmentalstandards, such as roadworthiness and vehicle emissionstandards, of used four-wheeled motor vehicles as may beagreed by the Parties, exported from the exporting Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="601">
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28240">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “competent governmental authority” meansthe authority that, according to the legislationof each Party, is responsible for the issuing ofthe certificate of origin or for the designationof the certification entities or bodies. In the case of Japan, the Ministry of Economy, Trade andIndustry, and in the case of the Philippines, theBureau of Customs; 


(b) the term “customs authority” means the authoritythat, according to the legislation of each Partyor non-Parties, is responsible for theadministration and enforcement of its customs laws and regulations. In the case of Japan, the Ministry of Finance, and in the case of thePhilippines, the Bureau of Customs; 


(c) the term “exporter” means a person located in anexporting Party who exports a good from theexporting Party; 


(d) the term “factory ships of the Party” and“vessels of the Party” respectively means factoryships and vessels: 

(i) which are registered in the Party; 

(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; 

(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least sixty (60) percent by nationals of theParty, or by a juridical person with itshead office in the Party, of which therepresentatives, chairman of the board ofdirectors, and the majority of the membersof such boards are nationals of the Party,and of which at least sixty (60) percent ofthe equity interest is owned by nationals orjuridical persons of the Party; 

(iv) 	of which the master and officers are all nationals of the Party; and 

(v) of which at least seventy five (75) percentof the crew are nationals of the Party; 

(e) the term “fungible originating goods of a Party”or “fungible originating materials of a Party”respectively means originating goods or materialsof a Party that are interchangeable forcommercial purposes, whose properties areessentially identical; 


(f) the term “Generally Accepted AccountingPrinciples” means the recognized consensus orsubstantial authoritative support within a Partyat a particular time as to which economicresources and obligations should be recorded asassets and liabilities, which changes in assetsand liabilities should be recorded, how theassets and liabilities and changes in them shouldbe measured, what information should be disclosedand how it should be disclosed, and whichfinancial statements should be prepared. These standards may be broad guidelines of generalapplication as well as detailed practices andprocedures; 


(g) the term “importer” means a person who imports agood into the importing Party; 


(h) the term “indirect material” means a good used inthe production, testing or inspection of anothergood but not physically incorporated into thegood, or a good used in the maintenance ofbuildings or the operation of equipmentassociated with the production of another good,including: 

(i) fuel and energy; 

(ii) tools, dies and molds; 

(iii) spare parts and goods used in themaintenance of equipment and buildings; 


(iv) lubricants, greases, compounding materialsand other goods used in production or usedto operate equipment and buildings; 

(v) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safetyequipment and supplies; 

(vi) equipment, devices and supplies used fortesting or inspecting the good; 
(vii) catalysts and solvents; and 

(viii) any other goods that are not incorporatedinto the good but whose use in theproduction of the good can reasonably bedemonstrated to be a part of thatproduction; 

(i) the term “material” means a good that is used inthe production of another good; 


(j) the term “originating material of a Party” meansan originating good of a Party which is used inthe production of another good in the Party,including that which is considered as anoriginating material of the Party pursuant toparagraph 1 of Article 30; 


(k) the term “packing materials and containers forshipment” means goods that are used to protect agood during transportation, other than packagingmaterials and containers for retail sale referred to in Article 38; 


(l) the term “preferential tariff treatment” meansthe rate of customs duties applicable to anoriginating good of the exporting Party inaccordance with paragraph 1 of Article 18; and 


(m) the term “production” means methods of obtaininggoods including manufacturing, assembling,processing, raising, growing, breeding, mining,extracting, harvesting, fishing, trapping,gathering, collecting, hunting and capturing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="28241">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, agood shall qualify as an originating good of a Party where: 


(a) the good is wholly obtained or produced entirelyin the Party, as defined in paragraph 2 below; 


(b) the good is produced entirely in the Partyexclusively from originating materials of theParty; or 


(c) the good satisfies the product specific rules setout in Annex 2, as well as all other applicablerequirements of this Chapter, when the good isproduced entirely in the Party using non-originating materials. 
2. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a) above, thefollowing goods shall be considered as being whollyobtained or produced entirely in a Party: 


(a) live animals born and raised in the Party; 


(b) animals obtained by hunting, trapping, fishing,gathering or capturing in the Party; 


(c) goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 


(d) plants and plant products harvested, picked orgathered in the Party; 


(e) minerals and other naturally occurringsubstances, not included in subparagraphs (a)through (d) above, extracted or taken in theParty; 


(f) goods of sea-fishing and other goods taken byvessels of the Party from the sea outside theterritorial sea of a Party; 


(g) goods produced on board factory ships of theParty from the goods referred to in subparagraph

(f) above; 

(h) goods taken from the seabed or subsoil beneaththe seabed outside the territorial sea of the Party, provided that the Party has rights oversuch seabed or subsoil in accordance with its laws and regulations and international law; 

Note: 	Nothing in this subparagraph shall affectthe rights and obligations of the Partiesunder international law, including thoseunder the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. 

(i) articles collected in the Party which can nolonger perform their original purpose in theParty nor are capable of being restored orrepaired and which are fit only for disposal orfor the recovery of parts or raw materials; 


(j) scrap and waste derived from manufacturing orprocessing operations or from consumption in theParty and fit only for disposal or for therecovery of raw materials; 


(k) parts or raw materials recovered in the Partyfrom articles which can no longer perform theiroriginal purpose nor are capable of beingrestored or repaired; and 


(l) goods obtained or produced in the Partyexclusively from the goods referred to insubparagraphs (a) through (k) above. 

3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c) above, theproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2 requiring thatthe materials used undergo a change in tariffclassification or a specific manufacturing or processingoperation shall apply only to non-originating materials. 


4. 	(a) For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c) above, the product specific rules set out in Annex 2 usingthe value-added method require that thequalifying value content of a good, calculated inaccordance with subparagraph (b) below, is notless than the percentage specified by the rulefor the good. 
(b) For the purposes of calculating the qualifyingvalue content of a good, the following formulashall be applied: 

F.O.B. - V.N.M. 

Q.V.C. = --------------- × 100 

F.O.B. 

Where: 

Q.V.C. is the qualifying value content of a good,expressed as a percentage; 

F.O.B. is, except as provided for in paragraph 5below, the free-on-board value of a good payable bythe buyer of the good to the seller of the good,regardless of the mode of shipment, not including anyinternal excise taxes reduced, exempted, or repaidwhen the good is exported; and 

V.N.M. is the value of non-originating materials usedin the production of a good. 

5. F.O.B. referred to in subparagraph 4(b) above shall bethe value: 


(a) adjusted to the first ascertainable price paidfor the good from the buyer to the producer ofthe good, if there is free-on-board value of agood, but it is unknown and cannot beascertained; or 


(b) determined in accordance with Articles 1 through8 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if thereis no free-on-board value of the good. 
6. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying valuecontent of a good under subparagraph 4(b) above, the valueof a non-originating material used in the production of thegood in a Party: 


(a) 	shall be determined in accordance with the Agreement on Customs Valuation, and shall includefreight, insurance where appropriate, packing andall the other costs incurred in transporting thematerial to the importation port in the Partywhere the producer of the good is located; or 


(b) 	if such value is unknown and cannot be ascertained, shall be the first ascertainableprice paid for the material in the Party, but mayexclude all the costs incurred in the Party intransporting the material from the warehouse ofthe supplier of the material to the place wherethe producer is located such as freight,insurance and packing as well as any other knownand ascertainable cost incurred in the Party. 

7. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying valuecontent of a good under subparagraph 4(b) above indetermining whether the good qualifies as an originatinggood of a Party, V.N.M. of the good shall not include thevalue of non-originating materials used in the productionof originating materials of the Party which are used in theproduction of the good. 


8. For the purposes of subparagraph 5(b) or 6(a) above,in applying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to determinethe value of a good or non-originating material, theAgreement on Customs Valuation shall apply mutatis mutandis to domestic transactions or to the cases where there is no transaction of the good or non-originating material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="28242">1. For the purposes of determining whether a goodqualifies as an originating good of a Party, an originatinggood of the other Party which is used as a material in theproduction of the good in the former Party may beconsidered as an originating material of the former Party. 


2. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying valuecontent of a good under subparagraph 4(b) of Article 29 indetermining whether the good qualifies as an originatinggood of a Party, the value of a non-originating materialproduced in either Party and to be used in the productionof the good may be limited to the value of non-originatingmaterials used in the production of such non-originatingmaterial, provided that the good qualifies as anoriginating good of that Party under subparagraph 1(c) ofArticle 29.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="28243">For the application of the product specific rules setout in Annex 2, non-originating materials used in theproduction of a good that do not satisfy an applicable rulefor the good shall be disregarded, provided that thetotality of such materials does not exceed specificpercentages in value, weight or volume of the good and suchpercentages are set out in the product specific rule forthe good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="28244">A good shall not be considered to satisfy therequirement of change in tariff classification or specificmanufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2merely by reason of: 


(a) operations to ensure the preservation of productsin good condition during transport and storage(such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine) andother similar operations; 


(b) changes of packaging and breaking up and assemblyof packages; 


(c) disassembly; 


(d) placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simplepackaging operations; 


(e) collection of parts and components classified asa good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rulesfor the Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 


(f) mere making-up of sets of articles; or 


(g) any combination of operations referred to insubparagraphs (a) through (f) above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Consignment Criteria" article_identifier="28245">1. An originating good of the other Party shall be deemedto meet the consignment criteria when it is: 


(a) transported directly from the other Party; or 


(b) transported through one or more non-Parties forthe purpose of transit or temporary storage inwarehouses in such non-Parties, provided that itdoes not undergo operations other than unloading,reloading or any other operation necessary topreserve it in good condition. 
2. If the originating good of the other Party does notmeet the consignment criteria referred to in paragraph 1above, that good shall not be considered as the originatinggood of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Unassembled Or Disassembled Goods" article_identifier="28246">1. Where a good satisfies the requirements of therelevant provisions of Articles 29 through 32 and isimported into a Party from the other Party in adisassembled form but is classified as an assembled goodpursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules for theInterpretation of the Harmonized System, such a good shallbe considered as an originating good of the other Party. 


2. A good assembled in a Party from unassembled ordisassembled materials, which were imported into the Partyand classified as an assembled good pursuant to Rule 2(a)of the General Rules for the Interpretation of theHarmonized System, shall be considered as the originatinggood of the Party, provided that the good would havesatisfied the applicable requirements of the relevantprovisions of Articles 29 through 32 had each of the non-originating materials among the unassembled or disassembledmaterials been imported into the Party separately and notas an unassembled or disassembled form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="28247">1. For the purposes of determining whether a goodqualifies as an originating good of a Party, where fungibleoriginating materials of the Party and fungible non-originating materials that are commingled in an inventoryare used in the production of the good, the origin of thematerials may be determined pursuant to an inventorymanagement method set out in the Operational Procedures onTrade in Goods and Rules of Origin referred to in Article

25. 


2. Where fungible originating goods of a Party andfungible non-originating goods are commingled in aninventory and, prior to exportation do not undergo anyproduction process or any operation in the Party where theywere commingled other than unloading, reloading or anyother operation necessary to preserve them in goodcondition, the origin of the good may be determinedpursuant to an inventory management method set out in theOperational Procedures on Trade in Goods and Rules ofOrigin referred to in Article 25. 


3. Once an inventory management method set out inparagraphs 1 and 2 above has been chosen, it shall be usedthrough all the fiscal year or period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="28248">Indirect materials shall be, without regard to wherethey are produced, considered to be originating materialsof a Party where a good is produced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Accessories, Spare Parts And Tools" article_identifier="28249">1. In determining whether all the non-originatingmaterials used in the production of a good undergo theapplicable change in tariff classification or a specificmanufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2,accessories, spare parts or tools delivered with the goodthat form part of the good’s standard accessories, spareparts or tools, shall be disregarded, provided that: 


(a) the accessories, spare parts or tools are notinvoiced separately from the good, without regardof whether they are separately described in theinvoice; and 


(b) the quantities and value of the accessories,spare parts or tools are customary for the good. 
2. If the good is subject to a qualifying value contentrequirement, the value of the accessories, spare parts ortools shall be taken into account as the value of originating materials of a Party where the good is producedor non-originating materials, as the case may be, incalculating the qualifying value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Packaging Materials And Containers For Retail Sale" article_identifier="28250">1. In determining whether all the non-originatingmaterials used in the production of a good undergo theapplicable change in tariff classification or a specificmanufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2,packaging materials and containers for retail sale, whichare classified with the good pursuant to Rule 5 of theGeneral Rules for the Interpretation of the HarmonizedSystem, shall be disregarded. 


2. If the good is subject to a qualifying value contentrequirement, the value of such packaging materials andcontainers for retail sale shall be taken into account as the value of originating materials of a Party where thegood is produced or non-originating materials, as the casemay be, in calculating the qualifying value content of thegood.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Packing Materials And Containers For Shipment" article_identifier="28251">Packing materials and containers for shipment shallbe: 


(a) disregarded in determining whether all the non-originating materials used in the production of agood undergo the applicable change in tariffclassification or a specific manufacturing orprocessing operation set out in Annex 2; and 


(b) without regard to where they are produced,considered to be originating materials of a Partywhere the good is produced, in calculating thequalifying value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Claim For Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="28252">1. The importing Party shall require a certificate oforigin for an originating good of the exporting Party fromimporters who claim the preferential tariff treatment forthe good. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 above, the importing Partyshall not require a certificate of origin from importersfor: 


(a) an importation of a consignment of originatinggoods of the exporting Party whose aggregatecustoms value does not exceed two hundred (200)United States dollars or its equivalent amount inthe Party’s currency, or such higher amount as itmay establish; or 


(b) an importation of an originating good of theexporting Party, for which the importing Partyhas waived the requirement for a certificate oforigin. 

3. Where an originating good of the exporting Party isimported through one or more non-Parties, the importingParty may require importers, who claim the preferentialtariff treatment for the good, to submit: 


(a) a copy of through bill of lading; or 


(b) a certificate or any other information given bythe customs authorities of such non-Parties or other relevant entities, which evidences that ithas not undergone operations other thanunloading, reloading or any other operationnecessary to preserve it in good condition inthose non-Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="28253">1. The certificate of origin referred to in paragraph 1of Article 40 shall be issued by the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party on request having beenmade in writing by the exporter or its authorized agent.Such certificate of origin shall include minimum dataspecified in Annex 3. 


2. For the purposes of this Article, the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party may designateother entities or bodies to be responsible for the issuanceof the certificate of origin, under the authorization givenin accordance with the applicable laws and regulations ofthe exporting Party. 


3. Where the competent governmental authority of theexporting Party designates other entities or bodies tocarry out the issuance of the certificate of origin, theexporting Party shall notify in writing the other Party ofits designees. 


4. For the purposes of this Chapter, upon the entry intoforce of this Agreement, the Parties shall establish aformat of the certificate of origin in English in theOperational Procedures on Trade in Goods and Rules ofOrigin referred to in Article 25. 


5. The certificate of origin shall be completed inEnglish. 


6. The issued certificate of origin shall be applicableto a single importation of an originating good of theexporting Party into the importing Party and be valid for 6months from the date of issuance or such longer period inaccordance with that Party’s laws and regulations. 


7. Where the exporter is not the producer of a good, theexporter may request a certificate of origin on the basisof: 


(a) a declaration provided by the exporter to thecompetent governmental authority or its designeesbased on the information provided by the producerof the good to that exporter; or 


(b) a declaration voluntarily provided by theproducer of the good directly to the competentgovernmental authority or its designees by therequest of the exporter. 

8. The certificate of origin shall be issued only afterthe exporter who requests a certificate of origin, or theproducer of a good in the exporting Party referred to insubparagraph 7(b) above, proves to the competentgovernmental authority or its designees that the good to beexported qualifies as an originating good of the exportingParty. 


9. The competent governmental authority of the exportingParty shall provide the other Party with specimensignatures and impressions of stamps used in the offices ofthe competent governmental authority or its designees. 


10. Each Party shall ensure that the competentgovernmental authority or its designees shall keep a recordof the certificates of origin issued for a period of five
(5) years after the date on which the certificate wasissued. Such record will include all antecedents, whichwere presented to prove the qualification as an originatinggood of the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Obligations Regarding Exportations" article_identifier="28254">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, ensure that the exporter to whom a certificateof origin has been issued, or the producer of a good in theexporting Party referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article41, shall notify in writing the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party or its designees withoutdelay when he knows that such good does not qualify as anoriginating good of the exporting Party. 


2. Each Party shall encourage that the exporter to whom acertificate of origin has been issued, or the producer of agood in the exporting Party referred to in subparagraph7(b) of Article 41, keep the records relating to the originof a good for five (5) years after the date on which thecertificate of origin was issued.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Request For Checking Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="28255">1. For the purposes of determining whether a goodimported from the other Party under preferential tarifftreatment qualifies as an originating good of the otherParty, the customs authority of the importing Party mayrequest information relating to the origin of the good fromthe competent governmental authority of the exporting Partyon the basis of a certificate of origin. 


2. For the purposes of paragraph 1 above, the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party shall, inaccordance with its laws and regulations, provide theinformation requested in a period not exceeding three (3)months after the date of the receipt of the request. 

If the customs authority of the importing Partyconsiders necessary, it may require additional informationrelating to the origin of the good. If additional information is requested by the customs authority of theimporting Party, the competent governmental authority ofthe exporting Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, provide the information requested in a periodnot exceeding two (2) months after the date of the receiptof the request. 

3. For the purposes of paragraph 2 above, the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party may requestthe exporter to whom a certificate of origin has beenissued, or the producer of the good in the exporting Partyreferred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 41, to providethe former with the information requested.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Verification Visit" article_identifier="28256">1. If the customs authority of the importing Party is notsatisfied with the outcome of the request for checkingpursuant to Article 43, it may request the exporting Partyto: 


(a) collect and provide the information relating tothe origin of the good and check, for thatpurpose, the facilities used in the production ofthe good, through a visit by its competentgovernmental authority along with the customsauthority of the importing Party to the premisesof the exporter to whom a certificate of originhas been issued, or the producer of the good inthe exporting Party referred to in subparagraph7(b) of Article 41; and 


(b) provide information relating to the origin of thegood in the possession of the competentgovernmental authority or its designee. 
2. 	(a) In cases where the customs authority of the importing Party considers as exceptional, thatcustoms authority may, before or during therequest for checking referred to in Article 43,put forward the exporting Party a requestreferred to in paragraph 1 above. 

(b) Where the request referred to in subparagraph (a)above is made, Article 43 shall not be applied. 


3. When requesting the exporting Party to conduct a visitpursuant to paragraph 1 or 2 above, the importing Partyshall deliver a written communication with such request tothe exporting Party at least forty (40) days in advance ofthe proposed date of the visit, the receipt of which is tobe confirmed by the latter Party. The competent governmental authority of the exporting Party shall requestthe written consent of the exporter, or the producer of thegood in the exporting Party whose premises are to bevisited. 


4. The communication referred to in paragraph 3 aboveshall include: 


(a) the identity of the customs authority issuing thecommunication; 


(b) the name of the exporter, or the producer of thegood in the exporting Party whose premises arerequested to be visited; 


(c) the proposed date and place of the visit; 


(d) the object and scope of the proposed visit,including specific reference to the good subjectof the verification referred to in the certificate of origin; and 


(e) 	the names and titles of the officials of the customs authority of the importing Party to bepresent during the visit. 

5. The exporting Party shall respond in writing to theimporting Party, within thirty (30) days of the receipt ofthe communication referred to in paragraph 3 above, if itaccepts or refuses to conduct a visit requested pursuant toparagraph 1 or 2 above. 


6. The competent governmental authority of the exportingParty shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations,provide within forty five (45) days or any other mutuallyagreed period from the last day of the visit, to thecustoms authority of the importing Party the informationobtained pursuant to paragraph 1 or 2 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Determination Of Origin And Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="28257">1. The customs authority of the importing Party may denypreferential tariff treatment to a good for which animporter claims preferential tariff treatment where thegood does not qualify as an originating good of theexporting Party or where the importer fails to comply withany of the relevant requirements of this Chapter. 


2. The competent governmental authority of the exportingParty shall, when it cancels the decision to issue thecertificate of origin, promptly notify the cancellation tothe exporter to whom the certificate of origin has beenissued, and to the customs authority of the importing Partyexcept where the certificate has been returned to thecompetent governmental authority. The customs authority of the importing Party may determine that the good does notqualify as an originating good of the exporting Party andmay deny preferential tariff treatment where it receivesthe notification. 


3. The customs authority of the importing Party maydetermine that a good does not qualify as an originatinggood of the exporting Party and may deny preferentialtariff treatment, and a written determination thereof shallbe sent to the competent governmental authority of theexporting Party: 


(a) where the competent governmental authority of theexporting Party fails to respond to the requestwithin the period referred to in paragraph 2 ofArticle 43 or paragraph 6 of Article 44; 


(b) where the exporting Party refuses to conduct avisit, or that Party fails to respond to thecommunication referred to in paragraph 3 ofArticle 44 within the period referred to inparagraph 5 of Article 44; or 


(c) where the information provided to the customsauthority of the importing Party pursuant toArticle 43 or 44, is not sufficient to prove thatthe good qualifies as an originating good of theexporting Party. 

4. After carrying out the procedures outlined in Article43 or 44 as the case may be, the customs authority of theimporting Party shall provide the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party with a writtendetermination of whether or not the good qualifies as anoriginating good of the exporting Party, including findingsof fact and the legal basis for the determination. The competent governmental authority of the exporting Partyshall inform such determination by the customs authority ofthe importing Party to the exporter, or the producer of thegood in the exporting Party, whose premises were subject tothe visit referred to in Article 44.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="28258">1. Each Party shall maintain, in accordance with its lawsand regulations, the confidentiality of informationprovided to it as confidential pursuant to this Chapter,and shall protect, in accordance with its laws andregulations, that information from disclosure that couldprejudice the competitive position of the persons providingthe information. 


2. Information obtained by the customs authority of theimporting Party pursuant to this Chapter: 


(a) may only be used by such authority for thepurposes of this Chapter; and 


(b) shall not be used by the importing Party in anycriminal proceedings carried out by a court or ajudge, unless the information is requested to theother Party and provided to the former Party,through the diplomatic channels or other channelsestablished in accordance with the applicablelaws of the requested Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Penalties, Sanctions Or Other Measures" article_identifier="28259">Each Party shall ensure, in accordance with its lawsand regulations, that appropriate penalties, sanctions orother measures are maintained or established against itsexporters to whom a certificate of origin has been issuedand its producers of the goods in the exporting Partyreferred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 41: 


(a) for providing false declaration or documents toits competent governmental authority or itsdesignees prior to the issuance of certificate oforigin; and 


(b) for failing to notify in writing to the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party orits designees without delay after having knownthat such good does not qualify as an originatinggood of the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="28260">1. Communications, including in the form of documents,between the importing Party and the exporting Party shallbe made in English. 


2. For the application of the relevant product specificrules set out in Annex 2 and the determination of origin,the Generally Accepted Accounting Principles in theexporting Party shall be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="28261">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Rules ofOrigin(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on: 

(i) the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 

(ii) any amendments to Annexes 2 and 3, proposedby either Party; and 

(iii) the Operational Procedures on Trade in Goodsand Rules of Origin referred to in Article 25; 

(b) considering any other matter as the Parties mayagree related to this Chapter; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(d) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="602">
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28262">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs proceduresrequired for the clearance of goods traded between theParties. 


2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties inaccordance with the laws and regulations in force in eachParty and within the available resources of theirrespective customs authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28263">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “customs authority” means the customsauthority as defined in subparagraph (b) ofArticle 28; and 


(b) 	the term “customs laws” means such laws and regulations administered and enforced by thecustoms authority of each Party concerning theimportation, exportation, and transit of goods,as they relate to customs duties, charges, andother taxes, or to prohibitions, restrictions,and other similar controls with respect to themovement of controlled items across the boundaryof the customs territory of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Transparency" article_identifier="28264">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant informationof general application pertaining to its customs laws isreadily available to any interested person. 


2. When information that has been made available must be amended due to changes in its customs laws, each Partyshall, wherever possible, continue to make the revisedinformation publicly available prior to the entry intoforce of the changes. 


3. At the request of the interested person, each Partyshall provide, as quickly and as accurately as possible,information relating to the specific matters raised by theinterested person and pertaining to its customs laws. Each Party shall supply not only the information specificallyrequested but also any other pertinent information which itconsiders the interested person should be made aware of.Each Party shall endeavor to provide such information inlanguage mutually understandable within its availableresources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="28265">1. Both Parties shall make cooperative efforts forsimplification and harmonization of their customsprocedures by observing the following principles: 


(a) the application of customs procedures in apredictable, consistent and transparent manner; 


(b) cooperation wherever appropriate with othernational authorities, customs authorities of non-Parties and the trading communities; and 


(c) the provision to affected parties of easilyaccessible processes of administrative andjudicial review. 
2. For the accomplishment of the purpose of paragraph 1above, each Party shall: 


(a) 	make use of information and communications technology; 


(b) reduce and simplify import and export
documentation requirements; and 



(c) harmonize its customs procedures, as far aspossible, with relevant international standardsand recommended practices such as those madeunder the auspices of the World CustomsOrganization.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Goods In Transit" article_identifier="28266">Each Party shall continue to facilitate customsclearance of goods in transit from or to the other Party inaccordance with paragraph 3 of Article V of the GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Cooperation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="28267">1. The Parties shall cooperate and exchange informationwith each other, in the fields of customs procedures,including their enforcement against trafficking ofprohibited goods and importation and exportation of goodssuspected of infringing intellectual property rights. 


2. For the effective implementation of paragraph 1 above,the Parties shall cooperate and exchange information, asprovided for in the Implementing Agreement. 


3. Article 9 shall not apply to the exchange ofinformation under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Sub-Committee On Customs Procedures" article_identifier="28268">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on CustomsProcedures (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

13. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(b) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; 


(c) identifying areas to be improved for facilitatingtrade between the Parties; and 


(d) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. The composition of the Sub-Committee shall bespecified in the Implementing Agreement. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue and times as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Paperless Trading" chapter_identifier="3357">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Cooperation On Paperless Trading Between The Parties" article_identifier="28269">The Parties, recognizing that trading using electronicfiling and transfer of trade-related information andelectronic versions of documents such as bills of lading,invoices, letters of credit and insurance certificates, asan alternative to paper-based methods (hereinafter referredto in this Chapter as “paperless trading”), willsignificantly enhance the efficiency of trade throughreduction of cost and time, shall cooperate through theexchange of views and information on realizing andpromoting paperless trading between them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Cooperation On Paperless Trading Between Private Entities" article_identifier="28270">The Parties shall encourage cooperation between theirrelevant private entities engaging in activities related topaperless trading. Such cooperation may include the setting up and operation by such private entities offacilities (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “thefacilities”) that provide efficient and secured flow ofelectronic trade-related information and electronic versions of documents between juridical persons of theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Review Of Realization Of Paperless Trading" article_identifier="28271">The Parties shall review, at such frequency as theParties may agree on, the progress made in realizingpaperless trading in which electronic trade-relatedinformation and electronic versions of relevant documents exchanged between enterprises of the Parties through thefacilities may be used as supporting documents by the traderegulatory bodies of the respective Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Mutual Recognition" chapter_identifier="3358">
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="General Obligations" article_identifier="28272">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with the provisions ofthis Chapter, permit participation of conformity assessmentbodies of the other Party, in the system of the formerParty providing for conformity assessment procedures andshall accept the results of conformity assessmentprocedures required by its applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions specified in the relevantSectoral Annex, including certificates of conformity, thatare conducted by the conformity assessment bodies of theother Party registered by the Registering Authority of theformer Party. 


2. Where a license is required by a Party in addition tocertificates of conformity referred to in paragraph 1above, for using marks of conformity, such license shall beissued immediately and unconditionally upon submission ofapplication for a license so as not to be used as a meansof avoiding obligations referred to in paragraph 1 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28273">1. This Chapter applies to registration of conformityassessment bodies and conformity assessment procedures forproducts or processes covered by the Sectoral Annex. The Sectoral Annex shall be attached to this Agreement as Annex4 and may consist of Part 1 and Part 2. 


2. Part 1 of the Sectoral Annex shall include, inter alia, provisions on scope and coverage. 


3. Part 2 of the Sectoral Annex shall set out the following matters: 


(a) the applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions of each Partystipulating the products covered by this Chapter; 


(b) the applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions of each Partystipulating the technical requirements covered bythis Chapter and the conformity assessmentprocedures covered by this Chapter to satisfysuch requirements; 


(c) the applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions of each Partystipulating the criteria for registration ofconformity assessment bodies; and 


(d) the list of Registering Authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28274">1. For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “certificates of conformity” meansdocuments issued by registered or accreditedconformity assessment bodies as a result ofconformity assessment procedures, stating thatproducts or processes fulfill relevant technicalrequirements set out in the applicable laws,regulations and administrative provisions of aParty specified in the relevant Sectoral Annex; 


(b) the term “conformity assessment bodies” meansbodies which conduct conformity assessmentprocedures; 


(c) the term “conformity assessment bodies of theother Party” means conformity assessment bodieslocated in the other Party; 


(d) the term “conformity assessment procedures” meansprocedures to determine, directly or indirectly,whether products or processes fulfill relevanttechnical requirements set out in the applicablelaws, regulations and administrative provisionsof a Party specified in the relevant SectoralAnnex; 


(e) the term “criteria for registration” means thecriteria which conformity assessment bodies of aParty are required to fulfill in order to beregistered or accredited by the RegisteringAuthority of the other Party, and other relevantconditions which conformity assessment bodiesregistered or accredited by the RegisteringAuthority of the other Party are required tocontinuously fulfill after the registration oraccreditation, as set out in the applicable laws,regulations and administrative provisions of thatother Party specified in the relevant SectoralAnnex; 


(f) the term “entities of the other Party” meansentities located in the other Party; 


(g) the term “Registering Authority” means anauthority of a Party which is authorized toregister or accredit the conformity assessmentbodies of the other Party and withdraw suchregistration or accreditation in accordance withthe applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions of the former Partyspecified in the relevant Sectoral Annex; and 


(h) the term “registration” means the registration oraccreditation of conformity assessment bodies ofa Party by the Registering Authority of the otherParty pursuant to the applicable laws,regulations and administrative provisions of thatother Party specified in the relevant SectoralAnnex. 
2. Any term used in this Chapter, unless otherwisedefined herein, has the meaning assigned to it in theISO/IEC Guide 2: 1996 Edition, “Standardization and relatedactivities – General vocabulary”.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Registration And Withdrawal Of Registration Of Conformity Assessment Bodies" article_identifier="28275">1. 	(a) The Registering Authority of a Party shall register the conformity assessment bodies of theother Party in accordance with the applicablelaws, regulations and administrative provisionsof the former Party specified in the relevantSectoral Annex, where the conformity assessmentbodies which apply for registration fulfill thecriteria for registration of the former Party setout in its applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions specified in therelevant Sectoral Annex. 

(b) The Registering Authority of a Party may withdrawthe registration of the conformity assessmentbodies of the other Party, where the conformityassessment bodies no longer fulfill the criteriafor registration of the former Party set out inits applicable laws, regulations andadministrative provisions specified in therelevant Sectoral Annex. 

2. 	(a) For the purposes of confirming the fulfillment of the criteria for registration by conformityassessment bodies of the other Party, theRegistering Authority of a Party may: 

(i) make inquiries by means of writtenquestionnaires to the conformity assessmentbodies of the other Party or during thevisit referred to in subparagraph (ii)below; 

(ii) conduct visit on the premises of theconformity assessment bodies of the otherParty on the condition that such other Partydo not object to such visit and theconformity assessment bodies concerned giveconsent to such visit and, if such otherParty so requests, officials of theRegistering Authority of such other Partyjoin the visit; and 

(iii) have its officials to accompany conformityassessment bodies of the other Partyapplying for registration as an observerwhere those bodies carry out, as part of theconformity assessment procedures, conformityassessment activities at the premises ofentities of the other Party subject to suchactivities on the condition that such other Party do not object to such accompanimentand the entities and conformity assessmentbodies concerned give consent to suchaccompaniment and, if such other Party sorequests, officials of the RegisteringAuthority of such other Party join theaccompaniment. 

Note: 	If no objection is communicated to theRegistering Authority concerned within ten

(10) days or a period specified by suchRegistering Authority, whichever islonger, from the receipt of the requestfor the visit or the accompaniment, as thecase may be, it shall be understood thatno objection was made. 


(b) The Registering Authority of a Party shallimmediately communicate to the other Partywhenever it sends questionnaires referred to insubparagraph (a)(i) above. 


(c) The visit and accompaniment referred to insubparagraphs (a)(ii) and (a)(iii) aboverespectively shall be carried out in a manner notinconsistent with the laws and regulations of theParty where the visit and accompaniment takeplace. 


(d) The Party shall use the information obtained byits Registering Authority in connection with suchinquiries, visit or accompaniment as an observeronly for the purposes referred to in subparagraph
(a) above. 

3. The Registering Authority of a Party may withdraw theregistration of the conformity assessment bodies of theother Party, where the inquiries specified in subparagraph2(a)(i) above are not responded to without valid reasons orare responded to falsely, or the other Party object to thevisit or the conformity assessment bodies concerned do notgive consent referred to in subparagraph 2(a)(ii) above, orthe visit specified in subparagraph 2(a)(ii) above isrefused, obstructed or evaded.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Sub-Committee On Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="28276">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on MutualRecognition (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchanging information on standards andconformity assessment procedures; 


(b) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(c) examining the possibility of negotiating onadditional products or processes for mutualrecognition; 


(d) discussing any issues related to this Chapter,including ways to promote cooperation onstandards and conformity assessment proceduresbetween the Parties in view of the effective implementation and operation of this Chapter; 


(e) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(f) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Operational Procedures On Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="28277">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement,the Joint Committee shall adopt the Operational Procedureson Mutual Recognition that provide detailed regulationspursuant to which the Registering Authorities shallimplement their functions under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="28278">Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to limitthe authority of a Party to take measures it considersappropriate, for protecting health, safety or theenvironment or prevention of deceptive practices.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Miscellaneous Provisions" article_identifier="28279">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed toauthorize a Party to take compulsory measures against theconformity assessment bodies of the other Party or entitiesof the other Party subject to conformity assessmentprocedures, or against their representatives, employees andother personnel. It is confirmed that each Party shall not impose any criminal, civil or administrative penalty on theconformity assessment bodies of the other Party or entitiesof the other Party subject to conformity assessmentprocedures, or on their representatives, employees andother personnel in connection with this Chapter. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed so as tooblige a Party to accept the standards of the other Party. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed so as toaffect the rights and obligations that either Party has asa party to the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="28280">1. Each Party shall maintain, in accordance with its lawsand regulations, the confidentiality of informationprovided to it as confidential pursuant to this Chapter andshall protect that information from disclosure that couldprejudice the competitive position of the persons providingthe information. 


2. Information obtained pursuant to this Chapter shallnot be used by a Party in any criminal proceedings carriedout by a court or a judge, unless the information isrequested to the other Party and provided to the formerParty, through the diplomatic channels or other channelsestablished in accordance with the applicable laws of therequested Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Sectoral Annex" article_identifier="28281">If a Party introduces new or additional conformityassessment procedures within the same product coverage tosatisfy the technical requirements set out in theapplicable laws, regulations and administrative provisionsspecified in the relevant Sectoral Annex, Part 2 of theSectoral Annex shall be amended to set out the applicablelaws, regulations and administrative provisions stipulatingsuch new or additional conformity assessment procedures, inaccordance with the procedures set out in paragraph 2 ofArticle 163.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="3359">
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28282">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Partyaffecting trade in services. 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to: 


(a) in respect of air transport services, measuresaffecting traffic rights, however granted; or tomeasures affecting services directly related tothe exercise of traffic rights, other thanmeasures affecting: 

(i) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 

(ii) the selling and marketing of air transportservices; and 

(iii) computer reservation system services; 

(b) cabotage in maritime transport services; 


(c) subsidies provided by a Party or a stateenterprise thereof, including grants, government-supported loans, guarantees and insurance; 


(d) measures pursuant to immigration laws andregulations; and 


(e) measures affecting natural persons seeking accessto the employment market of a Party, or measuresregarding nationality or citizenship, orresidence or employment on a permanent basis. 

3. Articles 72, 73 and 76 shall not apply to any measureby a Party with respect to government procurement. 


4. Annex 5 provides supplementary provisions to thisChapter with respect to measures affecting the supply offinancial services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28283">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “aircraft repair and maintenanceservices” means such activities when undertaken on an aircraft or a part thereof while it iswithdrawn from service and does not include so-called line maintenance; 


(b) the term “commercial presence” means any type ofbusiness or professional establishment, includingthrough: 
(i) the constitution, acquisition or maintenanceof a juridical person; or 

(ii) 	the creation or maintenance of a branch or a representative office; 

within the Area of a Party for the purposes ofsupplying a service; 


(c) the term “computer reservation system services”means services provided by computerized systemsthat contain information about air carriers’ schedules, availability, fares and fare rules,through which reservations can be made or ticketsmay be issued; 


(d) the term “juridical person of the other Party”means a juridical person which is either: 
(i) constituted or otherwise organized under thelaw of the other Party; or 

(ii) in the case of the supply of a servicethrough commercial presence, owned orcontrolled by: 

(aa) natural persons of the other Party; or 

(bb) juridical persons of the other Partyidentified under subparagraph (i)above; 


(e) a juridical person is: 

(i) “owned” by persons if more than fifty (50)percent of the equity interest in it isowned by such persons; 

(ii) “controlled” by persons if such persons havethe power to name a majority of itsdirectors or otherwise to legally direct itsactions; 

(iii) “affiliated” with another person when itcontrols, or is controlled by, that otherperson; or when it and the other person areboth controlled by the same person; 

(f) the term “measures by a Party” means measurestaken by: 

(i) central or local governments; and 

(ii) non-governmental bodies in the exercise ofpowers delegated by central or localgovernments; 

(g) the term “measures by a Party affecting trade inservices” includes measures in respect of: 

(i) the purchase, payment or use of a service; 

(ii) the access to and use of, in connection withthe supply of a service, services which arerequired by a Party to be offered to thepublic generally; 

(iii) the presence, including commercial presence,of persons of a Party for the supply of aservice in the Area of the other Party; 

(h) the term “monopoly supplier of a service” meansany person, public or private, which in therelevant market of the Area of a Party isauthorized or established formally or in effectby that Party as the sole supplier of thatservice; 


(i) the term “natural person of the other Party”means a natural person who resides in the otherParty or elsewhere and who under the law of theother Party is a national of the other Party; 


(j) the term “sector” of a service means: 

(i) with reference to a specific commitment, oneor more, or all, subsectors of that service,as specified in a Party’s Schedule ofSpecific Commitments in Part 1 of Annex 6;or 

(ii) otherwise, the whole of that service sector,including all of its subsectors; 

(k) the term “selling and marketing of air transportservices” means opportunities for the air carrierconcerned to sell and market freely its airtransport services including all aspects ofmarketing such as market research, advertisingand distribution. These activities do not include the pricing of air transport services northe applicable conditions; 


(l) the term “service consumer” means any person thatreceives or uses a service; 


(m) the term “service of the other Party” means aservice which is supplied: 

(i) from or in the Area of the other Party, orin the case of maritime transport, by avessel registered under the laws of theother Party, or by a person of the otherParty which supplies the service through theoperation of a vessel or its use in whole orin part; or 

(ii) in the case of the supply of a servicethrough commercial presence or through thepresence of natural persons, by a servicesupplier of the other Party; 

(n) the term “services” includes any service in anysector except services supplied in the exerciseof governmental authority; 


(o) the term “service supplied in the exercise ofgovernmental authority” means any service whichis supplied neither on a commercial basis nor incompetition with one or more service suppliers; 


(p) the term “service supplier” means any person thatsupplies a service; 

Note: 	Where the service is not supplied directlyby a juridical person but through otherforms of commercial presence such as abranch or a representative office, theservice supplier (i.e. the juridicalperson) shall, nonetheless, through suchpresence be accorded the treatmentprovided for service suppliers. Such treatment shall be extended to the presence through which the service issupplied and need not be extended to anyother parts of the supplier locatedoutside the Area where the service is supplied. 

(q) the term “service supplier of the other Party”means any natural person of the other Party orjuridical person of the other Party, thatsupplies a service; 


(r) the term “state enterprise” means an enterpriseowned or controlled by a Party; 


(s) the term “supply of a service” includes theproduction, distribution, marketing, sale anddelivery of a service; 


(t) the term “trade in services” means the supply ofa service: 

(i) from the Area of one Party into the Area ofthe other Party (“cross-border mode”); 

(ii) in the Area of one Party to the serviceconsumer of the other Party (“consumptionabroad mode”); 

(iii) by a service supplier of one Party, throughcommercial presence in the Area of the otherParty (“commercial presence mode”); 

(iv) by a service supplier of one Party, throughpresence of natural persons of that Party inthe Area of the other Party (“presence ofnatural persons mode”); and 

(u) the term “traffic rights” means the rights forscheduled and non-scheduled services to operateand/or to carry passengers, cargo and mail forremuneration or hire from, to, within, or over aParty, including points to be served, routes tobe operated, types of traffic to be carried,capacity to be provided, tariffs to be chargedand their conditions, and criteria fordesignation of airlines, including such criteriaas number, ownership and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Market Access" article_identifier="28284">1. With respect to market access through the modes ofsupply defined in subparagraph (t) of Article 71, eachParty shall accord services and service suppliers of theother Party treatment no less favorable than that providedfor under the terms, limitations and conditions agreed andspecified in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Part 1of Annex 6. 

Note: 	If a Party undertakes a market-accesscommitment in relation to the supply of aservice through the mode of supply referred toin subparagraph (t)(i) of Article 71 and if thecross-border movement of capital is anessential part of the service itself, thatParty is thereby committed to allow suchmovement of capital. If a Party undertakes a market-access commitment in relation to the supply of a service through the mode of supplyreferred to in subparagraph (t)(iii) of Article71, it is thereby committed to allow relatedtransfers of capital into its Area. 

2. In sectors where market-access commitments are undertaken, the measures which a Party shall not maintainor adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision oron the basis of its entire Area, unless otherwise specifiedin its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Part 1 of Annex6, are defined as: 


(a) limitations on the number of service supplierswhether in the form of numerical quotas,monopolies, exclusive service suppliers or therequirements of an economic needs test; 


(b) 	limitations on the total value of service transactions or assets in the form of numerical quotas or the requirement of an economic needstest; 


(c) 	limitations on the total number of service operations or on the total quantity of serviceoutput expressed in terms of designated numericalunits in the form of quotas or the requirement ofan economic needs test; 

Note: 	This subparagraph does not cover measuresof a Party which limit inputs for thesupply of services. 

(d) 	limitations on the total number of natural persons that may be employed in a particularservice sector or that a service supplier mayemploy and who are necessary for, and directlyrelated to, the supply of a specific service inthe form of numerical quotas or the requirementof an economic needs test; 


(e) measures which restrict or require specific typesof legal entity or joint venture through which aservice supplier may supply a service; and 


(f) limitations on the participation of foreigncapital in terms of maximum percentage limit onforeign shareholding or the total value ofindividual or aggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="28285">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of SpecificCommitments in Part 1 of Annex 6, and subject to anyconditions and qualifications set out therein, each Partyshall accord to services and service suppliers of the otherParty, in respect of all measures affecting the supply ofservices, treatment no less favorable than that it accordsto its own like services and service suppliers. 

Note: 	Specific commitments assumed under this Articleshall not be construed to require either Partyto compensate for any inherent competitivedisadvantages which result from the foreigncharacter of the relevant services or service suppliers. 

2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 aboveby according to services and service suppliers of the otherParty, either formally identical treatment or formallydifferent treatment to that it accords to its own like services and service suppliers. 


3. Formally identical or formally different treatmentshall be considered to be less favorable if it modifies the conditions of competition in favor of services or servicesuppliers of a Party compared to like services or servicesuppliers of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Additional Commitments" article_identifier="28286">The Parties may negotiate commitments with respect tomeasures affecting trade in services not subject toscheduling under Articles 72 and 73, including thoseregarding qualifications, standards or licensing matters.Such commitments shall be inscribed in a Party’s Scheduleof Specific Commitments in Part 1 of Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Schedule Of Specific Commitments" article_identifier="28287">1. Each Party shall set out in a schedule the SpecificCommitments it undertakes under Articles 72, 73 and 74. 


2. With respect to sectors where the specific commitmentsare undertaken, each Schedule of Specific Commitments inPart 1 of Annex 6 shall specify: 


(a) terms, limitations and conditions on marketaccess; 


(b) conditions and qualifications on nationaltreatment; 


(c) undertakings relating to additional commitments;and 


(d) where appropriate, the time-frame for
implementation of such commitments. 


3. With respect to sectors or subsectors where thespecific commitments are undertaken and which are indicatedwith “SS”, any terms, limitations, conditions andqualifications, referred to in subparagraphs 2(a) and (b)above, shall be limited to existing non-conformingmeasures. 


4. Measures inconsistent with both Articles 72 and 73 shall be inscribed in the column relating to Article 72.This inscription will be considered to provide a conditionor qualification to Article 73 as well. 


5. Schedules of Specific Commitments shall be annexed tothis Agreement as Part 1 of Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="28288">1. Each Party shall accord to services and servicesuppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorablethan that it accords, in like circumstances, to servicesand service suppliers of any non-Party. 


2. The provision of paragraph 1 above shall not apply toany measure by a Party with respect to sectors, subsectorsor activities, as set out in its Schedule to Part 2 ofAnnex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Authorization, Licensing Or Qualification" article_identifier="28289">With a view to ensuring that any measure by a Partyrelating to the authorization, licensing or qualificationof service suppliers of the other Party does not constitutean unnecessary barrier to trade in services, each Partyshall endeavor to ensure that such measure: 


(a) is based on objective and transparent criteria,such as competence and the ability to supply theservice; 


(b) is not more burdensome than necessary to ensurethe quality of the service; and 


(c) does not constitute a disguised restriction onthe supply of the services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="28290">1. A Party may recognize the education or experienceobtained, requirements met, or licenses or certificationsgranted in the other Party for the purposes of thefulfillment, in whole or in part, of its standards orcriteria for the authorization, licensing or certificationof service suppliers of the other Party. 


2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1 above, whichmay be achieved through harmonization or otherwise, may bebased upon an agreement or arrangement between the Partiesor may be accorded unilaterally. 


3. Where a Party recognizes, by agreement or arrangementbetween the Party and a non-Party or unilaterally, theeducation or experience obtained, requirements met orlicenses or certifications granted in the non-Party; 


(a) nothing in Article 76 shall be construed torequire the Party to accord such recognition tothe education or experience obtained,requirements met or licenses or certificationsgranted in the other Party; and 


(b) the Party shall accord the other Party anadequate opportunity to demonstrate that theeducation or experience obtained, requirementsmet or licenses or certifications granted in theother Party should also be recognized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Transparency" article_identifier="28291">1. The competent authorities referred to in paragraph 2of Article 3 shall, upon request by service suppliers ofthe other Party, promptly respond to specific questionsfrom, and provide information to, the service supplierswith respect to matters referred to in paragraph 1 ofArticle 3, including requirements and procedures forlicensing and qualification, through enquiry points. The enquiry points shall be notified to the other Party bydiplomatic note on the date of entry into force of thisAgreement. 


2. Each Party shall prepare, forward to the other Partyand make public a list providing all existing measures,within the scope of this Chapter, at the centralgovernmental level and, in the case of Japan, prefecturalgovernmental level, and in the case of the Philippines,provincial governmental level, which are inconsistent withArticles 72 and/or 73, whether or not these measures areincluded in its specific commitments in Part 1 of Annex 6.The list shall include the following elements and shall bereviewed annually and revised as necessary: 


(a) sector and subsector or matter; 


(b) type of inconsistency (i.e. Market Access and/orNational Treatment); 


(c) legal source or authority of the measure; and 


(d) succinct description of the measure. 
Note: 	The list under this paragraph will be madesolely for the purposes of transparency, andshall not be construed to affect any rights andobligations of a Party under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="28292">1. Each Party shall ensure that any monopoly supplier ofa service in its Area does not, in the supply of themonopoly service in the relevant market, act in a mannerinconsistent with the Party’s specific commitments. 


2. Where a Party’s monopoly supplier competes, eitherdirectly or through an affiliated company, in the supply ofa service outside the scope of its monopoly rights andwhich is subject to that Party’s specific commitments, theParty shall ensure that such a supplier does not abuse itsmonopoly position to act in its Area in a mannerinconsistent with such commitments. 


3. The provisions of this Article shall also apply tocases of exclusive service suppliers, where a Party,formally or in effect: 


(a) 	authorizes or establishes a small number of service suppliers; and 


(b) substantially prevents competition among thosesuppliers in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="28293">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article82, a Party shall not apply restrictions on internationaltransfers and payments for current transactions relating totrade in services. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights andobligations of the Parties as members of the InternationalMonetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of theInternational Monetary Fund, including the use of exchangeactions which are in conformity with the Articles ofAgreement of the International Monetary Fund, provided thata Party shall not impose restrictions on any capitaltransactions inconsistently with its commitments under thisChapter regarding such transactions, except under Article82, or at the request of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="28294">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments andexternal financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Partymay adopt or maintain restrictions on trade in services,including on payments or transfers for transactions. 


2. 	The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1 above: 


(a) shall ensure that the other Party is treated asfavorably as any non-Party; 


(b) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 


(c) shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,economic and financial interests of the other Party; 


(d) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with thecircumstances described in paragraph 1 above; and 


(e) shall be temporary and be phased outprogressively as the situation specified inparagraph 1 above improves. 

3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, aParty may give priority to the supply of services which aremore essential to their economic or development programs.However, such restrictions shall not be adopted ormaintained for the purposes of protecting a particularservice sector. 


4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph1 above, or any changes therein, shall be promptly notifiedto the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="28295">Subject to the requirement that such measures are notapplied in a manner which would constitute a means ofarbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination against the otherParty, or a disguised restriction on trade in servicesbetween the Parties, nothing in this Chapter shall beconstrued to prevent the adoption or enforcement by eitherParty of measures: 


(a) necessary to protect public morals or to maintainpublic order; 

Note: 	The public order exception may be invokedonly where a genuine and sufficientlyserious threat is posed to one of thefundamental interests of society. 

(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant lifeor health; 


(c) necessary to secure compliance with laws orregulations which are not inconsistent with theprovisions of this Chapter including thoserelating to: 
(i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulentpractices or to deal with the effects of adefault on services contracts; 

(ii) the protection of the privacy of individualsin relation to the processing anddissemination of personal data and theprotection of confidentiality of individualrecords and accounts; 

(iii) safety.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="28296">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed: 


(a) to require a Party to furnish any information,the disclosure of which it considers contrary toits essential security interests; or 


(b) to prevent a Party from taking any action whichit considers necessary for the protection of itsessential security interests: 

(i) relating to the supply of services ascarried out directly or indirectly for thepurposes of provisioning a militaryestablishment; 

(ii) relating to the implementation of nationalpolicies or international agreementsrespecting the non-proliferation of weapons,or relating to fissionable and fusionablematerials or the materials from which theyare derived; 

(iii) taken in time of war or other emergency ininternational relations; or 

(c) to prevent a Party from taking any action inpursuance of its obligations under the UnitedNations Charter for the maintenance of international peace and security. 
2. Each Party shall be informed to the fullest extentpossible of measures taken by the other Party undersubparagraphs 1(b) and (c) and of their termination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="28297">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to aservice supplier of the other Party where the Partyestablishes that the service is being supplied by ajuridical person that is owned or controlled by persons ofa non-Party, and that denying Party: 


(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with thenon-Party; or 


(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to thenon-Party that prohibit transactions with thejuridical person or that would be violated orcircumvented if the benefits of this Chapter wereaccorded to the juridical person. 
2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, aParty may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a servicesupplier of the other Party where the Party establishesthat the service is being supplied by a juridical personthat is owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party andthat has no substantial business activities in the Area of that other Party. This paragraph shall not apply to maritime transport services supplied by a vessel registeredunder the laws of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Services" article_identifier="28298">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Trade inServices (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

13. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing commitments, including the scope ofcommitments to be indicated with “SS” pursuant toparagraph 3 of Article 75, with respect tomeasures affecting trade in services in thisChapter, with a view to achieving furtherliberalization on a mutually advantageous basisand securing an overall balance of rights andobligations; 


(b) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(c) exchanging information on domestic laws andregulations; 


(d) discussing any issues related to this Chapter,including deadlines for preparing, forwarding tothe other Party and making public the listreferred to in Article 79; 


(e) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(f) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="3360">
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28299">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted ormaintained by a Party relating to: 


(a) investors of the other Party; and 


(b) investments of investors of the other Party inthe Area of the former Party. 

2. Nothing in this Chapter shall impose any obligation oneither Party regarding measures pursuant to immigrationlaws and regulations. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to expandthe scope of the specific commitments undertaken by eitherParty pursuant to Chapter 7. 


4. Articles 89, 90 and 93 shall not apply to any measurethat the Philippines adopts or maintains relating toinvestors of Japan and their investments in service sectorswith respect to the establishment, acquisition or expansionof investments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28300">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) 	the term “financial services” shall have the same meaning as in subparagraph 5(a) of theAnnex on Financial Services of the GATS; 


(b) the term “investments” means every kind of assetowned or controlled, directly or indirectly, byan investor of a Party, including: 
(i) a juridical person; 

(ii) shares, stocks or other forms of equityparticipation in a juridical person,including rights derived therefrom; 

(iii) bonds, debentures, and loans and other formsof debt, including rights derived therefrom; 


(iv) rights under contracts, including turnkey,construction, management, production orrevenue-sharing contracts; 

(v) claims to money and claims to anyperformance under contract having afinancial value; 

(vi) intellectual property rights, includingcopyrights, patent rights, rights relatingto trademarks, industrial designs, layout-designs of integrated circuits, newvarieties of plants, trade names,indications of source or geographicalindications and undisclosed information; 
(vii) rights conferred pursuant to laws andregulations or contracts such asconcessions, licenses, authorizations, andpermits; and 

(viii) any other tangible and intangible, movableand immovable property, and any relatedproperty rights, such as leases, mortgages,liens and pledges; 

investments also include profits, capital gains,dividends, royalties, interests, fees and othercurrent incomes accruing from investments. A change in the form in which assets are investeddoes not affect their character as investments; 

(c) the term “investor of a Party” means: 

(i) a natural person who is a national of aParty and who is not a national of the otherParty; or (ii) juridical person of a Party, 

that seeks to make, is making, or has madeinvestments in the Area of the other Party. A branch of a juridical person of a non-Party,which is located in the Area of a Party, shallnot be deemed as an investor of that Party; 


(d) a juridical person is: 

(i) “owned” by persons if more than fifty (50)percent of the equity interest in it isowned by such persons; or 

(ii) “controlled” by persons if such persons havethe power to name a majority of itsdirectors or otherwise to legally direct itsactions; 

(e) the term “a juridical person of a Party” means ajuridical person duly constituted or otherwiseorganized under the law of a Party, with its seatof control or substantial business activities in the Area of that Party; and 


(f) 	the term “transfers” means transfers and international payments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="28301">Each Party shall accord to investors of the otherParty and to their investments treatment no less favorablethan that it accords, in like circumstances, to its owninvestors and to their investments with respect to theestablishment, acquisition, expansion, management,operation, maintenance, use, possession, liquidation, sale,or other disposition of investments (hereinafter referredto in this Chapter as “investment activities”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="28302">Each Party shall accord to investors of the otherParty and to their investments treatment no less favorablethan that it accords, in like circumstances, to investorsof a non-Party and to their investments with respect toinvestment activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="28303">Each Party shall accord to investments of investors ofthe other Party treatment in accordance with internationallaw, including fair and equitable treatment and fullprotection and security. 

Note: 	This Article prescribes the customary internationallaw minimum standard of treatment of aliens as the minimum standard of treatment to be afforded to investments of investors of the other Party. The concepts of “fair and equitable treatment” and “fullprotection and security” do not require treatment inaddition to or beyond that which is required by thecustomary international law minimum standard oftreatment of aliens. A determination that there has been a breach of another provision of thisAgreement, or of a separate international agreement,does not ipso facto establish that there has been a breach of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Access To The Courts Of Justice" article_identifier="28304">Each Party shall in its Area accord to investors ofthe other Party treatment no less favorable than thetreatment which it accords, in like circumstances, to itsown investors or investors of a non-Party with respect toaccess to its courts of justice and administrativetribunals and agencies in all degrees of jurisdiction, bothin pursuit and in defense of such investors’ rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Prohibition Of Performance Requirements" article_identifier="28305">1. Neither Party shall impose or enforce, as a conditionfor investment activities in its Area of an investor of the other Party, any of the following requirements: 


(a) to export a given level or percentage of goods orservices; 


(b) to achieve a given level or percentage ofdomestic content; 


(c) to purchase, use or accord a preference to goodsproduced or services provided in its Area, or topurchase goods or services from persons in itsArea; 


(d) to relate the volume or value of imports to thevolume or value of exports or to the amount offoreign exchange inflows associated withinvestments related to such investment activities; 


(e) to restrict sales of goods or services in itsArea that investments related to such investment activities produce or provide by relating suchsales to the volume or value of its exports orforeign exchange earnings; 


(f) to appoint, as executives, managers or members ofboards of directors, individuals of anyparticular nationality; 


(g) to hire a given level of its nationals; 


(h) to transfer technology, a production process orother proprietary knowledge to a person in itsArea, except when the requirement: 

(i) is imposed or enforced by a court,administrative tribunal or competitionauthority to remedy an alleged violation ofcompetition laws; or 

(ii) 	concerns the transfer of intellectual property rights which is undertaken in amanner not inconsistent with the Agreementon Trade-Related Aspects of IntellectualProperty Rights in Annex 1C to the WTOAgreement (hereinafter referred to in thisChapter as “the TRIPS Agreement”); 

(i) to locate the headquarters of that investor for aspecific region or the world market in its Area; 


(j) to achieve a given level or value of research anddevelopment in its Area; or 


(k) to supply one or more of the goods that theinvestor produces or the services that theinvestor provides to a specific region or worldmarket, exclusively from its Area. 
2. The provision of paragraph 1 above does not precludeeither Party from conditioning the receipt or continuedreceipt of an advantage, in connection with investmentactivities in its Area of an investor of the other Party,on compliance with any of the requirements set forth insubparagraphs (g) through (k) of paragraph 1 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Reservations And Exceptions" article_identifier="28306">1. Articles 89, 90 and 93 shall not apply to: 


(a) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by a Party at the central governmentlevel, as set out in its Schedule to Part l ofAnnex 7; 


(b) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by: 

(i) a prefecture in the case of Japan or aprovince in the case of the Philippines, forone (1) year after the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement, and thereafter asto be set out by a Party in its Schedule toPart l of Annex 7 in accordance with paragraph 2 below; or 

(ii) a local government other than prefecturesand provinces referred to in subparagraph

(i) above; 

(c) the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs

(a) and (b) above; or 

(d) an amendment to any non-conforming measurereferred to in subparagraphs (a) and (b) above,provided that the amendment does not decrease theconformity of the measure, as it existedimmediately before the amendment, with Articles89, 90 and 93. 

2. Each Party shall set out in its Schedule to Part l ofAnnex 7, within one (1) year of the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement, any existing non-conformingmeasure maintained by a prefecture or a province referredto in subparagraph 1(b)(i) above and shall notify thereofthe other Party by a diplomatic note. 


3. Articles 89, 90 and 93 shall not apply to any measurethat a Party adopts or maintains with respect to sectors,subsectors or activities, as set out in its Schedule toPart 2 of Annex 7, subject to the conditions set outtherein. 


4. Neither Party may, under any measure adopted after thedate of entry into force of this Agreement and covered byPart 2 of Annex 7, require an investor of the other Party,by reason of its nationality, to sell or otherwise disposeof an investment existing at the time the measure becomeseffective. 


5. In cases where a Party makes an amendment referred toin subparagraph 1(d) above, or where a Party adopts any newor more restrictive measure with respect to sectors,subsectors or activities as set out in its Schedule to Part 2 of Annex 7 after the date of the entry into force of thisAgreement, that Party shall, prior to the implementation ofthe amendment or the new or more restrictive measure, or inexceptional circumstances, as soon as possible thereafter: 


(a) notify the other Party of the following elements: 

(i) sector and subsector or activity; 

(ii) type of reservation; 

(iii) level of Government; 

(iv) measures; and 

(v) description; and 

(b) hold, upon request by the other Party,consultations in good faith with that other Partywith a view to achieving mutual satisfaction. 

6. Each Party shall endeavor, where appropriate, toreduce or eliminate the reservation set out in its Schedules to Parts 1 and 2 of Annex 7 respectively. 


7. Articles 89, 90 and 93 shall not apply to any measurethat a Party adopts or maintains with respect to governmentprocurement. 


8. Articles 89 and 90 shall not apply to any measurecovered by an exception to the obligations under Articles 3and 4 of the TRIPS Agreement, as specifically provided inthose Articles and in Article 5 of the TRIPS Agreement. 


9. Nothing in this Article shall be construed so as toderogate from the obligations of the Parties under theAgreement on Trade Related Investment Measures in Annex 1Ato the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="28307">1. Neither Party shall expropriate or nationalizeinvestments in its Area of investors of the other Party ortake any measure equivalent to expropriation ornationalization (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as“expropriation”) except: (a) for a public purpose; (b) on anon-discriminatory basis; (c) in accordance with dueprocess of law; and (d) upon payment of prompt, adequateand effective compensation. 


2. Compensation shall be equivalent to the fair marketvalue of the expropriated investments at the time when theexpropriation was publicly announced or when theexpropriation occurred without public announcement,whichever is the earlier. The fair market value shall not reflect any change in market value occurring because theexpropriation had become publicly known earlier. 


3. The compensation shall be paid without delay and shallcarry an appropriate interest, taking into account thelength of time from the time of expropriation until thetime of payment. It shall be effectively realizable and freely transferable and shall be freely convertible, at themarket exchange rate prevailing on the date of theexpropriation, into the currency of the Party of theinvestors concerned and freely usable currencies defined inthe Articles of Agreement of the International MonetaryFund. 


4. The investors affected by expropriation shall have aright of access to the courts of justice or theadministrative tribunals or agencies of the Party makingthe expropriation to seek a prompt review of the investor’scase and the amount of compensation in accordance with theprinciples set out in this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="28308">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the otherParty that have suffered loss or damage relating to theirinvestments in the Area of the former Party due to armedconflict or state of emergency such as revolution,insurrection, civil disturbance or any other similar eventin the Area of that former Party, treatment, as regardsrestitution, indemnification, compensation or any othersettlement, that is no less favorable than the mostfavorable treatment which it accords to any investors. 


2. Any payments made pursuant to paragraph 1 above shallbe effectively realizable, freely convertible and freelytransferable.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Transfers" article_identifier="28309">1. Each Party shall ensure that all transfers relating toinvestments in its Area of an investor of the other Partymay be made freely into and out of its Area without delay.Such transfers shall include: 


(a) the initial capital and additional amounts tomaintain or increase investments; 


(b) profits, capital gains, dividends, royalties,interests, fees and other current incomesaccruing from investments; 


(c) proceeds from the total or partial sale orliquidation of investments; 


(d) payments made under a contract including loanpayments in connection with investments; 


(e) earnings and remuneration of personnel from theother Party who work in connection withinvestments in the Area of the former Party; and 


(f) payments made in accordance with Articles 95 and
96. 


2. Neither Party shall prevent transfers into and out ofits Area from being made without delay in freely usablecurrencies at the market rate of exchange prevailing on thedate of the transfer. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2 above, a Party maydelay or prevent a transfer into and out of its Areathrough the equitable, non-discriminatory and good-faithapplication of its laws relating to: 


(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of therights of creditors; 


(b) issuing, trading or dealing in securities,futures, options or derivatives; 


(c) criminal or penal offences; 


(d) registration, reportorial and prior approvalrequirement concerning transfers of currency orother monetary instruments; or 

Note: 	Prior approval requirement applies only toshort-term foreign currency loans with theoriginal maturity of up to one (1) year. 

(e) ensuring compliance with orders or judgments inadjudicatory proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="28310">1. If a Party or its designated agency makes a payment toany of its investors pursuant to an indemnity, guarantee orinsurance contract, arising from or pertaining to aninvestment of that investor within the Area of the other Party, that other Party shall: 


(a) recognize the assignment, to the former Party orits designated agency, of any right or claim ofsuch investor that formed the basis of such payment; and 


(b) recognize the right of the former Party or itsdesignated agency to exercise by virtue ofsubrogation any such right or claim to the sameextent as the original right or claim of theinvestor. 
2. Articles 95, 96 and 97 shall apply mutatis mutandis as regards payment to be made to the Party or its designatedagency first mentioned in paragraph 1 above by virtue ofsuch assignment of right or claim, and the transfer of suchpayment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="28311">1. Subject to the requirement that such measures are notapplied in a manner which would constitute a means ofarbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination against the otherParty, or a disguised restriction on investments ofinvestors of the other Party in the Area of a Party,nothing in this Chapter other than Article 96 shall beconstrued to prevent a Party from adopting or enforcingmeasures: 


(a) necessary to protect human, animal or plant lifeor health; 


(b) necessary to protect public morals or to maintainpublic order; 

Note: 	The public order exception may be invokedonly where a genuine and sufficientlyserious threat is posed to one of thefundamental interests of society. 

(c) which it considers necessary for protection ofits essential security interests; 

(i) taken in time of war, or armed conflict, orother emergency in that Party or ininternational relations; or 

(ii) relating to the implementation of nationalpolicies or international agreementsrespecting the non-proliferation of weapons;or 

(d) in pursuance of its obligations under UnitedNations Charter for the maintenance of international peace and security. 
2. In cases where a Party takes any measure, pursuant toparagraph 1 above, that does not conform with theobligations of the provisions of this Chapter other thanArticle 96, that Party shall, prior to the entry into forceof the measure or as soon thereafter as possible, notifythe other Party of the following elements: 


(a) sector and subsector or activity; 


(b) obligation or article in respect of the measure; 


(c) legal source of the measure; 


(d) succinct description of the measure; and 


(e) purpose of the measure. 
3. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 89, eachParty may prescribe special formalities in connection withthe establishment of investments by investors of the otherParty in its Area such as the compliance with registrationrequirements, provided that such special formalities do notimpair the substance of the rights under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="28312">1. A Party may adopt or maintain measures inconsistentwith its obligations provided for in Article 89 relating tocross-border capital transactions and Article 97: 


(a) in the event of serious balance-of-payments andexternal financial difficulties or threat thereof; or 


(b) in cases where, in exceptional circumstances,movements of capital cause or threaten to causeserious difficulties for macroeconomic managementin particular, monetary and exchange ratepolicies. 
2. 	Measures referred to in paragraph 1 above: 


(a) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund solong as the Party taking the measures is a partyto the said Articles of Agreement; 


(b) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with thecircumstances set out in paragraph 1 above; 


(c) shall be temporary and shall be eliminated assoon as conditions permit; and 


(d) shall promptly be notified to the other Party. 
3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be regarded as alteringthe rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party asa party to the Articles of Agreement of the InternationalMonetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Prudential Measures" article_identifier="28313">Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Chapter,a Party may adopt or maintain measures relating tofinancial services for prudential reasons, includingmeasures for the protection of investors, depositors,policy holders or persons to whom a fiduciary duty is owedby a person supplying financial services, or to ensure theintegrity and stability of the financial system. Where such measures do not conform with the provisions of thisChapter, they shall not be used as a means of avoiding theParty’s commitments or obligations under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Environmental Measures" article_identifier="28314">Each Party recognizes that it is inappropriate toencourage investments by investors of the other Party byrelaxing its environmental measures. To this effect each Party should not waive or otherwise derogate from suchenvironmental measures as an encouragement forestablishment, acquisition or expansion in its Area ofinvestments by investors of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Investment And Labor" article_identifier="28315">1. The Parties recognize that it is inappropriate toencourage investment by weakening or reducing theprotections afforded in domestic labor laws. Accordingly, each Party shall strive to ensure that it does not waive orotherwise derogate from, or offer to waive or otherwisederogate from, such laws in a manner that weakens orreduces adherence to the internationally recognized laborrights referred to in paragraph 2 below as an encouragementfor the establishment, acquisition, expansion or retentionof an investment in its Area. If a Party considers thatthe other Party has offered such an encouragement, it mayrequest consultations with the other Party and the Partiesshall consult with a view to avoiding any suchencouragement. 


2. For purposes of this Article, “labor laws” means eachParty’s laws or regulations that are directly related tothe following internationally recognized labor rights: 


(a) the right of association; 


(b) the right to organize and bargain collectively; 


(c) a prohibition on the use of any form of forced orcompulsory labor; 


(d) labor protections for children and young people,including a minimum age for the employment ofchildren and the prohibition and elimination ofthe worst forms of child labor; and 


(e) acceptable conditions of work with respect tominimum wages, hours of work, and occupationalsafety and health.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Taxation Measures As Expropriation" article_identifier="28316">1. Article 95 shall apply to taxation measures, to theextent that such taxation measures constitute expropriationas provided for in paragraph 1 of Article 95. 


2. Where paragraph 1 above applies, Articles 92 and 106shall also apply in respect of taxation measures. 
Note: A taxation measure which is applied in a nondiscriminatory manner shall not be considered toconstitute expropriation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="28317">A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to aninvestor of the other Party that is a juridical person ofsuch Party and to an investment of such investor if thejuridical person is owned or controlled by investors of anon-Party and the denying Party: 


(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with thenon-Party; or 


(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to thenon-Party that prohibit transactions with thejuridical person or that would be violated orcircumvented if the benefits of this Chapter wereaccorded to the juridical person or to itsinvestments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Sub-Committee On Investment" article_identifier="28318">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Investment(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation of this Chapter; 


(b) reviewing the reservations set out in the Schedules to Parts 1 and 2 of Annex 7 for the purposes of contributing to the reduction orelimination, where appropriate, of suchreservation, and encouraging favorable conditionsfor investors of both Parties; 


(c) discussing any issues related to this Chapter, including issues related to taxation measures asexpropriation; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to the Joint Committee; and 


(e) performing other functions as may be delegated by the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Further Negotiation" article_identifier="28319">1. The Parties shall enter into negotiations after thedate of entry into force of this Agreement to establish amechanism for the settlement of an investment disputebetween a Party and an investor of the other Party. 


2． In the absence of the mechanism for the settlement of an investment dispute between a Party and an investor ofthe other Party, the resort to international conciliationor arbitration tribunal is subject to mutual consent of theparties to the dispute. This means that the disputing Party may, at its option or discretion, grant or deny itsconsent in respect of each particular investment disputeand that, in the absence of the express written consent ofthe disputing Party, an international conciliation orarbitration tribunal shall have no jurisdiction over theinvestment dispute involved.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="3361">
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28320">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting themovement of natural persons of a Party who enter into theother Party and who fall under one of the categories inparagraph 1 of Article 110. 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures regardingnationality or citizenship, or residence or employment on apermanent basis. 


3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applyingmeasures to regulate the entry of natural persons of theother Party into, or their temporary stay in, the formerParty, including the requiring of visas from nationals ofthe other Party or such measures necessary to protect theintegrity of, and to ensure the orderly movement of naturalpersons across, its borders, provided that such measuresare not applied in such a manner as to nullify or impairthe benefits accruing to the other Party under the terms ofa specific commitment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Definition" article_identifier="28321">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “naturalperson of the other Party” means a natural person whoresides in the other Party or elsewhere and who under thelaw of the other Party is a national of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Specific Commitments" article_identifier="28322">1. Each Party shall set out in Annex 8 the specificcommitments it undertakes for: 


(a) short-term business visitors of the other Party; 


(b) intra-corporate transferees of the other Party; 


(c) investors of the other Party; 


(d) natural persons of the other Party who engage inprofessional services; 


(e) natural persons of the other Party who engage insupplying services, which require technology orknowledge at an advanced level or which requirespecialized skills belonging to particular fieldsof industry, on the basis of a contract withpublic or private organizations in the formerParty; and 


(f) natural persons of the other Party who engage insupplying services as nurses or certifiedcareworkers or related activities, on the basisof a contract with public or privateorganizations in the former Party or on the basisof admission to public or private trainingfacilities in the former Party. 

2. Natural persons covered by a specific commitmentreferred to in paragraph 1 above shall be granted entry andtemporary stay in accordance with the terms and conditionsof the specific commitment set out in Annex 8, providedthat the natural persons comply with immigration laws andregulations applicable to entry and temporary stay whichare not inconsistent with the provisions of this Chapter. 


3. Neither Party shall impose or maintain anyquantitative restriction on the number of natural personsto be granted entry and temporary stay under paragraph 1above, without prejudice to any right of either Party toregulate the entry and temporary stay of natural persons ofthe other Party for the orderly implementation of thespecific commitments under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Requirements And Procedures Relating To The Movement Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="28323">1. Each Party shall establish and make publicly availablerequirements and procedures for application for a renewalof the period of temporary stay, a change of status oftemporary stay or an issuance of a work permit for anatural person of the other Party who has been grantedentry and temporary stay under paragraph 2 of Article 110. 


2. Each Party shall endeavor to provide, upon request bya natural person of the other Party, information onrequirements and procedures for applications referred to inparagraph 1 above. 


3. Each Party shall ensure that fees charged by itscompetent authorities on application referred to inparagraph 1 above do not in themselves represent anunjustifiable impediment to movement of natural personsunder this Chapter. 


4. Each Party shall endeavor, to the maximum extentpossible, to undertake measures to simplify therequirements and facilitate the procedures relating to themovement of natural persons of the other Party. Specific commitments on such measures shall be set out in Annex 8.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="28324">1. For the purposes of smooth movement of natural personsunder this Chapter, a Party may recognize the education orexperience obtained, requirements met, or licenses orcertifications granted in the other Party for the purposesof the fulfillment, in whole or in part, of its standardsor criteria for the authorization, licensing orcertification of natural persons of the other Party. 


2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1 above, whichmay be achieved through harmonization or otherwise, may bebased upon an agreement or arrangement between the Partiesor may be accorded unilaterally. 


3. Where a Party recognizes, by agreement or arrangementbetween the Party and a non-Party or unilaterally, theeducation or experience obtained, requirements met, orlicenses or certifications granted in the non-Party, theParty shall accord the other Party an adequate opportunityto demonstrate that the education or experience obtained,requirements met or licenses or certifications granted inthe other Party should also be recognized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Sub-Committee On Movement Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="28325">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Movement ofNatural Persons (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing scope of commitments under this Chapterincluding examining possibilities of making othercommitments on supplying service, that are notincluded in the specific commitments underparagraph 1 of Article 110 and of mutual interestto both Parties; 


(b) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(c) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(e) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representativesof the Governments of the Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at least once a year. 


5. 	(a) For purposes of the effective implementation and operation of Section 6 in Annex 8, the Sub-Committee shall establish a Special Sub-Committeeon Nurses and Certified Careworkers. 


(b) The functions of the Special Sub-Committee shallbe: 

(i) reviewing the implementation and operationof the said Section; 

(ii) discussing any issues related to the saidSection; and 

(iii) reporting the findings of the Special Sub-Committee, through the Sub-Committee, to theJoint Committee. 

(c) The Special Sub-Committee shall be composed ofrepresentatives of the Governments of theParties. 

6. 	(a) For purposes of the effective implementation and operation of Article 112, the Sub-Committee shallestablish a Special Sub-Committee on MutualRecognition. 

(b) The functions of the Special Sub-Committee shallbe: 

(i) reviewing the implementation and operationof the said Article; 

(ii) discussing any issue related to the saidArticle; and 

(iii) reporting the findings of the Special Sub-Committee, through the Sub-Committee, to theJoint Committee. 

(c) The Special Sub-Committee shall be composed ofrepresentatives of the Governments of theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="28326">Subject to the requirement that such measures are notapplied in a manner which would constitute a means ofarbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination against the otherParty, or a disguised restriction on movement of naturalpersons between the Parties, nothing in this Chapter shallbe construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement byeither Party of measures: 


(a) necessary to protect public morals or to maintainpublic order; 

Note: 	The public order exception may be invokedonly where a genuine and sufficientlyserious threat is posed to one of thefundamental interests of society. 

(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant lifeor health; or 


(c) necessary to secure compliance with laws orregulations which are not inconsistent with theprovisions of this Chapter including thoserelating to: 
(i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulentpractices or to deal with the effects of adefault on services contracts; 

(ii) the protection of the privacy of individualsin relation to the processing anddissemination of personal data and theprotection of confidentiality of individualrecords and accounts; or 

(iii) safety.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="28327">Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed: 


(a) to require a Party to furnish any information thedisclosure of which it considers contrary to itsessential security interests; 


(b) to prevent a Party from taking any action whichit considers necessary for the protection of itsessential security interests: 

(i) relating to the supply of services ascarried out directly or indirectly for thepurposes of provisioning a militaryestablishment; 

(ii) relating to the implementation of nationalpolicies or international agreementsrespecting the non-proliferation of weapons,or relating to fissionable and fusionablematerials or the materials from which theyare derived; or 

(iii) taken in time of war or other emergency ininternational relations; or 

(c) to prevent a Party from taking any action inpursuance of its obligations under the UnitedNations Charter for the maintenance of international peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Review" article_identifier="28328">The Parties shall undertake a review of the implementation and operation of, scope of commitmentsunder, and any issues related to, this Chapter, taking intoaccount the report of the Sub-Committee, every five (5)years after the entry into force of this Agreement andfurther whenever agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="3362">
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="28329">1. The Parties shall ensure adequate and nondiscriminatory protection of intellectual property,efficient and transparent administration of intellectualproperty protection system, and adequate and effectiveenforcement of intellectual property rights againstinfringement, counterfeiting and piracy, in accordance withthe provisions of this Chapter and the internationalagreements to which both Parties are parties. 


2. The Parties, recognizing the growing importance ofintellectual property for promoting economiccompetitiveness in the knowledge-based economy, and ofintellectual property protection in this new environment,shall develop and strengthen their cooperation in the fieldof intellectual property. 


3. Intellectual property referred to in this Chaptershall cover all categories of intellectual property: 


(a) that are subject of Articles 123 through 128;and/or 


(b) that are under the TRIPS Agreement and/or therelevant international agreements referred to inthe TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Definitions" article_identifier="28330">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) 	the term “Paris Convention” means the Stockholm Act of 1967 of the Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property; 


(b) the term “rights management information” meansinformation which identifies a work, performanceor phonogram; the author of the work, theperformer of the performance or the producer ofthe phonogram; the owner of any right in thework, performance or phonogram; or informationabout the terms and conditions of the use of the work, performance or phonogram; and any numbersor codes that represent such information, whenany of these items of information is attached toa copy of a work, a fixed performance or aphonogram or appears in connection with thecommunication or making available of a work, afixed performance or a phonogram to the public;and 


(c) the term “TRIPS Agreement” means the Agreement onTrade-Related Aspects of Intellectual PropertyRights in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="28331">1. The areas and forms of cooperation referred to inparagraph 2 of Article 117 may include, but not be limitedto: 


(a) exchange of information and experts in the fieldof intellectual property; 


(b) strengthening the intellectual propertyprotection system; 


(c) promotion of mutual understanding of intellectualproperty protection system of each Party; 


(d) promotion of public awareness on intellectualproperty; 


(e) organizing international symposiums, workshopsand fairs; and 


(f) technical assistance to be agreed upon betweenthe Parties in the development of information andcommunications technology-related projects forefficient administration of intellectual propertyprotection system. 

2. The implementation of such cooperation shall besubject to the availability of appropriated funds and theapplicable laws and regulations of each Party. 


3. Costs of such cooperation shall be borne in as anequitable manner as possible between the Parties throughefficient and effective utilization of resources. 


4. The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Article. Any differences between the Parties as to the implementation ofthis Article may be, upon agreement between the Parties,referred to the Sub-Committee on Intellectual Property forappropriate action.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Streamlining And Harmonization Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="28332">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administrationof intellectual property protection system, each Partyshall endeavor to streamline its administrative proceduresconcerning intellectual property. 


2. No Party may require the authentication of signaturesor other means of self-identification on documents to be submitted to the competent authority of the Party,including applications, translations into a languageaccepted by such authority of any earlier application whosepriority is claimed, powers of attorney and certificationsof assignment, in the course of application procedure orother administrative procedures on patents, utility models,industrial designs, or trademarks except as provided inparagraph 3 below. 


3. A Party may require as exceptions to paragraph 2above: 


(a) the authentication of signatures or other meansof self-identification, if the law of the Partyso provides, where the signatures or other meansof self-identification concern the surrender of a patent or a registration of utility models,industrial designs or trademarks; and 


(b) 	the submission of evidence if there is reasonable doubt as to the authenticity of signatures orother means of self-identification on documents submitted to the competent authority of theParty. Where the competent authority notifies the person that evidence is required, thenotification shall state the substantial reason for requiring the submission. 

4. Where the certification of a translation of an earlier application whose priority is claimed is required by aParty under its laws and regulations, such a requirementshall be deemed to be satisfied by the submission of awritten statement by the translator that, to the best ofhis knowledge, the translation of the earlier applicationis faithful and accurate. 


5. Applications for and registrations of relevantintellectual property rights and publications thereof shallbe classified in accordance with the laws and regulationsof each Party and, to the extent possible, in conformitywith the international patent classification system andinternational classification system of goods and servicesfor the purposes of the registration of marks underexisting international intellectual property agreementsadministered under the auspices of the World IntellectualProperty Organization.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Transparency" article_identifier="28333">For the purposes of further promoting transparency inthe administration of its intellectual property protectionsystem, each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, take appropriate measures to: 


(a) publish information on applications for andgrants of patents, and applications forregistrations of and registrations of utilitymodels, industrial designs, trademarks, layout-designs of integrated circuits and new varietiesof plants, and make easily available to thepublic information contained in the files thereofheld by the competent authority; and 


(b) make easily available to the public informationon intellectual property protection systemincluding information on its efforts to provideeffective enforcement of intellectual propertyrights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="28334">The Parties shall take necessary measures to enhancepublic awareness of protection of intellectual propertyincluding educational and dissemination projects on the useof intellectual property as well as on the enforcement ofintellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Patents" article_identifier="28335">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, ensure that any applicant for a patent mayfile a request to the competent authority that hisapplication be examined promptly. 

Note: 	For the purpose of this Article, the term “competentauthority” means, for the Philippines, the Directorof the Bureau of Patents of the Intellectual Property Office.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="28336">Each Party shall provide for the protection ofindustrial designs in accordance with the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Trademarks For Goods And Services" article_identifier="28337">Each Party shall provide for the protection oftrademarks in accordance with the Paris Convention and the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Copyright And Related Rights" article_identifier="28338">1. Each Party shall provide to authors, performers andproducers of phonograms the exclusive right of authorizingthe making available to the public of their works,performances fixed in phonograms and phonograms,respectively, by wire or wireless means, in such a way thatmembers of the public may access them from a place and at atime individually chosen by them. 


2. Each Party shall provide adequate legal protection andeffective legal remedies against the circumvention ofeffective technological measures that are used by authors,performers or producers of phonograms in connection withthe exercise of their rights under the laws and regulationsof the Party and that restrict acts, in respect of theirworks, performances or phonograms, which are not authorizedby the authors, performers or producers of phonogramsconcerned or permitted by the laws and regulations of theParty. 


3. Each Party shall provide adequate and effective legalremedies against any person knowingly performing any of thefollowing acts knowing, or with respect to civil remedieshaving reasonable grounds to know, that it will induce,enable, facilitate or conceal an infringement of copyrightsand related rights: 


(a) to remove or alter any electronic rightsmanagement information without authority; 


(b) to distribute, import for distribution,broadcast, communicate or make available to thepublic, without authority, works, copies ofworks, performances, copies of fixed performancesor phonograms knowing that electronic rightsmanagement information has been removed oraltered without authority.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="New Varieties Of Plants" article_identifier="28339">Each Party recognizes the importance of providing asystem of protection of new varieties of plants and shall,within its capabilities, endeavor to increase the number ofplant genera and species that can be protected under itslaws and regulations. In this regard, each Party shall consider the concerns of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="28340">1. Any act of competition contrary to honest practices inindustrial or commercial matters constitutes an act of unfair competition. 


2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, ensure that any acts of unfair competition,which shall include, but not be limited to, the followingacts, are prohibited: 


(a) acts of selling goods which imitate theappearance of another person’s goods; and 


(b) acts of such a nature as to create confusion byany means whatever with the services of acompetitor. 

3. Each Party shall ensure in its laws and regulationsadequate and effective protection of undisclosedinformation in accordance with the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Enforcement" article_identifier="28341">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations consistent with the TRIPS Agreement, providefor procedures concerning the suspension by the customsauthority of the release of infringing goods in cases ofinfringement of patents, utility models, industrialdesigns, trademarks or copyrights and related rights. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that the right holder ofintellectual property has the right to claim against theinfringer damages adequate to compensate for the injury theright holder has suffered because of an infringement ofthat person’s intellectual property right by an infringerwho knowingly, or with reasonable grounds to know, engagedin infringing activity. 


3. Each Party shall provide for criminal procedures andpenalties to be applied in cases of wilful trademarkcounterfeiting, copyright piracy, infringement of rightrelating to new varieties of plants or infringement orrepetition of infringement, as the case may be, of patents,utility models, industrial designs or layout-designs ofintegrated circuits on a commercial scale. Remedies available shall include imprisonment and/or monetary finessufficient to provide a deterrent, consistently with thelevel of penalties applied for crimes of a correspondinggravity as may be provided for in the laws and regulationsof each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Sub-Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="28342">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on IntellectualProperty (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

13. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(b) discussing the following issues, as appropriate,related to intellectual property with a view toenhancing protection of intellectual property andenforcement of intellectual property rights: 

(i) scope of patentable inventions and of priorart; 

(ii) translation requirements of prioritydocuments; 

(iii) scope of registrable industrial designs; 


(iv) protection of well-known trademarks; 

(v) international system for trademarkregistration; 

(vi) liability of internet service providers; 
(vii) collective management organizations forcopyright and related rights; 

(viii) protection of new varieties of plants; 

(ix) adequate and effective enforcement; and 

(x) fair and equitable enforcement procedures,including procedures for border measures; 

(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; 


(d) making appropriate recommendations, as needed, tothe Joint Committee; and 


(e) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 
3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue and times as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="3363">
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Procurement Principles" article_identifier="28343">The Parties recognize that it is important for a Partyto accord national treatment and most-favored-nation treatment to goods, services and suppliers of the otherParty with respect to the measures regarding governmentprocurement, and that it is desirable to providetransparency of the measures regarding governmentprocurement, with a view to achieving greaterliberalization and expansion of trade between the Parties.The Parties also recognize the need to take into accountthe development, financial and trade needs of the Parties.Each Party shall ensure a fair and effective implementationof the measures regarding government procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Negotiations On Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="28344">In the event that a Party offers a non-Party anyadvantages of access to its government procurement marketor any advantageous treatment concerning the measuresregarding government procurement, the former Party shallconsent to enter into negotiations with the other Partywith a view to extending these advantages or advantageoustreatment to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Sub-Committee On Government Procurement" article_identifier="28345">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on GovernmentProcurement (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchanging information on the measures regardinggovernment procurement of each Party; 


(b) analyzing available information on each Party’sgovernment procurement market; 


(c) discussing any issues relating to governmentprocurement, including: 

(i) possibility of according national treatmentand most-favored-nation treatment to goods,services and suppliers of the other Party; 

(ii) enhancement of transparency; 

(iii) fair and effective implementation of themeasures regarding government procurementincluding challenge procedures; and 

(iv) consistency of each Party’s measuresregarding government procurement withinternational principles on governmentprocurement, such as, but not limited to,the Agreement on Government Procurement inAnnex 4 to the WTO Agreement (hereinafterreferred to in this Chapter as “the GPA”); 

(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(e) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue as may beagreed by the Parties and shall make efforts to meet once ayear.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="28346">The Parties shall enter into negotiations at theearliest possible time, not later than five (5) years afterthe date of the entry into force of this Agreement, with aview to liberalizing their respective governmentprocurement markets. In such negotiations, the Parties shall review all aspects of their measures regardinggovernment procurement and shall consider the followingfactors: 


(a) according national treatment and most-favorednation treatment to goods, services and suppliersof the other Party; 


(b) enhancement of transparency; 


(c) consistency of each Party’s measures regardinggovernment procurement with internationalprinciples on government procurement, such as,but not limited to, the GPA; and 


(d) other matters necessary for a fair and effectiveimplementation of the measures regardinggovernment procurement including challengeprocedures.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="3364">
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Promotion Of Competition By Addressing Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="28347">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its applicablelaws and regulations, take measures which it considersappropriate to promote competition by addressing anticompetitive activities, in order to facilitate trade andinvestment flows between the Parties and the efficient functioning of its market. Any such measures shall be taken in conformity with the principles of transparency,non-discrimination and procedural fairness. 


2. Each Party shall, when necessary, review and improveor adopt laws and regulations to effectively promotecompetition by addressing anti-competitive activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Cooperation On Promoting Competition By Addressing Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="28348">1. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respectivelaws and regulations, cooperate in the field of promotingcompetition by addressing anti-competitive activities,subject to their respective available resources. 


2. The details and procedures of cooperation under thisArticle shall be specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="28349">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Improvement Of The Business Environment" chapter_identifier="3365">
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Principles And Cooperation" article_identifier="28350">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, take appropriate measures to further improvethe business environment for the persons of the other Partyconducting their business activities in the Area of theformer Party. 


2. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respectivelaws and regulations, promote cooperation to furtherimprove the business environment in the Area of the Partiesand take necessary measures including establishing suchinstitutions as provided for in Articles 139, 140 and 141.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Sub-Committee On Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="28351">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Improvementof the Business Environment (hereinafter referred to inthis Chapter as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be establishedpursuant to Article 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) supervising the activities of each ConsultativeGroup on Improvement of the Business Environment(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as“Consultative Group”) to be established underArticle 140; 


(b) addressing and resolving issues that the Sub-Committee considers appropriate taking intoaccount, as necessary, the findings reported byeach Consultative Group and each Liaison Officeon Improvement of the Business Environment(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as“Liaison Office”)to be designated under Article141; 


(c) reporting the findings and making recommendationsto the Parties including the measures to be takenby the Parties, regarding such functions asreferred to in subparagraphs (a) and (b) aboveand relevant issues. Such recommendations shall be taken into consideration by the Parties; 


(d) where appropriate, reviewing the measures takenby the Parties in relation to the recommendationsreferred to in subparagraph (c) above; 


(e) making available to those concerned, in anappropriate manner, the recommendations referredto in subparagraph (c) above and the results ofthe review referred to in subparagraph (d) above,to the extent allowed by the respective laws andregulations of the Parties; 


(f) reporting the findings and recommendationsreferred to in subparagraph (c) above and otherfindings in relation to the implementation andoperation of this Chapter to the Joint Committeeas fully and expeditiously as possible; 


(g) establishing its rules and procedures; and 


(h) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall cooperate with other Sub-Committees in an appropriate manner with a view to avoidingunnecessary duplication of works with those of other Sub-Committees established under this Agreement. 


4. The composition, frequency of meetings and otherdetails of the Sub-Committee shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Consultative Group On Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="28352">1. The Sub-Committee shall establish a Consultative Groupin the Area of each Party. 


2. The composition, functions, and frequency of meetingsof the Consultative Group shall be set forth in theImplementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Liaison Office On Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="28353">1. Each Party shall designate and maintain a LiaisonOffice in the Area of the Party. 


2. The functions and other details of the Liaison Office shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Resolution Of Issues Through Diplomatic Channels" article_identifier="28354">1. A Party may, through diplomatic channels, request theother Party to take measures for resolving issues which therequesting Party considers adversely affecting the businessactivities of its persons in the Area of the requestedParty. 


2. The requested Party shall promptly respond to suchrequest, and shall, where warranted, endeavor to takemeasures to resolve such issues in accordance with its applicable laws and regulations. The requested Party shall inform the requesting Party of the measures it has taken.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="28355">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Cooperation" chapter_identifier="3366">
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="28356">The Parties shall promote cooperation under thisAgreement for their mutual benefits in order to facilitateand liberalize trade and investment between the Parties in order to assist development goals and to promote the wellbeing of the peoples of the Parties. For this purpose, the Parties shall cooperate between the Governments of theParties and, where necessary and appropriate, encourage andfacilitate cooperation between parties, one or both of whomare entities other than the Governments of the Parties, inthe following fields: 


(a) Human Resource Development 


(b) Financial Services 


(c) Information and Communications Technology 


(d) Energy and Environment 


(e) Science and Technology 


(f) Trade and Investment Promotion 


(g) Small and Medium Enterprises 


 (h) Tourism 


(i) Transportation 


(j) Road Development</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Areas And Forms" article_identifier="28357">The areas, forms, and other details of each field ofcooperation under this Chapter may be set forth in theImplementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Implementation" article_identifier="28358">1. The implementation of cooperation under this Chaptershall be subject to the availability of appropriated fundsand the applicable laws and regulations of each Party. 


2. Costs of cooperation under this Chapter shall be bornein as an equitable manner as possible between the Partiesthrough efficient and effective utilization of resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Sub-Committee On Cooperation" article_identifier="28359">1. For purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Cooperation(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 13. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchanging views and information on cooperationin each field and identifying ways of furthercooperation between the Parties; 


(b) monitoring, reviewing and discussing issuesconcerning the effective implementation of thisChapter; 


(c) reporting the findings and actions taken by theSub-Committee to the Joint Committee regardingissues relating to the implementation of thisChapter; 


(d) supervising the functions and activities of theworking groups to be established pursuant to theparagraph 6 below; 


(e) establishing its own rules and procedures; 


(f) discussing any issues related to this Chapter;and 


(g) performing other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 13. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall respect existing consultationmechanisms between the Parties for Official DevelopmentAssistance and other existing cooperation schemes and, asappropriate, share information with such mechanisms toensure effective and efficient implementation ofcooperative activities. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representativesof the Governments of the Parties. The Sub-Committee mayinvite representatives of relevant entities other than theGovernments of the Parties as resource persons withnecessary expertise relevant to the issues to be addressed. 


5. The Sub-Committee shall hold its inaugural meetingwithin one (1) year after this Agreement enters into force.Subsequent meetings of the Sub-Committee shall be held atsuch frequency as the Parties may agree on. 


6. The Sub-Committee may establish a working group foreach field of cooperation under the Sub-Committee. The functions, composition and other details of the workinggroups may be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 148" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="28360">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Dispute Avoidance And Settlement" chapter_identifier="3367">
      <article number="ARTICLE 149" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="28361">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, thisChapter shall apply with respect to the avoidance andsettlement of disputes between the Parties concerning theinterpretation or application of this Agreement. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights ofthe Parties to have recourse to dispute settlementprocedures available under any other internationalagreement to which both Parties are parties. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 above, once a disputesettlement procedure has been initiated under this Chapteror under any other international agreement to which bothParties are parties with respect to a particular dispute,that procedure shall be used to the exclusion of any otherprocedure for that particular dispute. However, this shall not apply if substantially separate and distinct rights orobligations under different international agreements are indispute. 


4. Paragraph 3 above shall not apply where the Partiesexpressly agree to the use of more than one (1) disputesettlement procedure in respect of a particular dispute. 


5. Where an infringement of the obligations assumed underthis Agreement constitutes an infringement of theobligations assumed under the WTO Agreement, the Partiesshall give priority consideration to having recourse to thedispute settlement procedures under the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 150" name="General Consultations For The Avoidance And Settlement Of Disputes" article_identifier="28362">1. For the purposes of avoiding disputes, a Party mayrequest in writing consultations with the other Party withregard to any matter on the interpretation or applicationof this Agreement. 


2. When a Party requests consultations pursuant toparagraph 1 above, the other Party shall afford adequateopportunity for consultations and shall reply promptly tothe request and enter into consultations in good faith. 


3. The Parties shall make every effort to avoid possibledisputes through consultations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 151" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="28363">1. Good offices, conciliation or mediation may berequested in writing at any time by either Party. They may begin at any time if the Parties agree. The use of good offices, conciliation or mediation may be terminated at anytime at the request of either Party. While good offices, conciliation or mediation are in progress, the requestingParty of the consultations referred to in paragraph 1 ofArticle 152 shall not request the establishment of anarbitral tribunal pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article 153. 


2. If the Parties agree, good offices, conciliation ormediation may continue while proceedings of the arbitraltribunal provided for in this Chapter are in progress.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 152" name="Special Consultations For Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="28364">1. For the purposes of settling disputes, either Partymay make a request in writing for consultations to theother Party if the requesting Party considers that anybenefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under thisAgreement is being nullified or impaired, as a result offailure of the requested Party to carry out itsobligations, or as a result of the application by therequested Party of measures which conflict with itsobligations, under this Agreement. 


2. Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the requestedParty shall: 


(a) enter into consultations within thirty (30) daysafter the date of receipt of the request forconsultations made pursuant to paragraph 1 above;or 


(b) enter into consultations within ten (10) daysafter the date of receipt of the request forconsultations made pursuant to paragraph 1 aboveif the procedure provided for in Article 150 wasutilized in respect of the same dispute and sixty
(60) days or more have elapsed from the date ofthe initiation of consultations under that Article. 

3. The Parties shall make every effort to reach amutually satisfactory resolution through consultations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 153" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="28365">1. Unless otherwise agreed by the Parties, if the Partiesfail to resolve a dispute through consultations providedfor in Article 152, either Party may request theestablishment of an arbitral tribunal in respect of thatdispute: 


(a) after ninety (90) days, which may be extended upto one hundred eighty (180) days upon the requestof the requested Party, from the date on whichthe requested Party receives the request forconsultations made pursuant to subparagraph 2(a)of Article 152; or 


(b) after sixty (60) days, which may be extended upto one hundred fifty (150) days upon the requestof the requested Party, from the date on whichthe requested Party receives the request forconsultations made pursuant to subparagraph 2 (b)of Article 152. 
2. Any request to establish an arbitral tribunal pursuantto this Article shall identify: 


(a) the legal basis of the complaint including theprovisions of this Agreement alleged to have beenbreached and any other relevant provisions; and 


(b) the factual basis for the complaint. 

3. Each Party shall, within thirty (30) days after thedate of receipt of the request for the establishment of anarbitral tribunal, appoint one (1) arbitrator who may beits national and propose up to three (3) candidates toserve as the third arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal (hereinafter referred to in this Chapteras “the chair”). The chair shall not be a national of either Party, nor have his or her usual place of residencein either Party, nor be employed by either Party. 


4. The Parties shall, in consultation with theirappointed arbitrators, if necessary, agree on and appointthe chair within sixty (60) days after the date of receiptof the request for the establishment of an arbitraltribunal, taking into account the candidates proposedpursuant to paragraph 3 above. 


5. If the Parties fail to agree on and appoint the chairpursuant to paragraph 4 above, the chair shall be chosen bylot from the candidates proposed pursuant to paragraph 3above within seven (7) days after the expiry of the periodprovided for in paragraph 4 above. 


6. The arbitral tribunal should be composed ofarbitrators with international legal expertise or relevanttechnical knowledge.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 154" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="28366">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article

153: 


(a) should consult with the Parties as appropriateand provide adequate opportunities for thedevelopment of a mutually satisfactoryresolution; 


(b) 	shall make its award in accordance with this Agreement and applicable rules of internationallaw, including customary international law; 


(c) shall set out, in its award, its findings of lawand fact, together with the reasons therefore;and 


(d) may, apart from giving its findings, include inits award suggested implementation options forthe Parties to consider in conjunction withArticle 157. 

2. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on the Parties. 


3. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Parties, suchrelevant information as it considers necessary andappropriate. The Parties shall respond promptly and fully to any request by an arbitral tribunal for such informationas the arbitral tribunal considers necessary andappropriate. 


4. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from anyrelevant source and may consult experts to obtain theiropinion on certain aspects of the matter. With respect to factual issues concerning a scientific or other technicalmatter raised by a Party, the arbitral tribunal may requestadvisory reports in writing from an expert or experts. The arbitral tribunal may, at the request of a Party or on itsown initiative, select, in consultation with the Parties,no fewer than two (2) scientific or technical experts whoshall assist the arbitral tribunal throughout itsproceedings, but who shall not have the right to vote inrespect of any decision to be made by the arbitraltribunal, including its award. 


5. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted without the presence of the Parties, and in the light ofthe information provided and the statements made.


6. The arbitral tribunal shall, within ninety (90) daysafter the date of its establishment, submit to the Partiesits draft award, including both descriptive part and itsfindings and conclusions, for the purposes of enabling theParties to review precise aspects of the draft award,unless the dispute is settled otherwise or the proceedingof the arbitral tribunal is terminated in accordance with Article 156. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit to the Parties its draft award within the aforementioned ninety (90) day period, it may extend thatperiod with the consent of the Parties. A Party may submit comments in writing to the arbitral tribunal on the draftaward within fifteen (15) days after the date of receipt ofthe draft award. 


7. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award within thirty (30) days after the date of receipt of the draftaward by the Parties. 


8. The arbitral tribunal shall endeavor to make its decisions, including its award, by consensus but may alsomake such decisions, including its award, by majority voteshould a consensus not be reached.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 155" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="28367">1. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 


2. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal, thedocuments submitted to it and the draft award referred to in paragraph 6 of Article 154 shall be kept confidential. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 above, either Party maymake public statements as to its views regarding thedispute, but shall treat as confidential, information andwritten submissions submitted by the other Party to thearbitral tribunal which that other Party has designated asconfidential. Where a Party has provided information orwritten submissions designated to be confidential, theother Party may request a non-confidential summary of theinformation or written submissions which may be disclosedpublicly. The Party to whom such a request is made may agree to such a request and submit such a summary, orrefuse the request without needing to ascribe any reasonsor justification. 


4. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attendany of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in theproceeding and to submit any relevant information,including rulings of the Dispute Settlement Body of theWorld Trade Organization. Any information or written submissions submitted by a Party to the arbitral tribunal,including any comments on the descriptive part of the draftaward and responses to questions put by the arbitraltribunal, shall be made available to the other Party. 


5. Unless otherwise agreed by the Parties, English shallbe the language used in the proceedings of, and submissionsto, the arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 156" name="Suspension And Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="28368">Even if the arbitral tribunal has been established and the proceedings are in progress, the Parties may agree toterminate, or suspend, the proceedings at any time byjointly so notifying the chair.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 157" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="28369">1. The award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant toArticle 154 (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the original award”) shall be complied with promptly. A Party which is required by the arbitral tribunal to complywith its award (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the implementing Party”) shall, within forty five (45)days after the date of issuance of the original award,notify in writing the other Party (hereinafter referred toin this Article as “the other Party”) as to the periodwhich it assesses to be reasonable and necessary in orderto implement the original award. The other Party may request consultations if it considers the period notifiedto be unacceptable, in which case the Parties shall enterinto consultations within thirty (30) days after the dateof receipt of the request. 


2. If the implementing Party considers it impracticableto comply with the original award within the implementationperiod as determined pursuant to paragraph 1 above, theimplementing Party shall no later than the expiry of thatimplementation period enter into consultations with theother Party, with a view to developing mutually acceptablecompensation. If no satisfactory compensation has been agreed within forty five (45) days after the date of expiryof that implementation period, the other Party may notifythe implementing Party that it intends to suspend theapplication to the implementing Party of the obligations ofthe other Party under this Agreement. 


3. If the other Party considers that the measures takenby the implementing Party to comply with the original awarddo not comply with the original award, it may requestconsultations, in which case the Parties shall promptlyenter into consultations. 


4. Either Party may refer matters arising from theimplementation of the original award to an arbitraltribunal if: 


(a) consultations were initiated under paragraph 1above, and the Parties fail to reach agreement onthe period for implementation within thirty (30)days after the date of receipt of the request; or 


(b) consultations were initiated under paragraph 3above, and the Parties fail to resolve thematter, and at least forty five (45) days haveelapsed since the date of the expiration of theperiod for implementation provided for inparagraph 1 above. 

5. If the arbitral tribunal to which the matter is referred pursuant to subparagraph 4(b) above confirms thatthe implementing Party has failed to comply with theoriginal award within the implementation period asdetermined pursuant to paragraph 1 or subparagraph 4(a)above, the other Party may, within thirty (30) days afterthe date of such confirmation by the arbitral tribunal,notify the implementing Party that it intends to suspendthe application to the implementing Party of theobligations of the other Party under this Agreement. 


6. Suspension of the application of obligations pursuantto paragraph 2 or 5 above may only be implemented at leastthirty (30) days after the date of the notification inaccordance with that paragraph. Such suspension: 


(a) shall not be effected if, in respect of thedispute to which the suspension relates,consultations, or proceedings before an arbitraltribunal are in progress; 


(b) shall be temporary, and shall be discontinuedwhen the Parties reach a mutually satisfactoryresolution or where compliance with the originalaward is effected; 


(c) 	shall be restricted to the level of nullification or impairment that is attributable to the failureto comply with the original award; and 


(d) 	shall be restricted to the same sector or sectors to which the nullification or impairment relates,unless it is not practicable or effective tosuspend obligations in such sector or sectors. 

7. If the implementing Party considers that therequirements in paragraph 2, 5 or 6 above have not beenmet, it may request consultations with the other Party.The other Party shall enter into consultations within ten
(10) days after the date of receipt of the request. If the Parties fail to resolve matters within thirty (30) daysafter the date of receipt of the request for consultationspursuant to this paragraph, either Party may refer thematter to an arbitral tribunal. 

8. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes of this Article shall, wherever possible, have asits arbitrators, the arbitrators of the original arbitraltribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators tothe arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposesof this Article shall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 3through 6 of Article 153. Unless the Parties agree to a different period, such arbitral tribunal shall issue itsaward within sixty (60) days after the date when the matteris referred to it. The award of the arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall be final and bindingon the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 158" name="Expenses" article_identifier="28370">Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the expenses ofthe arbitral tribunal, including the remuneration of itsarbitrators, shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 159" name="Rules Of Procedure" article_identifier="28371">Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the details andprocedures for the arbitral tribunal provided for in thisChapter shall be in accordance with the Rules of Procedureto be adopted within the first year of the date of entryinto force of this Agreement and to be modified, ifnecessary, by the Joint Committee.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 16" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="3368">
      <article number="ARTICLE 160" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="28372">The table of contents and headings of the Chapters andthe Articles of this Agreement are inserted for convenienceof reference only and shall not affect the interpretationof this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 161" name="General Review" article_identifier="28373">The Parties shall undertake a general review of theAgreement and its implementation and operation in 2011 andevery five (5) years thereafter, unless otherwise agreed byboth Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 162" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="28374">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall form anintegral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 163" name="Amendment" article_identifier="28375">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between theParties. Such amendment shall be approved by the Partiesin accordance with their respective legal procedures. The amendment shall enter into force on the date to be agreedon by the Parties and by means of diplomatic notesexchanged between the Governments of the Parties informingeach other that their respective legal procedures necessaryfor its entry into force have been completed. 


2. If the amendments relate only to the following areas,the amendments may be made by diplomatic notes exchangedbetween the Governments of the Parties: 


(a) Annex 2 referred to in Chapter 3 Product SpecificRules; 


(b) Annex 3 referred to in Chapter 3 Minimum DataRequirement for Certificate of Origin; or 


(c) Part 2 of Annex 4 referred to in Chapter 6Sectoral Annex in relation to Article 61.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 164" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="28376">This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtiethday after the date on which the Governments of the Partiesexchange diplomatic notes informing each other that theirrespective legal procedures necessary for entry into forceof this Agreement have been completed. It shall remain in force unless terminated as provided for in Article 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 165" name="Termination" article_identifier="28377">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving,through diplomatic channels, one-year advance notice inwriting to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="3369">
      <article article_identifier="28378">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being dulyauthorized by their respective Governments, have signedthis Agreement. 

DONE at Helsinki on this ninth day of September, 2006in duplicate in the English language. 

For Japan: 	For the Republic ofthe Philippines: 

小泉純一郎	                       Gloria M. Arroyo</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
