<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Eurasian Economic Union (EAEU)</name>
    <type>Customs Union &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>909</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>440</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2014-05-29</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2015-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2014-12-12</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">RUS</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">ARM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KGZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">RUS</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">910</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">922</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/909/TOA/English/EAEU Treaty (unofficial translation).doc</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://economy.gov.ru/minec/about/structure/depSNG/agreement-eurasian-economic-union</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="4494">
      <article article_identifier="39007">TREATY ON THE EURASIAN ECONOMIC UNION
  
  The Republic of Belarus, the Republic of Kazakhstan and the Russian
  Federation, hereinafter referred to as the Parties,
based on of the Declaration on
  Eurasian Economic Integration dated 18th of
  November, 2011,
guided by the principle of the
  sovereign equality of States, the necessity of unconditional
  observance of the principle of priority of constitutional rights and
  freedoms of man and citizen,
desiring to enhance solidarity and
  deepen cooperation between their nations while respecting their
  history, culture and traditions,
expressing the confidence that
  further development of the Eurasian economic integration meets the
  national interests of the Parties,
motivated by the desire to
  strengthen the economies of the member States of the Eurasian Economic
  Union and to ensure their harmonious development and convergence, as
  well as to ensure sustainable growth in business activity, balanced
  trade and fair competition,
ensuring economic progress by means
  of joint activities intended to face common challenges of Member
  states of the Eurasian Economic Union on sustainable economic
  development, comprehensive modernization and strengthening the
  competitiveness of national economies within the global economy,
confirming the efforts for further
  strengthen of mutually beneficial and equal economic cooperation with
  other countries and international integration associations as well as
  international organizations,
taking into account the norms,
  rules and principles of the World Trade Organization,
reaffirming their commitments to
  the purposes and principles of the Charter of the United Nations, and
  other generally accepted principles and norms of international law,

  have agreed on the following.
  UNION</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION I" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="4495">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Establishment Of The Eurasian Economic Union." article_identifier="39008">Legal personality

  1. Under the present Treaty Parties shall establish the Eurasian
  Economic Union (hereinafter - the EAEU) and ensure free movement of
  goods, services, capital and labor as well as coordinated, agreed or
  common policy in the economic sectors defined in the present Treaty
  and in the international agreements within the EAEU.

  2. The EAEU shall be an international organization of regional
  economic integration that holds the international legal personality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39009">For the purposes of the present Treaty the following terms shall be
  used and understood as follows:

  “harmonization of legislation” - approximation of legislation of the
  member States aimed at the establishment of a similar (comparable)
  legal regulatory framework in particular areas;

  “member States” – states that are members of the EAEU and the Parties
  of the present Treaty;

  “officials” - citizens of the member States appointed to the positions
  of the Directors of the Eurasian Commission Departments, and deputy
  Directors of the Eurasian Commission Departments, as well as Head of
  the Secretariat of the Court of the EAEU, and deputy Head of the
  Secretariat of the Court of the EAEU and counsellors of the judges of
  the Court of the EAEU;

  “Single Economic space” - area consisting of the territories of the
  member States that provides for similar (comparable) and uniform
  mechanisms for economic regulation based on market principles and
  application of harmonized or unified legal norms, and common
  infrastructure;

  “common policy” - policy implemented by the member States in
  particular areas specified under the present Treaty, assuming
  application by member States of uniform legal regulation, also on the
  basis of decisions of the bodies of the EAEU within their authorities;

  “international agreements within the EAEU” - international agreements
  concluded between the member States on the issues related to the
  functioning and development of the EAEU;

  “agreements of the EAEU with a third party” - international agreements
  concluded with third States, their integration associations and
  international organizations;

  “common (single) market” - a set of economic relations within the EAEU
  that provides for free movement of goods, services, capital and labor;

  “disposal” - an act of the institutions of the EAEU, having
  organizational and administrative nature;

  “decision” - an act of the institutions of the EAEU, having a legal
  nature;

  “coordinated policy” - a policy, assuming the implementation of
  cooperation among member States on the basis of common approaches,
  approved within the bodies of the EAEU, aimed to achieve the
  objectives of the EAEU under the present Treaty;

  “agreed policy” – a policy implemented by member States in various
  fields, assuming harmonization of legal regulation, also on the basis
  of the decisions of the EAEU, to the extent necessary to achieve the
  objectives of the EAEU under the present Treaty;

  “employees” - nationals of the member States of the EAEU, working in
  the bodies of the EAEU on the basis of concluded labor agreements
  (contracts) and who at the same time work as non-officials;

  “Customs union” - a form of trade and economic integration of the
  member States that provides for a unified customs territory free from
  customs duties (other duties, taxes and charges having equivalent
  effect), non-tariff measures, special protective antidumping and
  countervailing measures, but with Common External Tariff and common
  assessment methods regulating foreign trade with third countries;

  “third party”- a state that is non-member of the EAEU, an
  international organization or international integration association;

  “unification of legislation” - approximation of legislation of the
  member States aimed at establishing of the identical mechanisms of
  legal regulation in particular areas defined under the present Treaty.

  Other terms used in the present Treaty shall have the definition
  specified in the relevant Sections and Annexes to the present Treaty.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION II" name="Basic Principles, Objectives, Competence And Law Of The Union" chapter_identifier="4496">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Basic Principles Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39010">The EAEU shall operate within the competence granted to it by the
  member States in accordance with the present Treaty, based on the
  following principles:

  respect the commonly recognized principles of the international law,
  including the principles of sovereign equality of the member States
  and their territorial integrity;

  respect the differences of political structures of the member States;

  provide the mutually beneficial cooperation, equality and the national
  interests of the Parties;

  ensure the principles of market economy and fair competition;

  functioning of the Customs union without exceptions and limitations
  after the transitional periods.

  member States shall create favorable conditions for fulfillment of the
  functions of the EAEU and shall refrain from measures that could
  prevent the achievement of the objectives of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Main Objectives Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39011">The main objectives of the EAEU shall include:
the creation of conditions for stable economic development
of the member States in order to improve the living standards of their people;
  the desire to create a common market for goods, services, capital and
  labor within the EAEU;

  comprehensive modernization, cooperation and competitiveness of
  national economies within the global economy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Competence" article_identifier="39012">1. The EAEU shall perform the scope of functions within the limits
  established under the present Treaty and international agreements
  within the EAEU.

  2. Member States shall carry out coordinated and agreed policy within
  the limits established under the present Treaty and international
  agreements within the EAEU.

  3. In other spheres of the economy the member States shall make an
  effort to implement a coordinated or agreed policy in accordance with
  the basic principles and objectives of the EAEU.

  With this purpose by decision of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council
  the subsidiary bodies (boards of the heads of state bodies of the
  Parties, working groups, special commissions) could be established in
  the corresponding areas and (or) the instructions for coordination of
  the interaction between Parties in the corresponding areas could be
  given by the Eurasian Economic Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="The Law Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39013">1. The law of the EAEU shall include:

  the present Treaty;

  international agreements within the EAEU;

  international agreements between the EAEU and the third party;

  decisions and resolutions of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council,
  Eurasian Intergovernmental Council as well as Eurasian Economic
  Commission that were accepted according to their authorities provided
  under the present Treaty as well as international agreements within
  the EAEU.

  Resolutions of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council and the Eurasian
  Intergovernmental Council shall be performed by member States in
  accordance with their national legislation.

  2. International agreements of the EAEU with a third party shall not
  contradict to the basic objectives, principles and rules of
  functioning of the EAEU.

  3. In case of conflict between international agreements within the
  EAEU and the present Treaty, the present Treaty shall have a priority.

  Resolutions and orders of the EAEU shall not be inconsistent with the
  present Treaty and international agreements within the EAEU.

  4. In case of conflict between the decisions of the Supreme Eurasian
  Economic Council, the Eurasian Intergovernmental Council and the
  Eurasian Economic Commission:

  decisions of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council take precedence
  over the decisions of the Eurasian Intergovernmental Council and the
  Eurasian Economic Commission;

  decisions of the Eurasian Intergovernmental Council take precedence
  over the decisions of the Eurasian Economic Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="International Activity Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39014">1. The EAEU shall have the right to exercise within its competence
  international activity aimed at achievement of objectives of the EAEU.
  Within such activity, the EAEU shall have the right to engage in
  international cooperation with states, international organizations and
  international integration associations and independently or together
  with the member States conclude agreements on matters corresponding to
  its competence.

  The procedure of international cooperation of the EAEU shall be
  established by the decision of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council.
  The issues concerning conclusion of agreements of the EAEU with a
  third party shall be determined by the international treaty within the
  EAEU.

  2. Negotiations on the drafts of international agreements of the EAEU
  with a third party, as well as their signing shall be performed
  according to the decision of the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council
  after implementation of the relevant internal procedures of the member
  States.

  The decision on the expression of consent of the EAEU to be bound by
  an international Treaty between the EAEU and a third party,
  termination, suspension or withdrawal of an international Treaty shall
  be adopted by the Supreme Eurasian Economic Council after
  implementation of the relevant internal procedures of the member
  States.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION III" name="Bodies Of The Eaeu" chapter_identifier="4497">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Bodies Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39015">1. Bodies of the EAEU shall include:

  Supreme Eurasian Economic Council (hereinafter - the Supreme Council);

  Eurasian Intergovernmental Council (hereinafter - the
  Intergovernmental Council);

  Eurasian Economic Commission (hereinafter - the Commission, the EEC);

  Court of the Eurasian Economic Union (hereinafter - the Court of the
  EAEU).

  2. Bodies of the EAEU shall act within the authorities that are given
  to them under the present Treaty and international agreements within
  the EAEU.

  3. Bodies of the EAEU shall act on the basis of principles specified
  in Article 3 of the present Treaty.

  4. Presidency at the Supreme Council, the Intergovernmental Council
  and the Council of the Commission shall be performed on a rotational
  basis in the alphabetical order of Russian language by one member
  State of the EAEU within one calendar year without right for
  prolongation.

  5. Conditions of residence for the bodies of the EAEU on the territory
  of the member States shall be determined by separate international
  agreements between the EAEU and the states of residence.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Appointments Within The Structural Subdivisions" article_identifier="39016">of the Permanent Bodies of the EAEU

  1. The right to take an appointment in the structural subdivisions of
  the permanent bodies of the EAEU shall belong to nationals of the
  member States with relevant education and expertise.

  2. Officials of the Commission department cannot be citizens of one
  state. The selection of candidates for these positions shall be
  performed by the competition commission of the EEC with respect to the
  principle of equal representation of the Parties. Candidates of the
  competition for these positions shall be presented by the member of
  the Council of the Commission from the relevant Party.

  3. Selection of candidates for positions at the Commission departments
  shall be performed by the Commission on a competitive basis, taking
  into account the Parties’ equity in the financing of the Commission.

  4. Composition of competition commission on selection of candidates
  for positions referred to in paragraph 2 of the present article shall
  include all members of the Council of the Commission, except for the
  Chairman of the Council of the Commission.

  Competition committee of the EEC shall take its decisions in the form
  of recommendations by a majority vote and submit them to the Chairman
  of the Collegium of the Commission for approval. If the Chairman of
  the Collegium of the Commission takes a decision in regard to a
  particular candidate that conflicts with the recommendation of the
  competition commission, the issue shall be submitted to the Council of
  the Commission for a final decision.

  Regulations concerning the competition commission of the EEC
  (including the rules of the competition), its composition, as well as
  qualification requirements for candidates for positions of directors
  and deputy directors of departments of the Commission shall be
  approved by the Council of the Commission.

  5. Procedure for the selection of candidates and appointment to
  positions in the Apparatus of the Court of the EAEU shall be
  established in accordance with the documents governing the activity of
  the Court of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Supreme Council" article_identifier="39017">1.  Supreme Council shall be the supreme body of the EAEU
  

  2. The members of the Supreme Council shall be the Heads of the member
  States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Procedure Of Work Of The Supreme Council" article_identifier="39018">1. Meetings of the Supreme Council shall be held at least once a year.

  In order to consider vital matters of the EAEU the extraordinary
  meetings of the Supreme Council shall be held at the initiative of any
  member State or the Chairman of the Supreme Council.

  2. Meetings of the Supreme Council shall be held under the guidance of
  the Chairman of the Supreme Council.

  Chairman of the Supreme Council shall:

  chair the meetings of the Supreme Council;

  organize the functioning of the Supreme Council;

  performs general management in preparation of the issues that shall be
  submitted to the Supreme Council for consideration.

  In the case of early termination of authorities of the Chairman of the
  Supreme Council a new member of the Supreme Council of the presiding
  member State shall exercise the powers of the Chairman of the Supreme
  Council for the remaining period.

  3. Chairman of the Supreme Council may invite members of the Council
  of Commission, the Chairman of the Collegium of Commission and other
  persons to participate in the meetings of the Supreme Council.

  List of participants and form of meetings shall be determined by the
  Chairman of the Supreme Council to be agreed with the members of the
  Supreme Council.

  The agenda of the meetings of the Supreme Council shall be formulated
  by the Commission on the basis of suggestions from member States.

  The attendance at the meetings of the Supreme Council of the
  accredited representatives of the mass media at the meetings of the
  Supreme Council shall be approved by the Chairman of the Supreme
  Council.

  4. Procedure for organization of the meetings of the Supreme Council
  shall be approved by the Supreme Council.

  5. Organizational, informational material and technical support for
  preparation and conduction of the meetings of the Supreme Council
  shall be provided by the Commission with assistance of the host member
  State. The meetings of the Supreme Council shall be financed from the
  budget of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Authorities Of The Supreme Council" article_identifier="39019">1. The Supreme Council shall consider fundamental issues of activity
  of the EAEU, define the strategy, direction and prospects of
  integration and take decisions aimed at achieving the objectives of
  the EAEU.

  2. The Supreme Council shall have the following responsibilities:

  1) elaborate the strategy, direction and prospects for the formation
  and development of the EAEU and take decisions aimed at achieving the
  objectives of the EAEU;

  2) approve the composition of the Collegium of Commission, allocate
  responsibilities among members of the Collegium of Commission and
  terminate their powers;

  3) appoint the Chairman of the Collegium of Commission and, if
  necessary, take a decision on early termination of his powers;

  4) upon suggestion of member States appoint the judges of the Court of
  the EAEU;

  5) approve the working order and interior regulations of the
  Commission;

  6) approve the budget of the EAEU, regulation on the budget of the
  EAEU and the report on implementation of budget of the EAEU;

  7) determine the size (scale) of the equity assessments of the Parties
  to the budget of the EAEU;

  8) upon request of any member State of the EAEU reconsider decisions
  adopted by the Intergovernmental Council and the Commission subject to
  the provisions of subparagraph 7 of Article 16;

  9) on the initiative of the Intergovernmental Council or the
  Commission consider the issues on which consensus was not achieved;

  10) request the opinion of the Court of the EAEU;

  11) approve the procedure for checking accuracy and completeness of
  information about income, assets and obligations of the judges of the
  Court of the EAEU, officials and staff of the Court of the EAEU and
  their family members;

  12) determine the procedure for accession of new members to the EAEU
  and termination of the membership in the EAEU;

  13) take decisions on granting observer or candidate status on
  accession to the EAEU;

  14) approve the procedure on implementation of international activity
  of the EAEU;

  15) take decisions on negotiations on behalf of the EAEU with third
  parties, including decisions on conclusion of international agreements
  and granting the right to negotiate as well as on expression of
  consent of the EAEU to be bound by international agreement with third
  party, temporary application, termination or suspension of
  international agreement;

  16) approve the overall number of staff of the EAEU, the
  characteristics of officials representation from the nationals of
  member States in the bodies of the EAEU, provided by the member States
  on a competitive basis;

  17) approve procedure of remuneration for the work of members of the
  Collegium of the Commission, judges of the Court of the EAEU,
  officials and employees of the EAEU;

  18) approve the rules on the external audit (control) within the
  bodies of the EAEU;

  19) consider the results of the external audit (control) within the
  bodies of the EAEU;

  20) approve the symbols of the EAEU;

  21) give orders to the Intergovernmental Council and the Commission;

  22) decide on establishment of subsidiary bodies in the relevant
  areas;

  23) exercise other powers provided under the present Treaty and
  international agreements within the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Decisions And Orders Of The Supreme Council" article_identifier="39020">1. The Supreme Council shall take decisions and orders.

  2. Decisions and orders of the Supreme Council shall be taken by
  consensus.

  Decisions of the Supreme Council, related to the termination of
  membership of a member State in the EAEU, shall be taken by “consensus
  minus the vote of the member State that has notified its intention to
  terminate its membership in the EAEU”.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Intergovernmental Council" article_identifier="39021">Intergovernmental Council shall be the body of the EAEU that consists
  of the Heads of Governments of the member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Procedure Of The Intergovernmental Council Functioning" article_identifier="39022">1. Meetings of the Intergovernmental Council shall be held when
  required but at least two times a year.

  In order to consider urgent issues of the EAEU extraordinary meeting
  of the Intergovernmental Council shall be convened at the initiative
  of any member State or the Chairman of the Intergovernmental Council;

  2. Meetings of the Intergovernmental Council shall be held under the
  guidance of the Chairman of the Intergovernmental Council.

  Chairman of the Intergovernmental Council shall:

  held meetings of the Intergovernmental Council;

  arrange the work of the Intergovernmental Council;

  perform general management in preparation of the issues that shall be
  submitted to the Intergovernmental Council for consideration.

  In case of early termination of powers of the Chairman of the
  Intergovernmental Council a new member of the Intergovernmental
  Council of the presiding member State shall exercise the authority of
  the Chairman of the Intergovernmental Council for the remaining
  period.

  3. Members of the Council of Commission, the Chairman of Collegium of
  the Commission and other persons shall participate at the meetings of
  the Intergovernmental Council by the invitation from the Chairman of
  the Intergovernmental Council.

  List of participants and format of meetings shall be determined by the
  Chairman of the Intergovernmental Council by agreement with the
  members of the Intergovernmental Council.

  The agenda of the meetings of the Intergovernmental Council shall be
  drawn by the Commission on the basis of suggestions from member
  States.

  The presence of accredited media representatives at the meetings of
  the Intergovernmental Council shall be agreed by the Chairman of the
  Intergovernmental Council.

  4. Procedure for arrangement of the meetings of the Intergovernmental
  Council shall be approved by the Intergovernmental Council.

  5. Organizational, informational material and technical support for
  preparation and conduction of the meetings of the Intergovernmental
  Council shall be provided by the Commission with the assistance of the
  host member State. Financial support of the meetings of the
  Intergovernmental Council shall be provided from the budget of the
  EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Authorities Of The Intergovernmental Council" article_identifier="39023">Intergovernmental Council shall perform the following functions:

      ensure the implementation and control of the implementation of the
      present Treaty, International agreements within the EAEU and the
      decisions of the Supreme Council;
    
  2) upon proposal of the Council of the Commission consider issues on
  which consensus is not achieved;

  3) give instructions to the Commission;

  4) propose to the Supreme Council candidates for the members of the
  Council and Collegium of the Commission;

  5) approve drafts of the budget of the EAEU, regulations on the budget
  of the EAEU and reports on performance of the budget of the EAEU;

      approve Rules on audit of financial and economic activities of the
      bodies of the EAEU, standards and methodology of audit of
      financial and economic activities of the bodies of the EAEU, take
      decisions on audit of financial and economic activities of the
      bodies of the EAEU and determine the terms of their conduction;
    
  7) upon proposal of any member State of the EAEU consider issues on
  reversal or amendment of the approved decision of the Commission or,
  if not agreed, submit them for consideration of the Supreme Council;

  8) take a decision on suspension of implementation of decisions of the
  Council or Collegium of the Commission;

  9) approve the procedure for verification of accuracy and completeness
  of information about income, assets and obligations of the members of
  the Collegium of the EAEU, officials and staff of the Commission and
  their family members;

  10) exercise other powers provided under the present Treaty and
  international agreements within the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Decisions And Orders Of The Intergovernmental Council" article_identifier="39024">1. The Intergovernmental Council shall takes decisions and orders.

  2. Decisions and orders of the Intergovernmental Council shall be
  taken by consensus.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Commission" article_identifier="39025">1. The Commission shall be an institutional body of the EAEU. The
  Commission shall consist of the Council and Collegium.

  2. Commission shall take decisions, orders and recommendations.

  Decisions, orders and recommendations of the Council of the Commission
  shall be taken by consensus;

  Decisions, orders and recommendations of the Collegium of the
  Commission shall be taken by the qualified majority or by consensus.

  The Supreme Council shall define a list of sensitive issues on which
  the Collegium of Commission shall take decisions by consensus.

  The qualified majority shall consists of two thirds of the total
  number of members of the Collegium of Commission.

  3. Status, objectives, composition, functions, powers and procedures
  of the Commission shall be determined according to Annex 1 hereto.

  4. Residence of the Commission shall be the city of Moscow, the
  Russian Federation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Court Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39026">1. Court of the EAEU shall be an institutional judicial body of the
  EAEU.

  2. Status, structure, competence, procedure of functioning and
  establishment of the Court of the EAEU shall be determined by the
  Statute of Court of the EAEU according to Annex 2 hereto.

  3. Residence of the Court of the EAEU shall be the city of Minsk, the
  Republic of Belarus.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION IV" name="Budget Of The Eaeu" chapter_identifier="4498">
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Budget Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39027">1. Funding for the activity of bodies of the EAEU shall be provided
  from the budget of the EAEU, that shall be formed in the manner
  determined under the Regulation on the budget of the EAEU.

  The EAEU budget for the next fiscal year shall be formed in Russian
  rubles by means of contributions of member States. Size (scale) of
  contribution of member States to the budget of the EAEU shall be
  established by the Supreme Council.

  EAEU budget must be balanced in income and expenditure. The fiscal
  year begins on the 1st of January 1 and
  ends on the 31st of December.

  2. Budget of the EAEU and Regulation on a Budget of the Eurasian
  Economic Union shall be approved by the Supreme Council.

  Amendments to the budget of the EAEU and in the Regulation on a Budget
  of the Eurasian Economic Union shall be made by the Supreme Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Audit Of Financial And Economic Activity Of The Eaeu’s Bodies" article_identifier="39028">To conduct control over the execution of the EAEU budget, an audit of
  financial and economic activity of the EAEU shall be conducted at
  least once in 2 years.

  At the initiative of any State Member an audit on specific issues of
  financial and economic activity of EAEU’s bodies might be carried out.

  Audits of financial and economic activity of the EAEU’s bodies shall
  be carried out by the group of auditors which consists of
  representatives of the state financial control authorities of the
  State Members.

  The results of conducted audits of financial and economic activity of
  the EAEU’s bodies shall be submitted in the prescribed manner for the
  consideration of the Intergovernmental Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="External Audit (Control)" article_identifier="39029">The external audit (control) shall be carried out in order to
  determine the efficiency of formation, management and disposal of the
  funds of the EAEU’s budget, the efficiency of the use of property and
  other assets of the EAEU. External audit (control) shall be carried
  out by the group of inspectors that formed from the representatives of
  the supreme bodies of state financial control of the State Members.
  Standards and methodology of the external audit (control) jointly
  shall be determined by the supreme bodies of state financial control
  of the State Members.

  The results of conducted external audit (control) in the bodies of the
  EAEU shall be submitted in the prescribed manner for consideration to
  the Supreme Council.

SECOND PART
CUSTOMS UNION</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION V" name="Information Interaction And Statistics" chapter_identifier="4499">
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Information Interaction Within The Eaeu" article_identifier="39030">1. Arrangements aimed at ensuring information cooperation using the
  information and communication technologies and cross-border space of
  trust within the EEU shall be developed and implemented in order to
  ensure informational support of the integration processes in all areas
  affecting the functioning of the EAEU,

  2. Exchange of information during the performance of common processes
  within the EEU is carried out by use of an integrated information
  system of the EAEU, supporting the integration of territorially
  distributed state information resources and information systems of the
  authorized bodies, as well as information resources and information
  systems of the Commission.

  3. To ensure effective integration of state information resources and
  information systems the member States shall carry a coordinated policy
  in the field of information and information technology.

  4. While using the software and hardware and information technologies
  the member States shall ensure the protection of intellectual property
  used or produced during the process of interaction.

  5. Fundamental principles of information exchange and coordination of
  its implementation within the EEU as well as the procedure of
  formation and development of an integrated information system are
  determined according to the Annex 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Official Statistical Information Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39031">order to provide effective functioning and development of the EEU the
  official statistical information of the EEU shall be formed.

  2. Formation of official statistical information provided of the EEU
  shall be carried out in accordance with the following principles:

  1) professional independence;

  2) scientific justification and comparability;

  3) completeness and accuracy;

  4) the actuality and promptness;

  5) open and general availability;

  6) cost effectiveness;

  7) statistical confidentiality.

  3. Formation and distribution of official statistical information of
  the EEU shall be performed in accordance with the procedure specified
  in the Annex 4.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION VI" name="Functioning Of The Customs Union" chapter_identifier="4500">
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Principles Of Functioning Of The Customs Union" article_identifier="39032">Within the framework of the Customs Union of member States:
    
      internal market of goods shall operate;
    
      Common External Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union and other
      common measures regulating foreign trade in goods with third
      parties shall be applied;
    
      common regime for trade in goods with third parties shall operate;
    
      common customs regulation shall be conducted;
    
      free movement of goods without customs declarations and state
      control (transport, sanitary, veterinary and sanitary,
      phytosanitary quarantine), is applied between territories of the
      member States, except for the cases, provided in this Treaty.
    
      2. For the purposes of this Treaty, the following definitions are
      used:
    
  “import customs duty” – compulsory payment, imposed by customs bodies
  of the member States in terms of imports to the customs territory of
  the EAEU;

  “Common Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic Activity if the
  Eurasian Economic Union” - commodity nomenclature of foreign economic
  activity based on Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding System
  of the World Customs Organization and Common Commodity Nomenclature of
  Foreign Economic Activity of the Commonwealth of Independent States;

  “Common External Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union (CET)” – a set
  of customs duty rates applied for goods being imported (imported) to
  the customs territory of the EAEU from third countries, classified in
  accordance with the Common Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic
  Activity of the Eurasian Economic Union;

  “tariff preferences” – import customs duty exemption or lowering of
  import customs duty rates in respect of goods, originating from
  countries, which form a free trade zone with the EAEU, or lowering of
  import customs duty rates in respect of goods originating from
  developing and least-developed countries-beneficiaries of the common
  system of tariff preferences of the EAEU</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Enrollment And Distribution Of Import Custom Duties" article_identifier="39033">(Other Duties, Taxes and Charges Having Equivalent Power)

  Paid (recovered) import custom duties shall be enrolled and
  distributed among the budgets of the member States.

  Enrollment and distribution of amounts of import customs duties and
  their transition to the budgets of the member States shall comply with
  the procedure specified in the Annex 5 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Establishment And Functioning Of Free (Special) Economic Zones And Free Warehouses" article_identifier="39034">In order to facilitate social and economic development of the member
  States, attraction of investments, establishment and development of
  industries, based on new technologies, development of transport
  infrastructure, tourism and health resort areas and other aims within
  the territories of member States free (special) economic zones (SEZs)
  and free warehouses shall be established and function.

  Conditions of establishment and functioning of free (special) economic
  zones and free warehouses are stipulated by international agreements
  within the framework of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Internal Market" article_identifier="39035">1. The EAEU shall take measures to ensure the functioning of the
  internal market in accordance with the provisions of this Treaty.

  2. Internal market covers economic space in which in accordance with
  the provisions of this Treaty a free movement of goods, persons,
  services and capital shall be provided.

  3. Within the functioning of the internal market in mutual trade of
  goods the member State shall not apply import and export customs
  duties (other duties, taxes and charges having equivalent effect),
  non-tariff measures, special safeguard, antidumping and countervailing
  measures, except otherwise provided in this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Exceptions From The Functioning Procedure Of Internal Market Of Goods" article_identifier="39036">1. Member States may apply restrictions in the mutual trade of goods
  (provided that these measures do not serve as unjustifiable
  discrimination or disguised restriction on trade), if such
  restrictions are necessary for:

  1) protection of human life and health;

  2) protection of public morals and public order;

  3) environmental protection;

  4) the protection of animal and plant species and cultural values;

  5) implementation of international obligations;

  6) the defense and security of the member State.

  2. Due to the reasons set out in paragraph 1 of this Article,
  sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine
  measures could be imposed at the internal market in accordance with
  the procedure determined by Section XI of this Treaty.

  3. Due to the reasons set out in paragraph 1 of this Article, the
  turnover of certain categories of goods can be limited.

  Procedure of movement or turnnover of such goods at the customs
  territory of the EAEU is stipulated in accordance with this Treaty and
  the international agreements within the framework of the EAEU.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION VII" name="Regulation Of Drugs And Medical Products Circulation" chapter_identifier="4501">
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Formation Of A Common Market Of Pharmaceuticals" article_identifier="39037">1. Member States within the framework of the EAEU shall establish a
  common market of pharmaceuticals which are consistent to standards of
  appropriate pharmaceutical practice, based on the following
  principles:

  1) harmonization and unification of the legal requirements of the
  member States in the field of drugs circulation;

  2) ensuring the unity of the mandatory requirements for the quality,
  effectiveness and safety of drugs which are circulated at the
  territory of the EAEU;

  3) adoption of common rules in the field of drugs circulation;

  4) development and application of the identical or comparable methods
  of research and monitoring in assessment of the quality, effectiveness
  and safety of drugs;

  5) harmonization of member States legislation in the field of control
  (supervision) in the field of drugs circulation;

  6) implementation of licensing and enforcement functions in the field
  of drugs circulation via relevant competent authorities of the member
  States.

  2. Functioning of the common market of pharmaceuticals within the EAEU
  shall be realized in accordance with an international agreement within
  the EAEU based on provisions of Article 100 of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Establishment Of Common Market Of Medical Products (Healthcare Products And Medical Devices)" article_identifier="39038">1. Member States within the framework of the EAEU shall establish the
  common market of medical products (healthcare products and medical
  devices) based on the following principles:

  1) harmonization of the legal requirements of the member States in the
  field of medical products (healthcare products and medical devices)
  circulation;

  2) ensuring the unity of the mandatory requirements for the
  effectiveness and safety of medical products (healthcare products and
  medical devices) in circulation at the territory of the EAEU;

  3) adoption of common rules in the field of medical products
  (healthcare products and medical devices) circulation;

  4) determination of common approaches for the establishment of system
  on provision of safety of medical products (healthcare products and
  medical devices);

  5) harmonization of legislation of member States in the field of
  control (supervision) in the field of medical products (healthcare
  products and medical devices) circulation;

  2. Functioning of the common market of the medical products
  (healthcare products and medical devices) within the framework of the
  EAEU shall be realized in accordance with an international agreement
  within the EAEU based on provisions of Article 100 of this Treaty.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION VIII" name="Customs Regulation" chapter_identifier="4502">
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Customs Regulation In The Eaeu" article_identifier="39039">Common customs regulations are conducted within the EAEU in accordance
  with the Customs Code of the EAEU and international agreements and
  acts governing customs relations, constituting the right of the EAEU,
  as well as in accordance with the provisions of this Treaty.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION IX" name="Foreign Trade Policy" chapter_identifier="4503">
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Objectives And Principles Of Foreign Trade Policy Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39040">1. The foreign trade policy of the EAEU is aimed at facilitation of
  sustainable economic development of the member States, diversification
  of the economies, innovative development, increase in volumes and
  improvement of structure of trade and investment, acceleration of
  integration processes, as well as at further development of the EAEU
  as efficient and competitive organization within the global economy.

  2. The basic principles of execution of foreign trade policy of the
  EAEU are as follows:

  application of measures and mechanisms of execution of foreign trade
  policy of the EAEU that are not more burdensome for participants of
  foreign trade activity of the member States than necessary to ensure
  the effective achievement of the objectives of the EAEU;

  transparency in the drafting, adoption and application of measures and
  mechanisms of execution of foreign trade policy of the EAEU;

  feasibility and objectivity of application of measures and mechanisms
  for making foreign trade policy of the EAEU;

  protection of rights and legitimate interests of participants of
  foreign trade activity of the member States, as well as the rights and
  legitimate interests of producers and consumers of goods and services;

  respect for the rights of foreign trade activity participants.

  3. Foreign trade policy is implemented by conclusion of international
  agreements with third parties by the EAEU unilaterally or jointly with
  the member States, in the spheres, where EAEU’s bodies take decisions,
  which are mandatory for the member States; participation in
  international organizations or autonomous application of measures and
  mechanisms of foreign trade policy.

  The EAEU is responsible for execution of obligations under
  international treaties concluded by the EAEU and shall exercise its
  rights under these agreements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Most Favored Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39041">The Most Favored Nation treatment in the meaning of the General
  Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT 1994) shall be granted for
  foreign trade in goods in cases and under conditions, when granting
  the most favored nation treatment is stipulated by international
  agreements of the EAEU with a third party, as well as by international
  agreements of the member States with a third party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Free Trade Regime" article_identifier="39042">Free trade regime in the meaning of the GATT 1994 is established in
  trade with a third party based on international agreement of the EAEU
  with such a third party taking into account provisions of Article 102
  of this Treaty.

  International treaty of the EAEU with a third party that establishes
  free trade regime may include other provisions, related to foreign
  trade activity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Tariff Preferences On Goods Originating In Developing And (Or) Least Developed Countries" article_identifier="39043">In order to assist economic development of developing and least
      developed countries, the EAEU may provide tariff preferences for
      goods originating in developing and/or least developed
      countries-beneficiaries of the common system of tariff preferences
      of the EAEU in accordance with this Treaty.
    
      In respect of preferential goods originating in developing
      countries- beneficiaries of the common system of tariff
      preferences of the EAEU imported into the customs territory of the
      EAEU, import customs duties at the level of 75 percent of import
      customs duties of the Common External Tariff of the Eurasian
      Economic Union, shall be applied.
    
      In respect of preferential goods originating in least developed
      countries-beneficiaries of the common system of tariff preferences
      of the EAEU imported into the customs territory of the EAEU, zero
      import customs duty rates of the Common External Tariff of the
      Eurasian Economic Union shall be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="39044">1. At the customs territory of the EAEU the common rules of origin of
  goods imported into the customs territory of the EAEU shall be
  applied.

  2. For the purpose of application of customs tariff regulation (except
  for the purposes of tariff preferences) the application of measures of
  non-tariff regulation and protection of the internal market, the
  establishment of requirements for labeling of origin of goods,
  government (municipal) procurement, recording statistics of foreign
  trade the rules of origin of goods imported into the customs territory
  of the EAEU (non-preferential rules of origin of goods) established by
  the Commission shall be applied.

  3. For the purposes of tariff preferences in respect of goods imported
  into the customs territory of the EAEU from developing or least
  developed countries the rules of origin of goods from developing and
  least developed countries - beneficiaries of the common system of
  tariff preferences of the EAEU established by the Commission shall be
  applied.

  4. For the purposes of tariff preferences in respect of goods imported
  into the customs territory of the EAEU from the States if in trade and
  economic relations between such a State and the EAEU the free trade
  regime is applied the rules of origin of goods stipulated by the
  relevant international agreement of the EAEU with such a third party
  providing the application of the free trade regime shall be applied.

  5. If in the international agreement of the EAEU with a third party,
  providing for the application of the free trade regime, do not
  stipulate the rules of origin of goods or such rules are not adopted
  at the time of entry into force of such an agreement, the rules of
  origin of goods provided for in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be
  applied until the appropriate rules of origin of goods would be
  adopted.

  6. If there are repeated violations in the area of determination
  (confirmation) of the origin of goods by a third party the Commission
  may take a decision to conduct monitoring by the customs authorities
  of the member States of the correctness of the (confirmation) of
  origin of goods imported from a particular country. In case of
  systematic violations by a third party in the sphere of determination
  (confirmation) of the origin of goods, the Commission may take a
  decision to suspend the acceptance of the documents confirming the
  origin of goods by the customs authorities of the member States. The
  provisions of this paragraph shall not limit the powers of the member
  States regarding the control of origin of the imported goods and the
  adoption of measures according to its results</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Foreign Trade Of Services" article_identifier="39045">Member States shall execute coordination in the sphere of trade in
  services with third parties.

  Execution of coordination does not mean supranational competence of
  the EAEU in this sphere.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Elimination Of Restrictive Measures In Trade With Third Parties" article_identifier="39046">The Commission shall provide assistance in access to markets of third
  parties, execute monitoring of restrictive measures of third party in
  respect of the member States and jointly with the member States shall
  conduct consultations with the relevant third party in case of
  adoption of any measure by third party in respect of the EAEU or trade
  dispute between the EAEU and such third party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Retaliatory Measures With Regard To Third Party" article_identifier="39047">1. In case, if the possibility of application of retaliatory measures
  provided by international agreement between the EAEU and a third party
  and (or) between member States and third parties, the Commission may
  take a decision on introduction of retaliatory measures on the customs
  territory of the EAEU, including the increase of import customs duty
  rates, introduction of quantitative restrictions, temporary suspension
  of preferences or adoption of other measures within the competence of
  the Commission, affecting results of foreign trade with the relevant
  State.

  2. In cases provided in the international agreements of the member
  States with third parties concluded before 1 January 2015, the member
  States may unilaterally apply as retaliatory measures higher import
  customs duty rates in comparison with the Common External Tariff of
  the Eurasian Economic Union and unilaterally suspend granting of
  tariff preferences provided that administration mechanisms of such
  measures do not violate provisions of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Measures For Exports Development" article_identifier="39048">The EAEU in accordance with international agreements, norms and rules
  of the World Trade Organization may apply joint measures to develop
  the exports of goods of Members States to the markets of the third
  parties.

  Joint measures shall include, in particular, insurance and crediting
  of exports, international leasing, promotion of the concept of “goods
  of the Eurasian Economic Union” and the introduction of a common
  labeling of goods of the EAEU, organization of fairs and expositions,
  advertising and branding activities abroad.

  2.Customs and Tariff Regulation and Non-tariff Regulation</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Common External Tariff Of The Eurasian Economic Union" article_identifier="39049">The Common Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic Activity of
      the Eurasian Economic Union and the Common External Tariff, which
      are approved by the Commission, are applied on the common
      territory of the EAEU and are the instruments of trade policy.
    
  2. The main objectives of application of the Common External Tariff of
  the Eurasian Economic Union are as follows:

  1) to provide conditions for effective integration of the EAEU into
  the world economy;

  2) to rationalize the structure of the imports of goods to the customs
  territory of the EAEU;

  3) to maintain a rational proportion of exports and imports of goods
  on the customs territory of the EAEU;

  4) to create conditions for progressive changes in the structure of
  manufacturing and consumption of goods in the EAEU;

  5) support of the sectors of the economy of the EAEU.

  3. The following types of import customs duties shall be applied at
  the Common External Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union:

  1) ad valorem, established as a percentage of the customs value of
  customable goods;

  2) specific, established depending on physical characteristics of
  customable goods in kind (quantity, weight, volume or other
  characteristics);

  3) combined, combining both types specified in subparagraphs 1 and 2
  of this paragraph.

  4. Import customs duty rates of the Common External Tariff of the
  Eurasian Economic Union are unified and are not subject to change
  depending on persons, transferring goods through the customs border of
  the customs union, except for the cases provided by Articles 35, 36
  and 43 of this Treaty.

  5. For the purpose of expeditious regulation of imports of goods into
  the customs territory of the EAEU, seasonal customs duty rates, which
  are valid no more than 6 months a year, may, if necessary, be
  established instead of import customs duty rates of the Common
  External Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union.

  6. The State acceded to the EAEU is eligible to apply import customs
  duty rates that are different from the rates of the Common External
  Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union, in accordance with the list of
  goods and rates, which are approved by the Commission based on
  international agreement on the accession of that State to the EAEU.

  The State acceded to the EAEU must ensure the use of goods towards
  which the lower import customs duty rates in comparison with the
  Common Customs Tariff of the Eurasian Economic Union are applied, only
  within its territory and adopt measures in order to prevent exports of
  such goods to other member States without additional payment of import
  customs duties equal to the difference between the sums of the customs
  import duties calculated at the rates of the Common External Tariff of
  the Eurasian Economic Union and the sums of import customs duties paid
  in imports of the goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Tariff Exemptions" article_identifier="39050">Tariff exemptions in the form of import customs duty exemption or
      a lower customs duty rate may be applied for goods being imported
      (imported) into the customs territory of the EAEU.
    
      Tariff exemptions may not be individually applied and shall be
      applied regardless the country of origin.
    
      Tariff exemptions shall be granted in accordance with Annex 6 to
      this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Tariff Rate Quotas" article_identifier="39051">In respect of certain agricultural products originating in third
      countries and imported into the customs territory of the EAEU it
      is allowed to establish the tariff quotas, if the like goods are
      produced (extracted, cultivated) on the customs territory of the
      EAEU.
    
      With regard to goods referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article
      imported into the customs territory of the EAEU within the
      established volume of tariff rate quota the relevant import duties
      according to the Common External Tariff of the Eurasian Economic
      Union shall be applied.
    
      Introduction of tariff rate quotas for certain types of
      agricultural products originating in third countries and imported
      into the customs territory of the EAEU as well as the distribution
      of the volumes of tariff quotas shall be carried out in accordance
      with the procedure provided in Annex 6 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Competence Of The Commission On Customs And Tariff Regulation Issues" article_identifier="39052">The Commission shall:
    
  - maintain the Common Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic
  Activity of the Eurasian Economic Union and the Common External Tariff
  of the Eurasian Economic Union;

  - establish import customs duty rates, including seasonal;

  - establish cases and conditions for granting tariff exemptions;

  - determine the procedure for application of tariff exemptions;

  - determine conditions and the procedure of application of the common
  system of tariff preferences of the EAEU, including approval of:

  - the list of developing countries-beneficiaries of the common system
  of tariff preferences of the EAEU;

  - the list of least-developed countries-beneficiaries of the common
  system of tariff preferences of the EAEU;

  - the list of goods originating from developing or least developed
  countries, towards which tariff preferences shall be granted at the
  importation into the customs territory of the EAEU;

  - establish tariff rate quotas, allocate the volume of tariff rate
  quota between member States, determine the method and procedure for
  allocation of volume of tariff rate quota among participants of
  foreign trade activity, and if necessary allocate volumes of tariff
  rate quota among third countries or adopt an act under which the
  member States determine the method and procedure for allocation of
  tariff rate quotas among participants of foreign trade activities, and
  if necessary, allocate volume of tariff rate quota among third
  countries.

  2. The list of sensitive goods, towards which the decision on changes
  to import customs duty rates is taken by the Council of the
  Commission, shall be approved by the Supreme Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Non-Tariff Measures" article_identifier="39053">trade with third countries the EAEU shall apply the following common
  non-tariff measures:

  1) the prohibition of import and (or) export of goods;

  2) quantitative restrictions on the import and (or) export of goods;

  3) the exclusive right to export and (or) import of goods;

  4) automatic licensing (monitoring) of export and (or) import of
  goods;

  5) authorization procedure for import and (or) export of goods.

  2. Non-tariff measures are to be introduced and applied on the
  principles of transparency and non-discrimination in the manner
  prescribed in Annex 7 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Imposing Of Non-Tariff Regulation On The Unilateral Basis" article_identifier="39054">Member States in trade with third countries may unilaterally introduce
  and apply non-tariff measures in the manner prescribed in Annex 7 to
  this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="General Provisions On Imposition Of Measures For Protection Of The Internal Market" article_identifier="39055">order to protect the economic interests of producers of goods of the
  EAEU the measures for protection of the internal market from goods
  originating in third countries and imported into the customs territory
  of the EAEU may be imposed in the form of safeguard, anti-dumping and
  countervailing measures, as well as other measures in cases specified
  in Article 50 of this Treaty.

  2. Decision on the application of safeguard, anti-dumping or
  countervailing measure, modification or cancellation of safeguard,
  anti-dumping or countervailing measure or non-application of a measure
  are taken by the Commission.

  3. Safeguard, anti-dumping and countervailing measures shall be
  applied in the order and on the terms specified in Annex 8 to this
  Treaty.

  4. Application of safeguard, anti-dumping or countervailing measures
  on import of a product shall be preceded by an investigation carried
  out in accordance with Annex 8 to this Treaty by the authority
  identified by the Commission as responsible for such investigations
  (hereinafter – the investigating body).

  5. Crediting and distribution of special, anti-dumping and
  countervailing duties are carried out in accordance with Annex 8 to
  this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Principles Of Application Of Safeguard, Anti-Dumping And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="39056">safeguard measure may be applied to a product, if as a result of
  investigation carried out by the investigating body it has been
  determined that this product is being imported into the customs
  territory of the EAEU in such increased quantities (in absolute terms
  or relative to the total volume of production in member States of like
  or directly competitive product) and under such conditions that it
  causes serious injury to the sector of economy of the member States or
  threatens to cause such injury.

  2. An anti-dumping measure may be applied to a product which is
  subject to the dumped imports, if as a result of investigation carried
  out by the investigating body it was determined that imports of such
  product into the customs territory of the EAEU causes material injury
  to the sector of economy of member States, threatens to cause such
  injury or significantly retards the establishment of the sector of
  economy of the member States.

  3. Countervailing measure may be applied to an imported product during
  production, exportation or transportation of which a specific subsidy
  of an exporting third country was used, if as a result of
  investigation carried out by the investigating body it was found that
  the import of this good into the customs territory of the EAEU causes
  material injury to the sector of economy of the member States,
  threatens to cause such injury or significantly delays the
  establishment of the sector of economy of the member States.

  4. For the purposes of the application of measures for protection of
  the internal market the sector of economy of the member States shall
  be understood as all producers of the like product (for the purposes
  of anti-dumping and countervailing investigations) or like or directly
  competitive product (for the purposes of safeguard investigation) in
  the member States, or those whose share in the total production of
  either like product or like or directly competitive product in the
  member States constitutes a significant proportion, but not less than
  25 percent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Other Measures Of Protection Of The Internal Market" article_identifier="39057">An international treaty of the EAEU with a third party on the
  establishment of a free trade regime in order to eliminate a negative
  impact of imports from this third party on the manufacturers of the
  member States may provide for the right to apply measures of
  protection of the internal market on a bilateral basis, different from
  safeguard, anti-dumping and countervailing measures, including those
  in relation to the importation of agricultural goods.

  The decision to apply such measures shall be taken by the Commission.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION X" name="Technical Regulation" chapter_identifier="4504">
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="General Principles Of Technical Regulation" article_identifier="39058">1. Technical regulation within the EAEU shall be implemented in
  accordance with the following principles:

  1) establishment of mandatory requirements to products and product
  related requirements to design processes (including research),
  manufacturing, construction, installation, adjustment, operation,
  storage, transportation, marketing and utilization;

  2) establishment of common mandatory requirements in technical
  regulations of the EAEU or national mandatory requirements in the
  legislation of the member-states in respect to the products included
  in the Common List of products for which established mandatory
  requirements within the EAEU are established (hereinafter - the Common
  List);

  3) application and enforcement of technical regulations of the EAEU at
  the territories of the member-states without exceptions;

  4) compliance of technical regulations within the EAEU to the level of
  economic development of member-states and the level of scientific and
  technological development;

  5) independence of accreditation bodies of the member-states, the
  certification bodies of the member-states and the supervisory(control)
  authorities of the member-states from manufacturers, sellers and
  purchasers and consumers;

  6) unity of the rules and methods of research (tests) and measurements
  in the mandatory conformity assessment procedures;

  7) unity of application of technical regulations of the EAEU
  regardless of the types and (or) characteristics of the transactions;

  8) inadmissibility of restriction of competition in conducting
  conformity assessment procedures;

  9) implementation of state control (supervision) over observance of
  technical regulations of the EAEU on the basis of the harmonization of
  legislation of the member-states;

  10) voluntary application of standards;

  11) development and implementation of intergovernmental standards;

  12) harmonization of the intergovernmental standards with
  international and regional standards;

  13) unity of the rules and procedures of mandatory conformity
  assessment procedures;

  14) to ensure harmonization of legislation of member-states with
  regard to establishing liability for violation of the mandatory
  requirements for products, mandatory conformity assessment procedures
  and rules;

  15) coherent policies in the area of ensuring the uniformity of
  measurement within the EAEU;

  16) preventing the establishing of exceeding barriers on the business
  activities;

  17) establishment of the transitional period provisions aimed at
  phased transition to the new requirements and documents.

  2. Provisions of this section do not apply to the establishment and
  application of sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary
  quarantine measures.

  3. Policies, regulations and procedures of technical regulation within
  the EAEU shall be established in accordance with Annex 9.

  4. Coherent policies in the area of uniformity of measurement within
  the EAEU shall be established in accordance with Annex 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Technical Regulations Of The Eaeu And Standards" article_identifier="39059">1. Technical regulations of the EAEU shall be used for the purpose of
  protecting life and (or) human health, property, the environment,
  protecting life and (or) health of animals and plants, prevention of
  actions misleading consumers as well as to ensure energy efficiency
  and resource conservation within the EAEU.

  Adoption of technical regulations of the EAEU for other purposes is
  not allowed.

  Procedure for development and adoption of technical regulations of the
  EAEU as well as the procedure for introduction of amendments and their
  cancellation are adopted by the Commission.

  The technical regulations of the EAEU or national mandatory
  requirements apply only to the products included in Common List
  approved by the Commission.

  Procedure for the formation and maintenance of the Common List shall
  be approved by the Commission.

  Member States do not allow imposing the mandatory requirements in
  their legislation for products not included in the Common Llist.

  2. Technical Regulations of the EAEU are directly applicable at the
  territory of the EAEU.

  The procedure for entering into force of the technical regulations of
  the EAEU and transitional provisions are to be determined under the
  technical regulations of the EAEU and (or) an act of the Commission.

  3. To meet the requirements of technical regulations and conformity
  assessment to the requirements of technical regulations of the EAEU on
  a voluntary basis international, regional (intergovernmental)
  standards, and in their absence (before the adoption of the regional
  (intergovernmental) standards) - the national (state) standards of the
  member-states can be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Circulation Of Products And Technical Regulations Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39060">1. Products manufactured and put into the circulation on the territory
  of the EAEU shall be safe.

  Rules and procedures for ensuring the safety and circulation of
  products, for which requirements are not established under the
  technical regulations of the EAEU, shall be determined by the
  international treaty within the EAEU.

  2. Products that are subject to the enforced technical regulation of
  the EAEU (technical regulations of the EAEU) can be put into the
  circulation at the territory of the EAEU, provided that it has passed
  the necessary conformity assessment procedures established under the
  technical regulation of the EAEU (technical regulations of the EAEU).

  Member States shall ensure circulation of products conforming to the
  requirements of the technical regulation of the EAEU (technical
  regulations of the EAEU) on its territory without application of
  additional requirements to such products with regard to the technical
  regulation of the EAEU (technical regulations of the EAEU) and without
  additional conformity assessment procedures.

  The provisions of the second paragraph of this paragraph shall not be
  applied with respect to the sanitary, veterinary and sanitary as well
  as phytosanitary quarantine measures.

  3. From the date of entry into force of the technical regulations of
  the EAEU at the territories of the member-states the relevant
  mandatory requirements for products and related requirements for
  product design process (including research), manufacturing,
  construction, installation, adjustment, operation, storage,
  transportation, marketing and utilization established under the
  legislation of the member-states or the Commission’s acts are to be
  applied only in part determined by the transitional provisions and
  from the date of termination of the transitional provisions,
  determined under the technical regulation of the EAEU and (or) under
  the Commission’s act shall not be applied for the putting of the
  products into circulation, conformity assessment of the objects of the
  technical regulation, state control (supervision) over observance of
  technical regulations of the EAEU.

  The provisions of the first subparagraph of this paragraph shall not
  be applied to the sanitary, veterinary and sanitary as well as
  phytosanitary quarantine measures.

  Mandatory requirements for products and related requirements for
  product design processes (including research), manufacturing,
  construction, installation, adjustment, operation, storage,
  transportation, marketing and utilization established under the acts
  of the Commission prior to the entry into force of the technical
  regulation of the EAEU shall be included into the technical
  regulations of the EAEU.

  4. State control (supervision) over observance of technical
  regulations of the EAEU shall be carried out in accordance with the
  legislation of the member-states.

  Principles and approaches to the harmonization of legislation of
  member-states in the sphere of state control (supervision) over
  observance of technical regulations of the EAEU shall be defined under
  the international treaty within the EAEU.

  5. Responsibility for non-compliance with the technical regulations of
  the EAEU, as well as for violation of procedures for assessment of
  conformity of products with the technical regulations of the EAEU are
  established in accordance with the laws of the member-states.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Accreditation" article_identifier="39061">1. Accreditation within the EAEU shall be implemented in accordance
  with the following principles:

  1) harmonization of rules and approaches in the field of accreditation
  with international standards;

  2) provision of voluntary accreditation, transparency and
  accessibility of information on procedures, rules and results of
  accreditation;

  3) ensuring objectivity, impartiality and competence of the
  accreditation bodies of the member-states;

  4) ensuring that applicants for accreditation faced equal conditions
  in respect of accreditation and ensuring of the confidentiality of
  information obtained during the accreditation;

  5) inadmissibility of combination of accreditation functions with
  functions of state control (supervision) by the same authority of the
  member-state, except for carrying out monitoring the activities of
  accredited conformity assessment bodies of the member-states
  (including certification bodies, testing laboratories (centers));

  6) inadmissibility of combination by one authority of the member-state
  of the accreditation and conformity assessment functions.

  2. Accreditation of conformity assessment bodies of the member-states
  shall be carried out by the accreditation bodies of member-states
  authorized in accordance with the laws of the member-states on the
  implementation of these activities.

  3. Accreditation bodies of one member-state shall not compete with the
  accreditation bodies of the other member-states.

  To avoid competition between accreditation bodies of the
  member-states, the conformity assessment body of a member-state shall
  for accreditation purposes apply to the accreditation body of the
  member-state, on which territory it was registered as a legal entity.

  If the accreditation body of one member-state applies for
  accreditation purposes to the conformity assessment body registered as
  a legal entity at the territory of another State Member, this
  accreditation body shall inform the accreditation body of the
  member-state at whose territory the conformity assessment body is
  registered. In this case it is allowed to carry out accreditation by
  the accreditation bodies of the member-states, if the accreditation
  body of the member-state, at whose territory this conformity
  assessment body is registered, does not exercise accreditation in the
  required area. In this case the accreditation body of the
  member-state, at whose territory conformity assessment body is
  registered has the right to act as an observer.

  4. Accreditation bodies of member-states carry out mutual comparative
  evaluation in order to achieve equivalence of the procedures.

  Recognition of the results of the accreditation of conformity
  assessment bodies of the member-state shall be carried out according
  to Annex 11.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Elimination Of Technical Barriers" article_identifier="39062">in Mutual Trade with Third Countries

  Procedures and conditions for the elimination of technical barriers in
  trade with third countries shall be defined under the international
  treaty within the EAEU</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XI" name="Sanitary, Veterinary And Sanitary And Phytosanitary Quarantine Measures" chapter_identifier="4505">
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="General Principles Of The Application Of Sanitary, Veterinary And Sanitary And Phytosanitary Quarantine Measures" article_identifier="39063">1. Sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine
  measures shall be applied on the basis of principles having a
  scientific justification and only to the extent necessary to protect
  human, animal and plant life and health.

  Sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine
  measures applied within the EAEU shall be based on international and
  regional standards, guidelines and (or) recommendations except for the
  cases when, based on appropriate scientific justification, sanitary,
  veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine measures that
  ensure a higher level of sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and
  phytosanitary quarantine protection than measures based on relevant
  international and regional standards, guidelines and (or)
  recommendations are applied.

  order to ensure sanitary and epidemiological welfare of the
  population, as well as veterinary and sanitary, quarantine
  phytosanitary safety in the EAEU a coordinated policy in the sphere of
  application of sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary
  quarantine measures shall be conducted.

  3. Coordinated policy is implemented through joint development,
  adoption and implementation of international agreement and acts of the
  Commission by the member States in the field of application of
  sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine
  measures.

  4. Each member State has the right to develop and implement temporary
  sanitary-epidemiological, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary
  quarantine measures.

  The Commission shall approve the procedure of interaction of member
  States authorized bodies with the introduction of temporary sanitary,
  veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary quarantine measures.

  5. Coordinated approaches when conducting identification, registration
  and traceability of animals and products of animal origin shall be
  applied in accordance with the acts of the Commission.

  6. Application of sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and phytosanitary
  quarantine measures and interaction of the member States authorized
  bodies in the field of sanitary, veterinary and sanitary and
  phytosanitary quarantine measures shall be performed in accordance
  with Annex 12 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Application Of Sanitary Measures" article_identifier="39064">1. Sanitary measures shall be applied to persons, vehicles, as well as
  products (goods) subject to sanitary-epidemiological supervision
  (control), included into the common list of products (goods) subject
  to state sanitary-epidemiological supervision (control) in accordance
  with the acts of the Commission.

  2. Common sanitary-epidemiological and hygienic requirements and
  procedures shall be established to products subject to state
  sanitary-epidemiological supervision (control).

  Common sanitary and epidemiological and hygienic requirements to
  products (goods), in respect of which technical regulations of the
  EAEU are being developed, shall be included into the technical
  regulations of the EAEU in accordance with the acts of the Commission.

  3. The Commission shall approve the procedure for the development,
  approval, amendment and implementation of the common
  sanitary-epidemiological and hygienic requirements and procedures.

  order to ensure sanitary-epidemiological welfare of the population,
  the authorized bodies of the member States in the field of the
  sanitary-epidemiological welfare of the population shall implement
  state sanitary and epidemiological supervision (control) in accordance
  with the legislation of the member States and acts of the Commission.

  Authorized bodies in the field of sanitary and epidemiological welfare
  of the population can implement state supervision (control) over
  compliance with requirements of technical regulations of the EAEU
  within the framework of state sanitary and epidemiological supervision
  (control) in accordance with the legislation of the member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Application Of Veterinary And Sanitary Measures" article_identifier="39065">1. Veterinary and sanitary measures shall be applied to goods
  (including goods for personal use), imported into the custom territory
  of the EAEU and transported within the custom territory of the EAEU,
  included in the Common list of goods subject to veterinary control
  (supervision) approved by the Commission, as well as to facilities
  subject to veterinary control (supervision).

  2.  Common veterinary (veterinary and sanitary) requirements approved
  by the Commission shall be applied to goods and facilities subject to
  veterinary control (supervision).

  order to prevent importation and distribution of agents of infectious
  animal diseases, including those common to humans and animals, and
  goods not corresponding to a common veterinary (veterinary-sanitary)
  requirements veterinary control (supervision) over goods subject to
  veterinary control (supervision), including goods for personal use, as
  well as facilities subject to the veterinary control (supervision)
  shall be implemented according to the acts of Commission.

  Interaction of member States in prevention, diagnosis, localization
  and liquidation of centers of particularly dangerous, quarantine and
  zoonotic animal diseases shall be carried out in the order established
  by the Commission.

  4. Authorized bodies in the veterinary field shall exercise veterinary
  control (supervision) at the transition of goods controlled by the
  veterinary control (supervision) across the customs border of the EAEU
  at checkpoints of the state border of the member States or at other
  locations specified in national legislation of the member States that
  are fitted and equipped with means of veterinary control in accordance
  with the legislation of the member States.

  5. Each batch of goods subject to veterinary control (supervision)
  shall be imported into the customs territory of the EAEU according to
  the Common veterinary (veterinary and sanitary) requirements approved
  by the Commission and in a presence of a permit issued by the
  authorized body of the member States in the veterinary field on whose
  territory these goods are imported and/or a veterinary certificate
  issued by the authorized body of the country of dispatch of these
  goods.

  6. Goods subject to veterinary control (supervision) shall be
  transported from the territory of one member State into the territory
  of the other member State according to the Common veterinary
  (veterinary and sanitary) requirements. A veterinary certificate shall
  accompany these goods, unless otherwise determined by the Commission.

  The member States mutually recognize veterinary certificates issued by
  authorized bodies in the field of veterinary using unified forms
  approved by the Commission.

  7. The basic principle of ensuring safety of goods subject to
  veterinary control (supervision) in their production, processing,
  transportation and/or storage in a third country, is an audit of
  foreign official supervision.

  Authorized bodies in the veterinary field shall conduct audits of
  foreign official systems of supervision and inspections of facilities
  subject to veterinary control (supervision) in accordance with the
  acts of the Commission.

  8. The member States have the right to develop and implement temporary
  veterinary (veterinary and sanitary) requirements and measures in case
  of receiving official information from the relevant international
  organizations, the member States, as well as third countries on the
  deterioration of the epizootic situation in the territories of third
  countries or member States.

  In case of presence of such information, but in the absence of
  adequate scientific evidence or if such evidence cannot be submitted
  within necessary time limits, the member States may take immediate
  veterinary and sanitary measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Quarantine Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="39066">1. Quarantine phytosanitary measures shall be applied to the regulated
  products included in the list of quarantineable products (regulated
  cargo, regulated substances, regulated goods) subject to quarantine
  phytosanitary control (supervision) at the customs border of the EAEU
  and the customs territory of the EAEU (hereinafter - the list of
  quarantineable products), quarantine facilities included in the
  consolidated list of quarantine objects of the EAEU, as well as
  objects under quarantine.

  2. Quarantine phytosanitary control (supervision) at the customs
  territory of the EAEU and the customs border of the EAEU shall be
  carried out in respect of the products included in the list of
  quarantineable products, quarantine objects included in the common
  list of quarantine objects of the EAEU, as well as objects under
  quarantine.

  3. The List of quarantineable products, the Consolidated list of
  quarantine objects of the EAEU and the Common quarantine phytosanitary
  requirements shall approved by the Commission.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XII" name="Consumer Rights Protection" chapter_identifier="4506">
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Guarantees For The Consumer Rights Protection" article_identifier="39067">1. Consumer rights protection is guaranteed under the legislation of
  the member State on the consumer rights protection and under this
  Treaty.

  2. The citizens of member State and other persons living on its
  territory shall enjoy the same legal protection in the field of
  consumer protection at the territories of the other member States as
  their citizens and shall have the right to apply to state and
  non-governmental organizations for the protection of consumer rights
  and other organizations and to the courts and (or) carry out other
  procedural actions on the same conditions as the citizens of the other
  member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Policy In The Area Of Consumer Protection" article_identifier="39068">1. Member States shall conduct a coordinated policy in the field of
  consumer protection aimed at formation of the equal conditions for
  citizens of member States to protect their interests from unfair
  activities of commercial entities.

  2. Implementation of agreed policies on consumer protection is
  provided in accordance with this Treaty and the laws of the member
  States on the protection of consumer right on the basis of the
  principles specified in Annex 13.

  SINGLE ECONOMIC SPACE</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XIII" name="Macroeconomic Policy" chapter_identifier="4507">
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Main Directions Of The Coordinated Macroeconomic Policy" article_identifier="39069">1. Within the EAEU a coordinated macroeconomic policy providing for
  the development and implementation of joint actions by the member
  States shall be carried out in order to achieve balanced development
  of economies of the member States.

  2. Coordination of the implementation by the member States of the
  coordinated macroeconomic policy shall be carried out by the
  Commission in accordance with the Annex 14 to this Treaty.

  3. Main directions of the coordinated macroeconomic policy of the
  member States include:

  1) ensuring sustainable development of economies of the member States
  with the use of integration potential of the EAEU and competitive
  advantages of each member State;

  2) creation of common principles of functioning of economies of the
  member States and their effective interaction;

  3) creation of conditions for increase of the internal stability of
  economies of the member States, including ensuring of macroeconomic
  stability, as well as resistance to external effects;

  4) development of common principles and guidelines for forecasting
  social and economic development of the member States.

  4. Implementation of the main directions of coordinated macroeconomic
  policy shall be carried out in accordance with the Annex 14 to this
  Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Main Macroeconomic Indicators Determining Sustainability Of Economic Development" article_identifier="39070">Member States form the economic policy within the following
  quantitative parameters of macroeconomic indicators determining
  sustainability of economic development:

  annual deficit of consolidated general governmental budget - does not
  exceed 3 percent of gross domestic product;

  general governmental debt - does not exceed 50 percent of gross
  domestic product;

  inflation rate (consumer price index) on annual basis (from December
  to December of the previous year, in percentage) - does not exceed by
  more than 5 percentage points the inflation rate in the member State
  where this index is the lowest.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XIV" name="Monetary Policy" chapter_identifier="4508">
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Purposes And Principles Of Harmonized Monetary Policy" article_identifier="39071">1. Member States for the purposes of deepening economic integration,
  development of cooperation in the monetary and financial field,
  ensuring free movement of goods, services and capital in the
  territories of the member States, enhancing the role of national
  currencies of the member States in foreign trade and investment
  transactions as well as providing mutual convertibility of these
  currencies, shall develop and carry out coordinated monetary policy
  based on the following principles:

  1) gradual implementation of harmonization and convergence of
  approaches to the formation and conduction of the currency policy to
  the extent where it corresponds the current macroeconomic integration
  cooperation demand;

  2) creation the necessary organizational and legal conditions at
  national and intergovernmental levels for the integration processes
  development in the monetary field, coordination and correlation of
  monetary policy;

  3) prevention of actions in the monetary field that may adversely
  affect the integration processes development, and in case of its
  forced application - minimization of the consequences of such actions;

  4) economic policy aimed at increasing confidence as regards national
  currencies of the member States both in the domestic market of each
  member State as well as in the international monetary markets.

  2. For the purposes of the coordinated monetary policy the member
  States shall implement the measures in accordance with the Annex 15 to
  this Treaty.

  3. Coordination of the exchange rate policy is carried out by a
  separate body that consists of the heads of national (central) banks
  of the member States and its operation procedures are determined by
  the international treaty within the EAEU.

  4. Correlated approaches are used by the member States in respect of
  monetary relations regulation and adoption of liberalization measures
  shall be determined under an international agreement within the EAEU.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XV" name="Trade In Services, Establishment, Activities And Investments" chapter_identifier="4509">
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Objectives And Purposes, Scope Of Application" article_identifier="39072">1. The objective of this section is to ensure the freedom of trade in
  services, establishment, activities and investments within the EAEU in
  accordance with the conditions of this section and Annex 16 to this
  Treaty.

  The legal basis of regulation of trade in services, establishment,
  activities and investments in the territories of the member States is
  determined in accordance with Annex 16 to this Treaty.

  2. Provisions of this section shall be applied to measures of the
  member States affecting supply and consumption of services,
  establishment, activities and investments.

  The provisions of this section shall not apply:

  to the government (municipal) procurement which is regulated by the
  section XXII of this Treaty;

  to the services supplied and activities carried out in the exercise of
  governmental authority.

  3. Services covered by the sections XVI, XIX, XX and XXI of this
  Treaty shall be regulated by the provisions of these sections,
  respectively. The provisions of this section shall be applied to the
  extent not inconsistent with the specified sections.

  4. Specificities of legal relations arising in relation to the trade
  of electric communication services shall be determined in accordance
  with the Procedure for Trade in Electric Communication services (
  Annex 1 to the Annex 16 hereto).

  5. Specificities of the entry, departure, stay and employment of
  natural persons shall be regulated by the section XXVI of this Treaty
  to the extent not inconsistent with this section.

  6. Nothing in this section shall be interpreted as:

  1) a requirement to any member State to furnish any information, the
  disclosure of which it considers contrary to its essential security
  interests;

  2) a prevention for any member State from taking any action it
  considers necessary for theprotection of its the essential security
  interests through the adoption of legislation, including:

  relating to the supply of services as carried out directly or
  indirectly for the purpose of provisioning a military establishment;

  relating to fissionable and fusionable materials or the materials from
  which they are derived;

  taken in time of war or other emergency in international relations;

  3) a prevention for any member State State from taking any action in
  pursuance of its obligations under the the United Nations Charter for
  the maintainance of international peace and security.

  7. Provisions of this section shall not prevent the member State to
  adopt or enforce the measures:

  1) necessary for the protection of the public morals or for
  maintaining the public order. Exceptions for the reasons of public
  order can only be applied in cases when there is a genuine and
  sufficiently serious threat for one of the fundamental interests of
  the society.

  2) necessary for the protection of human, animal or plant life or
  health;

  3) necessary for compliance with the legislation of the member States
  that are not contrary to the provisions of this section, including
  those related to:

  the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or to deal with
  the effects of a default on civil contracts;

  the protection of the privacy of individuals in relation to the
  processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of
  confidentiality of individual records and accounts;

  safety;

  4) inconsistent with paragraphs 21 and 24 of the Annex 16 to this
  Treaty, provided that the difference in actual treatment is aimed at
  ensuring the equitable or effective imposition or collection of direct
  taxes from persons of another member State or of third States in
  respect of trade in services, establishment and activities and such
  measures should not be inconsistent with the provisions of
  international treaties of the member States;

  5) inconsistent with paragraphs 27 and 29 of the Annex 16 to this
  Treaty, provided that the difference in treatment is the result of an
  agreement on taxation matters, including on the avoidance of double
  taxation where the respective member State is a party to such an
  agreement.

  8. Application of measures stipulated in paragraph 7 of this Article
  shall not result in arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination between
  member States or a disguised restriction on trade in services,
  establishment, activities and investments.

  9. If a member State retains restrictions or prohibitions on trade in
  services, establishment, activities and investments against a third
  State, nothing in this section shall be interpreted as obliging this
  member State to apply the provisions of this section to the persons of
  another member State if such person is owned or controlled by a person
  of the specified third State, and the application of the provisions of
  this section will lead to circumvention or violation of these
  prohibitions and restrictions.

  10. A member State may not apply its obligations under this section,
  on the person of another member State in respect of trade in services,
  establishment, activities and investments if it is proven that the
  entity of another member State does not exercise significant business
  operations in the territory of another member State, and that it is
  owned or controlled by a person of the first member State or by a
  personof a third State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Liberalization Of Trade In Services, Establishment, Activities And Investments" article_identifier="39073">1. Member States shall not introduce new discriminatory measures in
  respect of trade in services, establishment, and activities of persons
  of the other member State as compared to the treatment in force at the
  date of entry into force of this Treaty.

  2. To ensure free trade in services, establishment, activities and
  investments, the member States carry out gradual liberalization of
  conditions for mutual trade in services, establishment, activities and
  investments.

  3. Member States aspire to create and ensuring operation of a single
  services market stipulated by paragraph 38 - 43 of the Annex 16 to
  this Treaty, in the maximum number of services sectors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Principles Of Liberalization Of Trade In Services, Establishment, Activities And Investments" article_identifier="39074">1. Liberalization of trade in services, establishment, activities and
  investments is carried out with consideration of the international
  principles and standards through the harmonization of the legislation
  of the member States and organization of mutual administrative
  cooperation between the competent authorities of the member States.

  2. Within the process of liberalization of trade in services,
  establishment, activities and investments the member States are guided
  by the following principles:

  1) optimization of domestic regulation - gradual simplification and
  (or) elimination of excessive domestic regulation, including approval
  requirements and procedures for service suppliers, service consumers,
  persons carrying out establishment or activities as and investors with
  consideration of the best international practice of regulation the
  specific services sectors, and in case of lack of such a practice - by
  selecting and applying the most advanced models used by the member
  States;

  2) proportionality - a necessary and sufficient level of harmonization
  of legislation of the member States and the mutual administrative
  cooperation for the effective functioning of the services market,
  establishment, activities or investments;

  3) mutual benefit - the liberalization of trade in services,
  establishment, activities and investments on the basis of fair
  distribution of benefits and obligations, taking into account the
  sensitivity of the services sectors and types of activities for each
  member State;

  4) consistency – the adoption of any measures in respect of trade in
  services, establishment, activities and investments including the
  harmonization of legislation of the member States and administrative
  cooperation that are to be based on the following:

  deterioration of conditions of mutual access in comparison with the
  conditions prevailing at the date of completion of this Treaty as well
  as with the conditions set forth in this Treaty in any sectors of
  services and activities is unacceptable;

  gradual reduction of restrictions, exemptions, additional requirements
  and conditions stipulated by individual national lists of
  restrictions, exemptions, additional requirements and conditions
  approved by the Supreme Council stipulated in subparagraph 4 of
  paragraph 2 and paragraphs 15-17, 23, 26, 28, 31, 33 and 35 of the
  Annex 16 to this Treaty;

  5) the economic feasibility – conduction within the single services
  market, provided by paragraphs 38 - 43 of the Annex 16 to this Treaty,
  of liberalization of trade in services as a priority in relation to
  the services sectors that have the most significant impact on the cost
  price, competitiveness and (or) the volumes of produced and sold goods
  in the domestic market of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Administrative Cooperation" article_identifier="39075">1. The member States shall assist each other in ensuring effective
  cooperation between the competent authorities on matters regulated by
  this section.

  To ensure the effectiveness of cooperation including the exchange of
  information the competent authorities of the member States should
  conclude the agreements.

  2. Administrative cooperation includes:

  1) an operational information exchange between the competent
  authorities of the member States in respect of services sector as a
  whole, as well as in relation to individual market participants;

  2) creation of a mechanism for preventing the violation by services
  suppliers of rights and interests of consumers, fair market
  participants as well as public (state) interests.

  3. Competent authorities of a member State may request under the
  concluded agreements the competent authorities of other member States
  information within the competence of the latter and necessary for the
  effective implementation of the requirements of this section,
  including:

  1) on the persons of these other member States carrying out
  establishment or providing services in the territory of the first
  member State, and in particular the information on the evidences
  confirming that such persons are established in their territories and
  that according to the competent authorities these persons are engaged
  in business activities;

  2) on the permits issued by the competent authorities, and types of
  activities to be implemented under these permits;

  3) on administrative measures, penal sanctions or decisions on the
  recognition of insolvency (bankruptcy) of a person, that were taken by
  the authorities in respect to this person and that directly affect
  their competence or business reputation. The competent authorities of
  a member State shall provide the relevant information requested from
  the competent authorities of another member State, including the
  grounds for bringing to justice those who carried out establishment or
  supplied services in the territory of the first member State.

  4. Administrative cooperation of the competent authorities of the
  member States (including the monitoring and supervision of the
  activities) aimed at:

  1) creation of an effective system to protect the rights of services
  consumers of one member State with the supply of these services by
  services supplier of another member State;

      fulfillment of tax obligations and other obligations by the
      services consumers and services suppliers;
    
      preventing unfair business practices;
    
  4) ensure the reliability of statistical data on the amounts of
  services supplied by the member States.

  5. If the member State became aware of the actions of any of the
  services suppliers or persons carrying out establishment or
  activities, or investors who are capable of causing damage to the
  health or safety of humans, animals, plants or the environment in the
  territory of that member State or in the territories of other member
  States, the first member State shall as soon as possible informs all
  the member States and the Commission about it.

  6. Commission promotes the development and participates in the process
  of operation of the information systems of the EAEU on matters
  regulated by this section.

  7. The member States may inform the Commission on cases of
  non-compliance of the obligations under this Article by other member
  States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Transparency" article_identifier="39076">1. Each member State shall ensure openness and availability of its
  legislation on matters regulated by this section.

  For these purposes, all of the normative legal acts of the member
  State which affect or may affect the matters regulated by this section
  shall be published in the sources of official information, and if
  possible also on the respective website in the Internet so that any
  person whose rights and (or) obligations might be affected by such
  normative legal acts had the opportunity for comment.

  2. Normative legal acts of the member States specified in paragraph 1
  of this Article shall be published within the period providing legal
  certainty and the reasonable expectations of persons whose rights and
  (or) obligations might be affected by these normative legal acts, but
  in any case prior to the date of their entry into force.

  3. Member States shall ensure the publication of the preliminary draft
  of normative legal acts specified in paragraph 1 of this Article.

  Member States shall place the draft normative legal act, information
  on the procedure of submission by persons of comments and proposals on
  those draft normative legal acts, as well as information on the time
  period for public comment of draft normative legal act in the Internet
  on the official websites of government agencies responsible for the
  development of the draft normative legal acts, or on specially created
  websites in order to provide all interested persons with the
  opportunity to submit their comments and proposals.

  The drafts normative legal acts are to be published usually within 30
  calendar days before the date of their adoption. Such prior
  publication is not required in exceptional cases that require a rapid
  response and in cases where prior publication of draft regulations may
  prevent their application or otherwise be contrary to the public
  interest.

  Comments and (or) proposals received by the competent authorities of
  the member States during the public consultations shall be taken into
  account while revising draft normative legal acts.

  4. Publication of normative legal acts (their drafts) referred to in
  paragraph 1 of this Article shall be accompanied by an explanation of
  the purposes of their adoption and application.

  5. The member States create a mechanism providing for responding to
  written or electronic requests of any person in respect of the
  normative legal acts in force and (or) normative legal acts planned
  for adoption referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article.

  6. The member States shall provide for consideration of applications
  of persons of other member States on matters regulated by this
  section, in accordance with its legislation in the manner prescribed
  for its persons.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XVI" name="Regulation Of The Financial Markets" chapter_identifier="4510">
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Purposes And Principles Of The Regulation Of Financial Markets" article_identifier="39077">1. Member States within the EAEU carry out the coordinated regulation
  of financial markets in accordance with the following objectives and
  principles:

  1) to deepen economic integration of member States in order to create
  within the EAEU a common financial market and to ensure
  non-discriminatory access to the financial markets of the member
  States;

  2) to ensure a secure and effective protection of the rights and
  legitimate interests of financial services consumers;

  3) to create the conditions for mutual recognition of licenses in the
  banking and insurance sectors as well as in the services sector within
  the securities market issued by authorized bodies of one member State
  in the territories of other member States;

  4) to determine approaches in respect of risk management in the
  financial markets of the member States in accordance with
  international standards;

  5) to determine the requirements for banking activities, insurance
  activities, and activities in the securities market (prudential
  requirements);

  6) to determine the order of supervising of the financial market
  participants;

  7) to ensure transparency of financial market participants.

  2. With a view to create the conditions in the financial market for
  assuring free movement of capital the member States shall apply the
  following basic forms of cooperation, including:

  1) exchange of information including the confidential one between the
  competent authorities of the member States on the matters related to
  regulation and development of banking activities, insurance activities
  and activities in the securities market, control and supervision in
  accordance with the international agreement in framework of the EAEU;

  2) conduction of the agreed actions concerning the discussion of
  current and potential issues in the financial markets and development
  of proposals for solution of those issues;

  3) mutual consultations carried out by the competent authorities of
  the member States in respect of regulation of banking activities,
  insurance activities and activities in the securities market .

  3. To achieve the objectives set out in paragraph 1 of this Article,
  the member States in accordance with an international agreement in the
  framework of the EAEU and subject to Annex 17 of this Treaty and
  Article 103 of this Treaty shall harmonize their legislation in
  respect of financial market.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XVII" name="Taxes And Taxation" chapter_identifier="4511">
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Principles Of Member States Cooperation In The Field Of Taxation" article_identifier="39078">1. Goods imported from the territory of one member State into the
  territory of another member State shall be levied by indirect taxes.

  2. Member States in mutual trade shall collect taxes, other charges
  and payments so that taxation in the member State on the territory of
  which the goods of other member States are sold is no less favorable
  than the taxation applied by this member State under the similar
  circumstances in respect of like goods, originating from its
  territory.”

  3. Member States shall determine directions, as well as forms and
  procedure of harmonization of tax legislation that affect mutual trade
  in order to avoid violation of competition conditions and not to
  prevent free movement of goods, works and services at the national
  level or at the level of the EAEU, including:

  1) harmonization (approximation) of excise rates on the most sensitive
  excisable goods;

  2) further improvement of the system on collection of value added tax
  in mutual trade (including the use of information technologies).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Principles Of Indirect Taxes Collection In Member States" article_identifier="39079">1. Collection of indirect taxes in mutual trade of goods shall be
  carried out by the principle of country of destination, providing for
  an application of zero rate of value added tax and (or) exemption from
  payment of excise taxes upon exportation of goods, as well as levying
  indirect taxes upon importation.

  Collection of indirect taxes and the mechanism of control over their
  payment upon exportation and importation of goods shall be carried out
  under the procedure provided for in Annex 18 of this Treaty.

  2. Collection of indirect taxes upon performing works and services
  supply shall be carried out in a member State, which territory is
  recognized as a place of selling works, supply of services.

  Collection of indirect taxes upon performing works, services supply
  shall be carried out under the procedure provided for in Annex 18 of
  this Treaty.

  3. Exchange of information between tax authorities of member States,
  which is required to ensure the full payment of indirect taxes, shall
  be carried out in accordance with separate international interagency
  agreement, which shall establish the procedure on exchange of
  information, form of application on importation of goods and payment
  of indirect taxes, rules of filling and requirement for exchange
  format.

  4. Upon importation of goods to the territory of one member State from
  the territory of another member State indirect taxes shall be
  collected by tax authorities of the importing member State, unless
  otherwise provided by the legislation of this member State in relation
  to the goods subject to marking with excise stamps (accounting control
  marks, signs).

  5. The rates of indirect taxes in mutual trade upon importation of
  goods to the territory of a member State shall not exceed the rates of
  indirect taxes levied on similar domestically produced goods that are
  being sold in the territory of this member State.

  6. Indirect taxes should not be collected upon importation to the
  territory of a member State of:

  1) goods, which in accordance with the legislation of this member
  State are not subject to taxation (exempted from taxation) when
  importing in its territory;

  2) goods being imported into the territory of a member State by
  natural persons not for the purposes of business activity;

  3) goods, imports of which into the territory of one member State from
  the territory of another member State is carried out in connection
  with their transfer within one juridical person ( obligation of
  notification of tax authorities on import (export) of such goods could
  be established in accordance with the legislation of a member State).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Income Taxation Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="39080">If one member State in accordance with its legislation and provisions
  of international treaties is entitled to levy the income of a tax
  resident (person with a permanent residence) of another member State
  earned in connection with employment in the first member State, such
  income shall be levied in the first member State as of the first day
  of employment at the rates established for such incomes of natural
  persons that are tax residents (persons with permanent place of
  residence) of this first member State.

  The provisions of this Article shall apply to taxation of income
  related to employment earned by the citizens of member States.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XVIII" name="Common Principles And Rules Of Competition" chapter_identifier="4512">
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="39081">1. The subject of this Article is establishment of common principles
  and rules of competition, providing detection and restraint of
  anticompetitive practices in the territory of the member States and
  actions, adversely affecting competition on transboundary markets in
  the territory of two and more member States.

  2. The provisions of this sector are applied to relationship,
  connected with implementation of competition (antimonopoly) policy in
  the territory of the member States, and to the relationship with
  participation of business entities (market participants) of the member
  States, which adversely affect or may affect competition on
  transboundary markets in the territory of two and more member States.
  Criteria of reference of the market to transboundary for the purposes
  of determining competence of the Commission are established by the
  decision of the Supreme council.

  3. The member States are eligible to establish additional prohibitions
  in the legislation, and additional requirements and limitations
  regarding prohibitions, provided for in Article 75 and 76 of this
  Treaty.

  4. The member States pursue the aligned competition (antimonopoly)
  policy regarding actions of business entities (market participants) of
  the third countries, if these actions may adversely affect the
  condition of competition on the goods markets of the member States.

  5. Nothing in this section should not be interpreted as preventing any
  member State from taking any measures it considers necessary for
  protection of the major interests of national defense or security of
  the State.

  6. Provisions of this section are applied to natural monopoly entities
  as provided for by this Treaty.

  7. Implementation of provisions of this Article is performed pursuant
  to Annex 19 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Common Principles Of Competition" article_identifier="39082">1. Application by the member States of the provisions of their
  competition (antimonopoly) legislation to business entities (market
  entities) of the member States is carried out similarly and equally
  irrespective of legal form and place of registration of such business
  entities (market entities ) on equal terms.

  2. The member States establish prohibitions in their legislation,
  including on the following:

  1) agreements between public authorities, local governments, other
  authorities or organizations carrying out their function or between
  them and business entities (market entities) if such agreements lead
  to or may lead to prevention, restriction or elimination of
  competition, except for the cases provided by this Treaty and/or by
  other international agreements of the member States;

  2) granting of the State or municipal preferences, except for the
  cases provided for in the legislation of the member States and with
  consideration of specificities as provided for by this Treaty and/or
  other international agreements of the member States.

  3. The Member states take effective measures for the prevention,
  identification and suppression of the actions (inaction) provided by
  subparagraph 1 of paragraph 2 of this Article.

  4. The member States in accordance with their legislation ensure
  effective control over economic concentration to the extent necessary
  for the protection and development of competition in the territories
  of each member State.

  5. Each member State provides existence of the national authority of
  the government whose competence includes implementation and (or)
  carrying out competition (antimonopoly) policy, which means,
  inter alia, granting to such authority powers to
  control observance over prohibition of anti-competitive actions and
  prohibition of unfair competition, control over economic
  concentration, and also powers on prevention, identification of
  violation of the competition (antimonopoly) legislation, take measures
  on termination of the mentioned violation and bringing to
  responsibility for such violation (hereinafter – the authorized body
  of the member State).

  6. The member States establish in their legislation effective
  sanctions for conducting anticompetitive actions regarding business
  entities (market entities) and officials of authorized bodies, based
  on the principles of effectiveness, proportionality, security,
  inevitability and definiteness, and provide control of their
  application. The member States recognize that in case of application
  of penalties, the highest penalties have to be established for the
  violations constituting the greatest threat for competition
  (agreements limiting competition, abuse of the dominant position by
  business entities (market entities) of the member States), thus the
  preferable fines are estimated from the sum of revenues of the
  offender gained from sale of goods or from the sum of expenses of the
  offender on purchase of goods, in the market where the violation took
  place.

  7. The member States pursuant to their legislation provide
  informational openness of competition (antimonopoly) policy pursued by
  them, including by publication of information on activity of the
  authorized bodies of the member States in mass media and the Internet.

  8. Authorized bodies of the member States in accordance with the
  legislation of their State and this Treaty carry out cooperation by
  sending notices, requests for providing information, carrying out
  consultations, informing on the investigations (hearing of cases)
  affecting interests of the other member State, carrying out
  investigations (hearing of cases) at the request of the authorized
  body of one of the member States and informing on its results.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Common Rules Of Competition" article_identifier="39083">1. Actions (inaction) of the business entities (market entities) with
  a dominant position resulted in prevention, restriction, elimination
  of the competition and (or) infringement of interests of other
  persons, including the following actions (inaction), are forbidden:

  1) establishment, support of monopolistically high or monopolistically
  low price of a good;

  2) withdrawal of a good from circulation, if such withdrawal resulted
  in increase of the price of goods ;

  3) imposition on the counter-partner economically or technologically
  unreasonable terms of the agreement which are unprofitable for him or
  do not relate to subject of the agreement;

  4) economically or technologically unreasonable reduction or
  termination of goods production if there is a demand for these goods
  or orders are placed for its deliveries with the possibility of its
  profitable production, and also if such reduction or such termination
  of goods production isn't directly provided for by this Treaty and/or
  other international agreements of the member States;

  5) economically or technologically unreasonable refusal or avoidance
  of the conclusion of the agreement with certain buyers (customers)
  with the possibility of production or delivery of the corresponding
  goods with specificities provided for in this Treaty and/or other
  international agreements of the member States;

  6) economically, technologically or otherwise unreasonable
  establishment of various prices (tariffs) for the same goods, creation
  of discriminatory conditions with specificities provided for in this
  Treaty and/or other international agreements of the member States;

  7) creation of restrictionson access to the goods market or exit from
  the goods market for other business entities (market entities).

  2. Unfair competition is not allowed, including:

  1) dissemination of the false, inadequate or distorted information
  which can cause losses to a business entity (market entity) or can
  cause damage of its business reputation;

  2) misleading concerning character, method and place of production,
  consumer properties, quality and quantity of goods or concerning its
  producers;

  3) incorrect comparison by the business entities (market entities ) of
  the goods produced or sold by it with the goods produced or sold by
  other business entities (market participants).

  3. Agreements are forbidden between business entities (market entities
  ) - competitors acting in one goods market which lead or can lead to:

  1) establishment or maintenance of the prices (tariffs), discounts,
  extra charges (surcharges), margins;

  2) increase, decrease or support of the prices at the auctions;

  3) division of the goods market by the territorial principle, volume
  of sale or purchase of goods, the range of goods sold or structure of
  sellers or buyers (customers);

  4) reduction or termination of goods production;

  5) refusal of the conclusion of agreements with certain sellers or
  buyers (customers).

  4. Vertical agreements are forbidden between business entities (market
  entities) (except for vertical agreements which are admissible
  according to the criteria of admissibility established by the Annex.
  19 to this Treaty), if:

  1) such agreements lead or can lead to establishment of the price of
  resale of goods, except for the case when the seller establishes a
  ceiling price of resale of goods for the buyer;

  2) such agreements stipulate the obligation of the buyer not to sell
  goods of the business entity (market entity), who is a competitor of
  the seller. Such prohibition does not concern agreement on
  organization by the buyer of sale of goods under the trademark or
  other means of individualization of the seller or the producer.

  5. Other agreements are forbidden between the business entities
  (market entities) (except for vertical agreements which are admissible
  according to the criteria of admissibility established by the Annex 19
  to this Treaty) if it is established that such agreements lead or can
  lead to competition restriction.

  6.Natural persons, commercial organizations and non-commercial
  organizations are forbidden to carry out coordination of economic
  activity of business entities (market entities) if such coordination
  leads or can lead to the consequences, stated in paragraphs 3 and 4 of
  this Article, which cannot be admitted as admissible under the
  criteria of admissibility, established by Annex 19 to this Treaty. The
  member States are entitled to establish in their legislation
  prohibition of coordination of economic activity, if such coordination
  leads or may lead to the consequences stated also in paragraph 5 of
  this Article, which cannot be admitted as admissible under the
  criteria of admissibility, established by Annex 19 to this Treaty.

  7. Prevention of violation by business entities (market entities ) of
  the member States, and also by natural persons and non-commercial
  organizations which do not carry out business activity, of common
  rules of competition established in this section if such violations
  affect or can adversely affect competition on transboundary markets in
  the territory of two and more member States, except for financial
  markets, is carried out by the Commission in the order provided by the
  Annex. 19 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="State Price Regulation" article_identifier="39084">The order of introduction of the State price regulation, and also
  challenging the decisions of the member States on its introduction are
  determined by the Annex 19 to this Treaty.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XIX" name="Natural Monopolies" chapter_identifier="4513">
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Sectors And Natural Monopoly Entities" article_identifier="39085">1. Member States in the regulation of natural monopolies are guided by
  rules and regulations provided by Annex 20 to this Treaty.

  2. Provisions of this section shall be applied to the relationships
  involving natural monopoly entities, consumers, executive authorities
  and local governments of the member States in the sectors of natural
  monopolies, affecting trade between member States as well as those
  specified in Appendix No. 1 to Annex 20 of this Treaty.

  3. Legal relations in the specific sectors of natural monopolies are
  defined under this section taking into account the specificities
  provided in Sections XX and XXI of this Treaty.

  4. In the member States the sectors of natural monopolies specified in
  Appendix No. 2 to Annex 20 of this Treaty are also fall within the
  scope of natural monopolies.

  In respect of natural monopolies specified in Appendix No. 1 to Annex
  20 of this Treaty requirements of the national legislation of the
  member States shall be applied.

  5. List of the services of natural monopolies attributable to the
  sectors of natural monopolies shall be established by the national
  legislation of the member States.

  6. Member States shall seek harmonization of the natural monopoly
  sectors specified in Appendixes No. 1 and 2 to Annex 20 to this
  Treaty, by means of reducing their number and by possible
  determination of a transitional period in Sections XX and XXI of the
  Treaty.

  7. Expansion of the sectors of natural monopolies in the member States
  is carried out:

  in accordance with the national legislation of the member States, if a
  member State intends to qualify a sector that is a natural monopoly
  sector in another member State and is specified in Appendixes No. 1 or
  No. 2 of Annex 20 to this Treaty as a natural monopoly sector.

  by the Commission Decision, in case if a member State intends to
  qualify another natural monopoly sector, which is not specified in
  Appendixes No. 1 or No. 2 to Annex 20 to this Treaty as a natural
  monopoly sector, upon an appropriate application made by this Member
  state to the Commission.

  8. This section does not apply to relations regulated by effective
  international bilateral agreements between the member States.
  Re-concluded international bilateral agreements between member States
  cannot contradict this section.

  9. Provisions of Section XVIII of this Treaty shall apply to natural
  monopolies taking into account specificities provided by this section.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XX" name="Energy" chapter_identifier="4514">
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Interaction Of The Member States In The Energy Sector" article_identifier="39086">1. For the purposes of the effective use of the potential of fuel and
  energy complexes of the member States as well as providing national
  economies with the main types of energy resources (electricity, gas,
  oil and petroleum products), member States shall develop a long-term
  mutually beneficial cooperation in the energy sector, conduct a
  coordinated energy policy, implement the gradual formation of common
  markets of energy resources in accordance with international
  agreements provided for in Articles 81, 83 and 84 of this Treaty, with
  a view to ensure energy security, based on the following basic
  principles:

  1) ensuring the market pricing of energy resources;

  2) ensuring the development of competition in the common market of
  energy resources;

  3) lack of technical, administrative and other barriers to trade in
  energy resources, appropriate equipment, technology and services
  related to them;

  4) provision of transport infrastructure development of common markets
  of energy resources;

  5) ensuring non-discriminatory conditions for economic entities of
  member States in the common markets of energy resources;

  6) creation of favorable conditions for attracting investments in the
  energy sector of the member States;

  7) harmonization of national norms and rules of the technological and
  commercial infrastructure of common markets of the energy resources.

  2. The relations of economic entities of member States operating in
  the sphere of electric power, gas, oil and petroleum products not
  covered by this section shall be implemented in accordance with the
  legislation of the member States.

  3. Provisions of section XVIII of this Treaty with respect to economic
  entities of member States in the fields of electric power, gas, oil
  and petroleum products are applied subject to particularities provided
  by this section and Section XIX of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Indicative (Estimated) Balances Of Gas, Oil And Petroleum Products" article_identifier="39087">1. For the purpose of effective use of the total interstate energy
  potential and optimization of energy resources supply, the competent
  authorities of the member States shall develop and coordinate:

  indicative (estimated) gas balance of the EAEU;

  indicative (estimated) oil balance of the EAEU;

  indicative (estimated) petroleum products balances of the EAEU.

  2. Development of the balances referred to in paragraph 1 of this
  Article shall be carried out with the participation of the Commission
  and in accordance with the methodology of developing indicative
  (estimated) balances of gas, oil and petroleum products, developed
  within the period provided in paragraph 1 of Article 104 of this
  Treaty and agreed by the competent authorities of the member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Creation Of A Common Energy Market Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39088">1. Member States shall carry out phased creation of a common energy
  market of the EAEU on the basis of parallel operation of electric
  power systems subject to the transitional provisions specified in
  paragraphs 2 and 3 of Article 104 of this Treaty.

  2. Member States shall develop the concept and program of creation of
  a common energy market of the EAEU approved by the Supreme Council.

  3. Member States conclude an international agreement within the EAEU
  on the creation of a common energy market based on the provisions of
  the approved concept and program of formation of a common energy
  market of the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Providing The Access To Services Of Natural Monopolies Subjects In The Energy Sector" article_identifier="39089">1. Within existing technical capabilities the member States shall
  ensure free access to services of entities of natural monopolies in
  the energy sector, provided the priority use of these services for the
  domestic demand in electric energy (power) of the member States in
  accordance with common principles and rules according to the Annex 21
  to this Treaty.

  2. Principles and rules of access to the services of natural
  monopolies subjects in the electric energy sector, including the
  basics of pricing and tariff policy set out in the Annex 21 to this
  Treaty shall be effective to the Republic of Belarus, Republic of
  Kazakhstan and the Russian Federation. In the case of accession of new
  members to the EAEU the indicated Annex shall be amended accordingly.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Creation Of A Common Gas Market Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39090">and Access to Services of Natural Monopolies in the field of Gas
  Transportation

  1. Member States shall carry out the phased creation of a common
  market of gas of the EAEU in accordance with Annex 22 subject to the
  transitional provisions provided for in paragraphs 4 and 5 of Article
  104 of this Treaty.

  2. Member States shall develop the concept and program creation of a
  common gas market of the EAEU approved by the Supreme Council.

  3. Member States conclude an international agreement within the EAEU
  on the formation of the common gas market, based on the provisions of
  the approved concept and program for the creation of a common market
  of gas in the EAEU.

  4. Member States within the existing technical capabilities, free
  capacities of gas transmission systems taking into account the agreed
  indicative (estimated) gas balance of the EAEU and on the basis of
  civil contracts of the economic entities shall provide free access for
  the economic entities of other member States to gas transmission
  systems located in the territories of the member States, to transport
  natural gas on the basis of common principles, conditions and rules
  provided under the Annex 22 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Formation Of Common Oil And Petroleum Products Market Of The Eaeu" article_identifier="39091">and Providing Access to Services of Natural Monopolies Subjects in the
  field of Oil and Petroleum Products Transportation

  1. Member States shall carry out the phased formation of a common
  market of oil and petroleum products of the EAEU in accordance with
  Annex 23 subject to the transitional provisions provided for in
  paragraphs 6 and 7 of Article 104 of this Treaty.

  2. Member States shall develop the concept and program formation of a
  common oil and petroleum products market of the EAEU approved by the
  Supreme Council.

  3. Member States conclude an international agreement within the EAEU
  on the formation of the common oil and petroleum products market,
  based on the provisions of the approved concept and program for the
  formation of a common market of oil and petroleum products in the
  EAEU.

  4. Member States within the existing technical possibilities in regard
  to the agreed indicative (estimated) oil balance of the EAEU as well
  as agreed indicative (estimated) petroleum products balance of the
  EAEU and on the basis of civil contracts of the economic entities
  shall provide free access for the economic entities of other member
  States to transmission systems located in the territories member
  States on the basis of common principles, conditions and rules
  provided under the Annex 23 hereto.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="The Authority Of The Commission In The Energy Sector" article_identifier="39092">In the energy sector the Commission monitors the enforcement of this
  section.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXI" name="Transport" chapter_identifier="4515">
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Coordinated (Correlated) Transport Policy" article_identifier="39093">1. The EAEU carries out coordinated (correlated) transport policy
  aimed at ensuring economic integration, consistent and gradual
  creation of a common transport space on the principles of competition,
  openness, security, reliability, availability and environmental
  compatibility.

  2. Objectives of coordinated (correlated) transport policy are:

  1) creation of a common market for transport services;

  2) adoption of correlated measures ensuring common benefits in the
  transport field and the implementation of best practices ;

  3) integration of the transport systems of the member States into the
  global transport system;

  4) efficient use of transit potential of the member States;

  5) improvement of quality of transport services;

  6) provision of transport security;

  7) reduction of the harmful effects of transport on the environment
  and human health;

  8) creation of a favorable investment climate.

  3. The main priorities of the coordinated (correlated) transport
  policy are:

  1) forming a common transport space;

  2) creation and development of the Eurasian transport corridors;

  3) implementation and development of the transit potential within the
  EAEU;

  4) coordination of the development of transport infrastructure;

  5) creation of logistics centers and transport organizations providing
  the transportation process optimization;

  6) involvement and use of human resources capacity of the member
  States;

  7) development of science and innovation in the field of transport.

  4. Coordinated (correlated) transport policy is formed by the member
  States.

  5. The main directions and stages of coordinated (aligned) transport
  policy are determined by the Supreme Council.

  6. Monitoring of the implementation by the member States of the
  coordinated (aligned) transport policy is conducted by the Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Scope Of Application" article_identifier="39094">1. Provisions of this section shall apply to road, air, water and rail
  transport taking into account provisions of Sections XVIII and XIX of
  this Treaty and the peculiarities stipulated in Annex 24 to this
  Treaty.

  2. The member States shall seek a gradual liberalization of transport
  services between the member States.

  Procedures, conditions and stages of liberalization are determined by
  international treaties within the EAEU with peculiarities stipulated
  in Annex 24 to this Treaty.

  3. Requirements for transport security (transport safety and transport
  operation security) are determined by the legislation of the member
  States and international agreements.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXII" name="Government (Municipal) Procurement" chapter_identifier="4516">
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Objectives And Regulatory Principles In The Field Of Government (Municipal) Procurement" article_identifier="39095">1. The member States shall determine the following objectives and
  principles of regulation in the government (municipal) procurement
  (hereinafter - Procurement):

  regulation of relations in the field of procurement by the legislation
  of the member States on procurement and international treaties of the
  member States;

  ensuring optimal and efficient expenditure of funds used for
  procurement in the member States;

  granting national treatment in procurement to member States;

  inadmissibility to third countries in the field of procurement of a
  more favorable treatment than that accorded among the member States;

  ensuring openness of information and transparency of procurement;

  ensuring unhindered access of potential suppliers and suppliers of the
  member States to participate in the procurement conducted
  electronically through the mutual recognition of electronic signature,
  designed ​in accordance with the legislation of a member State, by
  another member State;

  ensuring existence of authorized regulatory and supervisory
  authorities of the member State in procurement (it is allowed that
  these functions to be carried out by one body);

  establishment of liability for violation of the procurement
  legislation of the member States

  development of competition and opposition to corruption and other
  abuses in procurement.

  2. This Treaty shall not apply to the procurement, which details
  constitute the state secret (state secrets).

  3. Procurement in the member States shall be conducted in accordance
  with Annex 25.

  4. This section shall not apply to procurement conducted by the
  national (central) banks of the member States, subject to the
  provisions of paragraphs second - fourth of this item.

  The national banks (central) banks of the member States shall conduct
  procurement for administrative purposes, construction work and capital
  repair in accordance with their internal rules for procurement
  (hereinafter – rules for procurement). Regulations on procurement
  should not be contrary to the purposes and principles set out in this
  article, including provision of equal access to potential suppliers of
  the member States. In exceptional cases the decision of the supreme
  body of the national (central) bank may establish exceptions to these
  principles.

  Rules for procurement should include requirements for procurement,
  including the procedure for the preparation and conduct of procurement
  procedures (including procurement methods) and the conditions for
  their application, the procedure for concluding agreements
  (contracts).

  The rules for procurement and information on planned and implemented
  procurement by the national (central) banks of the member States shall
  be posted on the official websites of national (central) banks of the
  member States on the Internet in the manner determined by the rules
  for procurement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXIII" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="4517">
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="39096">Member States shall perform cooperation in the sphere of
      protection and enforcement of intellectual property rights and
      provide protection and enforcement of intellectual property rights
      in their territories in accordance with provisions of
      international law, legal acts of the EAEU and legislation of
      member States.
    
  Cooperation of member States shall be performed in order to:

  - harmonize legislation of member States in the sphere of protection
  and enforcement of intellectual property rights;

  - protect interests of right owners of intellectual property rights of
  member States.

  2. Cooperation of member States shall be performed in accordance with
  the following directions:

  1) support of scientific and innovative development;

  2) improvement of mechanisms for commercialization and use of
  intellectual property objects;

  3) providing of favorable conditions for copyright and related rights
  owners;

  4) introduction of system of registration for trademarks and service
  marks of the Eurasian Economic Union and appellations of origin of
  goods of the Eurasian Economic Union;

  5) enforcement of intellectual property rights also in Internet;

  6) effective customs register, including introduction of common
  customs registry of intellectual property rights objects;

  7) application of coordinated measures in order to prevent circulation
  of counterfeit goods.

  3. In order to provide effective protection and enforcement of
  intellectual property rights member States shall participate in
  consultations organized by the Commission.

  Upon results of the consultations, the member States shall elaborate
  proposals on problem issues defined within their cooperation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Legal Regime Of Intellectual Property Objects" article_identifier="39097">Persons of one member State at the territory of another member
      State shall be granted national treatment with regard to the
      protection of intellectual property. Legislation of member State
      may provide for exception to national treatment in relation to
      judicial and administrative procedures, including the designation
      of an address for service or the appointment of an agent.
    
      Member States may implement in their law more extensive
      regulations for protection and enforcement of intellectual
      property than is required in international legal acts applicable
      to member States and legal acts of the EAEU.
    
      Member States shall perform its activity in the sphere of
      protection and enforcement of intellectual property rights in
      accordance with provisions of the following international
      treaties:
    
      
        The Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic
        Works of September 9, 1886;
      
  
      Budapest Treaty on the International Recognition of the Deposit of
      Microorganisms for the Purposes of Patent Procedure of April 28,
      1977;
    
      The WIPO Performances and Phonograms Treaty of December 20, 1996;
    
      The WIPO Copyright Treaty of December 20, 1996;
    
      The Patent Law Treaty of June 1, 2000;
    
      The Patent Cooperation Treaty of June 19, 1970;
    
      The Convention for the Protection of Producers of Phonograms
      Against Unauthorized Duplication of Their Phonograms of October
      29, 1971;
    
      The Madrid Agreement Concerning the International Registration of
      Marks of April 14, 1891, and the Protocol Relating to the Madrid
      Agreement Concerning the International Registration of Marks of
      June 27, 1989;
    
  - The International Convention for the Protection of Performers,
  Producers of Phonograms and Broadcasting Organizations of October 26,
  1961 (the Rome Convention);

  - The Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property of
  March 20, 1883 (hereinafter referred to as the Paris Convention);

      The Singapore Treaty on the Law of Trademarks of March 27, 2006.
    
  Member States, which are not Parties of the international treaties
  mentioned above, shall take an obligation to accede to these treaties.

  4. Regulation of protection and enforcement of intellectual property
  rights, including legal regime with regard to certain objects of
  intellectual property shall be provided in accordance with Annex 26 to
  the present Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Enforcement" article_identifier="39098">1. Member States shall perform enforcement measures on effective
  protection of intellectual property rights.

  2. Member States shall perform activity on enforcement with regard to
  objects of intellectual property rights, including those measures
  provided in the Customs Code of the Eurasian Economic Union and
  international treaties and acts of the EAEU on customs regulations.

  3. Competent authorities of member States in the sphere of enforcement
  of intellectual property ensures cooperation and interaction with the
  purpose of coordination of activity on detection, prevention and
  restraint of infringements on intellectual property at the territories
  of member States.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXIV" name="Industry" chapter_identifier="4518">
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Industrial Policy And Cooperation" article_identifier="39099">1. The member States independently develop, form and implement
  national industrial policies, which includes adoption of national
  programs of industry development and other measures of industrial
  policy, and also determine methods, forms and directions of granting
  industrial subsides which are not contrary to Article 93 of this
  Treaty.

  Industrial policy within the EAEU shall be formed by the member States
  in the main directions of industrial cooperation, which shall be
  approved by the Intergovernmental Council and carried out with
  consultative assistance and coordination of the Commission.

  2. Industrial policy within the EAEU shall be carried out by the
  member States on the basis of the following principles:

  1) equality and consideration of the member States’ national
  interests;

  2) mutual benefit;

  3) fair competition;

  4) non-discrimination;

  5) transparency.

  3. The goals of industrial policy implementation within the framework
  of the EAEU shall be acceleration and increase of industrial
  development stability, increase of competitiveness of the member
  States’ industrial systems, implementation of effective cooperation,
  which shall be addressed to increase of innovation activity,
  elimination of barriers in industrial area as well as on the way of
  movement of the member States’ industrial products.

  4. The member States to achieve goals of industrial policy
  implementation within the EAEU may:

  1) carry out mutual informing
  ation about plans on
  industry development;

  2) carry out regular meetings (consultations) of the representatives
  of the member States’ competent authorities, which are responsible for
  the development and implementation of national industrial policy, as
  well as at the Commission forum;

  3) develop and implement joint programs of development of priority
  economic activities for industrial cooperation;

  4) develop and coordinate the list of sensitive goods;

  5) implement joint projects, such as of development of infrastructure
  necessary to increase the effectiveness of industrial cooperation and
  to deepen industrial cooperation of the member States;

  6) develop technological and informative resources for the goals of
  industrial cooperation;

  7) carry out joint research and development works with the goals of
  promoting hi-tech production;

  8) implement alternative measures directed at elimination of barriers
  and development of mutually beneficial cooperation.

  5. If so required the relevant procedures on implementation of
  measures provided in paragraph 4 of this Article shall be developed
  following the decision of the Intergovernmental Council.

  6. The member States shall develop the Main Directions of Industrial
  Cooperation Within the EAEU (hereinafter – the Main directions), which
  are approved by the Intergovernmental Council and include economic
  activities of priority for industrial cooperation and sensitive goods.

  The Commission shall monitor and analyze the results of implementation
  of the Main directions annually, and if so required, in coordination
  with the member States shall prepare proposals on detailing of the
  Main directions.

  7. During the process of development and implementation of policies in
  the spheres of trade, customs and tariff, competition, government
  procurement, technical regulation, development of business activity,
  transport and infrastructure and in other areas the interests of the
  member States in industrial development shall be taken into account.

  respect of sensitive goods before the adoption of measures of
  industrial policy the member States shall carry out consultations for
  mutual consideration of positions.

  Member states shall preliminary mutually inform each other about
  planned directions of implementation of national industrial policies
  under the approved list of sensitive goods.

  The member States jointly with the Commission shall develop the
  procedure of carrying out the said consultations and (or) mutual
  information which shall be approved by the Council of the Commission.

  9. To implement industrial cooperation within the EAEU the member
  States with consultative assistance and coordination by the Commission
  will be able to develop and apply the following instruments:

  1) promotion of mutually beneficial industrial cooperation with the
  aim of creation of hi-tech, innovative and competitive production;

  2) joint programs and projects with the participation of the member
  States on a mutually beneficial ground;

  3) joint technological platforms and industrial clusters;

  4) other instruments, which assist for development of industrial
  cooperation.

  10. To implement the provisions of this Article the member States with
  a participation of the Commission may develop additional documents and
  mechanisms.

  11. The Commission shall carry out consultative assistance and
  coordination of the member States’ activity in the main directions of
  industrial cooperation within the limits of authorities, which are
  provided by the Annex 27 to this Treaty.

  For the purposes of this Article, the terms shall be used in
  accordance with the Annex 27 to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Industrial Subsidies" article_identifier="39100">order to provide conditions for the sustainable and efficient
  development of the member States economies, as well as conditions
  encouraging the development of mutual trade and fair competition
  between the member States, within the territories of the member States
  common rules for granting subsidies with regards to the industrial
  goods, including during rendering or receiving services that are
  directly associated with the production, sale and consumption of the
  industrial goods, under Annex 28 of this Treaty shall be effective.

  2. Commitments of the member States arising from the provisions of
  this Article and Annex 28 to this Treaty shall not apply to the legal
  relations between the member States and third countries.

  3. For the purposes of this article a subsidy shall mean:

  a) financial contribution made by the subsidizing body of the member
  State (or a body authorized by the member State), in the result of
  which benefits are created (conferred) and which is carried out in the
  form of:

  direct transfer of funds (e.g., in the form of irrevocable loans,
  credits) or acquisition of shares in the charter capital, or its
  increase, or an obligation to transfer such funds (e.g., loan
  guarantees);

  full or partial waiver of the collection of payments that would have
  to flow into the revenue of the member State (for example, tax
  exemptions, debt relief). In this case an exemption of an exported
  industrial good from duties and taxes borne by the like product when
  destined for domestic consumption, or reduction of such duties and
  taxes, or refund of such duties or taxes in amounts not exceeding
  those which actually have been accrued, shall not be regarded as a
  subsidy;

  provision of goods or services (except industrial goods or services
  for the maintenance and development of common infrastructure);

  purchase of industrial goods;

  b) any other form of income or price support which affects (directly
  or indirectly) the reduction of import of an industrial good from the
  territory of any member State or the increase of export of an
  industrial good to the territory of any member State which results in
  an advantage that is provided.

  Types of subsidies are provided in Annex 28 to this Treaty.

  4. The subsidizing body may entrust or prescribe to any other
  organization to carry out one or more of its functions related to the
  provision of subsidies. The actions of such organization shall be
  deemed as actions of subsidizing body.

  Legal acts signed by the Head of a member State aimed at providing
  subsidies shall be deemed as actions of the subsidizing body.

  5. An investigation in order to analyze the conformity of subsidies
  granted on the territory of a member State to the provisions of this
  Article and Annex 28 to this Treaty shall be conducted pursuant to the
  procedure provided for in the Annex 28 to this Treaty.

  6. The Commission shall ensure control of the implementation of the
  provisions of this Article and Annex 28 to this Treaty and shall be
  entrusted with the following authorities:

  1) monitoring and carrying out of comparative legal analysis of member
  States’ legislation for compliance with the provisions of this Treaty
  in respect of granting subsidies as well as preparation of annual
  reports on the compliance of the member States with the provisions of
  this Article and Annex 28 to this Treaty;

  2) assisting in organization of consultations of the member States on
  the issues of harmonization and unification of the member States’
  legislation in the sphere of provision of subsidies;

  3) adoption of decisions binding for the member States provided for by
  Annex 28 to this Treaty, following the procedure of voluntary approval
  of specific subsidies to be provided or provided, including:

  making decisions on the admissibility or non-admissibility of specific
  subsidies in accordance with paragraph 6 of Annex 28 to this Treaty on
  the basis of criteria which are provided by international agreement
  within the EAEU provided for in paragraph 7 of Annex 28 to this
  Treaty;

  conducting investigations on the facts of provision of specific
  subsidies and making decisions binding in relation to them, in cases
  specified by the international agreement within the EAEU provided for
  in paragraph 7 of Annex 28 to this Treaty;

  resolution of disagreements on matters related to the implementation
  of the provisions of this Article and Annex 28 to this Treaty, and
  provision of explanations on their application;

  4) requesting and receiving information on the granted subsidies in
  the manner and on the terms set by the international treaty within the
  EAEU provided for in paragraph 7 of Annex 28 to this Treaty.

  The application of subparagraphs 3 and 4 of this Article shall be
  carried out taking into account the transitional provisions, provided
  for in paragraph 1 of Article 105 of this Treaty.

  7. Disputes in respect of the provisions of this Article and Annex 28
  to this Treaty shall be primarily resolved through negotiations and
  consultations. If the dispute is not settled through negotiations and
  consultations within 60 calendar days from the date of a formal
  written request for their conduct sent by the member State that
  initiated the dispute, to the respondent member State, than the
  complainant member State has the right to appeal to the Court of the
  EAEU.

  If the decisions of the Court of the EAEU are not implemented within
  the specified period of time or if the Court of the EAEU decides that
  the measures which were notified by the respondent member State are
  inconsistent with the provisions of this Article and Annex 28 to this
  Treaty, the complainant member State shall be entitled to take
  proportionate counter measures.

  8. The period during which the member States may challenge a specific
  subsidy, provided in violation of Annex 28 to this Treaty, shall be 5
  years from the date of provision of specific subsidy.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXV" name="Agro-Industrial Complex" chapter_identifier="4519">
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Objectives And Tasks Of Coordinated Agro-Industrial Policy." article_identifier="39101">1. In order to ensure the development of agriculture and rural areas
  in favor of the population of each member State and of the EAEU as a
  whole as well as of economic integration in the framework of the EAEU,
  the member States shall implement coordinated agro-industrial policy
  by, among other things, the following:

  application of regulatory mechanisms provided for in this Agreement
  and other international agreements within the EAEU in the sphere of
  agro-industrial complex;

  mutual provision by each member State to the other and to the
  Commission of production development plan for each of sensitive
  agricultural product. The list of such products shall be developed
  based on proposal of the member States and approved by the Council.

  2. The aim of coordinated agro-industrial complex is the efficient
  realization of the member States resource potential for optimizing the
  volumes of production of competitive agricultural and food products,
  meeting the needs of the common agricultural market, and increasing
  export of agricultural and food products.

  3. Implementation of coordinated agro-industrial complex shall cover
  the following objectives:

  balanced development of production and markets of agricultural and
  food products;

  ensuring fair competition between entities of the member States,
  including equal access to the common agricultural market;

  unification of requirements relating to circulation of agricultural
  and food products;

  protection of the interest of agricultural producers on domestic and
  foreign markets.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Basic Areas Of Coordinated Agro-Industrial Policy And Measures Of State Support To Agriculture:" article_identifier="39102">1. Development of objectives of coordinated agro-industrial complex
  shall provide interstate cooperation in the following areas:

  1) forecasting in the agro-industrial complex;

  2) state support to agriculture;

  3) regulation of common agricultural market;

  4) unified requirements relating to the production and circulation of
  the products;

  5) development of export process of agricultural and food products;

  6) scientific and innovative development of agro-industrial complex;

  7) integrated information support for agro-industrial complex.

  2. To implement measures of coordinated agro-industrial complex,
  regular consultations regarding, among other things, sensitive
  agricultural products shall be held at least once a year by the member
  States organized by the Commission. Based upon the results of
  consultations, recommendations regarding implementation of coordinated
  agro-industrial complex shall be developed within areas specified in
  the paragraph 1 of this Agreement.

  3. In implementing coordinated agro-industrial complex, member States
  shall take into account peculiar nature of activity of the
  agro-industrial complex, which may include not only industrial and
  economic significance of the sector, but social significance of the
  sector as well as structural and natural-climatic differences between
  regions and territories of member States.

  4. Implementation of policy in other areas of integrative cooperation,
  including in the sphere of sanitary, phytosanitary and veterinary
  (veterinary-sanitary) measures for agricultural products, shall be
  made based upon aim, objectives and areas of coordinated
  agro-industrial complex.

  5. Within the EAEU, state support to agriculture shall be implemented
  in accordance with the "Protocol on Measures of State Support for
  Agriculture (Annex 29 to this Treaty).

  6. Disputes relating to this Article and to the Annex 29 to this
  Treaty shall be primary settled through negotiations and consultations
  with participation of the Commission. In the event that the dispute is
  not resolved through negotiations and consultations within 60 calendar
  days from the date of a formal request for consultations made by the
  member State that initiated the dispute to a member State defendant,
  member State appellant has the right to submit the dispute for
  settlement to the Court of the EAEU. When submitting a formal request
  for consultation, a member State appellant shall inform the Commission
  within 10 days after the date the request is submitted.

  7. To implement coordinated agro-industrial complex, the Commission
  shall perform the following duties:

  to develop, coordinate and implement together with member States areas
  of coordinated agro-industrial complex within the limits of its
  competence;

  to coordinate the preparation by member States of joint forecasts of
  agro-industrial complex development as well as of demand and supply of
  agricultural and food products;

  to coordinate information sharing on member States’ agricultural
  sector development programs;

  to monitor member States’ agriculture development and measures of
  state support to agriculture;

  to monitor prices and to analyze competitiveness of products based on
  the HS Code mutually agreed by member States;

  to assist in conducting consultations and negotiations regarding the
  harmonization of legislation in the sphere of agro-industrial complex,
  including regulation on state support to agriculture and disputes
  settlement related to compliance of the commitment on state support to
  agriculture;

  to monitor and implement comparative legal analysis of the legislation
  of member States’ in the sphere of state support to agriculture on its
  compliance with the commitment under the EAEU;

  to prepare and provide to the member States state policy review in the
  sphere of agriculture and state support to agriculture, including
  recommendations on how to improve the effectiveness of state support;

  to provide an assistance to the member States on issues related to the
  calculation of state support to agriculture;

  to develop together with member States recommendations on
  implementation of coordinated measures aimed at developing export
  potential in agro-industrial complex;

  to coordinate joint scientific and innovative activities in the sphere
  of a agro-industrial complex, including those under the implementation
  of interstate programs by member States;

  to coordinate the development and implementation by member States of
  unified requirements for import, export and movement of breeding
  products on the territory of Customs Union as well as of methods for
  determining the breeding value of breeding animals and breeding
  certificates;

  to coordinate the development and implementation of unified
  requirements in the sphere of testing varieties and seed crops as well
  as the mutual recognition by member States of documents certifying
  varietal and sowing qualities of seeds;

  to promote a level playing field for competition within the areas of
  coordinated agro-industrial complex.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXVI" name="Labor Migration" chapter_identifier="4520">
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Cooperation Between Member States In The Field Of Labor Migration" article_identifier="39103">1. The member States shall cooperate to coordinate policies in the
  field of labor migration within the EAEU, as well as to assist the
  organized recruitment and attracting member States workers for the
  their employment in the member States.

  2. Cooperation of member States in the field of labor migration is
  carried out by collaboration of the state authorities of the member
  States who have the competence regarding relevant issues.

  3. Cooperation of the member States in the field of labor migration
  within the EAEU is carried out in the following forms:

  1) coordination of common approaches and principles in the labor
  migration field ;

  2) exchange of statutory legal acts;

  3) information exchange;

  4) implementation of measures aimed at preventing the spread of
  inadequate information;

  5) the exchange of experiences, organization of probation period,
  seminars and training courses;

  6) cooperation within advisory bodies.

  4. Upon agreement the member States may define other forms of
  cooperation in the field of migration.

  5. The definitions used in this section mean the following:

  “State of entry” – the member State in whose territory a citizen of
  another member State is going to;

  “State of permanent domicile” - a member State where the member State
  worker is a citizen;

  “State of employment” - the member State in whose territory the labor
  activity is carried out;

  “Educational documents” - documents of State standard on education, as
  well as documents on education, recognized at the level of State
  documents on education ;

  “Customer of works (services )” - a legal or natural person who
  provides a worker of a member State a job on the basis of a civil
  agreement concluded with him under terms and conditions prescribed by
  the legislation of the state of employment;

  “Migration card (card)” - a document that contains information about a
  citizen of a member State to enter the territory of another member
  State and is used for accounting and control of their temporary stay
  in the territory of State of entry;

  “Employer” - a legal or a natural person who provides a member State
  worker a job on the basis of an employment agreement concluded with
  him in the manner and conditions prescribed by the legislation of the
  State of employment;

  “Social welfare (social insurance)” – a compulsory insurance against
  temporary disability and maternity, compulsory insurance against
  accidents at work and occupational diseases and compulsory medical
  insurance;

  “Work activity” - activity based on the labor agreement or activity on
  work performance (supply of services) on the basis of a civil law
  contract carried out in the territory of the state of employment in
  accordance with the legislation of that State;

  “A member State worker” - a person who is a citizen of a member State
  lawfully residing and lawfully performing work within the territory of
  the State of employment, of which he is not citizen and who does not
  permanently reside in it;

  “Family member” - a person married to the member State worker as well
  as children dependent on them and other persons who are recognized as
  members of the family in accordance with the legislation of the State
  of employment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Labor Activity Of The Member States Workers" article_identifier="39104">1. Employers and (or) customers of works (services) of a member State
  are entitled to employ member States workers without restrictions for
  the protection of the national labor market. At the same time, the
  member States workers are not required to obtain a permit for
  conduction of the work activities in the State of employment.

  2. The member States shall not impose and apply restrictions set by
  their legislation in order to protect the national labor market, with
  the exception of restrictions stipulated by this Treaty and by the
  legislation of the member States in order to ensure national security
  (including the economic sectors of strategic importance) and public
  order regarding work activity, the occupation, and territory of stay
  carried out by the member States workers.

  3. For the purposes of conduction of work activities by the member
  States worker in the State of employment the education documents,
  issued by education organizations (educational institutions,
  educational organizations) shall be recognized without referring to
  the procedures for the recognition of the education documents set by
  the legislation of the State of employment.

  The workers of onу member States who aspire to engage in the
  educational, medical or pharmaceutical activities in other member
  State, shall undergo a procedure for the recognition of education
  documents stipulated by the legislation of the State of employment and
  may be allowed accordingly to educational, medical or pharmaceutical
  activities in accordance with the legislation of the State of
  employment.

  Documents of academic degrees and academic titles issued by the
  authorized bodies of the member States are recognized in accordance
  with the legislation of the State of employment.

  Employers (customers of works (services)) have the right to request
  notarial translations of documents on education to be translated into
  the language of the State of employment, as well as, if necessary, for
  the purpose of verification of documents on education of the member
  States workers to send requests, including by reference to information
  databases, in educational organizations (educational institutions,
  educational organizations) that issued the document on education and
  receive appropriate answers.

  4. Labor activity of a member State worker is regulated by the
  legislation of the State of employment consideration the provisions of
  this Treaty.

  5. Period of temporary stay ( domicile) of a member State worker and
  their family members in the State of employment are determined by the
  expiration period of labor agreement or a civil law contract conducted
  by the member State worker with the employer or customer of works
  (services).

  6. Citizens of a member State who arrived for the purpose of
  conduction of the work activity or employment in the territory of
  another member State and family members shall be exempt from the
  obligation to register (getting registered) for30 days from the date
  of entry.

  In the case of stay of a citizens of one member State in the territory
  of another member State for more than 30 days from the date of entry,
  these citizens are required to register (registration) in accordance
  with the legislation of the State of entry, if such obligation is
  established by the legislation of the state of entry.

  7. Citizens of a member State when entering the territory of another
  member State in cases specified by the legislation of the State of
  entry, use the migration cards (cards), unless otherwise is stipulated
  by international agreements of the member States.

  8. Citizens of the member States when entering the territory of
  another member State with one of the valid documents that allow
  putting the state border crossing marks by border control bodies,
  provided that the period of their stay does not exceed 30 days from
  the date of entry, shall be exempt from the use of migration cards
  (cards), if such a requirement set by the legislation of the State of
  entry.

  case of preschedule abrogation of labor agreement or civil law
  contract after the expiration of 90 days from the date of entry into
  the territory of the State of employment, a member State worker has
  the right without leaving the territory of the State of employment
  within 15 days to sign a new labor or civil law contract.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Rights And Obligations Of A Member State Worker" article_identifier="39105">member State worker has the right to conduct professional activities
  in accordance with the specialty and qualifications specified in the
  education documents, documents awarding academic degrees and (or)
  academic title, recognized in accordance with this Treaty and
  legislation of the Sate of employment.

  member State worker and their family members realize in accordance
  with the legislation of the State of employment, the right to:

  1) own, use and dispose their property;

  2) protect their property ;

  3) freely transfer their funds.

  3. The social welfare (social insurance) (except for pensions) of
  member States workers and their family members is provided on the same
  terms and conditions as for the citizens of the State of employment.

  Employment (insurance) experience of member States workers shall be
  counted in the total employment (insurance) experience for the
  purposes of social welfare (social insurance) except for pensions in
  accordance with the legislation of the State of employment.

  Retirement of member States workers and their family members is
  regulated by the legislation of the State of permanent domicile, as
  well as in accordance with separate international agreements between
  member States.

  4. The right of member States workers and their family members to
  receive emergency medical care (in emergency and urgent forms) and
  other health care is regulated in accordance with the Annex 30, as
  well as the legislation the State of employment and international
  agreements to which it is a Party.

  member State worker shall have the right to join trade unions on par
  with the citizens of the State of employment.

  member State worker is entitled to receive information regarding the
  order of their stay, the conditions of conduction of work activities,
  as well as the rights and obligations stipulated by the legislation of
  the State of employment from the State authorities of the State of
  employment (which are competent in relevant issues) and from the
  employer (customer of works (services)).

  7. At the request of a member State worker (including the ex -worker
  ), the employer (customer of works (services) shall at no charge to
  give him a certificate (certificates) and (or) a certified copy of the
  certificate (certificates) with the profession (specialty,
  qualifications and positions) , the period of work and wages within
  the terms established by the legislation of the State of employment .

  8. Children of a member State worker residing with them in the
  territory of the State of employment are entitled to attend preschool,
  get education in accordance with the legislation of the State of
  employment.

  9. Member States workers and their family members must observe the
  legislation of the State of employment, respect the culture and
  traditions of the State of employment and be liable for offenses
  committed under the legislation of the State of employment.

  10. Revenues of a member State worker received as a result of
  conduction of the work activity in the territory of the State of
  employment shall be subject to taxation in accordance with
  international agreements and legislation of the State of employment
  subject to the provisions of this Treaty.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXVII" name="Transitional Provisions" chapter_identifier="4521">
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="General Transitional Provisions" article_identifier="39106">1. International agreements of member States concluded within the
  legal framework of the Customs Union and the Single Economic Space,
  and which are effective on the date of entry into force of this
  Treaty, shall be the part of the law of the EAEU and shall be applied
  to the extent unless contradicts to this Treaty.

  2. The Decisions of the Eurasian Economic Supreme Council at the level
  of head of the states and Eurasian Economic Supreme Council at the
  level of Heads of governments and Eurasian Economic Commission, which
  are effective on the date of entry into force of this Treaty, shall
  remain in full force and shall be applied to the extent unless
  contradicts to this Treaty.

  3. From the date of entry into force of this Treaty:

  functions and powers of the Eurasian Economic Supreme Council at the
  level of head of the states and Eurasian Economic Supreme Council at
  the level of Heads of governments , acting in accordance with the
  Treaty on the Eurasian Economic Commission of 18 November 2011, shall
  be carried out by the Supreme Council and Intergovernmental Council
  correspondingly, acting in accordance with this Treaty;

  Eurasian Economic Commission, established in accordance with the
  Treaty on the Eurasian Economic Commission of 18 November 2011, shall
  act in accordance with this Treaty;

  the members of the Collegium of the Commission appointed before the
  entry into force of this Treaty, shall continue to fulfill their
  functions until the expiration of the term for which they have been
  assigned;

  the directors and deputy directors of departments, that have signed
  their labor agreements up to the entry into force of this Treaty,
  shall continue to perform their duties until the expiration of the
  terms stipulated in the labor agreements;

  the vacant positions in the structural units of the Commission shall
  be carried out based on procedure, provided by this Treaty.

  4. The International treaties listed in Annex 31 to this Treaty are
  also effective within the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Vii" article_identifier="39107">1. Functioning of common market of pharmaceuticals within the
  framework of the EAEU shall be carried out since 1 January accordance
  with an international agreement within the framework of the EAEU,
  which defining the common principles and rules for the circulation of
  pharmaceuticals which shall be concluded by member States no later
  than January 1, 2015.

  2. Functioning of common market of medical products (medical devices
  and medical equipment) within the framework of the EAEU shall be
  carried out since 1 January accordance with an international agreement
  within the framework of the EAEU, defining the common principles and
  rules for circulation of medical products (medical devices and medical
  equipment), which shall be concluded by member States no later than
  January 1, 2015.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Viii" article_identifier="39108">1. Unless the Customs Code of the Eurasian Economic Union enters into
  force, the customs regulation in the EAEU shall be conducted in
  accordance with the Treaty on the Customs Code of the customs union of
  27 November 29 and other international treaties of the member States,
  stipulating customs legal relations, which were concluded within the
  framework of formation of the legal base of the Customs Union and
  Single Economic Space, and included in to the Law of the EAEU in
  accordance with Article 99 of this Treaty, taking into account the
  provisions of this Article.

  2. For the purpose of application of international agreements,
  provided in Paragraph 1 of this Article, the following definitions are
  used:

  Member States of the Customs Union – member States in the meaning,
  determined by this Treaty;

  “common customs territory of the customs union (customs territory of
  the customs union)” – customs territory of the EAEU;

  “common commodity nomenclature of foreign economic activity of the
  customs union (commodity nomenclature of foreign economic activity)” –
  common Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic Activity of the
  Eurasian Economic Union;

  “common external tariff of the customs union” – Common External Tariff
  of the Eurasian Economic Union;

  “Commission of the Customs Union” - Eurasian Economic Commission;

  “international treaties of the member States of the customs union” -
  international treaties within the framework of the EAEU, including
  international treaties of the member States, included into the Law of
  the EAEU according to Article 99 of this Treaty;

  “customs border of the customs union (customs border)” – customs
  border of the Eurasian Economic Union;

  “product of the customs union” – product of the Eurasian Economic
  Union.

  4. Article 51 of the Customs Code of the Customs Union concerning
  maintenance of the common Commodity Nomenclature shall be applied
  taking into account Article 45 of this Treaty.

  5. Article 74 of the Customs Code of the Customs Union concerning
  tariff exemptions shall be applied taking into account Article 43 of
  this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Ix" article_identifier="39109">1. Regardless the provisions of Article 35 of this Treaty, member
  States are eligible to grant tariff preferences in trade with third
  countries unilaterally based on international treaty of the member
  State with the third country concluded before 1 January 2015, or
  international treaty concluded by all member States.

  Member States shall unify treaties based on which tariff preferences
  are granted.

  2. Safeguard, antidumping and countervailing measures applied in
  respect of goods imported into the customs territory of the EAEU
  through the review of safeguard, antidumping and countervailing
  measures in force in accordance with the legislation of member States
  shall apply until the expiry of the measures established by the
  relevant decision of the Commission, and may be subject to review in
  accordance with the provisions of Section IX of this Treaty and Annex
  8 to it.

  3. For the purpose of implementation of Article 36 of this Treaty, the
  Protocol on Common System of Tariff Preferences of the Customs Union
  of 12 December 2008 shall be applied until a Commission Decision,
  stipulating conditions and procedure for application of common system
  of tariff preferences of the EAEU in respect of goods originating from
  developing and (or) least-developed countries, enters into force.

  4. Prior to the entry into force of the decision of the Commission
  under paragraph 2 of Article 37 of this Treaty and establishing the
  rules for determining the country of origin of goods, the Agreement on
  common rules for determining the country of origin of goods, as of
  January 25, 2008 is applied.

  5. Prior to the entry into force of the decision of the Commission
  under paragraph 3 of Article 37 of this Treaty establishing the rules
  for determining the country of origin of goods, there is applied the
  Agreement on Rules of Origin of goods from developing and least
  developed countries as of December 12, 2008.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Xvi" article_identifier="39110">order to achieve the objectives set out in paragraph 1 of Article 70
  of this Treaty, member States will accomplish harmonization of their
  legislation in the field of financial markets by accordance with an
  international agreement within the framework of the EAEU and the
  Protocol on financial services (Annex 17 to this Treaty).

  2. Member States upon harmonization of legislation in the field of
  financial markets will decide on the powers and functions of a
  supranational body to regulate financial markets and create this
  supranational body in Almaty in 2025.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Xx" article_identifier="39111">1. To ensure the development of indicative (predictive) balances of
  gas, oil and oil products of the EAEU, contributing to the effective
  use of the total energy potential and optimization of interstate
  supply of fuel and energy resources, the competent authorities of
  member States before 1 January 2015 shall develop and approve
  methodology of forming the indicative (predictive) balances of gas,
  oil and oil products.

  order to create a common electric energy market of the EAEU the
  Supreme Council shall approve before July 1, concept, and before July
  1, program for creating a common electric energy market of the EAEU,
  providing term for fulfilment of the program activities until July 1,
  2018.

  3. After the completion of the fulfilment of program for creating a
  common electric energy market of the EAEU the member States shall
  conclude an international agreement within the EAEU on the creation of
  a common electric energy market of the EAEU, including common rules
  for access to the services of subjects of natural monopolies in the
  electricity sector, and ensure its entry into force not later than
  July 1, 2019.

  4. For the purposes of creating a common gas market of the EAEU the
  Supreme Council shall approve before January 1, concept, and before
  January 1, 2018 the program for the creation of common gas market of
  the EAEU, providing term for the fulfilment of program activities
  until January 1, 2024.

  5. After the completion of the program of activities to form a common
  gas market of the EAEU the member States shall conclude an
  international agreement within the EAEU on the creation of a common
  gas market of the EAEU, including common rules for access to
  transmission systems located in the territories of the member States,
  and will provide its entry into force not later than January 1, 2025.

  order to create common markets of oil and oil products the Supreme
  Council shall approve until January 1, 2016, and a concept until
  January 1, program for creating common markets of oil and oil products
  of the EAEU, providing a term for the fulfilment of program activities
  until January 1, 2024.

  7. After the completion of the fulfilment of program of activities the
  common markets for oil and oil products of the EAEU the member States
  shall conclude an international agreement on the creation of common
  markets for oil and oil products of the EAEU, containing common rules
  for access to the systems of transportation of oil and petroleum
  products, located in the territories of the member States, and ensure
  its entry into force no later than January 1, 2025

  8. Protocol on access to services of subjects of natural monopolies in
  the electric energy sector, including the basics of pricing and tariff
  policy (Annex 21 to this Treaty) shall be effective before the
  international agreement, provided in paragraph 3 of this Article, come
  into force. 9. Protocol on the rules of access to services of subjects
  of natural monopolies in the sphere of transportation of gas on
  transportation systems, including the basics of pricing and tariff
  policy (Annex 22 to this Treaty) shall be effective before the
  international agreement provided in paragraph 5 of this Article come
  into force.

  10. Protocol on the organization, management, operation and
  development of common markets of oil and oil products (Annex 23 of
  this Treaty) shall be effective before the international agreement
  provided in paragraph 7 of this Article come into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Transitional Provisions For Section Xxiv" article_identifier="39112">1. The member States shall ensure the entry into force of an
  international treaty within the EAEU, provided by paragraph 7 of the
  Protocol on Common Rules for Granting Industrial Subsidies (Annex 28
  to this Treaty), from January 1, 2017.

  From the date of entry into force of the international agreement, the
  provisions of sub-paragraphs 3 and 4 of paragraph 6 of Article 93 of
  this Treaty, paragraphs 6, 15, 20, 87 and 97 of the Protocol on Common
  Rules for the Granting of Industrial Subsidies (Annex 28 to this
  Treaty) shall enter into force.

  2. Provisions of Article 93 of this Treaty and Protocol on Common
  Rules for Granting of Industrial Subsidies (Annex 28 to his Treaty)
  shall not apply to the subsidies granted to the territories of the
  member States before January 1, 2012.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Transition Provisions For Section Xxv" article_identifier="39113">1. For the Republic of Belarus regarding paragraph 8 of the Protocol
  on Measures of State Support to Agriculture (Annex 29 to this Treaty)
  transition period is established until 1 of January 2016, during which
  the Republic of Belarus takes a commitment to reduce trade-distorting
  level of support as follows:

  in 2015 – 12 per cent;

  in 2016 - 10 per cent.

  2. Methodology for calculation of state support volumes provided for
  in paragraph 8 of the Protocol on Measures of State Support to
  Agriculture (Annex 29 to this Treaty), shall be developed and approved
  by 1 of January 2016.

  3. Commitments provided for in the third point of paragraph 8 of the
  Protocol on Measures of State Support to Agriculture (Annex 29 to this
  Treaty) shall come into force for the Republic of Belarus no later
  than 1 January 2025.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION XXVIII" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="4522">
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Social Guarantees, Privileges And Immunities" article_identifier="39114">On the territories of each member State, the members of the Council of
  the Commission and Collegium of the Commission, judges of the Court of
  the EAEU, officers and employees of the Commission and the Court of
  the EAEU shall enjoy social guarantees, privileges and immunities as
  are necessary for the exercise of their mandates and official
  (service) duties. The volume of these social guarantees, privileges
  and immunities is identified in accordance with the Annex 32 to this
  Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Accession To The Eaeu" article_identifier="39115">1. EAEU membership is open to any State that share its aims and
  principles, on terms agreed by the member States.

  2. To obtain the status of a candidate for membership in the EAEU the
  State concerned shall send an appropriate appeal to the Chairman of
  the Supreme Council.

  decision to grant a state the status of a candidate for membership the
  EAEU is adopted by consensus by the Supreme Council.

  4. On the basis of the decision of the Supreme Council a working group
  of representatives of the candidate country, member States and bodies
  of the EAEU (hereinafter - the working group) shall be formed to
  examine the degree of preparedness of a candidate to take on the
  obligations arising from the law of the EAEU, development of the draft
  program of actions for accession of the candidate country to the
  Eurasian Economic Union, as well as a draft of international agreement
  on accession of the State in the EAEU , which defines the scope of the
  rights and obligations of a candidate , as well as the format of its
  participation in the work of the EAEU .

  5. The Program of Actions for the accession of a candidate country
  into the EAEU shall be approved by the Supreme Council.

  6. The working Group on a regular basis shall submit to the Supreme
  Council a report on the implementation of the State Program of Action
  by candidate for accession to the EAEU. Upon the basis of the
  conclusion of the working group that the State Candidate has fully
  complied with its obligations under the law of the EAEU, the Supreme
  Council shall take a decision to sign with the State Candidate the
  international treaty of accession to the EAEU. The above mentioned
  international treaty is subject to ratification.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Observer States" article_identifier="39116">1. Any State may apply to the Chairman of the Supreme Council with a
  request to grant it a status of an Observer State at the EAEU.

  2. The decision on granting the status of an Observer State at the
  EAEU or refusal to grant such status shall be taken by the Supreme
  Council, taking into account the interests of integration development
  and achievement of the objectives of this Treaty.

  3. Authorized representatives of an Observer State of the EAEU may
  attend meetings at the invitation of the EAEU and receive
  non-confidential documents adopted by the EAEU.

  4. The Status of an Observer State to the EAEU does not imply the
  right to participate in decision-making process of EAEU bodies.

  5. The State that is receiving the status of the observer at the EAEU
  is obliged to refrain from any action that could harm the interests of
  the EAEU and its member States, the object and purpose of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="The Working Language Of The Eaeu." article_identifier="39117">Language of International Treaties within the EAEU and the Commission
  Decisions

  1. The working language of the EAEU shall be the Russian language.

  2. International treaties with the EAEU and the Commission decisions
  that are binding for member States shall be adopted in Russian with
  subsequent translation into national languages ​​of the member States,
  if provided so by their legislation, in the manner determined by the
  Commission.

  The translation into the national languages ​​of the member States
  shall be made at the expense of the funds allocated in the budget of
  the EAEU for the purpose.

  case of divergence of interpretation of the international agreements
  and the decisions referred to in paragraph 2 of this article, the
  Russian text shall be used.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Access And Publication" article_identifier="39118">1. International treaties within the EAEU, international agreements
  with a third party and decisions of the EAEU bodies shall be
  officially published on the official website of the EAEU in the way
  determined by the Intergovernmental Council.

  The date of publication of decision of the EAEU’s body on the official
  website of the EAEU is considered to be the date of official
  publication of this decision.

  2. No decision referred to in Paragraph 1 of this Article may not
  enter into force before their official publication.

  3. Decisions of the EAEU body shall be forwarded to the member States
  not later than three calendar days from the date of the decision.

  4. Bodies of the EAEU shall provide preliminary publication of the
  draft decisions on the official website of the EAEU, at least 30
  calendar days before the date on which a decision is scheduled for
  adoption. Draft decisions of the EAEU bodies taken in exceptional
  cases requiring an immediate response may be published in other terms.

  The interested persons may submit to this body their comments and
  suggestions.

  The procedure for collection, analysis and assessment of these
  comments and suggestions shall be determined by the rules of the
  relevant body of the EAEU.

  5. The decisions of the EAEU bodies, containing information of limited
  distribution and its decision drafts shall not be officially
  published.

  6. Provisions of this Article shall not apply to decisions of the
  Court of the EAEU, the procedure of entering into force and the
  publication of which is determined by the Statute of the Court of the
  Eurasian Economic Union (Annex 2 to this Treaty).

  7. The provisions of the paragraph 4 of this Article shall not apply
  to decisions of the EAEU bodies in cases where pre-publication drafts
  of such decisions may prevent their enforcement or otherwise be
  contrary to the public interests.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="39119">Disputes relating to the interpretation and (or) the application of
  provisions of this Treaty shall be settled through consultation and
  negotiation.

  If no agreement has been reached within 3 months from the date when
  one party of dispute send the other party of the dispute a formal
  written request for consultations and negotiations, unless otherwise
  provided by the Statute of the Court (Annex 2 to the Treaty), the
  dispute may be submitted by either of the parties to the dispute to
  the Court of the EAEU, if the parties to the dispute have not agreed
  upon the use of other mechanisms for its resolution.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Entry Of The Treaty Into Force" article_identifier="39120">This Treaty shall come into force from the date of receipt by the
  Depositary of the last written notification on the implementation by
  the member States of the internal procedures necessary for its entry
  into force.

  With the entry into force of this Treaty, the international agreements
  concluded in the framework of the Customs Union and the Single
  economic space according to the Annex 33 to this Treaty shall be
  terminated.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Relation Of This Treaty To Other International Agreements" article_identifier="39121">1. This Treaty shall not prevent the member States from concluding
  international agreements not inconsistent with the purposes and
  principles of this Treaty.

  2. Bilateral international agreements between the member States,
  providing more in-depth level of integration or provision of
  additional benefits in favor of their natural and (or) legal persons
  as compared with the provisions of this Treaty or international
  agreements within the EAEU, shall apply to relations between the
  countries that have concluded them and can be concluded provided that
  they do not affect the exercise by them and by other member States of
  the EAEU of their rights and fulfillment of their obligations
  hereunder and under international treaties within the EAEU.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Introduction Of Amendments To The Treaty" article_identifier="39122">This Treaty may be amended and supplemented by separate protocols,
  which shall be an integral part of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Registration Of The Treaty In The Secretariat Of The United Nations Organization" article_identifier="39123">This Treaty is subject to registration by the Secretariat of the
  United Nations Organization in accordance with Article 102 of the
  Charter of the United Nations Organization.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Clauses" article_identifier="39124">Reservations to this Treaty shall not be permitted.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Withdrawal From The Treaty" article_identifier="39125">1. Any member State may withdraw from this Treaty, having sent the
  Depositary of this Treaty through diplomatic channels a written notice
  of its intention to withdraw from this Treaty. This Treaty in respect
  of that State shall cease after 12 months from the date of receipt by
  the depositary of this Treaty of such notification.

  2. A member State that has made the notification in accordance with
  paragraph 1 of this Article on its intention to withdraw from this
  Treaty shall be obliged to settle its financial obligations incurred
  in connection with its participation in this Treaty. This obligation
  remains in force despite the withdrawal of the state from this Treaty,
  up to its full implementation.

  3. On the basis of the notification referred to in paragraph 1 of this
  Article the Supreme Council shall decide to begin the process of
  settlement of obligations arising in connection with the participation
  of a member State in this Treaty.

  4. Withdrawal from this Treaty shall automatically entail the
  termination of membership in the EAEU and withdrawal from the
  international agreements in the framework of the EAEU.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="4523">
      <article article_identifier="39126">Done in Astana on 29 May 2014, signed in a single copy in the
  Belarusian, Kazakh and Russian languages, all texts shall be equally
  authentic.

  In case of any divergence of interpretation of this Treaty, the
  Russian text shall be used.

  The original of this Treaty shall be deposited at the Eurasian
  Economic Commission, which, as the depositary of this Treaty, shall
  send each Party a certified copy of this Treaty.

  for the Republic of Belarus for the Republic of Kazakhstan for Russian
  Federation

  (signature) (signature) (signature)</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
