<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU - Algeria</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>18</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>16</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2002-04-22</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2005-09-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2006-07-24</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2017-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DZA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">DZA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Africa; Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398350436383&amp;uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/ES/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398350436383&amp;uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398350436383&amp;uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398350436383&amp;uri=CELEX:22005A1010(01)</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="198">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="1508">1. An Association is hereby established between the Community and its
  Member States of the one part and Algeria of the other part.

  2. The aims of this Agreement are to:

  - provide an appropriate framework for political dialogue between the
  Parties, allowing the development of close relations and cooperation
  in all areas they consider relevant to such dialogue,

  - promote trade and the expansion of harmonious economic and social
  relations between the Parties and establish the conditions for the
  gradual liberalisation of trade in goods, services and capital,

  - facilitate human exchanges, particularly in the context of
  administrative procedures,

  - encourage integration of the Maghreb countries by promoting trade
  and cooperation within the Maghreb group and between it and the
  Community and its Member States,

  - promote economic, social, cultural and financial cooperation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="1509">Respect for the democratic principles and fundamental human rights
  established by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights shall inspire
  the domestic and international policies of the Parties and shall
  constitute an essential element of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="Political Dialogue" chapter_identifier="199">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="1510">1. A regular political and security dialogue shall be established
  between the Parties. It shall help build lasting links of solidarity
  between the partners which will contribute to the prosperity,
  stability and security of the Mediterranean region and bring about a
  climate of understanding and tolerance between cultures.

  2. Political dialogue and cooperation are intended in particular to:

  (a) facilitate rapprochement between the Parties through the
  development of better mutual understanding and regular coordination on
  international issues of common interest;

  (b) enable each party to consider the position and interests of the
  other;

  (c) contribute to consolidating security and stability in the
  Euro-Mediterranean region;

  (d) help develop joint initiatives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="1511">Political dialogue shall cover all issues of common interest to the
  Parties, in particular the conditions required to ensure peace,
  security and regional development through support for cooperation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="1512">Political dialogue shall be established at regular intervals and
  whenever necessary, notably:

  (a) at ministerial level, mainly in the framework of the Association
  Council;

  (b) at the level of senior officials representing Algeria, on the one
  hand, and the Council Presidency and the Commission on the other;

  (c) taking full advantage of all diplomatic channels including regular
  briefings, consultations on the occasion of international meetings and
  contacts between diplomatic representatives in third countries;

  (d) where appropriate, by any other means which would contribute to
  consolidating dialogue and increasing its effectiveness.

  FREE MOVEMENT OF GOODS</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="1513">The Community and Algeria shall gradually establish a free-trade area
  over a transitional period lasting a maximum of 12 years starting from
  the date of the entry into force of this Agreement in accordance with
  the following provisions and in conformity with those of the 1994
  General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade and the other multilateral
  agreements on trade in goods annexed to the Agreement establishing the
  World Trade Organisation (WTO), hereinafter referred to as
  "GATT".</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Industrial Products" chapter_identifier="200">
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="1514">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to products originating in
  the Community and Algeria falling within Chapters 25 to 97 of the
  Combined Nomenclature and of the Algerian Customs tariff with the
  exception of the products listed in Annex 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="1515">Products originating in Algeria shall be imported into the Community
  free of customs duties and charges having equivalent effect.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="1516">1. Customs duties and charges having equivalent effect applicable on
  import into Algeria of products originating in the Community listed in
  Annex 2 shall be abolished upon the entry into force of this
  Agreement.

  2. Customs duties and charges having equivalent effect applicable on
  import into Algeria of the products originating in the Community
  listed in Annex 3 shall be progressively abolished in accordance with
  the following timetable:

  - two years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 80 % of the basic duty,

  - three years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement
  each duty and charge shall be reduced to 70 % of the basic duty,

  - four years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 60 % of the basic duty,

  - five years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 40 % of the basic duty,

  - six years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 20 % of the basic duty.

  - seven years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement the
  remaining duties shall be abolished.

  3. Customs duties and charges having equivalent effect applicable on
  import into Algeria of the products originating in the Community other
  than those listed in Annexes 2 and 3 shall be progressively abolished
  in accordance with the following timetable:

  - two years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 90 % of the basic duty,

  - three years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement
  each duty and charge shall be reduced to 80 % of the basic duty,

  - four years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 70 % of the basic duty,

  - five years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 60 % of the basic duty,

  - six years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 50 % of the basic duty,

  - seven years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement
  each duty and charge shall be reduced to 40 % of the basic duty,

  - eight years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement
  each duty and charge shall be reduced to 30 % of the basic duty,

  - nine years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 20 % of the basic duty,

  - 10 years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 10 % of the basic duty,

  - 11 years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement each
  duty and charge shall be reduced to 5 % of the basic duty,

  - 12 years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement the
  remaining duties shall be abolished.

  4. In the event of serious difficulties for a given product, the
  timetables established in accordance with paragraphs 2 and 3 may be
  reviewed by the Association Committee by common accord on the
  understanding that the schedule for which the review has been
  requested may not be extended in respect of the product concerned
  beyond the maximum transitional period referred to in Article 6. If
  the Association Committee has not taken a decision within 30 days of
  its application to review the timetable, Algeria may suspend the
  timetable provisionally for a period which may not exceed one year.

  5. For each product concerned, the basic duty to be gradually reduced
  as provided in paragraphs 2 and 3 shall be the rates referred to in
  Article 18.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="1517">The provisions concerning the abolition of customs duties on imports
  shall also apply to customs duties of a fiscal nature.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="1518">1. Exceptional measures of limited duration which derogate from the
  provisions of Article 9 may be taken by Algeria in the form of an
  increase or reintroduction of customs duties.

  These measures may concern only infant industries, or certain sectors
  undergoing restructuring or facing serious difficulties, particularly
  where these difficulties produce major social problems.

  Customs duties on imports applicable in Algeria to products
  originating in the Community introduced by these measures may not
  exceed 25 % ad valorem and shall maintain an element of preference for
  products originating in the Community. The total value of imports of
  the products subjected to such measures may not exceed 15 % of total
  imports of industrial products from the Community during the last year
  for which statistics are available.

  These measures shall be applied for a period not exceeding five years
  unless a longer duration is authorised by the Association Committee.
  They shall cease to apply at the latest on expiry of the maximum
  transitional period referred to in Article 6.

  No such measures may be introduced in respect of a product if more
  than three years have elapsed since the elimination of all duties and
  quantitative restrictions or charges or measures having equivalent
  effect concerning that product.

  Algeria shall inform the Association Committee of any exceptional
  measures it intends to take and, at the request of the Community,
  consultations shall be held on such measures and the sectors to which
  they apply before they are implemented. When adopting such measures,
  Algeria shall provide the Association Committee with a schedule for
  the abolition of the customs duties introduced pursuant to this
  Article. Such schedule shall provide for the phasing-out of the duties
  concerned by equal annual instalments, starting no later than the end
  of the second year following their introduction. The Association
  Committee may decide on a different schedule.

  2. By way of derogation from the fourth subparagraph of paragraph 1,
  the Association Committee may exceptionally, in order to take account
  of the difficulties involved in setting up a new industry, authorise
  Algeria to maintain the measures already taken pursuant to paragraph 1
  for a maximum period of three years beyond the transitional period
  referred to in Article 6.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Agricultural, Fisheries And Processed Agricultural Products" chapter_identifier="201">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="1519">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to products originating in
  the Community and Algeria falling within Chapters 1 to 24 of the
  Combined Nomenclature and of the Algerian Customs tariff and to the
  products listed in Annex 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="1520">The Community and Algeria shall progressively establish a greater
  liberalisation of their reciprocal trade in agricultural, fisheries
  and processed agricultural products of interest to both Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="1521">1. Agricultural products originating in Algeria listed in Protocol No
  1 on importation into the Community shall be subject to the
  arrangements set out in that Protocol.

  2. Agricultural products originating in the Community listed in
  Protocol No 2 on importation into Algeria shall be subject to the
  arrangements set out in that Protocol.

  3. Fisheries products originating in Algeria listed in Protocol No 3
  on importation into the Community shall be subject to the arrangements
  set out in that Protocol.

  4. Fisheries products originating in the Community listed in Protocol
  No 4 on importation into Algeria shall be subject to the arrangements
  set out in that Protocol.

  5. Trade in processed agricultural products falling under this Chapter
  shall be subject to the arrangements set out in Protocol No 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="1522">1. Five years after the entry into force of this Agreement, the
  Community and Algeria shall assess the situation in order to determine
  the liberalisation measures to be applied by the Community and Algeria
  six years after the entry into force of the Agreement, in accordance
  with the objective set out in Article 13.

  2. Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraph 1 and taking
  account of the patterns of trade in agricultural products, fisheries
  products and processed agricultural products between the Parties and
  the particular sensitivity of such products, the Community and Algeria
  shall examine in the Association Council, product by product and on a
  reciprocal basis, the possibilities of granting each other further
  concessions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="1523">1. Should specific rules be introduced as a result of implementation
  of their agricultural policies or modification of their existing
  rules, or should the provisions on the implementation of their
  agricultural policies be modified or developed, the Community and
  Algeria may modify the arrangements laid down in this Agreement in
  respect of the products concerned.

  2. The Party carrying out such modification shall inform the
  Association Committee thereof. At the request of the other Party, the
  Association Committee shall meet to take due account of the interests
  of the other Party.

  3. If the Community or Algeria, in applying paragraph 1, modifies the
  arrangements made by this Agreement for agricultural products, they
  shall accord imports originating in the other Party an advantage
  comparable to that provided for in this Agreement.

  4. Any modification of the arrangements made by this Agreement shall
  be the subject, at the request of the other Contracting Party, of
  consultations within the Association Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Common Provisions" chapter_identifier="202">
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="1524">1. No new customs duties on imports or exports or charges having
  equivalent effect shall be introduced in trade between the Community
  and Algeria, nor shall those already applied upon entry into force of
  this Agreement be increased.

  2. No new quantitative restriction on imports or exports or measure
  having equivalent effect shall be introduced in trade between the
  Community and Algeria.

  3. Quantitative restrictions on imports or exports and measures having
  equivalent effect in trade between Algeria and the Community shall be
  abolished upon the entry into force of this Agreement.

  4. Algeria shall abolish by 1 January 2006 at the latest the
  provisional additional duty applied to the products listed in Annex 4.
  That duty shall be reduced on a linear basis by 12 points per year
  starting on 1 January 2002.

  If Algeria's commitments in respect of its accession to the WTO
  provide for a shorter period for the abolition of the provisional
  additional duty, that shorter period shall be applicable.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" article_identifier="1525">1. For each product concerned, the basic duty to be reduced as
  provided in Articles 9(2) and (3) and 14 shall be the rate actually
  applied vis-à-vis the Community on 1 January 2002.

  2. In the event of Algerian accession to the WTO, the applicable rates
  for imports between the Parties shall be the WTO bound rate or lower
  applied rate enforced as of accession. If, after accession to the WTO,
  a tariff reduction is applied on an erga omnes basis, the reduced rate
  shall apply.

  3. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall apply to any tariff reduction
  applied erga omnes introduced after the date on which the negotiations
  are concluded.

  4. The Parties shall communicate to each other their respective basic
  rates applied on 1 January 2002.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="1526">Products originating in Algeria shall not enjoy more favourable
  treatment when imported into the Community than that applied by Member
  States among themselves.

  The provisions of this Agreement shall apply without prejudice to the
  provisions of Council Regulation (EEC) No 1911/91 of 26 June 1991 on
  the application of the provisions of Community law to the Canary
  Islands (OJ L 171, 29.6.1991, p. 1), as last amended by Regulation
  (EC) No 1105/2001 (OJ L 151, 7.6.2001, p. 1).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" article_identifier="1527">1. Both Parties shall refrain from any measure or practice of an
  internal fiscal nature establishing, whether directly or indirectly,
  discrimination between the products of one Party and like products
  originating in the territory of the other Party.

  2. Products exported to the territory of one of the Parties may not
  benefit from repayment of indirect internal taxation in excess of the
  amount of indirect taxation imposed on them directly or indirectly.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" article_identifier="1528">1. This Agreement shall not preclude the maintenance or establishment
  of customs unions, free trade areas or arrangements for frontier trade
  insofar as they do not have the effect of altering the trade
  arrangements provided for in this Agreement.

  2. Consultation between the Parties shall take place within the
  Association Committee concerning agreements establishing customs
  unions or free trade areas and, where requested, on other major issues
  related to their respective trade policies with third countries. In
  particular in the event of a third country acceding to the Community,
  such consultations shall take place so as to ensure that account is
  taken of the mutual interests of the Community and Algeria stated in
  this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" article_identifier="1529">If one of the Parties finds that dumping is taking place in trade with
  the other Party within the meaning of Article VI of GATT 1994, it may
  take appropriate measures against this practice in accordance with the
  WTO Agreement on the Implementation of Article VI of GATT 1994,
  related internal legislation and the procedures laid down in Article
  26.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" article_identifier="1530">The WTO Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures shall be
  applicable between the Parties.

  If one of the Parties finds that subsidies are being used in trade
  with the other Party within the meaning of Articles VI and XVI of GATT
  1994, it may take appropriate measures against this practice in
  accordance with the WTO Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing
  Measures and its own legislation on the matter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" article_identifier="1531">1. Except where otherwise stated in this Article, the provisions of
  Article XIX of GATT 1994 and of the WTO Agreement on Safeguards are
  applicable between the Parties.

  2. Each Party shall inform the Association Committee forthwith of any
  step that it takes or intends to take with regard to the application
  of safeguard measures. Each Party shall send the Association
  Committee, immediately or at least one week in advance, a
  communication in writing containing all information pertinent to:

  - the opening of a safeguard investigation,

  - the outcome of the investigation.

  The information provided shall include an explanation of the procedure
  on which the investigation is based and details of the schedule of
  hearings and other suitable occasions for the parties concerned to
  submit their opinions.

  Each Party shall also give the Association Committee an advance
  written notification containing all relevant information about the
  decision to apply provisional safeguard measures; this notification
  must be received at least one week before the measures are applied.

  3. On being notified of the final results of the investigation and
  before applying safeguard measures in accordance with Article XIX of
  GATT 1994 and the WTO Agreement on Safeguards, the Party intending to
  apply such measures shall refer the matter to the Association
  Committee for a thorough examination of the situation with a view to
  finding a mutually acceptable solution.

  4. In order to find such a solution, the Parties shall immediately
  hold consultations within the Association Committee. If the Parties
  fail to reach an agreement within 30 days of the initiation of such
  consultations on a solution to avoid the application of the safeguard
  measures, the Party intending to apply safeguard measures may apply
  the provisions of Article XIX of GATT 1994 and of the WTO Agreement on
  Safeguards.

  5. In the selection of safeguard measures pursuant to this Article,
  the Parties shall give priority to those which cause least disturbance
  to the achievement of the objectives of this Agreement. Such measures
  shall not go beyond what is necessary to remedy the difficulties
  arising and shall maintain the level or margin of preference granted
  pursuant to this Agreement.

  6. The Party intending to apply safeguard measures pursuant to this
  Article shall offer the other Party compensation in the form of
  liberalisation of trade vis-à-vis imports from the latter; that
  compensation will be essentially equivalent to the adverse trade
  effects of the measures on the other Party with effect from the date
  of their implementation. The offer shall be made before the safeguard
  measure is adopted and concurrently with the notification of and
  referral to the Association Committee, in accordance with paragraph 3.
  If the Party whose product is the intended subject of the safeguard
  measure considers the offer of compensation unsatisfactory, the two
  Parties may agree to other forms of trade compensation in the
  framework of the consultations referred to in paragraph 3.

  7. If the Parties fail to agree on the matter of compensation within
  30 days of the initiation of the above consultations, the Party whose
  product is the subject of safeguard measures may adopt compensatory
  tariff measures having trade effects essentially equivalent to the
  safeguard measure adopted pursuant to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" article_identifier="1532">Where compliance with the provisions of Article 17(3) leads to:

  (i) re-export towards a third country against which the exporting
  party maintains, for the product concerned, quantitative export
  restrictions, export duties, or measures having equivalent effect,

  or

  (ii) a serious shortage, or threat thereof, of a product essential to
  the exporting party;

  and where the situations referred to above give rise, or are likely to
  give rise, to major difficulties for the exporting Party, that Party
  may take appropriate measures under the conditions and in accordance
  with the procedures laid down in Article 26. The measures shall be
  non-discriminatory and shall be abolished when conditions no longer
  justify their maintenance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" article_identifier="1533">1. In the event of the Community or Algeria subjecting imports of
  products liable to give rise to the difficulties referred to in
  Article 24 to an administrative procedure having as its purpose the
  rapid supply of information on trade flow trends, it shall inform the
  other Party.

  In the cases specified in Articles 22 and 25, before taking the
  measures provided for therein or, in cases to which paragraph 2(c) of
  this Article applies, as soon as possible, the Community or Algeria,
  as the case may be, shall supply the Association Committee with all
  relevant information with a view to seeking a solution acceptable to
  the two Parties.

  In the selection of measures, priority shall be given to those which
  least disturb the functioning of this Agreement.

  2. For the implementation of the second subparagraph of paragraph 1,
  the following provisions shall apply:

  (a) as regards Article 22, the exporting Party shall be informed of
  the dumping case as soon as the authorities of the importing Party
  have initiated an investigation. When no end has been put to the
  dumping within the meaning of Article VI of GATT 1994 or no other
  satisfactory solution has been reached within 30 days of the matter
  being referred, the importing Party may adopt the appropriate
  measures;

  (b) as regards Article 25, the difficulties arising from the
  situations referred to in that Article shall be referred for
  examination to the Association Committee.

  The Association Committee may take any decision needed to put an end
  to the difficulties. If it has not taken such a decision within 30
  days of the matter being referred to it, the exporting party may apply
  appropriate measures on the exportation of the product concerned;

  (c) where exceptional circumstances requiring immediate action make
  prior information or examination, as the case may be, impossible, the
  Community or Algeria, whichever is concerned, may, in the situations
  specified in Articles 22 and 25, apply forthwith the precautionary
  measures strictly necessary to deal with the situation and shall
  inform the other Party immediately thereof.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" article_identifier="1534">Nothing in this Agreement shall preclude prohibitions or restrictions
  on imports, exports or goods in transit justified on grounds of public
  morality, public policy or public security, of the protection of
  health and life of humans, animals or plants, of the protection of
  national treasures possessing artistic, historic or archaeological
  value, of the protection of intellectual, industrial and commercial
  property or of regulations concerning gold and silver. Such
  prohibitions or restrictions shall not, however, constitute a means of
  arbitrary discrimination or a disguised restriction on trade between
  the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" article_identifier="1535">The concept of "originating products" for the application of
  the provisions of the present Title and the methods of administrative
  cooperation relating to them are set out in Protocol No 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" article_identifier="1536">The Combined Nomenclature of goods shall be applied to the
  classification of goods for imports into the Community. The Algerian
  customs tariff shall be applied to the classification of goods for
  imports into Algeria.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE III" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="203">
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Reciprocal Commitments" article_identifier="1537">1. The European Community and its Member States shall extend to
  Algeria the treatment which they are obliged to grant under Article
  II. I of the General Agreement on Trade in Services, hereinafter
  referred to as GATS.

  2. The European Community and its Member States shall grant to
  Algerian service suppliers no less favourable treatment than that
  accorded to like service suppliers as specified in the schedule of
  specific commitments taken by the European Community and its Member
  States under the GATS to which it is annexed.

  3. This treatment shall not apply to advantages accorded by either
  Party under the terms of an agreement of the type defined in Article V
  of the GATS or to measures taken on the basis of such an agreement and
  to other advantages granted in accordance with the list of
  most-favoured-nation exemptions annexed by the European Community and
  its Member States to the GATS.

  4. Algeria shall grant no less favourable treatment to service
  suppliers of the European Community and its Member States than that
  specified in Articles 31 to 33.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Cross-Border Supply Of Services" article_identifier="1538">With regard to the supply of services by Community service suppliers
  into the territory of Algeria, other than through a commercial
  presence or the presence of natural persons, as referred to in
  Articles 32 and 33, Algeria shall grant treatment to Community service
  suppliers no less favourable than that accorded to companies of any
  third country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Commercial Presence" article_identifier="1539">(a) Algeria shall grant for the establishment of Community companies
  in its territory treatment no less favourable than that accorded to
  companies of any third country;

  (b) Algeria shall grant to subsidiaries and branches of Community
  companies, established in its territory in accordance with its
  legislation, in respect of their operations, treatment no less
  favourable than that accorded to its own companies or branches, or to
  Algerian subsidiaries or branches of companies of any third country,
  whichever is the better.

  2. The treatment referred to in paragraph 1(a) and (b) shall be
  granted to companies, subsidiaries and branches established in Algeria
  on the date of entry into force of this Agreement and to companies,
  subsidiaries and branches established there after that date.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Temporary Presence Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="1540">1. A Community company or Algerian company established in the
  territory of Algeria or the Community respectively shall be entitled
  to temporarily employ, or have temporarily employed by one of its
  subsidiaries or branches, in accordance with the legislation in force
  in the host country of establishment, employees who are nationals of
  Community Member States and Algeria respectively, provided that such
  employees are key personnel as defined in paragraph 2, and that they
  are employed exclusively by such companies, subsidiaries or branches.
  The residence and work permits of such employees shall only cover the
  period of such employment.

  2. Key personnel of the abovementioned companies herein referred to as
  "organisations" are "intra-corporate transferees"
  as defined in (c) in the following categories, provided that the
  organisation is a legal person and that the persons concerned have
  been employed by it or have been partners in it (other than as
  majority shareholders), for at least the 12 months immediately
  preceding such movement:

  (a) persons working in a senior position with an organisation, who
  primarily direct the management of the establishment, receiving
  general supervision or direction principally from the board of
  directors or stockholders of the business or their equivalent,
  including:

  - directing the establishment or a department or sub-division of the
  establishment,

  - supervising and controlling the work of other supervisory,
  professional or managerial employees,

  - having the authority personally to recruit and dismiss or recommend
  recruiting, dismissing or other personnel actions,

  (b) persons working within an organisation who possess uncommon
  knowledge essential to the establishment's service, research
  equipment, techniques or management. The assessment of such knowledge
  may reflect, apart from knowledge specific to the establishment, a
  high level of qualification referring to a type of work or trade
  requiring specific technical knowledge, including membership of an
  accredited profession,

  (c) an "intra-corporate transferee" is defined as a natural
  person working within an organisation in the territory of a Party, and
  being temporarily transferred in the context of pursuit of economic
  activities in the territory of the other Party; the organisation
  concerned must have its principal place of business in the territory
  of a Party and the transfer be to an establishment (branch,
  subsidiary) of that organisation, effectively pursuing like economic
  activities in the territory of the other Party.

  3. The entry into and the temporary presence within the respective
  territories of Algeria and the Community of nationals of the Member
  States or of Algeria respectively shall be permitted when these
  representatives of companies are persons working in a senior position,
  as defined in paragraph 2(a), within a company, and are responsible
  for the establishment of an Algerian or a Community company, in the
  Community or Algeria respectively, when:

  - those representatives are not engaged in making direct sales or
  supplying services, and

  - the company has no other representative, office, branch or
  subsidiary in a Community Member State or Algeria respectively.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Transport" article_identifier="1541">1. Articles 30 to 33 shall not apply to air, inland waterway or land
  transport or to national shipping (cabotage), subject to the
  provisions of paragraphs 2 to 6 of this Article.

  2. In respect of activities undertaken by shipping agencies for the
  provision of international maritime transport services, including
  inter-modal activities involving a sea leg, each Party shall permit to
  the companies of the other Party their commercial presence in its
  territory in the form of subsidiaries or branches, under conditions of
  establishment and operation no less favourable than those accorded to
  its own companies or to subsidiaries or branches of companies of any
  third country, whichever are the better. Such activities include, but
  are not limited to:

  (a) marketing and sales of maritime transport and related services
  through direct contact with customers, from quotation to invoicing,
  whether these services are operated or offered by the service supplier
  itself or by service suppliers with which the service seller has
  established standing business arrangements;

  (b) purchase and use, on their own account or on behalf of their
  customer (and the resale to their customers), of any transport and
  related services, including inward transport services by any mode,
  particularly inland waterways, road and rail, necessary for the supply
  of an integrated service;

  (c) preparation of transport documents, customs documents, or other
  documents related to the origin and character of the goods
  transported;

  (d) provision of business information of any means, including
  computerised information systems and electronic data interchange
  (subject to any non-discriminatory restrictions concerning
  telecommunications);

  (e) setting up of any business arrangement, including participation in
  the company's stock and the appointment of personnel recruited locally
  (or, in the case of foreign personnel, subject to the relevant
  provisions of this Agreement), with any locally established shipping
  agency;

  (f) acting on behalf of the companies, organising the call of the ship
  or taking over cargoes when required.

  3. With respect to maritime transport, the Parties undertake to apply
  effectively the principle of unrestricted access to the international
  market and traffic on a commercial basis.

  However, the legislation of each Party shall apply to the preferential
  right of the national flag for national cabotage and for salvage,
  towage and pilotage.

  These provisions do not prejudice the rights and obligations arising
  under the United Nations Convention on a Code of Conduct for Liner
  Conferences, as applicable for either Party to this Agreement.
  Non-conference lines shall be free to operate in competition with a
  conference line as long as they adhere to the principle of fair
  competition on a commercial basis.

  The Parties affirm their commitment to a freely competitive
  environment as being an essential feature of the dry and liquid bulk
  trade.

  4. In applying the principles of paragraph 3 above, the Parties shall:

  (a) not introduce cargo-sharing arrangements in future bilateral
  Agreements with third countries concerning dry and liquid bulk and
  liner trade. However, this does not exclude the possibility of such
  arrangements concerning liner cargo in those exceptional circumstances
  where liner shipping companies from one or other Party to this
  Agreement would not otherwise have an effective opportunity to ply for
  trade to and from the third country concerned;

  (b) abolish, upon entry into force of this Agreement, all unilateral
  measures, administrative, technical and other obstacles which could
  constitute a disguised restriction or have discriminatory effects on
  the free supply of services in international maritime transport.

  5. Each Party shall grant, inter alia, a treatment no less favourable
  than that accorded to its own ships, for the ships used for the
  transport of goods, passengers or both, sailing under the flag of the
  other Party or operated by its nationals or companies, with respect to
  access to ports, the use of infrastructure and auxiliary maritime
  services of those ports, as well as related fees and charges, customs
  facilities and the assignment of berths and facilities for loading and
  unloading.

  6. With a view to coordinated development of transport between the
  Parties, adapted to their commercial needs, the conditions of mutual
  market access and provision of air, road, rail and inland waterway
  transport services may be dealt with by specific arrangements, where
  appropriate, negotiated between the Parties after the entry into force
  of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="1542">1. The provisions of Title III shall not prejudice the application by
  each Party of any measures necessary to prevent the circumvention of
  its measures concerning third country access to its market, through
  the provisions of this Agreement.

  2. The provisions of this Title shall be applied subject to
  limitations justified on grounds of public policy, public security or
  public health. They shall not apply to activities which in the
  territory of either Party are connected, even occasionally, with the
  exercise of official authority.

  3. The provisions of this title do not preclude the application by a
  Party of particular rules concerning the establishment and operation
  in its territory of branches of companies of another Party not
  incorporated in the territory of the first Party, which are justified
  by legal or technical differences between such branches as compared to
  branches of companies incorporated in its territory or, as regards
  financial services, for prudential reasons. The difference in
  treatment shall not go beyond what is strictly necessary as a result
  of such legal or technical differences or, as regards financial
  services, for prudential reasons.

  4. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Agreement, a Party
  shall not be prevented from taking measures for prudential reasons,
  including for the protection of investors, depositors, policy holders
  or persons to whom a fiduciary duty is owed by a financial service
  supplier, or to ensure the integrity and stability of the financial
  system. Where such measures do not conform with the provisions of the
  Agreement, they shall not be used as a means of avoiding the
  obligations of a Party under the Agreement.

  5. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to require a Party to
  disclose information relating to the affairs and accounts of
  individual customers or any confidential or proprietary information in
  the possession of public entities.

  6. For the purpose of the movement of natural persons supplying a
  service, nothing in this Agreement shall prevent the Parties from
  applying their laws and regulations regarding entry and stay, work,
  labour conditions and establishment of natural persons and supply of
  services, provided that, in so doing, they do not apply them in a
  manner as to nullify or impair the benefits accruing to any Party
  under the terms of a specific provision of the Agreement. The above
  provision does not prejudice the application of paragraph 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Definitions" article_identifier="1543">For the purposes of this Agreement:

  (a) a "service supplier" shall mean any natural or legal
  person who supplies a service from the territory of one Party into the
  territory of the other Party, in the territory of one Party to the
  service consumer of the other Party, through commercial presence
  (establishment) in the territory of the other Party and through the
  presence of a natural person of a Party in the territory of the other
  Party;

  (b) a "Community company" or "Algerian company"
  respectively shall mean a company set up in accordance with the laws
  of a Member State or of Algeria respectively and having its registered
  office or central administration or principal place of business in the
  territory of the Community or Algeria respectively.

  However, should the company, set up in accordance with the laws of a
  Member State or Algeria respectively, have only its registered office
  in the territory of the Community or Algeria respectively, the company
  shall be considered a Community or Algerian company respectively if
  its operations possess a real and continuous link with the economy of
  one of the Member States or Algeria respectively;

  (c) "subsidiary" of a company shall mean a company which is
  controlled by the first company;

  (d) "branch" of a company shall mean a place of business not
  having legal personality which has the appearance of permanency, such
  as the extension of a parent body, has a management and is materially
  equipped to negotiate business with third parties so that the latter,
  although knowing that there will, if necessary, be a legal link with
  the parent body, the head office of which is abroad, do not have to
  deal directly with such parent body but may transact business at the
  place of business constituting the extension;

  (e) "establishment" shall mean the right of Community or
  Algerian companies as referred to in subparagraph (b) to take up
  economic activities by means of the setting-up of subsidiaries and
  branches in Algeria or in the Community respectively;

  (f) "operation" shall mean the pursuit of economic
  activities;

  (g) "economic activities" shall mean activities of an
  industrial, commercial and professional character;

  (h) "national of a Member State or of Algeria" shall mean a
  natural person who is a national of one of the Member States or of
  Algeria respectively.

  With regard to international maritime transport, including inter-modal
  operations involving a sea leg, nationals of the Member States or of
  Algeria established outside the Community or Algeria respectively, and
  shipping companies established outside the Community or Algeria and
  controlled by nationals of a Member State or Algerian nationals
  respectively, shall also be subject to the provisions of this Title if
  their vessels are registered in that Member State or in Algeria
  respectively in accordance with their respective legislations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="1544">1. The Parties shall avoid taking any measures or actions which render
  the conditions for the establishment and operation of each other's
  companies more restrictive than the situation existing on the day
  preceding the date of signature of this Agreement.

  2. The Parties undertake to consider development of this Title with a
  view to the establishment of an "economic integration
  agreement" as defined in Article V of GATS. In making such
  recommendations, the Association Council shall take account of past
  experience of implementation of the most-favoured-nation treatment and
  of the obligations of each Party under the GATS, and in particular
  Article V thereof.

  The Association Council shall also, when making such examination, take
  into account progress made in the approximation of laws between the
  Parties in the relevant activities. This objective shall be subject to
  a first examination by the Association Council at the latest five
  years after the entry into force of this Agreement.

  PAYMENTS, CAPITAL, COMPETITION AND OTHER ECONOMIC PROVISIONS</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Current Payments And Movement Of Capital" chapter_identifier="204">
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" article_identifier="1545">1. The Community and Algeria shall ensure, from the entry into force
  of the Agreement, that capital relating to direct investments in
  Algeria in companies formed in accordance with current laws can move
  freely and that the yield from such investments and any profit
  stemming therefrom can be liquidated and repatriated.

  2. The Parties shall consult each other and cooperate with a view to
  establishing the necessary conditions for facilitating and fully
  liberalising the movement of capital between the Community and
  Algeria.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" article_identifier="1546">Where one or more Member States of the Community, or Algeria, is in
  serious balance of payments difficulties, or under threat thereof, the
  Community or Algeria, as the case may be, may, in accordance with the
  conditions established under the General Agreement on Tariffs and
  Trade and Articles VIII and XIV of the Articles of Agreement of the
  International Monetary Fund, adopt restrictions on current
  transactions which shall be of limited duration and may not go beyond
  what is strictly necessary to remedy the balance of payments
  situation. The Community or Algeria, as the case may be, shall inform
  the other Party forthwith and shall submit to it as soon as possible a
  timetable for the abolition of the measures concerned.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Competition And Other Economic Matters" chapter_identifier="205">
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" article_identifier="1547">The Member States and Algeria shall progressively adjust, without
  prejudice to their commitments to the GATT, any State monopolies of a
  commercial character, so as to ensure that, by the end of the fifth
  year following the entry into force of this Agreement, no
  discrimination regarding the conditions under which goods are procured
  and marketed exists between nationals of the Member States and
  Algeria. The Association Committee will be informed about the measures
  adopted to implement this objective.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" article_identifier="1548">With regard to public enterprises and enterprises which have been
  granted special or exclusive rights, the Association Council shall
  ensure, from the fifth year following the entry into force of this
  Agreement, that no measure which disturbs trade between the Community
  and Algeria in a manner which runs counter to the interests of the
  Parties is adopted or maintained. This provision should not obstruct
  the performance in law or in fact of the particular tasks assigned to
  these enterprises.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" article_identifier="1549">1. The Parties shall provide suitable and effective protection of
  intellectual, industrial and commercial property rights, in line with
  the highest international standards. This shall encompass effective
  means of enforcing such rights.

  2. Implementation of this Article and of Annex 6 shall be regularly
  assessed by the Parties. If difficulties which affect trade arise in
  connection with intellectual, industrial and commercial property
  rights, either Party may request urgent consultations to find mutually
  satisfactory solutions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" article_identifier="1550">The Parties undertake to adopt appropriate measures to ensure the
  protection of personal data in order to eliminate barriers to the free
  movement of such data between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" article_identifier="1551">1. The Parties shall set as their objective a reciprocal and gradual
  liberalisation of public procurement contracts.

  2. The Association Council shall take the steps necessary to implement
  paragraph 1.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE V" name="Economic Cooperation" chapter_identifier="206">
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Objectives" article_identifier="1552">1. The Parties undertake to step up economic cooperation in their
  mutual interest and in the spirit of partnership which is at the root
  of this Agreement.

  2. The objective of economic cooperation shall be to support Algeria's
  own efforts to achieve sustainable economic and social development.

  3. Such economic cooperation is in keeping with the objectives set out
  in the Barcelona Declaration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Scope" article_identifier="1553">1. Cooperation will be targeted first and foremost at areas of
  activity suffering the effects of internal constraints and
  difficulties or affected by the process of liberalising Algeria's
  economy as a whole, and more particularly by the liberalisation of
  trade between Algeria and the Community.

  2. Similarly, cooperation shall focus on areas likely to bring the
  economies of the Community and Algeria closer together, particularly
  those which will generate growth and employment, and foster the
  development of trade flows between Algeria and the Community, notably
  by encouraging the diversification of Algerian exports.

  3. Cooperation shall foster economic integration within the Maghreb
  group of countries using any measures likely to further such relations
  within the region.

  4. Preservation of the environment and ecological balances shall
  constitute a central component of the various fields of economic
  cooperation.

  5. The Parties may determine by agreement other fields of economic
  cooperation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Methods" article_identifier="1554">Economic cooperation shall be implemented in particular by:

  (a) regular economic dialogue between the Parties covering all areas
  of macro-economic policy;

  (b) communication and exchanges of information;

  (c) transfer of advice, expertise and training;

  (d) implementation of joint actions;

  (e) technical, administrative and regulatory assistance;

  (f) measures to support partnerships and direct investment by
  operators, in particular private operators, and privatisation
  programmes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Regional Cooperation" article_identifier="1555">In order to maximise the impact of this Agreement vis-à-vis the
  development of the Euro-Mediterranean partnership and within the
  countries of the Maghreb, the Parties shall foster all activities
  which have a regional impact or involve third countries, notably:

  (a) economic integration;

  (b) development of economic infrastructure;

  (c) environmental matters;

  (d) scientific and technological research;

  (e) education, teaching and training;

  (f) cultural matters;

  (g) customs matters;

  (h) regional institutions and the establishment of common or
  harmonised programmes and policies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Scientific, Technical And Technological Cooperation" article_identifier="1556">Cooperation shall be aimed at:

  (a) encouraging the establishment of permanent links between the
  Parties' scientific communities, notably by means of:

  - the access of Algeria to Community technological research and
  development programmes, in conformity with Community provisions
  concerning the participation of third countries in those programmes;

  - the participation of Algeria in decentralised cooperation networks;

  - the promotion of synergy between training and research;

  (b) strengthening research capacity in Algeria;

  (c) stimulating technological innovation, the transfer of new
  technologies and know-how, implementation of technological research
  and development projects and optimisation of the results of scientific
  and technical research;

  (d) encouraging all activities aimed at establishing synergy at
  regional level.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Environment" article_identifier="1557">1. The Parties shall encourage cooperation in preventing deterioration
  of the environment, controlling pollution and ensuring the rational
  use of natural resources, with a view to ensuring sustainable
  development and guaranteeing the quality of the environment and the
  protection of public health.

  2. Cooperation shall in particular focus on:

  - issues related to desertification,

  - rational water resource management,

  - salinisation,

  - the impact of agriculture on soil and water quality,

  - the appropriate use of energy and transport,

  - the impact of industrial development on the environment, in
  particular the safety of industrial plant,

  - waste management, in particular toxic waste,

  - the integrated management of sensitive areas,

  - the control and prevention of urban, industrial and marine
  pollution,

  - use of advanced environmental management and monitoring tools,
  particularly environmental information and statistical systems,

  - technical assistance, in particular for the preservation of
  bio-diversity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Industrial Cooperation" article_identifier="1558">Cooperation shall be aimed at:

  (a) encouraging or supporting measures designed to promote direct
  investment and industrial partnership ventures in Algeria;

  (b) encouraging direct cooperation between the Parties' economic
  operators, including cooperation in the context of access for Algeria
  to Community business networks and decentralised cooperation networks;

  (c) backing the effort to modernise and restructure Algeria's public
  and private sector industry (including the agri-food industry);

  (d) fostering the development of small- and medium-sized enterprises;

  (e) fostering an environment which favours private initiative, with
  the aim of stimulating and diversifying output for the domestic and
  export markets;

  (f) making the most of Algeria's human resources and industrial
  potential through better use of policy in the fields of innovation and
  research and technological development;

  (g) supporting the restructuring of industry and the industrial
  upgrading programme with a view to the creation of the free trade area
  so as to make products more competitive;

  (h) contributing to the development of exports of Algerian
  manufactures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Promotion And Protection Of Investments" article_identifier="1559">The aim of cooperation shall be to create a favourable climate for
  investment flows, in particular by means of the following:

  (a) the establishment of harmonised and simplified procedures,
  co-investment machinery (especially to link small and medium-sized
  enterprises) and methods of identifying and providing information on
  investment opportunities;

  (b) a legal environment conducive to investment between the two
  Parties, where appropriate through the conclusion by the Member States
  and Algeria of investment protection agreements, and agreements to
  prevent double taxation;

  (c) technical assistance to schemes to promote and guarantee national
  and foreign investments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Standardisation And Conformity Assessment" article_identifier="1560">Cooperation shall aim at reducing divergences in standardisation and
  certification.

  Cooperation shall be realised in particular through:

  - encouraging the use of European standards and conformity assessment
  procedures and techniques;

  - upgrading Algerian conformity assessment and metrology bodies and
  helping to establish the necessary conditions for the eventual
  negotiation of mutual recognition agreements in these fields;

  - cooperation in the area of quality management;

  - providing assistance to the Algerian bodies responsible for
  intellectual, industrial and commercial property and for
  standardisation and quality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Approximation Of Laws" article_identifier="1561">Cooperation shall be aimed at helping Algeria to bring its legislation
  closer to that of the Community in the areas covered by this
  Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Financial Services" article_identifier="1562">Cooperation shall be aimed at the improvement and development of
  financial services.

  This will basically involve:

  - the exchange of information concerning financial regulations and
  practices and training schemes, in particular with a view to the
  creation of small and medium-sized enterprises;

  - support for the reform of Algeria's banking and financial system,
  including development of the stock market.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Agriculture And Fisheries" article_identifier="1563">Cooperation shall be aimed at the modernisation and restructuring,
  where necessary, of the agriculture, forestry and fisheries sectors.

  It shall in particular be aimed at:

  - support for policies geared to developing and diversifying
  production,

  - food security,

  - integrated rural development, including improvement of basic
  services and development of ancillary economic activities,

  - promoting environmentally-friendly forms of agriculture and
  fisheries,

  - the evaluation and rational management of natural resources,

  - establishing closer relations, on a voluntary basis, between
  enterprises, groupings and professional organisations representing the
  agricultural, fisheries and agri-business sectors,

  - technical assistance and training,

  - harmonising phytosanitary and veterinary standards and checks,

  - cooperation between rural areas, exchange of experience and know-how
  on rural development,

  - support for privatisation,

  - the evaluation and rational management of fish stocks,

  - support for research programmes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Transport" article_identifier="1564">The aims of cooperation shall be:

  - to support the restructuring and modernisation of transport,

  - to improve the movement of passengers and goods,

  - the establishment and enforcement of operating standards comparable
  to those prevailing in the Community.

  The priority areas of cooperation shall be:

  - road transport, including the gradual improvement of transit,

  - the management of railways, airports and ports and cooperation
  between the relevant national authorities,

  - modernisation of road, rail, port and airport infrastructure on
  major trans-European routes of mutual interest and routes of regional
  interest, and navigation aids,

  - upgrading of technical equipment to bring it up to Community
  standards for road/rail t ransport, inter-modal transport,
  containerisation and transhipment,

  - technical assistance and training.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Information Society And Telecommunications" article_identifier="1565">Cooperation in this field shall focus in particular on:

  - a dialogue on issues related to the different aspects of the
  information society, including telecommunications policies,

  - the exchange of information and provision of any technical
  assistance required on regulations and standardisation, conformity
  testing and certification of information and communication
  technologies,

  - the dissemination of advanced information and telecommunication
  technologies, including satellite technology and information services
  and technologies,

  - the promotion and implementation of joint projects for research,
  technical development or industrial applications in information
  technologies, communications, telematics and information society,

  - giving Algerian bodies the opportunity to participate in pilot
  projects and European programmes under the specific arrangements
  pertaining to them in the sectors concerned;

  - the interconnection and interoperability of Community and Algerian
  networks and telematic services,

  - technical assistance with the planning and management of the radio
  frequency spectrum with a view to coordinated and effective use of
  radio communications in the Euro-Mediterranean region.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Energy And Mining" article_identifier="1566">The aims of cooperation in the energy and mining sectors shall be:

  (a) institutional, legislative and regulatory upgrading to ensure that
  activities are regulated and investment promoted;

  (b) technical and technological upgrading to prepare energy and mining
  companies for the requirements of the market economy and competition;

  (c) the development of partnerships between European and Algerian
  companies in the activities of exploration, production, processing,
  distribution and services in the energy and mining sectors.

  The priority areas of cooperation in this respect shall be:

  - adaptation of the institutional, legislative and regulatory
  framework of activities in the energy and mining sectors to market
  economy rules by means of technical, administrative and regulatory
  assistance,

  - support for efforts to restructure public enterprises in the energy
  and mining sectors,

  - building partnerships in the areas of,

  - oil and gas exploration, production and processing,

  - electricity production,

  - distribution of petroleum products,

  - production of equipment and services used in the production of
  energy products,

  - developing and transforming the potential of mining,

  development of gas, oil and electricity distribution,

  support for the modernisation and development of energy networks and
  for their linking to European Community networks,

  the setting-up of databases on the mining and energy sectors,

  the support and promotion of private investment in energy and mining
  sector activities,

  the environment, the development of renewable energies and energy
  efficiency,

  the promotion of technology transfers in the energy and mining
  sectors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Tourism And The Craft Sector" article_identifier="1567">Cooperation in this field will principally be aimed at:

  - stepping up the exchange of information on flows and policies on
  tourism, spa tourism and craft trades,

  - stepping up hotel administration and management training schemes and
  training in other areas of the tourism and craft sectors,

  - promoting exchanges of experiences with a view to the smooth and
  sustainable development of tourism,

  - encouraging youth tourism,

  - helping Algeria to develop its potential in the area of tourism,
  spas and crafts and to improve the image of its tourism products,

  - supporting privatisation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Cooperation In Customs Matters" article_identifier="1568">1. The aim of cooperation shall be to ensure compliance with the free
  trade arrangements. The priority areas shall be:

  (a) the simplification of customs controls and procedures;

  (b) the introduction of a single administrative document similar to
  the Community's and a possible link-up between the Community and
  Algerian transit systems.

  Technical assistance may be provided where necessary.

  2. Without prejudice to other forms of cooperation envisaged in this
  Agreement, notably for the fight against drugs and money laundering,
  the administrative authorities of the Contracting Parties shall
  provide mutual assistance in accordance with the provisions of
  Protocol No 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Cooperation In Statistics" article_identifier="1569">The main objective of cooperation in this sphere should be to ensure,
  in particular through the harmonisation of the methods used by the
  Parties, the comparability and usefulness of statistics on foreign
  trade, public finance and balance of payments, population, migration,
  transport and communications, and generally all the fields covered by
  this Agreement. Technical assistance may be provided where necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Cooperation On Consumer Protection" article_identifier="1570">1. The Parties agree that cooperation in this area should be aimed at
  making their respective consumer protection systems compatible.

  2. Cooperation shall focus mainly on:

  (a) the exchange of information on legislative activities and
  exchanges of experts, in particular consumer interest representatives;

  (b) the organisation of seminars and training courses;

  (c) the establishment of permanent systems of mutual information on
  dangerous products, i.e. those which constitute a hazard to health or
  consumer safety;

  (d) improving information provided to consumers especially on prices,
  characteristics of products and services offered;

  (e) institutional reforms;

  (f) technical assistance;

  (g) the establishment of Algerian laboratories for comparative
  analysis and testing and assistance with the introduction of a
  decentralised consumer information system;

  (h) assistance with the organisation and introduction of a warning
  system to be integrated into the European system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" article_identifier="1571">Given the particularities of the Algerian economy, both Parties shall
  establish the methods and procedures for implementing the economic
  cooperation activities agreed pursuant to this Title in order to
  support the process of modernising the Algerian economy and the
  creation of the free trade area.

  The identification and evaluation of requirements and the procedures
  for implementing the economic cooperation activities shall be examined
  in a framework to be introduced in accordance with the conditions laid
  down in Article 98.

  The Parties shall agree on the priorities to be carried out in the
  abovementioned framework.

  SOCIAL AND CULTURAL COOPERATION</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Workers" chapter_identifier="207">
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" article_identifier="1572">1. Each Member State shall accord to workers of Algerian nationality
  employed in its territory treatment which is free from any
  discrimination based on nationality, as regards working conditions,
  remuneration and dismissal, relative to its own nationals.

  2. All Algerian workers allowed to undertake paid employment in the
  territory of a Member State on a temporary basis shall be covered by
  the provisions of paragraph 1 with regard to working conditions and
  remuneration.

  3. Algeria shall accord the same treatment to workers who are
  nationals of a Member State and employed in its territory.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" article_identifier="1573">1. Subject to the provisions of the following paragraphs, workers of
  Algerian nationality and any members of their families living with
  them shall enjoy, in the field of social security, treatment free from
  any discrimination based on nationality relative to nationals of the
  Member States in which they are employed.

  The term "social security" shall cover the branches of
  social security dealing with sickness and maternity benefits,
  invalidity, old-age and survivors’ benefits, industrial accident and
  occupational disease benefits and death, unemployment and family
  benefits.

  These provisions shall not, however, cause the other coordination
  rules provided for in Community legislation based on Article 42 of the
  Treaty establishing the European Community to apply, except under the
  conditions set out in Article 70 of this Agreement.

  2. All periods of insurance, employment or residence completed by such
  workers in the various Member States shall be added together for the
  purpose of pensions and annuities in respect of old age, invalidity
  and survivors’ benefits, family, sickness and maternity benefits, and
  medical care for the workers and for members of their families
  resident in the Community.

  3. The workers in question shall receive family allowances for members
  of their families who are resident in the Community.

  4. The workers in question shall be able to transfer freely to
  Algeria, at the rates applied by virtue of the legislation of the
  debtor Member State or States, any pensions or annuities in respect of
  old age, survivor status, industrial accident or occupational disease,
  or of invalidity resulting from industrial accident or occupational
  disease, except in the case of special non-contributory benefits.

  5. Algeria shall accord to workers who are nationals of a Member State
  and employed in its territory, and to the members of their families,
  treatment similar to that specified in paragraphs 1, 3 and 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" article_identifier="1574">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to nationals of the Parties
  residing or working legally in the territory of their host countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" article_identifier="1575">1. Before the end of the first year following the entry into force of
  this Agreement, the Association Council shall adopt provisions to
  implement the principles set out in Article 68.

  2. The Association Council shall adopt detailed rules for
  administrative cooperation providing the necessary management and
  monitoring guarantees for the application of the provisions referred
  to in paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" article_identifier="1576">The provisions adopted by the Association Council in accordance with
  Article 70 shall not affect any rights or obligations arising from
  bilateral agreements linking Algeria and the Member States where those
  agreements provide for more favourable treatment of nationals of
  Algeria or of the Member States.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Dialogue In Social Matters" chapter_identifier="208">
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" article_identifier="1577">1. The Parties shall conduct regular dialogue on any social matter
  which is of interest to them.

  2. Such dialogue shall be used to find ways to achieve progress in the
  field of movement of workers and equal treatment and social
  integration for Algerian and Community nationals residing legally in
  the territories of their host States.

  3. The dialogue shall cover, inter alia, all issues related to:

  (a) the living and working conditions of workers and their dependants;

  (b) migration;

  (c) illegal immigration and the conditions governing the return of
  individuals who are in breach of the legislation dealing with the
  right to stay and the right of establishment in the host State;

  (d) schemes and programmes to encourage equal treatment between
  Algerian and Community nationals, mutual knowledge of cultures and
  civilisations, the furthering of tolerance and the removal of
  discrimination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" article_identifier="1578">Dialogue on social matters shall be conducted at the same levels and
  in accordance with the same procedures as provided for in Title I of
  this Agreement, which can itself provide a framework for that
  dialogue.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Cooperation In The Social Field" chapter_identifier="209">
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" article_identifier="1579">1. The Parties recognise the importance of social development, which
  must go hand in hand with economic development. They will give
  priority to respect for fundamental social rights.

  2. With a view to consolidating cooperation between the Parties in the
  social field, projects and programmes shall be carried out in any area
  of interest to them.

  In this context, the following shall be priority measures:

  (a) contributing to the improvement of living conditions, job creation
  and the development of training in areas from which emigrants come;

  (b) resettling those repatriated because of their illegal status under
  the legislation of the state in question;

  (c) productive investment or the creation of businesses in Algeria by
  Algerian workers legally settled in the Community;

  (d) promoting the role of women in the economic and social development
  process through education and the media, in keeping with Algerian
  policy;

  (e) bolstering Algerian family planning and mother and child
  protection programmes;

  (f) improving the social welfare and health systems;

  (g) implementing and financing exchange and leisure programmes for
  mixed groups of Algerian and European young people residing in the
  Member States, with a view to promoting mutual knowledge of their
  respective cultures and fostering tolerance;

  (h) improving living conditions in poor areas;

  (i) promoting socio-professional dialogue;

  (j) promoting respect for human rights in the socio-professional
  context;

  (k) contributing to the development of the housing sector, especially
  with regard to low-cost housing;

  (l) alleviating the adverse impact of the adjustment of economic and
  social structures;

  (m) improving the vocational training system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" article_identifier="1580">Cooperation schemes may be carried out in conjunction with the Member
  States and the relevant international organisations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" article_identifier="1581">A working party shall be set up by the Association Council by the end
  of the first year following the entry into force of this Agreement. It
  shall be responsible for the continuous and regular evaluation of the
  implementation of Chapters 1 to 3.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Cooperation In The Fields Of Education And Culture" chapter_identifier="210">
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" article_identifier="1582">This Agreement shall aim to promote the exchange of information and
  cultural cooperation, taking account of bilateral schemes in the
  Member States.

  Greater knowledge and better mutual understanding of the respective
  cultures will be promoted.

  Special attention must be paid to promoting joint activities in
  various fields, including the press, cinema and television, and to
  encouraging youth exchange schemes.

  This cooperation could cover the following areas:

  - literary translation,

  - conservation and restoration of monuments and sites of historical
  and cultural interest,

  - training of persons working in the cultural field,

  - exchanges of artists and works of arts,

  - organisation of cultural events,

  - raising mutual awareness and disseminating information on important
  cultural events,

  - encouragement of cooperation in the audiovisual field, particularly
  training and co-production,

  - distribution of literary, technical and scientific journals and
  publications.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" article_identifier="1583">The aim of cooperation in the field of education and training shall be
  to:

  (a) contribute to the improvement of the education and training
  system, including vocational training;

  (b) place special emphasis on giving the female population access to
  education, including technical training, higher education and
  vocational training;

  (c) develop the level of expertise of senior staff in the public and
  private sectors;

  (d) encourage the establishment of lasting links between specialist
  bodies on the Parties' territories in order to pool and exchange
  experience and methods.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VII" name="Financial Cooperation" chapter_identifier="211">
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" article_identifier="1584">In order to support the objectives of this Agreement, Algeria shall
  receive financial cooperation Algeria in accordance with the
  appropriate procedures and with the appropriate financial resources.

  These procedures shall be adopted by mutual agreement between the
  Parties by means of the most suitable instruments once this Agreement
  enters into force.

  In addition to the areas covered by Titles V and VI of this Agreement,
  cooperation shall apply to the following:

  - facilitating reforms designed to modernise the economy, including
  rural development,

  - upgrading economic infrastructure,

  - promoting private investment and job-creating activities,

  - offsetting the effects on the Algerian economy of the progressive
  introduction of a free trade area, in particular where the updating
  and restructuring of industry is concerned,

  - accompanying measures for policies implemented in the social
  sectors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" article_identifier="1585">Within the framework of the Community instruments designed to support
  structural adjustment programmes in the Mediterranean countries in
  order to restore key financial equilibria and create an economic
  environment conducive to faster growth and enhanced social welfare,
  the Community and Algeria, in close coordination with other
  contributors, in particular the international financial institutions,
  shall adapt the instruments intended to accompany development and
  liberalisation policies for the Algerian economy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" article_identifier="1586">In order to ensure a coordinated approach to dealing with any
  exceptional macroeconomic or financial problems which might stem from
  the progressive implementation of the provisions of this Agreement,
  the Parties shall closely monitor the development of trade and
  financial relations between the Community and Algeria as part of the
  regular economic dialogue established under Title V.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VIII" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Justice And Home Affairs" chapter_identifier="212">
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Institution-Building And The Rule Of Law" article_identifier="1587">In their cooperation in the field of justice and home affairs, the
  Parties shall attach particular importance to institution-building in
  the areas of law enforcement and the machinery of justice. This
  includes the consolidation of the rule of law.

  In this context the Parties shall also ensure that the rights of
  nationals of both Parties are respected without discrimination in the
  territory of the other Party.

  The provisions of this Article do not relate to differences of
  treatment based on nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Movement Of Persons" article_identifier="1588">Desirous of facilitating the movement of persons between them, the
  Parties shall ensure, in accordance with the relevant Community and
  national legislation in force, that the formalities for the issue of
  visas are carefully applied and executed and shall agree to examine,
  within the limits of their powers, ways of simplifying and speeding up
  the issue of visas to persons contributing to the implementation of
  this Agreement. The Association Committee shall periodically examine
  the implementation of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Cooperation In The Prevention And Control Of Illegal Immigration; Readmission" article_identifier="1589">1. The Parties reaffirm the importance which they attach to the
  development of mutually beneficial cooperation in relation to the
  exchange of information on illegal immigration flows and agree to
  cooperate in order to prevent and control illegal immigration. To this
  end:

  - Algeria, on the one hand, and each Member State of the Community, on
  the other hand, agree to readmit any of their nationals illegally
  present on the territory of the other Party after the necessary
  identification formalities have been completed,

  - Algeria and the Member States of the Community shall provide their
  nationals with the appropriate identity documents for this purpose.

  2. Desirous of facilitating the movement and residence of their
  nationals whose status is regular, the Parties agree to negotiate, at
  the request of either Party, the conclusion of agreements on combating
  illegal immigration and on readmission. If either Party considers it
  necessary, such agreements shall cover the readmission of nationals of
  other countries arriving in their territory direct from the territory
  of the other. The practical arrangements for the implementation of the
  abovementioned agreements shall be laid down, where appropriate, by
  the Parties in the agreements themselves or in their implementing
  protocols.

  3. The Association Council shall examine the possibility of other
  forms of joint action for the prevention and control of illegal
  immigration, including ways of detecting forged documents.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Legal And Judicial Cooperation" article_identifier="1590">1. The Parties agree that cooperation in the legal and judicial fields
  is essential and a necessary adjunct to the other forms of cooperation
  provided for in this Agreement.

  2. Such cooperation may include, where appropriate, the negotiation of
  agreements in these fields.

  3. Civil judicial cooperation will in particular cover:

  - strengthening mutual assistance with regard to cooperation in the
  handling of disputes or cases of a civil, commercial or family nature,

  - the exchange of experience in relation to managing and improving the
  administration of civil justice.

  4. Criminal judicial cooperation will cover:

  - strengthening existing mutual assistance or extradition
  arrangements,

  - the development of exchanges, in particular in relation to the
  practice of criminal judicial cooperation, the protection of
  individual rights and freedoms, action against organised crime and
  improving the efficiency of criminal justice.

  5. Cooperation in this area shall in particular include the
  introduction of specialist training courses.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Preventing And Tackling Organised Crime" article_identifier="1591">1. The Parties agree to cooperate in order to prevent and fight
  organised crime, in particular in the following fields: human
  trafficking; exploitation for sexual purposes; the illicit traffic of
  prohibited, counterfeited or pirated products, and illegal
  transactions concerning, in particular, industrial refuse or
  radioactive material; corruption; the trafficking of stolen cars; the
  trafficking of firearms and explosives; computer crime; and
  trafficking in cultural goods.

  The Parties shall cooperate closely in order to establish appropriate
  mechanisms and standards.

  2. Technical and administrative cooperation in this field may include
  training and improving the effectiveness of the authorities and bodies
  responsible for fighting and preventing crime and the design of crime
  prevention measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Combating Money Laundering" article_identifier="1592">1. The Parties agree on the need to work towards and cooperate on
  preventing the use of their financial systems to launder the proceeds
  of criminal activities in general and drug trafficking in particular.

  2. Cooperation in this area shall include administrative and technical
  assistance with the purpose of adopting and implementing suitable
  standards against money laundering equivalent to those adopted by the
  Community and international authorities active in this field,
  including the Financial Action Task Force (FATF).

  3. Cooperation shall have the objective of:

  (a) training agents of the services responsible for preventing,
  detecting and combating money laundering, and officials of the
  judiciary;

  (b) appropriate support for the creation of specialist institutions
  and the strengthening of existing institutions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Combating Racism And Xenophobia" article_identifier="1593">The Parties agree to take appropriate steps to prevent and combat
  discrimination in all its forms and manifestations, whether it be on
  grounds of race, ethnic origin or religion, particularly in the fields
  of education, employment, training and housing.

  Public information and awareness campaigns will be organised to this
  end.

  The Parties shall in particular ensure in this context that all
  persons who consider themselves victims of such discrimination have
  access to judicial and administrative procedures.

  The provisions of this Article do not relate to differences of
  treatment based on nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Combating Drugs And Drug Addiction" article_identifier="1594">1. Cooperation shall be aimed at:

  (a) improving the effectiveness of policies and measures to prevent
  and combat the growing, production, supply and consumption of, and
  trafficking in, narcotics and psychotropic substances;

  (b) eliminating illicit consumption of such products.

  2. The Parties shall determine together, in accordance with their
  respective laws, the strategies and cooperation methods appropriate
  for attaining these objectives. Their operations, other than joint
  operations, shall be the subject of consultation and close
  coordination.

  Such action may involve the appropriate public and private sector
  institutions and international organisations, in collaboration with
  the Government of Algeria and the relevant authorities in the
  Community and the Member States.

  3. Cooperation shall take the following forms in particular:

  (a) establishment or extension of social and health institutions and
  information centres for the treatment and rehabilitation of drug
  addicts;

  (b) the implementation of prevention, information, training and
  epidemiological research projects;

  (c) the establishment of standards for preventing diversion of
  precursors and other essential ingredients for the illicit manufacture
  of narcotics and psychotropic substances, which are equivalent to
  those adopted by the Community and the appropriate international
  authorities;

  (d) support for the creation of special anti-drug trafficking
  services.

  4. Both Parties shall encourage cooperation at regional and
  sub-regional level.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Fight Against Terrorism" article_identifier="1595">In accordance with the international conventions to which they are
  party and with their respective laws and regulations, both Parties
  agree to cooperate with a view to preventing and penalising acts of
  terrorism:

  - through the implementation in its entirety of United Nations
  Security Council resolution 1373 and other related resolutions,

  - through the exchange of information on terrorist groups and their
  support networks in accordance with international and national law,

  - by pooling experience of means and practices for combating
  terrorism, including experience in the technical and training fields.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Fight Against Corruption" article_identifier="1596">1. The Parties agree to cooperate, on the basis of the relevant
  international legal instruments, on action to combat corruption in
  international business transactions:

  - by taking effective practical measures against all forms of
  corruption, bribery and illicit activities of every sort in
  international business transactions practised by individuals or
  corporate bodies,

  - by providing mutual assistance in criminal investigations into acts
  of corruption.

  2. Cooperation shall also cover technical assistance for the training
  of officials and magistrates responsible for tackling corruption and
  support for initiatives designed to organise action against this form
  of crime.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IX" name="Institutional, General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="213">
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" article_identifier="1597">An Association Council is hereby established which shall meet at
  ministerial level once a year, where possible, on the initiative of
  its Chair and in accordance with the conditions laid down in its rules
  of procedure.

  It shall examine any major issues arising within the framework of this
  Agreement and any other bilateral or international issues of mutual
  interest.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" article_identifier="1598">1. The Association Council shall consist of the members of the Council
  of the European Union and members of the Commission of the European
  Communities, on the one hand, and of members of the Government of
  Algeria, on the other.

  2. Members of the Association Council may arrange to be represented in
  accordance with the provisions laid down in its rules of procedure.

  3. The Association Council shall establish its rules of procedure.

  4. The Association Council shall be chaired in turn by a member of the
  Council of the European Union and a member of the Government of
  Algeria in accordance with the provisions laid down in its rules of
  procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" article_identifier="1599">The Association Council shall, for the purpose of attaining the
  objectives of this Agreement, have the power to take decisions in the
  cases provided for therein.

  These decisions shall be binding on the Parties which shall take the
  measures necessary to implement the decisions taken. The Association
  Council may also make appropriate recommendations.

  It shall draw up its decisions and recommendations by agreement
  between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" article_identifier="1600">1. Subject to the powers conferred upon the Association Council, an
  Association Committee is hereby established which shall be responsible
  for the implementation of this Agreement.

  2. The Association Council may delegate to the Association Committee,
  in full or in part, any of its powers.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" article_identifier="1601">1. The Association Committee, which shall meet at official level,
  shall consist of representatives of members of the Council of the
  European Union and of the Commission of the European Communities, on
  the one hand, and of representatives of the Government of Algeria, on
  the other.

  2. The Association Committee shall establish its rules of procedure.

  3. The Association Committee shall meet in the Community or in
  Algeria.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" article_identifier="1602">The Association Committee shall have the power to take decisions for
  the management of this Agreement as well as in those areas in which
  the Association Council has delegated its powers to it.

  Decisions shall be adopted by agreement between the Parties and shall
  be binding on the Parties, which shall take the measures necessary to
  implement them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" article_identifier="1603">The Association Council may decide to set up any working group or body
  necessary for the implementation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" article_identifier="1604">The Association Council shall take all appropriate measures to
  facilitate cooperation and contacts between the European Parliament
  and the parliamentary institutions of Algeria, and between the
  Economic and Social Committee of the Community and its counterpart in
  Algeria.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" article_identifier="1605">1. Each of the Parties may refer to the Association Council any
  dispute relating to the application or interpretation of this
  Agreement.

  2. The Association Council may settle the dispute by means of a
  decision.

  3. Each Party shall be bound to take the measures involved in carrying
  out the decision referred to in paragraph 2.

  4. In the event of it not being possible to settle the dispute in
  accordance with paragraph 2, either Party may notify the other of the
  appointment of an arbitrator; the other Party must then appoint a
  second arbitrator within two months. For the application of this
  procedure, the Community and the Member States shall be deemed to be
  one party to the dispute.

  The Association Council shall appoint a third arbitrator.

  The arbitrators’ decisions shall be taken by majority vote.

  Each party to the dispute must take the steps required to implement
  the decision of the arbitrators.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" article_identifier="1606">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a Contracting Party from
  taking any measures:

  (a) which it considers necessary to prevent the disclosure of
  information contrary to its essential security interests;

  (b) which relate to the production of, or trade in, arms, munitions or
  war materials or to research, development or production indispensable
  for defence purposes, provided that such measures do not impair the
  conditions of competition in respect of products not intended for
  specifically military purposes;

  (c) which it considers essential to its own security in the event of
  serious internal disturbances affecting the maintenance of law and
  order, in time of war or serious international tension constituting
  threat of war or in order to carry out obligations it has accepted for
  the purpose of maintaining peace and international security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" article_identifier="1607">In the fields covered by this Agreement, and without prejudice to any
  special provisions contained therein:

  - the arrangements applied by Algeria in respect of the Community
  shall not give rise to any discrimination between the Member States,
  their nationals or their companies or firms,

  - the arrangements applied by the Community in respect of Algeria
  shall not give rise to any discrimination between Algerian nationals,
  companies or firms.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" article_identifier="1608">Nothing in this Agreement shall have the effect of:

  - extending the fiscal advantages granted by either Party in any
  international agreement or arrangement by which it is bound,

  - preventing the adoption or application by either Party of any
  measure aimed at preventing the avoidance or evasion of taxes,

  - opposing the right of either Party to apply the relevant provisions
  of its tax legislation to taxpayers who are not in identical
  situation, in particular as regards their place of residence.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" article_identifier="1609">1. The Parties shall take any general or specific measures required to
  fulfil their obligations under this Agreement. They shall see to it
  that the objectives set out in the Agreement are attained.

  2. If either Party considers that the other Party has failed to fulfil
  an obligation under the Agreement, it may take appropriate measures.
  Before so doing, except in cases of special urgency, it shall supply
  the Association Council with all the relevant information required for
  a thorough examination of the situation with a view to seeking a
  solution acceptable to the Parties.

  In the selection of measures, priority must be given to those which
  least disturb the functioning of the Agreement. These measures shall
  be notified immediately to the Association Council and shall be the
  subject of consultations within the Association Council if the other
  Party so requests.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" article_identifier="1610">Protocols 1 to 7 and Annexes 1 to 6 shall form an integral part of
  this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" article_identifier="1611">For the purposes of this Agreement, "Parties" shall mean, on
  the one hand, the Community or the Member States, or the Community and
  its Member States, in accordance with their respective powers, and, on
  the other hand, Algeria.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" article_identifier="1612">This Agreement shall be concluded for an unlimited period.

  Each of the Parties may denounce this Agreement by notifying the other
  Party. The Agreement shall cease to apply six months after the date of
  such notification.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" article_identifier="1613">This Agreement shall apply, on the one hand, to the territories in
  which the Treaty establishing the European Community is applied and
  under the conditions laid down in that Treaty and, on the other, to
  the territory of the People's Democratic Republic of Algeria.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" article_identifier="1614">This Agreement shall be drawn up in duplicate in the Danish, Dutch,
  English, Finnish, French, German, Greek, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish,
  Swedish and Arabic languages, each of these texts being equally
  authentic.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" article_identifier="1615">1. This Agreement will be approved by the Contracting Parties in
  accordance with their own procedures.

  This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the second
  month following the date on which the Contracting Parties notify each
  other that the procedures referred to in the first subparagraph have
  been completed.

  2. Upon its entry into force, this Agreement shall replace the
  Cooperation Agreement between the European Economic Community and the
  People's Democratic Republic of Algeria and the Agreement between the
  Member States of the European Coal and Steel Community and the
  People's Democratic Republic of Algeria, both of which were signed in
  Algiers on 26 April 1976.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="214">
      <article article_identifier="1616">Hecho en Valencia, el veintidós de abril del dos mil dos.

  Udfærdiget i Valencia den toogtyvende april to tusind og to.

  Geschehen zu Valencia am zweiundzwanzigsten April zweitausendundzwei.

  Έγινε στη Βαλένθια, στις εΐκοσι δύο Απριλΐον δύο χιλιάδες δύο.

  Done at Valencia on the twenty-second day of April in the year two
  thousand and two.

  Fait à Valence, le vingt-deux avril deux mille deux.

  Fatto a Valenza, addi’ ventidue aprile duemiladue.

  Gedaan te Valencia, de tweeëntwintigste april tweeduizendtwee.

  Feito em Valência, em vinte e dois de Abril de dois mil e dois.

  Tehty Valenciassa kahdentenakymmenentenätoisenä päivänä huhtikuuta
  vuonna kaksituhattakaksi.

  Som skedde i Valencia den tjugoandra april tjugohundratvå.

  Pour le Royaume de Belgique

  Voor het Koninkrijk België

  Für das Königreich Belgien

  Cette signature engage également la Communauté française, la
  Communauté flamande, la Communauté germanophone, la Région wallonne,
  la Région flamande et la Région de Bruxelles-Capitale.

  Deze handtekening verbindt eveneens de Vlaamse Gemeenschap, de Franse
  Gemeenschap, de Duitstalige Gemeenschap, het Vlaamse Gewest, het
  Waalse Gewest en het Brussels Hoofdstedelijk Gewest.

  Diese Unterschrift verbindet zugleich die Deutschsprachige
  Gemeinschaft, die Flämische Gemeinschaft, die Französische
  Gemeinschaft, die Wallonische Region, die Flämische Region und die
  Region Brüssel-Hauptstadt.

  På Kongeriget Danmarks vegne

  Für die Bundesrepublik Deutschland

  Για την Eλληνική Δημoκρατία

  Por el Reino de España

  Pour la République française

  Thar cheann Na hÉireann

  For Ireland

  Per la Repubblica italiana

  Pour le Grand-Duché de Luxembourg

  Voor het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden

  Für die Republik Österreich

  Pela República Portuguesa

  Suomen tasavallan puolesta

  För Republiken Finland

  För Konungariket Sverige

  For the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland

  Por la Comunidad Europea

  For Det Europæiske Fællesskab

  Für die Europäische Gemeinschaft

  Για την Eυρωπαϊκή Koινότητα

  For the European Community

  Pour la Communauté européenne

  Per la Comunità europea

  Voor de Europese Gemeenschap

  Pela Comunidade Europeia

  Euroopan yhteisön puolesta

  På Europeiska gemenskapens vägnar

  --------------------------------------------------</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
