<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Caribbean Free Trade Association (CARIFTA)</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>213</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>187</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1965-12-15</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1968-05-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1968-10-22</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>1973-08-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">ATG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BRB</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">DMA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">GRD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">GUY</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">JAM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">KNA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">LCA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">MSR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">TTO</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">VCT</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Caribbean; South America</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=90810052&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="2014">
      <article article_identifier="17009">THE GOVERNMENTS OF THE SIGNATORY TERRITORIES 

SHARING a common determination to fulfil within the shortest possible time 
the hopes and aspirations of the peoples of the Caribbean Territories for full 
employment and improved living standards; 


CONSCIOUS that these goals can most rapidly be attained by the optimum use 
of available human and other resources and by accelerated, co-ordinated and 
sustained economic development; 


AWARE that the broadening of domestic markets through the elimination of 
barriers to trade between the Territories is a prerequisite to such development; 


CONVINCED that such elimination of barriers to trade can best be achieved 
by the immediate establishment of a free-trade area which will contribute to the 
ultimate creation of a viable economic community of Caribbean Territories; 


MINDFUL of the different levels of development attained by the Territories 
of the Caribbean; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="2015">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Association" article_identifier="17010">1. An Association to be called the Caribbean Free Trade Association (hereinafter 
referred to as "The Association") is hereby established. 



2. The Members of the Association, hereinafter referred to as "Member 
Territories" shall be the Territories on behalf of the Governments of which this 
Agreement is ratified in accordance with Article 31 and such other Territories 
as participate therein by virtue of paragraph 1 of Article 32, and for the 
purposes hereof, "Territories" includes sovereign States internationally
recognized. 



3. The institutions of the Association shall be a Council and. such organs as 
are mentioned in paragraph 3 of Article 28. 



4. The Caribbean Free Trade Association shall operate over the areas of the 
Member Territories collectively called the Caribbean Free Trade Area (hereinafter
referred to as "The Area").</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Objectives" article_identifier="17011">The objectives of the Association shall be: 



(a) 	to promote the expansion and diversification of trade in the area of 
the Association; 



(b) 	to secure that trade between Member Territories takes place in 
conditions of fair competition; 

(c). 	to encourage the balanced and progressive development of the 


economies of the Area in keeping with paragraphs 3 to 10 of the 
Resolution adopted at the Fourth Conference of the Heads of Government 
of Commonwealth Caribbean Countries and set out in Annex A; 



(d) 	to foster the harmonious development of Caribbean trade and its 
liberalization by the removal of barriers to it; 



(e) 	to ensure that the benefits of free trade are equitably distributed, 

among the Member Territories.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Exclusion From This Agreement:" article_identifier="17012">1. The provisions of this Agreement shall.not affect the rights and obligations 
under any agreements entered into by any of the Parties to this Agreement before 
the effective date hereof and notified to the Council: 


Provided, however, that. each Party shall take any steps at its disposal 


which are necessary to reconcile the provisions of any of such agreements with 
the purposes. of this Agreement. 


Provided further that, in case of any non-observance of any provisions of 
this Agrememnt on the part of a Member Territory pursuant to its exemption in 
that behalf by virtue of the forgoing provisions of this Article, any other. 
Member Territory which considers that it would enjoy any benefit under this 
Agreement but for such exemption may, if no satisfactory settlement is reached 
between the Member Territories concerned, refer the matter to the Council, which 
may, by majority decision, authorize any Member Territory to suspend to the 
first-mentioned Member Territory the application of such obligations under this 
Agreement as the Council considers meet, due regard being had to the report of 
such committee (if any) as may have been constituted in accordance with Article 27 
to examine the matter, and paragraphs 2 and 5 of Article 26 shall apply mutatis 
mutandis in the case of any reference under this proviso as they apply in the 
case of a reference under paragraph 1 of Article 26. 



2. 	All such agreements shall be registered in such form as the Council shall 


decide and by way of such service in that behalf as shall be arranged pursuant 
to sub-paragraph (b) of paragraph 1 of Article 29. 



3. The Council shall annually review the observance by Parties to this 
Agreement of the first proviso to paragraph 1 of this Article and may from time 
to time, by majority vote, recommend to any of them the taking of any steps
for the purposes of that proviso. 



4. For the purposes of this Article, "agreements" means any agreements concluded 
by instruments, or any arrangements made in writing which the.Council decides, bv-majority vote, constitute agreements for those purposes, but does not inelvea 
any agreement ox-arrangements enter6d. into by a Party hercto, not being the 
Government of Grenada, in. respect of which negotiations commenced aftcr 

22 February, 1968.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Import Duties" article_identifier="17013">1. Subject to the provisions of Annex B, Member Territories shall not apply 
any import duties on goods which are eligible for Area tariff treatment in 
accordance with Article 5. 



2. For the purposes of this Article and Annex B, the term "import duties" 
means any tax or surtax of customs and any other charges of equivalent effect whether fiscal, monetary or exchange which are levied on imports, except 
duties notified under Article 7 and other charges which fall within that Article. 



3. The provisions of this Article do not apply to fees and similar charges in 
respect of services rendered and nothing in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be 
construed to exclude from the application of paragraph 1 of this Article any tax 
or surtax of customs on any product neither the like of which, nor a competitive
substitute for which, is produced in the importing Member Territory, or to 
extend such application to non-discriminatory internal charges on any such 
products. 



4. 	For the pUrpOSGS of paragraph 3 of this Article: 



(a) 	"non-discriminatory" means non-discriminatory as between goods eligible
for Area tariff treatment as aforesaid and goods not so eligible; 



(b) 	a charge shall not be deemed other than. internal by reason only that 
it is collected at the time and place of importation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Area Origin For Tariff Purposes" article_identifier="17014">1. For the purposes of Articles 4 to 8, goods shall, subject to Annex C, be 
accepted as eligible for Area tariff treatment if they are consigned from a 


Member Territory to a consignee in the importing Member Territory and if they 
are of Area origin under any one of the following conditions: 



(a) 	that they have been wholly produced within the Area; 



(b) 	that they fall within a description of goods listed in a Process List 
to be established by decision of the Council and have been produced
within the Area by the appropriate qualifying process described in 

that 	List; 


(c) 	that they have been produced within the Area and that the value of any
materials imported from outside the Area or of undetermined origin which 
have been used at any stage of the production of the goods does not 
exceed 50 per cent of the export price of the goods. 



2. For the purposes of sub-paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) of paragraph 1 of this 
Article, materials listed in the Basic Materials List which forms the Schedule 
to Annex C, which have been used in the state described in that List in a 
process of production within the Area, shall be deemed to contain no clement 
imported from outside the Area. 



3. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a Member Territory from accepting 
as eligible for Area tariff treatment any imports consigned from another Member 
Territory, provided that the like imports consigned from any Member Territory 
are accorded the same treatment. 



4. 	Provisions necessary for the administration and effective application of 



5. 	The Council may decide to amend the provisions of this Article,Annex C and 

this 	Article are contained in Annex C. 


the Process List established under sub-paragraph (b) of paragraph 1 of this 


Article. 



6. The council shall from time to time examine in what respect this Agreement 
can be amended in order to ensure the smooth operation of the origin rules. 



7. Nothing in this Agreement shall require a Member Territory to accept as 
eligible for Area tariff treatment any imports consigned from another Member 
Territory and consisting of, or manufactured from, oils and fats as definad by
clause 2 of the Oils and Fats Agreement, or any of such oils or fats, where the 
Government of one of such Territories is a party to the Oils and Fats Agreement,
and the Government of the other of such Territories is not a party to that 
Agreement, being the Agreement made on 26 January 1967, between the Governments 
of Barbados, Dominica, Grenada, Guyana, St. Lucia, St. Vincent and Trinidad 
and Tobago or any Agreerent amending or replacing the Same.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Deflection Of Trade" article_identifier="17015">1. 	For the purposes of this Article, trade is said to be deflected when: 


(a) 	imports into a Member Territory of consignments of a particular
product from another Member Territory are increasing: 



(i) 	as a result of the reduction or elimination in the importing
Member Territory of duties and charges on that product in 
accordance with Article 4 or 7, and 



(ii) 	because the duties or charges levied by the exporting Member 

Territory on imports of raw materials or intermediate products, 


used 	in the production of the product in question, are 


significantly lower than the corresponding duties or charges 


levied by the importing Member Territory, and 


(b) 	this increase in imports causes or would cause serious injury to 
production which is carried on in the importing Member Territory. 



2. The Council shall keep under review the question of deflections of trade 
and their causes. It shall take such decisions as are necessary in order to 
deal with the causes of deflection of trade by amending the rules of origin in 
accordance with paragraph 5 of Article 5 or by such other means as it may 
consider appropriate. 



3. If a deflection of trade of a particularly urgent nature occurs, any Member 
Territory may refer the matter to the Council. The Council shall take its 
decision as quickly as possible and, in general, within one month. The Council 
may, by majority decision, authorize interim measures to safeguard the position 
of the Member Territory in question. Such measures shall not continue for 
longer than is necessary for the procedure under paragraph 2 above to take place,
and for not more than two months, unless in exceptional cases, the Council. by 
majority decision, authorizes an extension of this period by not more than 
two months. 

4. A Member Territory which is considering the reduction of the effective level 
of its duties or charges on any product not eligible for Area tariff treatment 


shall, as far as may be practicable, notify the Council not less than thirty days


before such reduction comes into effect, and shall consider any representations
by other Member Territories that the reduction is likely to lead to a deflection 
of trade. Information received under this paragraph shall not be disclosed to 
any person outside the service of the Association or the Governments of Member 
Territories. 


5. When considering changes in their duties or charges on any product not 
eligible for Area tariff treatment, Mamber Territories shall have due regard to 


the desirability of avoiding consequentiel deflections of trade. In case of any 
such change, any Member Territory which considers that trade is being deflected 
may refer the natter to th; Council in accordance with Article 26. 



6. If, in the consideration of any complaint in accordance with Article 26, 
reference is made to a difference in the level of duties or charges on any
product not eligible for Area tariff treatment, that difference shall be taken 
into account only if the Council finds by majority vote that there is a 
deflection of trade. 



7. The Council shall review from time to time the provisions of this Article 
and may decide to amend those provisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Revenue Duties And Internal Txation" article_identifier="17016">1. 	Subject to the provisions of Annex D, Member Territories shall not: 



(a) 	apply directly or indirectly to imported goods any fiscal char-es 
in excess of those applied directly or indirectly to like domestic 
goods, nor otherwise apply such charges so as to afford effective 
protection to like domestic goods; or 



(b) 	apply fiscal charges to imported goods of .a kind which they do not 

produce, or which they do not produce in substantial quantities, in 
such a way as to afford effective protection to the domestic production:.


of goods of a different kind which are substitutable for the importeed
goods, which enter into direct. competition with them and which do no! 
bear, directly or indirectly, in the country of importation, fiscal 
charges of equivalent incidence. 


2. A Member Territory shall notify the Council of all fiscal charges applied by
it where, although the rates of charge, or the conditions governing the 
imposition of collection of the charge, are not identical in relation to the 
imported goods and to the like domestic goods, the Member Torritory applying
the charge considers that the charge is, or has been made, consistent with 



sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph 1 of this Article. Each Member Territory shall,
at the request of any other Member Territory,supply information about the 


application of paragraph 1 of this Article. 


3. 	For the purposes of this Article and Annex D: 


(a). 	"fiscal charges" moons revenue duties, internal taxes and other 
internal charges on goods; 



(b) 	"revenue duties"means customs duties and other similar charges
applied primarily for the purpose of raising revenue; and 



(c) 	importeed goods" means goods which are accepted as being eligible for 
Area tariff treatment in accordance with Article 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Export Drawback" article_identifier="17017">Each Member Territory may refuse to accept as eligible for Area tariff 
treatment goods which benefit from export drawback allowed by Member Territories 
in which the goods have undergone the processes of production which form the 
basis of the claim to Area origin. In applying this paragraph, each Member 
Territory shall accord the same treatment to imports consigned from all other 
Member Territories 


For the purposes of this Article: 


(a) 	"export drawback" means any arrangement for the refund or remission,
wholly or in part, of import duties applicable to imported materials,
provided that the arrangement, expressly or in effect, allows refund 


or remission if certain goods or materials are exported, but not if 


they 	are retained for home use; 



(b) 	"remission" includes exemption for materials brought into free ports
and other places which have similar customs privileges; 



(c) 	"'duties" means (i) all charges on or in connexion with importation, 
except fiscal charges to which Article 7 applies and (ii) any protective
element in such fiscal charges; 



(d) 	"materials" and "process of production" have the meanings assigned 
to them in Rule 1 of Annex C.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Prohibition Of Exirt Duties" article_identifier="17018">1. Member.Territories shall not apply any export duties. 



2. The provisions of this Article shall not prevent any Member Territory from 

taking such measures as are necessary to prevent evasion, by means of re-export,
of duties which it applied to exports to territories outside the Area. 



3. For the purposes of this Articles "export duties" means any duties or 
charges with equivalent effect imposed on or in connexion with the exportation 
of-goods from any Member Territory to a consignee in any other Member Territory. 



4. Nothing in this Article shall preclude a Member Territory from applying to 
any commodity listed in Annex E, within ten years from the effective date of 
this Agreement, export duty not exceeding that applicable by the Member Territory 
to such commodity immediately before the effective date of this Agreement. 



5. Any Member Territory which, pursuant to paragraph 4 of this Article, applies 
or continues to apply export duty to any commodity listed in Annex E shall notify 
the Council of every commodity on which export duty is applied and the rate of 
such duty. The Council shall keep under review the question of such export 
duties and may at any time by majority vote make; recommendations designed to 
moderate any damaging effect of those duties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Co-Operation In Customs Administration" article_identifier="17019">Member Territories shall take appropriate measures, including arrangements 
regarding administrative co-operation to ensure that the provisions of 
Articles 4 to 8 and of Annexes B, C and D are effectively and harmoniously
applied, taking account of the need to reduce as far as is possible the 
formalities imposed on trade and of the need to achieve mutually satisfactory 
solutions of any difficulties arising out of the operation of those provisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Freedom Of Transist" article_identifier="17020">Products imported into, or exported from, a Member Torritory shall enjoy 
freedom of transit within the Area and shall only be subject to the payment of 
the normal rates for services rendered.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Dumped And Subsidized Imports" article_identifier="17021">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent any Member Territory from taking
action against dumped or subsidized imports consistently with any international 
obligations to which it is subject. 



2. Any products which have been exported from. one Member Territory to a 
consignee in another Member Territory and have not undergone any manufacturing 

process since exportation shall, when reimported into the first Member Territory,
be admitted free of quantitative restrictions and measures with equivalent effect. 
They shall also be admitted free of customs duties and charges with equivalent
affect, except that any allowance by way of drawback, relief from duty or otherwise, given by reason of the exportation from the first Member Territory, may be 
recovered. 


3. If any industry in any Member Territory is suffering or is threatened with 
material injury as the result of the import of dumped or subsidized products 
into another Member Territory, the latter Member Territory shall, at the request
of the former Member Territory, examine the possibility of taking, consistently 
with any international obligations to which it is subject, action to remedy the 
injury or prevent the threatened injury.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Quantitative Import Restrictions" article_identifier="17022">1. Subject to anything to the contrary in any agricultural marketing arrangements made pursuant to paragraph 6 of Annex A and laid down in a Protocol between 
the Parties to this Agreement, a Member Territory shall not apply any quantitative 
restrictions on imports of goods from any other part of the Area. 



2. For the purposes of the preceding paragraph, "quantitative restrictions" 
means prohibitions or restrictions on imports into any Member Territory from any
other part of the Area whether made effective through quotas, import licences or 
other measures with equivalent effect, including administrative measures and 
requirements restricting import. 



3. The provisions of this Article shall not prevent any Mermber Territory from 
taking such measures as are necessary to prevent evasion, of any prohibitions or 
restrictions which it applies to imports from territories outside the Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Quantitative Export Restrictions" article_identifier="17023">1. Subject as mentioned in paragraph 1 of Article 13, a Member Territory shall 
not apply any prohibitions or restrictions on exports to any other part of the 
Area, whether made effective through quotas or export licences or other measures 
with equivalent effect. 



2. The provisions of this Article shall not prevent any Member Territory from 
taking such measures as are necessary to prevent evasion, of any. prohibitions or 

restrictions which it applies to exports to territories outside the Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="17024">Provided that such measures are not used as a means of arbitrary or.unjusti

fiable discrimination between Member Territories, or as a disguised restriction on 


the inter-territorial trade of the Area, nothing in Articles 13 and 14 shall 
prevent the adoption. or enforcement by any Member Territory of measures 



(a) 	necessary to protect public morals; 



(b) 	necessary for the prevention of disorder or crime; 



(c) 	necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health; 



(d) 	necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations relating to 
customs enforcement, or to the classification, grading or marketing
of goods, or to the operation of monopolies by means of State enterprises or enterprises given exclusive or special privileges; 



(e) 	necessary 'to protect industrial property or copyrights or to prevent
deceptive practices; 



(f) 	relating to gold or silver; 



(g) 	relating to the products of prison labour; 



(h) 	imposed for the protection of national treasures of artistic, historic 
or archaeological value; or 



(i) 	necessary to prevent or relieve critical shortages of foodstuffs in 
any exporting Member Territory.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="17025">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent any Member Territory from taking
action which it considers necessary for the protection of its essential security


interests, where such action: 



(a) 	is taken to prevent the disclosure of information; 



(b) 	relates to trade in arms, ammunition or war materials or to research,
development or production indispensable for defence purposes, provided
that such action does not include the application of import duties or 
the quantitative restriction of imports except in so far as such 
restriction is permitted in accordance with Article 15 or is authorized 
by decision of the Council; 



(c) 	is taken to ensure that nuclear materials and equipment made available 
for peaceful purposes do not further military purposes; or 



(d) 	is taken in time of war or other emergency in international relations. 

2. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent any member Territory from taking
action to perform any obligations to which it is subject for the purpose of 
maintaining international peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Government Aids" article_identifier="17026">1. 	A Member Territory shall not maintain or introduce: 



(a) 	the forms of aid to export of goods to any other part of the Area of 
the kinds which are described in Annex F; or 



(b) 	any other form of aid, the main purpose or effect of which is to 
frustrate the benefits expected from such removal or absence of duties 
and quantitative restrictions as is required by this Agreement. 

2. If the application of any form of aid by a Member Territory, although not 
contrary to paragraph 1 of this Article, frustrates the benefits expected from 
such removal or absence of duties and quantitative restrictions as is required
by this Agreement and provided that the procedure set out in paragraphs 1 to 3 of 
Article 26 has been followed, the Council may, by majority decision, authorize 
any Member Territory to suspend to the Member Territory which is applying the aid, 
the application of such obligations under this Agreement as the Council considers 
appropriate. 



3. 	The Council may decide to amend the provision of this Article and of Annex F. 



4. 	The provisions of this Article: 



(a) 	shall not apply in respect of inter-territorial trade within the Area 
in any agricultural products until such time as member Territories 
shall agree upon the regional policy with respect to the production 
and marketing, including the subsidization, of agricultural products; 



(b) 	exclusive of sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph 1 and paragraph 3, shall 
not apply in respect of inter-territorial trade within the Area in any 
manufactured goods until Member Territories have agreed upon a regional 
policy with respect to incentives to industry.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Public Undertakings" article_identifier="17027">1. Member Territories shall ensure the elimination in the practices of public
undertakings, of: 



(a) 	measures the effect of which is to afford protection to domestic 
production which would be inconsistent with this Agreement if achieved 
by means of a duty or charge with equivalent effect or quantitative 
restriction or Government aid; or 



(b) 	trade discrimination on grounds of Territorial origin in so far as it 
frustrates the benefits expected from such removal or absence of duties 
and quantitative restrictions as is required by this Agreement. 


2. In so far as the provisions of Article 19 are relevant to the activities 
of public undertakings, that Article shall apply to them in the same way as it 
applies to other enterprises. 



3. Member Territories shall ensure that new practices of the kind described in 
paragraph 1 of this Article are not introduced. 



4. Where Member Territorics do not have the necessary legal powers to control 
the activities of regional or local government authorities or enterprises under 
their control in those matters, they shall nevertheless endeavour to ensure that 
those authorities or enterprises comply with the provisions of this Article. 



5. The Council shall keep the provisions of this Article under review and may 
decide to amend them. 



6. For the purpose of this Article, "public undertakings" means central, regional, 
or local government authorities, public enterprises and any other organization by 
means of which a Member Territory by law or in practice controls or appreciably
influences imports from, or exports to, any other part of the Area. 

7. The provisions of this Article shall not apply in respect of inter-territorial 
trade within the Area: 



(a) 	in agricultural products until such time as Member Territories shall 
agree upon a regional policy with respect to the production and 
marketing, including the subsidization, of agricultural products; 



(b) 	in manufactured goods until Member Territories have agreed upon a 
regional policy with respect to incentives to industry.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Restrictive Business Practices" article_identifier="17028">1. Member Territories recognize that the following practices are incompatible
with this Agreement in so far as they frustrate the benefits expected from such 
removal or absence of duties and quantitative restrictions as is required by 
this Agreement: 



(a) 	agreements between enterprises, decisions by associations of enterprises 
and concerted practices between enterprises which have as their object 
or result the prevention, restriction or distortion of competition 
within the Area; 



(b) 	actions by which one or more enterprises take unfair advantage of a 
dominant position within the Area or a substantial part of it. 


2. If any practice of the kind described in paragraph 1 of this Article is 
referred to the Council in accordance with Article 26, the Council may, in any 
recommendation in accordance with paragraph 3 or in any decision in accordance 
with paragraph 4 of that Article, make provision for publication of a report on 
the circumstances of the matter. 



3. 	(a) In the light of experience gained, the Council shall consider before 
30 April 1970, and may consider at any time thereafter whether further 
or different provisions are necessary to deal with the effect of 
restrictive business practices or dominant enterprises on the inter-
territorial trade of the Area. 

(b) Such review shall include consideration of the following matters: 



(1) specification of the restrictive business practices or dominant 



(2) 	methods of securing information about restrictive business practices 

enterprises with which the Council should be concerned; 


or dominant enterprises; 



(3) 	procedures for investigations; 



(4) 	whether the right to initiate inquiries should be conferred 
on the Council. 

(c) 	The Council may decide to make the provisions found necessary as a 
result of the review envisaged in sub-paragraphs (a) and (b) of this 


paragraph.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Establishment" article_identifier="17029">1.. Each Member Torritory recognizes that restrictions on the establishment and 
operation of economic enterprises therein by persons belonging to other Member 
Territories should not be applied, through accord to such persons of treatment 
which is loss favourable than that accorded in such matters to persons belonging 
to that Member Territory, in such a way as to frustrate the benefits expected
from such removal or absence of duties and quantitative restrictions as is 
required by this Agreement. 



2. Member Territories shall not apply new restrictions in such a way that they
conflict with the principle set out in paragraph 1 of this Article. 



3. A Member Territory shall notify the Council within such period as the 
Council may decide of particulars of any restrictions which it applies in such 
a way that persons belonging to another Member Territory are accorded in the 

first-mentioned Territory less favourable treatment in respect of the matters 
set out in paragraph 1 of this Article than is accorded to persons belonging


thereto. 



4. The Council shall consider before 30 April 1970, and may consider at any
time thereafter, whether further or different provisions are necessary to give
effect to the principles set out in paragraph 1 of this Article and many decide 
to make the necessary provisions. 



5. Nothing in this Article shall prevent the adoption and enforcement by a 
Member Territory of measures for the control of entry, residence, activity and 
departure of persons where such measures are justified by reasons of public order,
public health or morality, or national security of that Member Territory. 



6. 	For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) 	a person shall be regarded as bolonging to a Member Territory if such 
person: 


(i) 	is a citizen of that Territory; 


(iii) is a company or other legal person constituted in the Member 
Territory in conformity with the law thereof and which that 
Territory regards as belonging to it, provided that such company 
or other legal person has been formed for gainful purposes and 
has its registered office and central administration, and carries 
on substantial activity, within the Area; 


(b) 	"economic enterprises" means any type of economic enterprises for 
production of or commerce in goods which are of Area origin, whether 
conducted by individuals or through agencies, branches or companies 
or other legal persons. 




(ii) 

has a connexion with that Territory of a kind which entitles him to be regarded as belonging to, or, if it be so expressed, as being a native of, the Territory for the purposes of such laws 




thereof relating to immigration as are for the time being in force; or</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Balance-Of-Payments Difficulties" article_identifier="17030">1. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 13 any Member Territory may, 
consistently with any international obligations to which it is subject, introduce 
quantitative restrictions on imports for the purpose of safeguarding its balance 
of payments. 



2. Any Member Territory taking measures in accordance with paragraph 1 of this 
Article shall notify them to the Council, if possible before they come into force. 
The Council shall examine the situation and keep it under review and may at any 
time by majority vote make recommendations designed to moderate any damaging
effect of these restrictions or to assist the Member Territory concerned to 
overcome its difficulties. If the balance-of-payments difficulties persist for 
more than eighteen months and the measures applied seriously disturb the operation
of the Association, the Council shall examine the situation and may, taking into 
account the interests of all Member Territories, by majority decision devise 
special procedures to attenuate or compensate for the effect of such measures. 



3. A Member Territory which has talken measures in accordance with paragraph 1 
of this Article shall have regard to its obligation to resume the full application
of Article 13 and shall, as soon as its balance-of-payments situation improves,
make proposals to the Council on the way in which this should be done. The Council, 
if it is not satisfied that these proposals are adequate, may recommend to the 
Member Territories alternative arrangements to the same end. Decisions of the 
Council pursuant to this paragraph shall be made by majority vote.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Difficulties.in Particular. Sectors" article_identifier="17031">1. 	If, in a Member Territory: 



(a) 	an appreciable rise in unemployment in a particular sector of industry 
or region is caused by a substantial decrease in internal demand for 
a domestic product, and 



(b) 	this decrease in demand is due to an increase in imports consigned from 
other Member Territories as a result of the progressive reduction or 
the elimination of duties, charges and quantitative restrictions in 
accordance with Articles 4, 7 and 13, that Member Territory may, 
notwithstanding any other provisions of this Agreement: 



(i) 	limit those imports by means of quantitative restrictions to a 
rate not less than the rate of such imports during any period of. 
twelve months which ended within twelve months of the date on 
which the restrictions come into force; the restrictions shall 
not be continued for a period longer than eighteen months, unless 
the Council, by majority decision, authorizes their continuance 
for such further period and on such conditions as the. Council 
considers appropriate; and 



(ii) take such measures, either instead of or in addition to restriction 
of imports in accordance with sub-paragraph (i) of this paragraph, 
as the Council may, by majority decision, authorize. 


2. In applying measures in accordance with paragraph 1 of this Article, a 
Member Territory shall give like treatment to imports consigned from all Member 
Territories. 



3. A Member Territory applying restrictions in accordance with sub-paragraph (i)
of paragraph 1 of this Article shall notify them to the Council, if possible 
before they come into force. 

The 	Council may at any time consider those restrictions 


and may, by majority vote, make recommendations designed to moderate any damaging
effect of those restrictions or to assist the Member State concerned to overcome 
its difficulties. 



4. 	This Article shall have effect until 30 April 1973. 



5. Before 1 May 1973, if the Council considers that some provision similar to 
those in paragraphs 1 to 3 of this Article will be required thereafter, it 
may decide that such provisions shall have effect for any period after that date.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Approximation Of Incentive Legislation" article_identifier="17032">1. A tax of any kind in a Member Territory shall not, by the introduction or 
extension of incontive provisions at any time after this Agreement takes effect, 
be rendered liable to mitigation to any extent to which no tax of that kind 


elsewhere in the Area (if any) is rendered, by incentive provisions previously 
introduced or extended, liable to mitigation: 


Provided that, in resolving any question whether any breach by a Member 
Territory of its obligations for the purposes of this Article is to be apprehended or has resulted from the introduction or extension of any incentive 
provisions, the Council shall take into account the overall level and structure 
of taxt-ion and the general economic circumstances in that Member Territory as 
compared with other Member Territories. 



2. The Council may, by majority decision, authorize any Member Territory to 
withhold, from imports of any products in relation to the manufacture of which it 
has been established to the satisfaction of a majority of the Council that any 
such broach by another Member Territory has resulted as aforesaid, treatment the 
benefit whereof is applicable in conformity with any provisions of this Agreemennt 
to such imports. 



3. A MemberTorritory which is considering the introduction or alteration of any 
incentive provisions shall, as far as may be practicable, notify the Council not 
less than thirty days before such introduction or alteration comes into effect, 
and shall consider any representations with respect thereto by other Member 
Territories, any of which may refer the matter to the Council under Article 26 
if a breach of this Article is apprehended. Information received under this 
paragraph shall not be disclosed to any person outside the service of the 
Association or the Governments of Member Territories. 



4. The Council may on its own initiative recommend to Member Territories 
proposals for the approximation of incentive provisions within the Area. Such 

proposals may include schemes for the increase or reduction of concessions within 
the Area consistently with the provisions of the foregoing Articles of this Agreement, 
and may be implemented notwithstanding ;anything provided in paragraph 1 of this 
Article. The Council may take any appropriate measure provided for in this 
Agreement in furtherance of the objectives of this Article. 


5. The Council may from time to time review the provisions of this Article and 
may decide to amend those provisions. 




6. For the purposes of this Aticle: 


"incentive provisions" means any legislation or practice providing for 


the granting of concessions for the purpose of encouraging the establishment 
or development of manufacturing industry; 


"concessions" means any tax exemptions or remissions or refunds of tax; 


"tax" includes any impost, duty or due.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Econnomic And Financial Policies" article_identifier="17033">Member Torritories recognize that the economic and financial policies of 
each of them affect the economies of other Member Torritories, and intend to 
pursue those policies in a manner which serves to promote the objectives of the 
Association. They shall periodically exchange viaws on all aspects of those 
policies. The Council may make recommendations to Member Torritorios on matters 
relating to these policies to the extent necessary to ensure the attainment of 
the objectives of tho smooth operation of the Association.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Invisibles" article_identifier="17034">The Council shall as soon as practicable, having due regard to international 
obligations, decide the treatment to be given to invisible transactions and 
transfer amongst Member Torritories with a view to promoting the objectives of 
this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="General Consultations And Coplaints Procedure" article_identifier="17035">1. If any Member Territory considers that any benefit conferred upon it by this 
Agreement or anly objective of the Association is boing or may be frustrated and 
if no satisfactory settlement is renched between the Member Territrios concerned, 


any of those Member Torritoriesmay refer the matter to the Council. 


2. The Council shall promptly, by majority voto make arrangements for examining
the matter. Such arrangements may includea reference to an examining committee 
constituted in accordance with Articla 27. Before taking action under pararaph 3 
of this Article, the Council shall so refer the matter at the request of any


Member Torritory concerned. member Territories shall furnish all inforimation. 


which they can, make available.and shall lend their assistance to establish the 


facts. 



3. When considering the matter, the Council shall have regard to whether it 
has been established that an obligation under this Agreement has not been 
fulfilled and whether and to what extent any benefit comferred by this Agreement 
or any objective of the Asscointion is being or may be frustrated. In the light
of this consideration and of the report of any examining committee which may 
have been appointed, the Council may, by majority vote, make to any Member 
Territory such rocomandations as it considers appropriate. 



4. If a Member Torritory does not or is unable to comply with a recommendation 
made in accordance with paragraph 3 of this Article and the Council finds, by 
majority veto, that an obligation uner this Agreement has not bee fulfilled, 
the Council may by majority decision, authorize any member Territory to suspend 
to the member Toritory which has not complie with the recommendations the application of such obligations under this Agreement as the Council considers 
appropriate. 



5. Any Member Territory may, at any time while the matter is under consideration, 
request the Council to authorize as a matter of urgoncy, interim measures to 
safeguard its position. If it is found by majority vote of the Council that the 
circumstances are sufficiently serious to justify interim action, and without 
prejudice to any action which it may subsequently take in accordance with the 
preceding paragraphs of this Article, the Council may, by majority decision, 
authorize aMember Territory to suspend its obligations under this Agreement to 
such an extent and for such a period as the Council considers appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Examining Committees" article_identifier="17036">The examining Committees referred to in Article 26 shall consist of persons 
selected for their competence and intogrity who, in the performance of their 
duties, shall neither sock nor receive instructions from any Territory or from 
any authority or orgenization other than the Association. They shall be 
appointed, on such terms and conditions as may be decided, by majority vote of 
the Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="The Council" article_identifier="17037">1. 	It shall be the responsibility of the Council: 



(a) 	to excrcise such powers and functions as are conferred upon it by 
this Agreement 



(b) 	to supervise the application of this A.greement and keep its operation 
under review; 

(c) 	to consider whether further action should be taken by Member 
Territories in order to promote the attainment of the objectives 
of the Association and to facilitate the establishment of closer 
links with other countries, unions of countries or international 
organizations. 



2. Each Member Territory shall be represented in the Council and shall have 
one vote. 



3. The Commonwealth Caribbean Regional Secretariat shall be the principal 
administrative organ of the Association and the Council may entrust it, and may 
set up other organs, committees and bodies and entrust them, with such functions 
as the Council considers necessary to assist it in accomplishing its tasks. 
Decisions of the Council pursuant to this paragraph shall be made by majority 
vote. 



4. In exercising its responsibility under paragraph 1 of this Article, the 
Council may take decisions which shall be binding on all Member Territories and 
may make recommendations to Member Territories. 



5. Decisions and recommendations of the Council shall be made by unanimous 
vote, except in so far as this Agreement provides otherwise. Decisions or 
recommendations shall be regarded as unanimous unless any Member Territory casts 
a negative vote. A decision or recommendation of the Council pursuant to any 
such provision as aforesaid requires the affirmative votes of not less than 
two thirds of all Member Territories, and reference in any such provision to a 
majority shall, in relation to the Council be construed accordingly. 



6. The Council may, by its decision to confer any authority under this 
Agreement, impose conditions to which such authority shall be subject.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Administrative Arrangeents Of The Association" article_identifier="17038">1. 	The Council shall take decision for the following purposes: 



(a) 	to lay down the Rules of Procedure of the Council and of any bodies of 
the Association, which may include provision that procedural questions 
may be decided by majority vote; 



(b) 	to make arrangements for the Secretariat services required by the 
Association; 



(c) 	to establish the financial arrangements necessary for the administrative 
expenses of the Association, and the procedure for establishing an 
annual budget. 

2. The expenses of the Association shall be shared between Member Territories 


in conformity with the appropriate basis of Territorial contributions to the 
annual budget of the Commonwealth Caribbean Regional Secretariat, approved at 
the Conference of Ministers of Trade held in Guyana on 21 and 22 February 1968, 


or in such other manner as the Council may decide.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Relations With International Organizations" article_identifier="17039">The Council acting in behalf of the Association, shall seek to procure the 
establishment of such relationships with other international organizations as 
may facilitate the attainment of the objectives of the Association.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Ratifications Required For Effectiveness" article_identifier="17040">1. This Agreement shall be subject to ratification by the Legislatures of all 
the Signatory Territories. 



2. Instruments signifying such ratification shall be deposited with the 

Government of Antigua, which shall notify the other Signatory Territories, and, 


subject to the next following paragraph, this Agreement shall take effect as 


soon as the number of Signatory Territories has been ascertained consistently 


with paragraphs 4 and 5 of this Article and all such instruments have been so 


deposited. 


3. If prior to the ratification of this Agreement by any Signatory Territory 


that Territory indicates by notice to the Government of Antigua that difficulties 
have arisen in relation to carrying any provision of this Agreement into effect, 
the Agreement shall not take effect with respect to that Territory except in 
accordance with the terms of a supplementary agreement between all the Signatory 
Territories providing for the resolution of such difficulties. 



4. Any Commonwealth Caribbean Country by whose Government an instrument 
signifying its endorsement of the Resolution set out in Annex A has been deposited 
with the Government of Antigua shall be deemed for the purposes of this Agreement 
to be a Signatory Territory as from the date of such deposits which shall be 
notified to the other Signatory Territories by the Government of Antigua. 



5. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in this Agreement, the preceding 

paragraph shall not apply on or after 1 May 1968, to a Commonwealth Caribbean 


Country unless, before that date, there has been deposited an instrument signifying 


ratification by its Legislature of this agreement, pursuant to the deposit by 


its Government of an instrument of endorsement, in accordance with this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Joining Asssociation" article_identifier="17041">1. Any Territory, though it be not a signatory hereto, may participate in this 
Agreement, subject to prior approval of the Council of the Territory's participation in this Agreement on terms and conditions decided by the Council. The 
instrument duly signifying the agreement of the Government of the Territory to 
its participation in this Agreement on the terms and conditions decided as aforesaid shall be deposited with the Government of Antigua which shall notify all 
other Member Territories. This Agreement shall have effect in relation to the 
participating Territery as, and from the time, indicated in the Council's decision. 



2. The Council may pursuant to any decision thereof in that behalf seek to 
procure the creation of an association consisting of Member Territories and any
other Territory, union of Territories, or international organization, and 
embodying such reciprocal rights and obligations, common actions and special 
procedures as may be appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Withdrawal" article_identifier="17042">Any Member Territory may withdraw from participation in this Agreement
provided that the Government thereof gives twelve months' notice in writing to 
the Government of Antigua which shall notify the other Member Territories.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Amendment" article_identifier="17043">1. Except where provision for modification is made elsewhere in this Agreement,
including the Annexes to it, an amendment to the provisions of this Agreement 
shall be submitted to the Governments of Member Territories for acceptance if it 
is approved by decision of the Council, and it shall have effect provided it is 
accepted by all such Governments. Instruments of acceptance shall be deposited
with the Government of Antigua which shall notify the other Member Territories.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Acquisition Of Sovereign Status" article_identifier="17044">1. If a Member Territory, upon becoming a sovereign State recognized internationally, intimates its willingness to continue to participate in this 
Agreement, then, notwithstanding its having become such a State, this Agreement
shall continue to have effect in relation to it. 



2. For the purposes of paragraph 1 of this Article, any intimation thereunder 
shall be given by notice to the Government of Antigua, which shall notify all 
other Member Territories.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Annexes" article_identifier="17045">The annexes tc this Agreement are an integral pert of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Legal Cabacity, Privilezes And Immunities" article_identifier="17046">1. The legal capacity, privileges and immunities to be recognized and granted 
by the Member Territories in connexion with the Association shall be laid down 
in a Protocol to this Agreement. 



2. The Council, acting on behalf of the Association, may conclude with the 
Government of the Territory in which the headquarters will be situated an 
agreement relating to the legal capacity and the privileges and immunities to be 
recognized and granted in connoxion with the Association.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Protection Of Guyanese Petroleum Products" article_identifier="17047">1. Notwithstanding anything in this Agreement, any quantitative restriction 
within the meaning of Article 13 may, during any period for which the Government 
of Guyana is a party to any protective agreement in that behalf relating to a 
petroleum product produced in Guyana, be applied on imports into Guyana of that 
petroleum product from any other part of the Area: 


Provided that no such restriction shall be so applied on imports of any 
petroleum product, other than Bund or C, asphalt or road oil, during any year 
except with a view to preventing the importation of that petroleum product into 


Guyana to any extent in excess of: 



(a) 	one third of such amount of that petroleum product as is reasonably 
considered by the Government of Guyana to be marketable in Guyana 
during such year; or 



(b) 	the difference between such amount of that petroleum product as is 
reasonably considered by the Government of Guyana to be marketable 
in Guyana during such year and any lesser amount of that petroleum 
product which is reasonably considered by the said Government to be 
producible in Guyana during such year, 

whichever is more. 




2. During any period first hereinbefore in this Article referred to in 
connexion with a petroleum product produced in Guyana, customs duties shall, at 
rates not lower than those in force when this Agreement takes effect, be 
applicable to any permitted imports into Guyan. of that petroleum product from 
outside the Area. 



3. 	Not later than: 



(a) 	the commencement, during any year, of any period mentioned in 
paragraph 2 of this Airticle; 



(b) 	the commencement, during any such period, of any year, 

Guyana shall notify to the councill the amounts mentioned in paragraph (b) of the 
proviso to paragraph 1 of this Article in relation to that year and shall, at 
the request of any Member Territory, inform the Council in strictest confidence 
of the reasons of the Government of Guyana for arriving at such amounts. 



4. In this Article, "that petroleum product" includes any like or substitutable 
petroleum product. 



5. This Article shall not have effect for longer than 15 years from the 
commencement of a period mentioned in paragraph 2 of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Promotion Of Industrial Development In Less-Developed Territcries" article_identifier="17048">Upon any appliationmade in that behalf by the less-developed Territories 
as defined in Annex B, the council may, if necessary as a temporary measure in 
order to promote theof any ofthese Territories,


developmentanindustry in 
authlorize by majority decision such Territerics to suspend Area tariff treatment 
of any description of impots aligible thereforon grounds of production in the 
other Member Territcris, any of whom mayduring the period for which such 
authorization is in ferce, suspondArea tariff treatment of the like description 


of imports eligible thereforongroundsofproduction in the les-developed


Territories.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
