<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Czech Republic - Slovak Republic Customs Union</name>
    <type>Customs Union</type>
    <wto_rta_id>229</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>203</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1992-10-29</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1993-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1993-04-30</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>2004-05-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">SVK</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=91700118&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="2088">
      <article article_identifier="17552">AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF THE CZECH REPUBLIC 
AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE SLOVAK REPUBLIC ON MUTUAL 
RELATIONS AND PRINCIPLES OF COOPERATION IN AGRICULTURE, 
FOOD PROCESSING, FORESTRY AND WATER MANAGEMENT WITHIN 
THE FRAMEWORK OF THE CUSTOMS UNION 


The Government of the Czech Republic and the Government of the Slovak 
Republic (hereinafter referred to as "the Contracting Parties"), 
represented by the Ministry of Agriculture of the Czech Republic and the 
Ministry of Agriculture of the Slovak Republic resolved 


to implement the objectives and principles of the Agreement 
establishing the Customs Union between the Czech Republic and the Slovak 
Republic signed on 29 October 1992 (hereinafter referred to as "the 
Agreement on the Customs Union") as well as further agreements concluded 
between the Contracting Parties, 


to develop their relations based on the principle of reciprocity in 
the interest of harmonious development and prosperity of agriculture, food 
processing, forestry and water management of the Contracting Parties 


have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART ONE" name="Economic Policy In Agriculture" chapter_identifier="2089">
      <article number="ARTICLE I" article_identifier="17553">1. The Contracting Parties shall pursue trade policy towards third 
countries in accordance with the provisions of the Agreement on the Customs 
Union. 



2. The Contracting Parties undertake that in pursuing conforming 
commercial policy in regard to third countries within the framework of the 
Agreement on the Customs Union they shall respect and apply the following 
principles: 


-uniform import and export licensing system, 
-uniform system of non-tariff protection. 



3. Allocation of quotas under the European Agreement and under the 
bilateral agreements with the EFTA States forms an annex to this Agreement. 



4. The Contracting Parties shall negotiate common procedures in 
re-negotiating treaties with the Member States of the Commonwealth of 
Independent States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE II" article_identifier="17554">1. Co-ordination of agricultural policies of the Contracting Parties 
according to Article I covers export subsidies, tax policy, prices, 
domestic support policy, activities of the Market Regulation Funds and 
other instruments for organization of markets. 



2. Co-ordination of agricultural policies includes the mutual exchange of 
information, consultations and agreed procedures in the matters of common 
interest. The agreed procedures may be of joint and uniform nature. 



3. The Contracting Parties shall inform each other in time on prepared
regulatory market interventions so that both Contracting Parties could 
consider the matter thoroughly in order to find a solution acceptable to 
both Contracting Parties. 



4. The instruments of economic policy applied by the Contracting Parties 
within the framework of agreed procedures may not prevent the 
accomplishment of the objectives of the Agreement on the Customs Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE III" article_identifier="17555">1. The Contracting Parties shall present a uniform draft offer concerning
the acceptance of the Uruguay Round commitments after their mutual 
consultations. 



2. The Contracting Parties shall co-operate also in transfer of rights
and obligations arising from the international treaties concluded by the 
Czech and Slovak Federal Republic and commitments resulting from its 
membership in the international organizations. The Contracting Parties 
undertake to fulfil jointly the obligations which cannot be separated or 
the division of which is not reasonable. 



3. The Contracting Parties shall choose the procedures which facilitate 
the speedy and smooth re-negotiation of the European Agreement with the 
European Community and the bilateral agricultural agreements with the EFTA 
States. 


4. The Contracting Parties shall retain unchanged Protocol A of the 
Agreement between the EFTA States and the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic 
concerning processed agricultural products. When implementing this 
Agreement they shall inform each other on possible changes in a timetable 
for reduction of a non-agricultural component in the duties and they shall 
present a uniform proposal to the individual EFTA States. 



5. The Contracting Parties shall conclude negotiations on the bilateral 
agreements with other CEFTA countries.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART TWO" name="Common Provisions" chapter_identifier="2090">
      <article number="ARTICLE IV" article_identifier="17556">1. The Contracting Parties undertake to inform each other on principal 
issues relating to the agricultural and foodstuffs policy as well as 
forestry and water management policies. 



2. The Contracting Parties undertake to carry out consultations on 
changes in their laws and other legal regulations to ensure that these 
shall not be contrary to the objectives of this Agreement and shall aim at 
harmonizing their legal orders with the legislation of the European 
Community. 



3. For the purpose of implementing the tasks arising from this Agreement,
the Contracting Parties shall establish, when necessary, ad hoc working 
groups, and a permanent working body with the Permanent Secretariat of the 
Council of the Customs Union (Committee on Co-ordination of Economic 
Policy in Agriculture). 



4. In the case of disputes and unilateral actions taken by any of the 
Contracting Parties under Articles 36 and 37 of the Agreement on the 
Customs Union respectively, the relevant proposals and measures are 
considered within the Committee on Co-ordination of Economic Policy in 
Agriculture prior to their submission to the Council of the Customs Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE V" article_identifier="17557">1. Mutual relations and co-operation of the Contracting Parties in the 
area of sanitary and phytosanitary care shall be regulated by a special 
agreement concluded by the Contracting Parties. Until its conclusion, 
procedures shall be laid down in the agreement between the State Veterinary
Offices of the Contracting Parties and the central control and testing 
institutes of agriculture. Similarly, an agreement shall be concluded 
between the respective bodies of the Contracting Parties responsible for 
supervision and State testing of foodstuffs. 



2. Unless the special agreement is concluded, the Contracting Parties 
shall take joint measures concerning the management and exploitation of 

common or border rivers and the flood control. They shall also inform each 
other on the measures taken under exceptional circumstances in the forests 
on the common border. 



3. The Contracting Parties consider useful to co-operate in the area of 
cultivation and improvement of plants and animals, in testing, in research 
and in training. Details shall be laid down in special agreements. 



4. Co-ordination of activities carried out by the Market Regulation Funds 
of the Contracting Parties shall be specified in a separate agreement. 



5. The Land Funds of the Contracting Parties shall conclude an agreement 
aiming at the reciprocal facilitation of the settlement of some land 
property rights of the citizens of the Contracting Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART THREE" name="Temporary And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="2091">
      <article number="ARTICLE VI" article_identifier="17558">1. Through their Ministries of Agriculture, the Contracting Parties shall 
co-operate in preparing and implementing the measures connected with the 
dissolution of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic. These Ministries 
shall co-operate with the respective bodies of the Czech and Slovak Federal 
Republic and of the Contracting Parties in transferring the competences and 
activities of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic to the new States in 
the area of registration, licensing and recognition of new varieties of 
plants and breeds, in legislation and standardization, including the Food 
Code, in activities carried out by the Chief Plant Health Officers and 
Chief Veterinary Officers, in foreign trade, foreign relations, foreign aid 
and in research. 



2. Winding up of the activities of the Federal Market Regulation Fund, 
shall be ensured by the Contracting Parties through their representatives 
in the Council of this Fund on the basis of the respective legal measure 
passed by the Federal Assembly of the Czech and Slovak Federal Republic. 



3. Within the scope of their activities, the Ministries of Agriculture of 
the Contracting Parties shall co-operate with the relevant authorities in 
settling the property of the Federal Office for Material Reserves. 



4. The Contracting Parties shall revise jointly the project drafted 
in 1992 under the PHARE Programme in the area of agriculture for the 
year 1993. After consultations with the respective bodies of the European 
Community, they shall adopt such procedures which shall facilitate the 
smooth completion of final versions of projects in order to draw without 
delay on the funds provided by the European Community for such projects. 

5. Definition of property and other issues related to the implementation 
of paragraphs 1 and 4 of this Article shall be specified in special 
protocols. The draft protocols shall be prepared in co-operation with the 
respective bodies and organizations of the Czech and Slovak Federal 
Republic and of the Contracting Parties in order to ensure their entry into 
force on 1 January 1993.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE VII" article_identifier="17559">1. The Agreement is concluded for an indefinite period and shall enter 
into force on 1 January 1993. 



2. The validity of the Agreement expires on the same date as that of the 
Agreement on the Customs Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE VIII" article_identifier="17560">Done at Bratislava on 23 November 1992 in duplicate in the Czech and 
Slovak languages both of them being equally authentic.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="2092">
      <article article_identifier="17561">For the Government For the Government 
of the Czech Republic of the Slovak Republic 


Ivan Kocárnik m.p. Vladimir Meciar m.p. 
Minister of Finance Prime Minister</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
