<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU - Eastern and Southern Africa States Interim EPA</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>469</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>332</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2009-08-29</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2012-05-14</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2012-02-09</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2022-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">MDG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SWE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="30">SYC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="31">ZWE</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MDG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">MUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="30">SWE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="31">SYC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="32">ZWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Europe; Africa</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398352746247&amp;uri=CELEX:22012A0424(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/ES/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22012A0424(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/?uri=uriserv:OJ.L_.2012.111.01.0001.01.FRA</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398352746247&amp;uri=CELEX:22012A0424(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1398352746247&amp;uri=CELEX:22012A0424(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/?uri=uriserv:OJ.L_.2012.111.01.0001.01.FRA</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="2924">
      <article article_identifier="24377">Interim Agreement

  establishing a framework for an Economic Partnership Agreement between
  the Eastern and Southern Africa States, on the one part, and the
  European Community and its Member States, on the other part

  UNION OF COMOROS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF MADAGASCAR,

  THE REPUBLIC OF MAURITIUS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF SEYCHELLES,

  THE REPUBLIC OF ZAMBIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF ZIMBABWE,

  hereinafter referred to as the "ESA States",

  on the one part, and

  THE KINGDOM OF BELGIUM,

  THE REPUBLIC OF BULGARIA,

  THE CZECH REPUBLIC,

  THE KINGDOM OF DENMARK,

  THE FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY,

  THE REPUBLIC OF ESTONIA,

  IRELAND,

  THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC,

  THE KINGDOM OF SPAIN,

  THE FRENCH REPUBLIC,

  THE ITALIAN REPUBLIC,

  THE REPUBLIC OF CYPRUS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF LATVIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF LITHUANIA,

  THE GRAND DUCHY OF LUXEMBOURG,

  THE REPUBLIC OF HUNGARY,

  MALTA,

  THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF POLAND,

  THE PORTUGUESE REPUBLIC,

  ROMANIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA,

  THE SLOVAK REPUBLIC,

  THE REPUBLIC OF FINLAND,

  THE KINGDOM OF SWEDEN,

  THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND,

  and

  THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY,

  hereinafter referred to as "the EC Party",

  on the other part,

  together hereinafter referred to as "the Parties",

  PREAMBLE

  WE the African, Caribbean and Pacific (ACP) States of the Eastern and
  Southern African (ESA) region, constituted as the ESA Group and its
  individual member States, on the one hand, and the European Community
  (EC) and its Member States, on the other;

  HAVING REGARD to the Partnership Agreement between the Members of the
  African, Caribbean and Pacific Group of States of the one part, and
  the EC and its Member States of the other part signed on 23 June 2000
  (hereinafter referred to as the "Cotonou Agreement"), the
  Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa (COMESA) Treaty signed
  on 5 November 1993, the Southern Africa Development Community (SADC)
  Treaty signed on 17 August 1992 and its Protocol on Trade, the East
  African Community (EAC) Treaty signed on 30 November 1999, and the
  African Union Constitutive Act signed and adopted on 11 July 2002;

  HAVING REGARD to the Treaty Establishing the European Community;

  HAVING ALSO REGARD to the decision of the eighth Summit of the COMESA
  Authority of Heads of State and Government held in Khartoum, Sudan on
  17 March 2003 on the establishment of the ESA configuration for the
  purpose of negotiation of an Economic Partnership Agreement (EPA) with
  the European Union (EU);

  CONSIDERING that the ESA States and the EC and its Member States have
  agreed that their trade and economic cooperation shall aim at
  fostering the smooth and gradual integration of the ESA States into
  the world economy with due regard to their political choices, levels
  of development and development priorities, thereby promoting their
  sustainable development and contributing to poverty eradication in the
  ESA States;

  REAFFIRMING their commitment to promote and expedite the economic,
  cultural and social development of the ESA States with a view to
  contributing to peace and security and to promoting a stable and
  democratic political environment conducive for sustainable national
  and regional development;

  REAFFIRMING also that the EPA shall be consistent with the objectives
  and principles of the Cotonou Agreement and, in particular, with the
  provisions of Part III, Title II thereof;

  REAFFIRMING that the EPA shall serve as an instrument for development
  and shall promote sustained growth, increase the production and
  supply-side capacity of ESA States, foster structural transformation
  of ESA economies and their diversification and competitiveness and
  lead to the development of trade, the attraction of investment and
  technology and the creation of employment in ESA States;

  RECALLING the commitments of the international community on the
  achievements of the Millennium Development Goals as contained in the
  UN Declaration of September 2000;

  REAFFIRMING that advancing the development agenda requires genuine
  international cooperation and the full implementation of agreed
  commitments made at the Conferences of Rio, Beijing, Copenhagen, Cairo
  and Monterrey, as well as in the Programmes of Action in favour of
  Least Developed Countries (LDCs), Landlocked Developing Countries
  (LLDCs) and Small Island Developing States (SIDS) respectively;

  BEARING in mind the rights and obligations of the Members of the World
  Trade Organisation (WTO), the importance they attach to the principles
  and rules governing international trade and the need for a
  transparent, predictable, open and fair multilateral trading system;

  REITERATING the need to ensure that particular emphasis be placed on
  regional integration and the provision of special and differential
  treatment to all ESA States, maintain special treatment for ESA LDCs,
  and take due account of the vulnerability of small economies,
  landlocked, island, coastal, drought prone and ESA States emerging
  from conflict;

  COGNISANT that substantial investments are required to uplift the
  standards of living of ESA States;

  RECALLING the commitments of the Parties within the framework of the
  WTO,

  HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER I" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="2925">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Scope Of The Interim Agreement" article_identifier="24378">This Interim Agreement establishes a framework for an Economic
  Partnership Agreement (EPA).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Epa Objectives" article_identifier="24379">The objectives of the Economic Partnership Agreement are:

  (a) contributing to the reduction and eventual eradication of poverty
  through the establishment of a strengthened and strategic trade and
  development partnership consistent with the objective of sustainable
  development, the Millennium Development Goals and the Cotonou
  Agreement;

  (b) promoting regional integration, economic cooperation and good
  governance in the ESA region;

  (c) promoting the gradual integration of the ESA region into the world
  economy, in conformity with its political choices and development
  priorities;

  (d) fostering the structural adjustment of the ESA economies and
  diversification including value addition;

  (e) improving the ESA region’s capacity in trade policy and trade
  related issues;

  (f) establishing and implementing an effective, predictable and
  transparent regional regulatory framework for trade and investment in
  the ESA region, thus supporting the conditions for increasing
  investment and private sector initiative and enhancing supply
  capacity, competitiveness and economic growth; and

  (g) strengthening the existing relations between the Parties on the
  basis of solidarity and mutual interest. To this end, consistent with
  WTO obligations, the Agreement shall enhance commercial and economic
  relations, support a new trading dynamic between the Parties by means
  of the progressive, asymmetrical liberalisation of trade between them
  and reinforce, broaden and deepen cooperation in all areas relevant to
  trade and investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Specific Objectives Of This Agreement" article_identifier="24380">1. Consistent with Articles 34 and 35 of the Cotonou Agreement, the
  objectives of this Agreement are:

  (a) to establish an agreement consistent with Article XXIV of General
  Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 (GATT 1994);

  (b) to establish the framework, scope and principles for further
  negotiations on trade in goods including rules of origin, trade
  defence instruments, customs cooperation and trade facilitation,
  sanitary and phytosanitary measures, technical barriers to trade, and
  agriculture, on the basis of the proposals already submitted; and

  (c) to establish a framework for and scope of potential negotiation in
  relation to other issues including trade in services, trade related
  issues as identified in the Cotonou Agreement and any other areas of
  interest to both Parties.

  2. The Parties undertake to complete negotiations with a view to
  concluding a comprehensive EPA, no later than 31 December 2008,
  including on subject matters listed in points (b) and (c) of paragraph
  1 according to the Agreed Joint Road Map adopted by the Parties on 7
  February 2004.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Principles" article_identifier="24381">The principles of this Agreement on the basis of which further
  negotiations between the Parties shall be held with a view to reaching
  a comprehensive EPA are the following:

  (a) building on the acquis of the Cotonou Agreement;

  (b) strengthening regional integration in the ESA region;

  (c) asymmetry in the liberalisation of trade and in the application of
  trade related measures and trade defence instruments;

  (d) special and differential treatment for the ESA LDCs and taking
  into account the vulnerability of small landlocked and island
  countries, including in the level and pace of trade liberalisation;

  (e) variable geometry to allow an ESA State in a position to do so to
  undertake liberalisation within an earlier timeframe and schedule;

  (f) inclusiveness of application of development cooperation provisions
  such that ESA LDCs not in a position to conclude a tariff offer should
  be able to benefit from all aspects of this Agreement in particular
  economic and development cooperation in this Interim Agreement;

  (g) allowing ESA LDCs that have not yet submitted tariff reduction
  offers to do so after signature of this Interim Agreement on the same
  or flexible conditions and to benefit fully from its provisions;

  (h) allowing ESA States to maintain regional preferences among
  themselves and with other African countries and regions without the
  obligation to extend them to the EC.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER II" name="Trade Regime For Goods" chapter_identifier="2926">
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Objectives" article_identifier="24382">The objectives of cooperation in the area of trade are:

  (a) the provision of full duty free and quota free market access
  conditions for goods originating in the ESA States into the market of
  the EC Party on a secure, long term and predictable basis;

  (b) the promotion of trade between the Parties and the acceleration of
  export led growth to enable the integration of ESA countries into the
  global economy;

  (c) the progressive and gradual liberalisation of the goods market in
  ESA in accordance with the modalities established in this Agreement;
  and

  (d) the preservation and improvement of market access conditions to
  ensure that all ESA States are better and not worse off.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Scope Of Application" article_identifier="24383">1. Only the Signatory ESA States listed in Annex II shall take
  commitments under this Chapter.

  2. The EC Party’s commitments under this Chapter shall only be
  applicable to goods originating in the Signatory ESA States listed in
  Annex II.

  3. For the purposes of this Chapter and for decisions adopted under
  this Chapter any reference to the Signatory ESA States or to goods
  originating in the Signatory ESA States shall extend only to the
  Signatory ESA States listed in Annex II.

  4. When a Signatory ESA State not listed in Annex II wants to join
  Chapter II, it shall notify its intention to the EPA Committee. The
  EPA Committee is competent to amend Annex II.

  5. The EPA Committee may decide on any transitional measures or
  amendments that might be necessary in order to facilitate the addition
  of such Signatory ESA States to Annex II.

  Free movement of goods</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Customs Duty" article_identifier="24384">For the purposes of elimination of customs duties on imports, a
  customs duty shall include any duty or charge of any kind imposed on
  or in connection with the importation of goods, including any form of
  surtax or surcharge in connection with such importation, but does not
  include:

  (a) charges equivalent to internal taxes levied on both imported and
  locally produced goods consistent with the provisions of Article 18;

  (b) anti-dumping or countervailing duties applied in accordance with
  the provisions of Article 19, and safeguard measures applied in
  accordance with Article 21; and

  (c) fees or other charges levied in accordance with the provisions of
  Article 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="24385">The classification of goods in trade covered by this Agreement shall
  be that set out in each Party’s respective tariff nomenclature in
  conformity with the Harmonised Commodity Description and Coding System
  (HS). The Signatory ESA States will use the COMESA nomenclature.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Basic Duty" article_identifier="24386">For each product, the basic customs duty to which the successive
  reductions are to be applied shall be that specified in each Party’s
  Tariff Schedules.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Fees And Other Charges" article_identifier="24387">Fees and other charges referred to in Article 7(c), shall be limited
  in amount to the approximate cost of services rendered and shall not
  represent an indirect protection for domestic products or a taxation
  of imports for fiscal purposes. They shall be based on specific rates.
  Trade related fees and charges shall not be imposed for consular
  services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The Esa States" article_identifier="24388">Products originating in the ESA States shall be imported into the EC
  Party free of customs duties under the conditions defined in Annex I.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The Ec Party" article_identifier="24389">1. Customs duties on imports of products originating in the EC Party
  shall be reduced or eliminated in accordance with the schedules of
  tariff liberalisation in Annex II, which shall contain the schedules
  of each Signatory ESA State or group of Signatory ESA States.

  2. The Parties may review the schedules of tariff liberalisation in
  Annex II with a view to harmonising them taking into account regional
  integration processes.

  3. Any new schedule of tariff liberalisation for customs duties on
  imports of products originating in the EC Party submitted after the
  ratification process of this Agreement has commenced may be annexed to
  this Agreement in Annex II by decision of the EPA Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="24390">For the purposes of this Chapter, "originating" means
  qualifying under the rules of origin set out in Protocol 1 to this
  Agreement. For the purposes of the comprehensive EPA, and during the
  period between the entry into force of this agreement and the entry
  into force of the comprehensive EPA, the Parties shall review the
  provisions of this Protocol with a view to their further
  simplification. In such review the Parties shall take into account the
  development needs of the ESA States and development of technologies,
  production processes and all other factors, including on-going reforms
  of rules of origin, which may require modifications to the provisions
  of this Protocol. Any such modifications shall be effected by a
  decision of the EPA Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Standstill" article_identifier="24391">Subject to Article 12, the Parties agree not to increase their applied
  customs duties on products imported from the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Duties, Taxes On Exports" article_identifier="24392">1. Except as otherwise provided in Annex III and for the duration of
  this Agreement, the Parties shall not institute any new duties or
  taxes on or in connection with the exportation of goods to the other
  Party in excess of those imposed on like products destined for
  internal sale.

  2. The EPA Committee may examine a request from any Signatory ESA
  State for a review of the goods listed in Annex III.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="More Favourable Treatment Resulting From Free Trade Agreements" article_identifier="24393">1. With respect to the subject matter covered by this Chapter, the EC
  Party shall accord to the Signatory ESA States any more favourable
  treatment applicable as a result of the EC Party becoming party to a
  free trade agreement with third parties after the signature of this
  Agreement.

  2. With respect to the subject matter covered by this Chapter, the
  Signatory ESA States shall accord to the EC Party any more favourable
  treatment applicable as a result of the Signatory ESA States becoming
  party to a free trade agreement with any major trading economy after
  the signature of this Agreement.

  3. The provisions of this Chapter shall not be so construed as to
  oblige the Parties to extend reciprocally any preferential treatment
  applicable as a result of one of them being party to a free trade
  agreement with third parties on the date of signature of this
  Agreement.

  4. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall not apply in respect of trade
  agreements between Signatory ESA States with other African countries
  and regions.

  5. For the purposes of this Article, "free trade agreement"
  means an agreement substantially liberalising trade and providing for
  the absence or elimination of substantially all discrimination between
  or among parties thereto through the elimination of existing
  discriminatory measures and/or the prohibition of new or more
  discriminatory measures, either at the entry into force of that
  agreement or on the basis of a reasonable time frame.

  6. For the purposes of this Article, "major trading economy"
  means any developed country, or any country accounting for a share of
  world merchandise exports above 1 percent in the year before the entry
  into force of the free trade agreement referred to in paragraph 2, or
  any group of countries acting individually, collectively or through a
  free trade agreement accounting collectively for a share of world
  merchandise exports above 1,5 percent in the year before the entry
  into force of the free trade agreement referred to in paragraph 2 [1].

  Non-tariff measures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Prohibition Of Quantitative Restrictions" article_identifier="24394">Except as otherwise specified in Annexes I and II of this Agreement,
  all prohibitions or restrictions in trade on the importation,
  exportation or sale for export between the Parties, other than customs
  duties, taxes, fees and other charges provided for under Article 7,
  whether made effective through quotas, import or export licences or
  other measures, shall be eliminated upon the entry into force of this
  Agreement. No new such measures shall be introduced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="National Treatment On Internal Taxation And Regulation" article_identifier="24395">1. Imported products originating in the other Party shall not be
  subject, either directly or indirectly, to internal taxes or other
  internal charges of any kind in excess of those applied, directly or
  indirectly, to like national products. Moreover, the Parties shall not
  otherwise apply internal taxes or other internal charges so as to
  afford protection to national production.

  2. Imported products originating in the other Party shall be accorded
  treatment no less favourable than that accorded to like national
  products in respect of all laws, regulations and requirements
  affecting their internal sale, offering for sale, purchase,
  transportation, distribution or use. The provisions of this paragraph
  shall not prevent the application of differential internal
  transportation charges which are based exclusively on the economic
  operation of the means of transport and not on the nationality of the
  product.

  3. No Party shall establish or maintain any internal quantitative
  regulation relating to the mixture, processing or use of products in
  specified amounts or proportions which requires, directly or
  indirectly, that any specified amount or proportion of any product
  which is the subject of the regulation must be supplied from domestic
  sources. Moreover, no Party shall otherwise apply internal
  quantitative regulations so as to afford protection to national
  production.

  4. The provisions of this Article shall not prevent the payment of
  subsidies exclusively to national producers, including payments to
  national producers derived from the proceeds of internal taxes or
  charges applied consistently with the provisions of this Article and
  subsidies effected through governmental purchases of national
  products.

  5. The provisions of this Article shall not apply to laws,
  regulations, procedures or practices governing public procurement.

  6. The EPA Committee may decide to authorise a Signatory ESA State to
  depart from the provisions of this Article to promote the
  establishment of domestic production and protect infant industry. In
  this respect the development needs of Signatory ESA States and, in
  particular, the special needs and concerns of ESA LDCs will be taken
  into account.

  7. A list of provisional derogations is attached as Annex III. Such
  derogations are granted to the interested Signatory ESA States for the
  periods of time which are set out in the same Annex.

  Trade defence measures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Anti-Dumping And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="24396">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall prevent the EC Party or Signatory ESA States, whether
  individually or collectively, from adopting anti-dumping or
  countervailing measures in accordance with the relevant WTO
  agreements. For the purpose of this Article, origin shall be
  determined in accordance with the non-preferential rules of origin of
  the Parties.

  2. Before imposing definitive anti-dumping or countervailing duties in
  respect of products imported from ESA States, the EC Party shall
  consider the possibility of constructive remedies as provided for in
  the relevant WTO agreements.

  3. Where anti-dumping or countervailing measures have been imposed on
  behalf of two or more Signatory ESA States by a regional authority,
  there shall be one single forum of judicial review, including at the
  stage of appeals.

  4. Where anti-dumping or countervailing measures can be imposed on a
  regional or sub-regional basis and on a national basis the Parties
  shall ensure that such measures are not applied simultaneously in
  respect of the same product by regional or sub-regional authorities on
  the one hand, and national authorities on the other.

  5. The EC Party shall notify the exporting Signatory ESA States of the
  receipt of a properly documented complaint before initiating any
  investigation.

  6. The provisions of this Article shall be applicable in all
  investigations initiated after this Agreement enters into force.

  7. The provisions of this Article shall not be subject to the Dispute
  Settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Multilateral Safeguards" article_identifier="24397">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall prevent the Signatory ESA States and the EC Party from
  adopting measures in accordance with Article XIX of GATT 1994, the WTO
  Agreement on Safeguards, and Article 5 of the WTO Agreement on
  Agriculture. For the purpose of this Article, origin shall be
  determined in accordance with the non-preferential rules of origin of
  the Parties.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the EC Party shall, in the light of
  the overall development objectives of this Agreement and the small
  size of the economies of the ESA States, exclude imports from any ESA
  State from any measures taken pursuant to Article XIX of GATT 1994,
  the WTO Agreement on Safeguards and Article 5 of the WTO Agreement on
  Agriculture.

  3. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall apply for a period of five
  years, beginning with the date of entry into force of this Agreement.
  Not later than 120 days before the end of this period, the EPA
  Committee shall review the operation of those provisions in the light
  of the development needs of the ESA States, with a view to determining
  whether to extend their application for a further period.

  4. The provisions of paragraph 1 shall not be subject to the Dispute
  Settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Bilateral Safeguards" article_identifier="24398">1. After having examined alternative solutions, a Party may apply
  safeguard measures of limited duration which derogate from the
  provisions of Articles 11, 12 and 17, under the conditions and in
  accordance with the procedures laid down in this Article.

  2. Safeguard measures referred to in paragraph 1 may be taken where a
  product originating in one Party is being imported into the territory
  of the other Party in such increased quantities and under such
  conditions as to cause or threaten to cause:

  (a) serious injury to the domestic industry producing like or directly
  competitive products in the territory of the importing Party, or;

  (b) disturbances in a sector of the economy, particularly where these
  disturbances produce major social problems, or difficulties which
  could bring about serious deterioration in the economic situation of
  the importing Party, or;

  (c) disturbances in the markets of agricultural like or directly
  competitive products [2] or mechanisms regulating those markets.

  3. Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall not exceed
  what is necessary to remedy or prevent the serious injury or
  disturbances, as defined in paragraph 2 and 5(b). Those safeguard
  measures of the importing Party may only consist of one or more of the
  following:

  (a) suspension of the further reduction of the rate of import duty for
  the product concerned, as provided for under this Agreement;

  (b) increase in the customs duty on the product concerned up to a
  level which does not exceed the customs duty applied to other WTO
  Members, and

  (c) introduction of tariff quotas on the product concerned.

  4. Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3, where any product
  originating in one or more Signatory ESA States or subgroups is being
  imported in such increased quantities and under such conditions as to
  cause or threaten to cause one of the situations referred to under
  paragraph 2 to one or several of the EC Party’s outermost regions, the
  EC Party may take surveillance or safeguard measures limited to the
  region or regions concerned in accordance with the procedures laid
  down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  5. (a) Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3, where any product
  originating in the EC Party is being imported in such increased
  quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten to cause
  one of the situations referred to under paragraph 2 to a Signatory ESA
  State, the Signatory ESA State concerned may take surveillance or
  safeguard measures limited to its territory in accordance with the
  procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  (b) A Signatory ESA State may take safeguard measures where a product
  originating in the EC Party as a result of the reduction of duties is
  being imported into its territory in such increased quantities and
  under such conditions as to cause or threaten to cause disturbances to
  an infant industry producing like or directly competitive products.
  Such provision is only applicable for a period of 10 years for
  non-LDCs and 15 years for LDCs from the date of entry into force of
  this Agreement. Measures must be taken in accordance with the
  procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  6. (a) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall only be
  maintained for such a time as may be necessary to prevent or remedy
  serious injury or disturbances as defined in paragraphs 2, 4 and 5.

  (b) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall not be
  applied for a period exceeding two years. Where the circumstances
  warranting imposition of safeguard measures continue to exist, such
  measures may be extended for a further period of no more than two
  years. Where the Signatory ESA States or a Signatory ESA State apply a
  safeguard measure, or where the EC Party applies a measure limited to
  the territory of one or more of its outermost regions, such measure
  may however be applied for a period not exceeding four years and,
  where the circumstances warranting imposition of safeguard measures
  continue to exist, extended for a further period of four years.

  (c) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article that exceed one
  year shall contain clear elements progressively leading to their
  elimination at the end of the set period, at the latest.

  (d) No safeguard measure referred to in this Article shall be applied
  to the imports of a product that has previously been subject to such a
  measure, for a period of at least one year since the expiry of the
  measure.

  7. For the implementation of the above paragraphs, the following
  provisions shall apply:

  (a) where a Party takes the view that one of the circumstances set out
  in paragraphs 2, 4 and 5 exists, it shall immediately refer the matter
  to the EPA Committee for examination;

  (b) the EPA Committee may make any recommendation needed to remedy the
  circumstances which have arisen. If no recommendation has been made by
  the EPA Committee aimed at remedying the circumstances, or no other
  satisfactory solution has been reached within 30 days of the matter
  being referred to the EPA Committee, the importing Party may adopt the
  appropriate measures to remedy the circumstances in accordance with
  this Article;

  (c) before taking any measure provided for in this Article or, in the
  cases to which paragraph 8 of this Article applies, as soon as
  possible, the EC Party or the Signatory ESA State concerned shall
  supply the EPA Committee with all relevant information required for a
  thorough examination of the situation, with a view to seeking a
  solution acceptable to the Parties concerned;

  (d) in the selection of safeguard measures pursuant to this Article,
  priority must be given to those which least disturb the operation of
  this Agreement;

  (e) any safeguard measure taken pursuant to this Article shall be
  notified immediately to the EPA Committee and shall be the subject of
  periodic consultations within that body, particularly with a view to
  establishing a timetable for their abolition as soon as circumstances
  permit.

  8. Where exceptional circumstances require immediate action, the
  importing Party concerned, whether the EC Party, the ESA States or a
  Signatory ESA State as the case may be, may take the measures provided
  for in paragraph 3, 4 and/or 5 on a provisional basis without
  complying with the requirements of paragraph 7. Such action may be
  taken for a maximum period of 180 days where measures are taken by the
  EC Party and 200 days where measures are taken by the ESA States or a
  Signatory ESA State, or where measures taken by the EC Party are
  limited to the territory of one or more of its outermost regions. The
  duration of any such provisional measure shall be counted as a part of
  the initial period and any extension referred to in paragraph 6. In
  the taking of such provisional measures, the interest of all Parties
  involved shall be taken into account. The importing Party concerned
  shall inform the other Party concerned and shall immediately refer the
  matter to the EPA Committee for examination.

  9. If an importing Party subjects imports of a product to an
  administrative procedure having as its purpose the rapid provision of
  information on the trend of trade flows liable to give rise to the
  problems referred to in this Article, it shall inform the EPA
  Committee without delay.

  10. The WTO Agreement shall not be invoked to preclude a Party from
  adopting safeguard measures in conformity with this Article.

  Administrative provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Special Provision On Administrative Cooperation" article_identifier="24399">1. The Parties agree that administrative cooperation is essential for
  the implementation and control of the preferential treatment granted
  under this Chapter and underline their commitment to combat
  irregularities and fraud in customs and related matters.

  2. Where a Party has made a finding, on the basis of objective
  information, of a failure to provide administrative cooperation and/or
  of irregularities or fraud, the Party concerned may temporarily
  suspend the relevant preferential treatment of the product(s)
  concerned in accordance with this Article.

  3. For the purpose of this Article, a failure to provide
  administrative cooperation shall mean, inter alia:

  (a) a repeated failure to respect the obligations to verify the
  originating status of the product(s) concerned;

  (b) a repeated refusal or undue delay in carrying out and/or
  communicating the results of subsequent verification of the proof of
  origin;

  (c) a repeated refusal or undue delay in obtaining authorisation to
  conduct administrative cooperation missions to verify the authenticity
  of documents or accuracy of information relevant to the granting of
  the preferential treatment in question.

  4. For the purpose of this Article a finding of irregularities or
  fraud may be made, inter alia, where there is a rapid increase,
  without satisfactory explanation, in imports of goods exceeding the
  usual level of production and export capacity of the other Party that
  is linked to objective information concerning irregularities or fraud.

  5. The application of a temporary suspension shall be subject to the
  following conditions:

  (a) the Party which has made a finding, on the basis of objective
  information, of a failure to provide administrative cooperation and/or
  of irregularities or fraud shall without undue delay notify the EPA
  Committee of its finding together with the objective information and
  enter into consultations within the EPA Committee, on the basis of all
  relevant information and objective findings, with a view to reaching a
  solution acceptable to both Parties.

  (b) where the Parties have entered into consultations within the EPA
  Committee as above and have failed to agree on an acceptable solution
  within three months following the notification, the Party concerned
  may temporarily suspend the relevant preferential treatment of the
  product(s) concerned. A temporary suspension shall be notified to the
  EPA Committee without undue delay.

  (c) temporary suspensions under this Article shall be limited to that
  necessary to protect the financial interests of the Party concerned.
  They shall not exceed a period of six months, which may be renewed.
  Temporary suspensions shall be notified immediately after their
  adoption to the EPA Committee. They shall be subject to periodic
  consultations within the EPA Committee in particular with a view to
  their termination as soon as the conditions for their application are
  no longer satisfied.

  6. At the same time as the notification to the EPA Committee under
  paragraph 5(a) of this Article, the Party concerned should publish a
  notice to importers in its Official Journal. The notice to importers
  should indicate for the product concerned that there is a finding, on
  the basis of objective information, of a failure to provide
  administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities or fraud.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Management Of Administrative Errors" article_identifier="24400">In case of error by the competent authorities in the proper management
  of the preferential system of export, and in particular in the
  application of the provisions of Protocol 1 concerning the definition
  of the concept of "originating products" and methods of
  administrative cooperation, where this error leads to consequences in
  terms of import duties, the Party facing such consequences may request
  the EPA Committee to examine the possibilities of adopting all
  appropriate measures with a view to resolving the situation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Custom Valuation" article_identifier="24401">1. Article VII of GATT 1994 and the Agreement on the implementation of
  Article VII of GATT 1994 shall govern customs valuation rules applied
  to reciprocal trade between the Parties.

  2. The Parties shall cooperate with a view to reaching a common
  approach to issues relating to customs valuation.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER III" name="Fisheries" chapter_identifier="2927">
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" article_identifier="24402">1. The Parties recognise that fisheries constitute a key economic
  resource of the ESA region, contribute significantly to the economies
  of the Signatory ESA States and have great potential for future
  regional economic development and poverty reduction. It is also an
  important source of food and foreign exchange.

  2. The Parties further recognise that fisheries resources are also of
  considerable interest to both the EC Party and the Signatory ESA
  States, and agree to cooperate for the sustainable development and
  management of the fisheries sector in their mutual interests taking
  into account the economic, environmental and social impacts.

  3. The Parties agree that the appropriate strategy to promote the
  economic growth of the fisheries sector and to enhance its
  contribution to the ESA economy, while taking into consideration its
  long term sustainability, is through increasing value adding
  activities within the sector.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Objectives" article_identifier="24403">The objectives of cooperation in fisheries are to:

  (a) promote sustainable development and management of fisheries;

  (b) promote and develop regional and international trade based on best
  practices;

  (c) create an enabling environment, including infrastructure and
  capacity building, for the ESA States to cope with the stringent
  market requirements for both industrial and small scale fisheries;

  (d) support national and regional policies aimed at increasing
  productivity and competitiveness of the fisheries sector; and

  (e) build links with other economic sectors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Scope" article_identifier="24404">Cooperation in fisheries trade and development shall cover marine,
  inland fisheries and aquaculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Principles" article_identifier="24405">1. The principles of cooperation in fisheries include:

  (a) support for the development and strengthening of regional
  integration;

  (b) preservation of the acquis of the Cotonou Agreement;

  (c) provision of special and differential treatment;

  (d) the need to take into account the best available scientific
  information for resource assessment and management;

  (e) a functioning monitoring system of the environmental, economic and
  social impacts in the Parties;

  (f) conformity with existing national laws and relevant international
  instruments including the United Nations Convention on the Law Of the
  Sea (UNCLOS), regional and sub-regional agreements; and

  (g) preservation and priority of particular needs of the
  artisanal/subsistence fishery.

  2. These guiding principles should contribute to sustainable and
  responsible development of the living inland and marine resources,
  aquaculture, and to optimising the benefits of this sector for present
  and future generations, through increased investment, capacity
  building and improved market access.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Preferential Access" article_identifier="24406">The Parties shall cooperate to ensure that financial and other support
  will be provided to improve the competitiveness and production
  capacity of the processing factories, the diversification of the
  fishing industry and the improvement of port facilities.

  Marine fisheries</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Scope" article_identifier="24407">The scope of this Title is the utilisation, conservation and
  management of marine fisheries resources to optimise the benefits from
  fisheries for the ESA region through investment capacity building and
  improved market access.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Objectives" article_identifier="24408">The objectives of cooperation are to:

  (a) strengthen cooperation in order to ensure the sustainable
  exploitation and management of fisheries resources as a strong basis
  for regional integration, given the straddling and migratory species
  which are shared among island and coastal States and as no individual
  ESA State has the capacity to ensure sustainability of the resource;

  (b) ensure a more equitable share of the benefits derived from the
  fisheries sector;

  (c) ensure effective monitoring control and surveillance (MCS)
  necessary for combating illegal, unreported and unregulated (IUU)
  fishing; and

  (d) promote effective exploitation, conservation and management of the
  living marine resources in the exclusive economic zone (EEZ) and
  waters in which ESA States have jurisdiction based on international
  instruments, including UNCLOS, for the mutual social and economic
  benefit of the ESA States and the EC Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Areas Of Cooperation" article_identifier="24409">1. To achieve the objectives of cooperation in marine fisheries within
  the described principles, cooperation will include fisheries
  management and conservation issues, vessel management and post harvest
  arrangements and financial and trade measures and development of
  fisheries and fishery products and marine aquaculture.

  2. The EC Party will contribute to the mobilisation of the resources
  for the implementation of the identified areas of cooperation at
  national and regional levels, which will also include support for
  regional capacity building. Furthermore, the EC Party shall contribute
  to the measures as described in the section concerning financial and
  trade measures, and on infrastructure development specific for
  fisheries and marine aquaculture.

  (a) Fisheries Management and Conservation Issues

  1. The precautionary approach shall be applied in determining levels
  of sustainable catch, fishing capacity and other management strategies
  to avoid or reverse undesirable outcomes such as over-capacity and
  over-fishing, as well as undesirable impacts on the ecosystems and
  artisanal fisheries.

  2. Each ESA State may take appropriate measures, including seasonal
  and gear restrictions in order to further protect its territorial
  waters and ensure the sustainability of the artisanal and coastal
  fishery.

  3. The Parties will promote the membership of all the concerned States
  to the Indian Ocean Tuna Commission (IOTC) and other relevant
  fisheries organisations. These countries, with the EC Party, should
  coordinate action to ensure the management and conservation of all
  fish species, including tuna and tuna-like resources and facilitate
  relevant scientific research.

  4. Where there is insufficient scientific evidence for the competent
  national management authority to determine limits and target levels of
  sustainable catch in an ESA EEZ, both Parties in consultation with the
  competent national authority and together with IOTC and where
  relevant, other regional fisheries organisations, shall support such
  scientific analysis.

  5. The Parties agree to take appropriate measures where an increase in
  effort results in catch levels above the target sustainable level
  established by the competent national authority.

  6. In order to conserve and manage straddling stocks and highly
  migratory fish stocks, the EC Party and the ESA States shall ensure
  compliance by vessels flying their flags with relevant national,
  regional and sub-regional fisheries management measures and related
  national laws and regulations.

  (b) Vessel Management and Post Harvest Arrangements

  1. Vessel Management and post harvest arrangements emerging from IOTC
  and any other relevant regional fisheries organisations will be
  observed. ESA States and the EC Party shall set out minimum terms and
  conditions with respect to MCS of EC Party fishing vessels operating
  in the waters of ESA States, which should include the following:

  (i) a Vessel Monitoring System (VMS) will be set up for all ESA
  States, and all ESA States will use a compatible VMS. Those ESA States
  which do not have a VMS will be assisted by the EC Party to set up a
  compatible VMS;

  (ii) in addition to a compulsory compatible VMS system, all ESA
  States, in conjunction with the EC Party, will develop other
  mechanisms to ensure effective MCS and the EC Party will support ESA
  States to put such an agreed system in place and assist in
  implementation;

  (iii) the Parties shall have the right to place observers, whether in
  national or international waters, with the procedures concerning the
  deployment of observers being well stipulated. Observers are to be
  paid by the national governments but all costs on board are to be met
  by the ship-owner. The EC Party will support the costs of training
  observers;

  (iv) common systems of reporting of fishing will be developed and be
  used throughout the region, with minimum terms set for reporting;

  (v) all vessels that land or tranship their catches within the ESA
  State shall do it in ports or outer-port areas. No transhipment shall
  be allowed at sea, except on particular conditions foreseen by the
  relevant Regional Fisheries Management Organisations (RFMO). Both
  Parties shall cooperate to modernise landing or transhipment
  infrastructure in ports of ESA States, including development capacity
  of fish products;

  (vi) all vessels should endeavour to use the facilities of the ESA
  States and undertake to make use of local supplies;

  (vii) discards reporting shall be compulsory. Priority should be given
  to avoid discards through the use of selective fishing methods in line
  with the principles of the IOTC and relevant regional fisheries
  organisations. As far as possible, by-catch shall be brought ashore.

  2. The Parties agree to cooperate in developing and implementing
  national/regional training programmes for ESA nationals in order to
  facilitate their effective participation in the fishing industry.
  Where the EC Party has negotiated bilateral fisheries agreements,
  employment of ESA nationals shall be encouraged. The International
  Labour Organisation (ILO) Declaration on fundamental principles and
  rights at work shall apply as of right to seamen signed on Community
  vessels.

  3. Both Parties shall undertake coordinated efforts to improve the
  means for preventing, deterring, and eliminating IUU fishing and to
  this end take appropriate measures. Fishing vessels involved in IUU
  fishing should be prosecuted and should not be allowed to fish again
  in ESA waters, unless prior authorisation has been obtained from both
  the flag State and the concerned ESA States as well as, where
  relevant, the concerned RFMO.

  (c) Financial and Trade Measures and Development issues

  Inland fisheries and aquaculture development</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Scope" article_identifier="24410">The scope of this Title shall cover inland fisheries, coastal and
  aquaculture development in the ESA region with respect to capacity
  building, technology transfer, Sanitary and Phytosanitary (SPS)
  standards, investment, and investment finance, environmental
  protection as well as legal and regulatory frameworks.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Objectives" article_identifier="24411">The objectives of cooperation in inland fisheries and aquaculture
  development will be to promote sustainable exploitation of inland
  fisheries resources, enhance aquaculture production, remove supply
  side constraints, improve fish and fish product quality to meet SPS
  standards in the EC market, improve access to the EC market, address
  intra-regional trade barriers, attract capital inflows and investment
  into the sector, build capacity and enhance access to financial
  support for the private investors for inland fisheries and aquaculture
  development.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Areas Of Cooperation" article_identifier="24412">1. The areas of cooperation shall include EC Party contributions to
  the following:

  (a) capacity building and export market development through:

  (i) building capacity in industrial and artisanal production,
  processing and product diversification that strengthen the
  competitiveness of the region’s inland fisheries and aquaculture. This
  could, for example, be achieved by the creation of Research and
  development (R&amp;D) centres including the development of aquaculture
  for commercial fishing farms;

  (ii) building capacity for managing export market chains, including
  the introduction and management of certification schemes for specific
  product lines; and implementation of market promotion, value addition
  and reduction in post harvest losses in fishery products;

  (iii) increasing capacity in the region through, for example,
  improving competent authorities, traders’ associations and fishermen’s
  associations in order to participate in fisheries trade with the EC
  Party and training programs in product development and branding.

  (b) Infrastructure

  (i) developing and improving infrastructure for inland fisheries and
  aquaculture;

  (ii) facilitating access to funding for infrastructure, including all
  types of equipment.

  (c) Technology

  (i) contributing to the development of technical capabilities,
  including value adding technology promotion, for example, through
  fisheries technology transfer from the EC Party to the ESA countries;

  (ii) enhancing fisheries management capacity in the region, for
  example through research and data collection systems and contribution
  towards appropriate technologies on harvesting and post harvest
  management.

  (d) Legal and regulatory

  (i) supporting the development of inland fisheries and aquaculture
  regulations and monitoring control and surveillance systems;

  (ii) supporting ESA States in developing appropriate legal and
  regulatory instruments on intellectual property rights (IPR) and
  building capacity for their implementation in international trade;

  (iii) eco-labelling and intellectual property protection.

  (e) Investment and finance

  (i) promoting joint ventures and other forms of mixed investments
  between stakeholders in ESA States and the EC Party, for example for
  the setting up of modalities for identifying investors for joint
  venture operations in inland fisheries and aquaculture;

  (ii) contributing to providing access to credit facilities for the
  development of small to medium scale enterprises as well as industrial
  scale inland fisheries.

  (f) Socio-economic and poverty alleviation measures

  (i) contributing to the promotion of small and medium scale fisheries,
  processors, and fish traders by building the capacity of ESA States to
  participate in trade with the EC Party;

  (ii) encouraging participation of marginal groups in the fishing
  industry, for example, through the promotion of gender equality in
  fisheries by developing the capacity of women engaged in fisheries, as
  well as other disadvantaged groups with the potential to engage in
  fisheries for sustainable social economic development.

  2. Both Parties shall contribute to measures to ensure that fish trade
  supports environmental conservation and safeguards against stocks
  depletion, and to the maintenance of biodiversity and the cautious
  introduction of exotic species for aquaculture (to be introduced only
  in managed/closed spaces in consultation with all concerned
  neighbouring countries).</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER IV" name="Economic And Development Cooperation" chapter_identifier="2928">
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="24413">1. The Parties agree to address the developmental needs of the ESA
  States in order to promote sustained growth in the ESA region,
  increase production and supply capacity of the States concerned,
  foster structural transformation and competitiveness of their
  economies and their diversification and value addition and support
  regional integration.

  2. The Parties commit themselves to cooperating in order to facilitate
  the implementation of this Agreement and to support regional
  integration and development strategies. The Parties agree that
  cooperation will be based on the ESA Development Cooperation Strategy
  and the jointly agreed Development Matrix. The matrix is attached as
  Annex IV to this Agreement. The ESA Development Cooperation Strategy
  and the Development Matrix will be regularly reviewed subject to the
  provisions of Chapter VI on Dispute Avoidance, Settlement,
  Institutional, General and Final Provisions. This cooperation will be
  measured against jointly agreed development benchmarks to be developed
  and adopted and annexed to this Agreement. The cooperation shall be in
  the form of financial and non-financial support to the ESA region.

  3. In this regard, the financing pertaining to development cooperation
  between the ESA Region and the EC Party for the implementation of this
  Agreement shall be carried out within the framework of the rules and
  relevant procedures provided for by the Cotonou Agreement, in
  particular the programming procedures of the European Development Fund
  within successive financial frameworks of the EU during the period of
  this Agreement as well as within the frameworks of relevant
  instruments financed by the General Budget of the EU. In this context,
  taking into account the new challenges deriving from enhanced regional
  integration and competition on the global markets, the Parties agree
  that supporting the implementation of the EPA shall be one of the
  priorities.

  4. Both Parties shall cooperate to mobilise resources additional to
  the financial framework of the EU, from EU Member States and other
  donors, in particular expanding Aid for Trade commitments, relating
  specifically to EPA support requirements and adjustment costs. The
  programmes/projects proposed for financing will be worked out jointly
  based on a detailed costed development matrix.

  5. Sufficient resources should be mobilised on a predictable, timely
  and sustainable basis including through grants and concessional loans
  based on the Development Matrix. The EC shall contribute to these
  efforts under its international commitment on the scaling up of
  Official Development Aid. The Parties agree to monitor and coordinate
  the use of these resources.

  6. Consistent with the Paris Declaration on Aid Effectiveness, the
  Parties agree to use and support as appropriate nationally and/or
  regionally owned delivery mechanisms, funds or facilities for
  channelling and coordinating resources for implementing the EPA. The
  Parties shall, in that regard, support the establishment of an EPA
  Fund to channel EPA related resources. The Parties also agree that all
  forms of aid delivery pertaining to their cooperation under this
  Agreement shall be guided by the Paris Declaration on Aid
  Effectiveness.

  7. The trade-related issues to be provided for in the comprehensive
  EPA shall be the subject of development cooperation in accordance with
  this Article taking into consideration the Paris Declaration on Aid
  Effectiveness.

  8. The Parties agree that EPA monitoring, on the basis of agreed
  indicators, will need to address all aspects of the EPA, including
  achievements at the national level and at the level of regional
  integration and development strategies, as well as the effectiveness
  of the institutional arrangements and their achievements in meeting
  Aid effectiveness objectives, including ensuring predictability of the
  resources.

  9. The Parties agree that, without prejudice to the provisions of
  Article 95.4 of the Cotonou Agreement, the review process provided
  therein will constitute an opportunity for the Parties to review the
  achievements, constraints and way forward regarding their development
  cooperation strategies as provided for within the Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Objectives" article_identifier="24414">1. Economic and development cooperation shall aim at enhancing the
  competitiveness of ESA economies, building up supply capacity and
  enabling Signatory ESA States in implementing the EPA smoothly.

  2. Economic and development cooperation shall aim at the structural
  transformation of ESA economies by establishing a strong, competitive
  and diversified economic base in the ESA States through enhancing
  production, distribution, transport, marketing, developing trade
  capacity of ESA States as well as capacity to attract investment,
  strengthening the ESA States’ trade and investment policies and
  regulations and deepening regional integration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Scope" article_identifier="24415">1. The Parties shall set out the development objectives related to the
  EPA that are specific to the ESA region and needed for the success of
  regional integration within the areas and sectors highlighted in this
  Article.

  2. The areas that will be addressed by the cooperation are:

  (a) regional cooperation and integration to ensure trans-regional
  coordination in all sectors;

  (b) trade policy and regulations in order to assist the ESA States in
  participating more effectively in trade negotiations, in implementing
  international trade related conventions, trade related legislation and
  regulatory reforms amongst others;

  (c) trade development which covers namely business development and
  activities aimed at improving information management systems,
  partnerships, linkages, joint ventures and exchange of information and
  experiences, access to credit and investment finance, trade promotion
  and market development, institutional support as well as support to
  trade in services, including financial services;

  (d) trade related infrastructure, including transport, energy and
  water;

  (e) building productive capacities in relevant sectors of ESA
  economies;

  (f) research and development, innovation and technology transfer;

  (g) trade related adjustment costs, which include restructuring and
  social costs arising from the reduction of production by firms in
  import competing sectors and the loss of fiscal revenues dues to the
  tariff reductions;

  (h) gender mainstreaming;

  (i) empowerment of local communities, which includes social and
  cultural development; and

  (j) mainstreaming of environmental issues into trade and development.

  3. The cooperation shall, in particular, cover the following sectors:

  (a) Private Sector Development, particularly Industrial Development,
  micro-enterprises, small and medium-sized enterprises (MSME), Mining
  and Minerals as well as Tourism.

  (b) Infrastructure Development, namely in the Transport, Energy,
  Information and Communications Technology (ICT) sectors.

  (c) Natural Resources and Environment, including Water Resources and
  Biodiversity.

  (d) Agriculture.

  (e) Fisheries.

  (f) Services including Tourism; and

  (g) Trade related issues, namely Investment, Competition, Intellectual
  Property Rights, Standards, Trade Facilitation and Statistics.

  Private sector development</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="24416">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation to develop the
  ESA region’s private sector as the main engine of wealth creation in
  view to set up an appropriate enabling environment which is conducive
  to investment and growth. The Community support and cooperation shall
  take account of the economic structure of the ESA States and their
  priorities in strengthening productive capacities and value addition,
  and the application of Production, Marketing, Distribution, and
  Transportation (PMDT) functions to improve supply capacities and
  competitiveness.

  2. The scope of cooperation of private sector development will cover,
  inter alia, investment, industrial development and competitiveness
  enhancement, micro-enterprises, small and medium sized enterprises
  development, mining and minerals and tourism development as well as
  other productive sectors which are directly and indirectly covered by
  this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Investment" article_identifier="24417">1. The Parties recognise the importance of investment. The objectives
  in this area are to:

  (a) create an environment for sustainable and equitable economic
  development of ESA through investment, including foreign direct
  investment (green field or portfolio), technology transfer, capacity
  building and institutional support from the EC Party;

  (b) provide deeper cooperation with institutions and intermediary
  organisations dealing with investment promotion in the EC Party,
  including the Centre for the Development of Enterprise (CDE) and ESA
  through, inter alia, business dialogue, cooperation and partnership;

  (c) support, through appropriate instruments, the promotion and
  encouragement of investment in the ESA region, including establishing
  a framework for funding and assistance to support economic development
  programmes in ESA;

  (d) strengthen and build the capacity of private development
  institutions such as investment promotion agencies, chambers of
  commerce, associations and indigenous development organisations in
  individual ESA States and the region as a whole so as to enable the
  emergence of a dynamic and vibrant private sector; and

  (e) develop a legal framework that promotes investment by both
  Parties, with a view to promoting and protecting investment and work
  towards harmonised and simplified procedures and administrative
  practices.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36 the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) support to policies and strategies for investment to help creating
  and maintaining a predictable and secure investment climate;

  (b) support policy reforms and advocacy, human resource development,
  institutional capacity-building or other forms of institutional
  support to strengthen the capacities of the private financial and
  non-financial intermediaries, investment facilitation and promotion
  and competitiveness enhancement activities;

  (c) encourage the EU-ESA private sector partnership and joint ventures
  to promote investment, venture capital financing for greenfield
  investment and technology transfer;

  (d) support efforts of the ESA States to attract financing, with
  particular emphasis on private financing, for infrastructure
  investments and revenue generating infrastructure critical for the
  private sector, including small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs);

  (e) support to develop regulatory capacity;

  (f) improve access of ESA enterprises to investment finance
  instruments in the EU such as the European Investment Bank (EIB);

  (g) establish financial instruments adapted to SMEs of the ESA region;

  (h) ensure the increasing availability and use of risk insurance as a
  risk-mitigating mechanism in order to boost investor confidence in the
  ESA States; and

  (i) offer guarantees and assist with guarantee funds covering risks
  for qualified investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Industrial Development And Competitiveness" article_identifier="24418">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in industrial
  development and competitiveness. The objectives in this area are to:

  (a) facilitate the establishment, development, restructuring and
  modernisation of the Signatory ESA States’ industry while fostering
  its competitiveness and self-sustainable and balanced growth taking
  into account environmental protection, sustainable development and
  economic empowerment; and

  (b) establish an environment favourable to the development of private
  enterprise in order to stimulate the growth and diversification of
  industrial production.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) promote the development of activities in the areas of processing,
  marketing, distribution and transportation of products;

  (b) transfer of technology, knowledge and research and development;

  (c) support ESA States’ financial institutions and the development of
  the capital market for the purpose of enhancing the private sector
  access to both short term and long term capital;

  (d) capacity building for public and private sector;

  (e) encourage EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint ventures between
  economic operators; and

  (f) promote and strengthen innovation, diversification and value
  addition product development and quality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Micro, Small And Medium-Sized Enterprises" article_identifier="24419">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in MSME. The
  objectives in this area are to:

  (a) promote a favourable environment for the development of MSME and
  for attracting investment therein; and

  (b) support MSMEs to adjust to trade liberalisation.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) capacity building and institutional support;

  (b) technology development and transfer, innovation, information
  exchange and networks and marketing;

  (c) development of MSME databases;

  (d) access to finance;

  (e) encourage EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint ventures between
  economic operators;

  (f) trade and investment promotion;

  (g) strengthen value chains;

  (h) promote diversification and value addition.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Mining And Minerals" article_identifier="24420">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development and management of the mining and minerals sector. The
  objectives in this area are to:

  (a) establish a conducive environment for attracting investment in the
  sector;

  (b) promote value addition and environmentally friendly technologies
  in the mining productive processes; and

  (c) ensure participation of local communities.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) capacity building and institutional support for the exploration,
  exploitation and marketing of minerals;

  (b) information exchange;

  (c) encourage EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint ventures between
  economic operators;

  (d) improve health and safety standards in the mining industry;

  (e) transfer of technology, knowledge, innovation and Research and
  Development; and

  (f) address vulnerability of mineral export dependency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Tourism Development" article_identifier="24421">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development of tourism. The objectives in this area are to:

  (a) develop and strengthen a competitive tourism industry as a
  generator of economic growth and empowerment, employment and foreign
  exchange;

  (b) strengthen the linkages between tourism and other sectors of the
  economy; and

  (c) preserve, safeguard and promote natural, historical and cultural
  tourist attractions, while respecting the integrity and interests of
  local communities, particularly in rural areas.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) establish strategic alliances involving public, private and local
  community interests in order to ensure the sustainable development of
  tourism;

  (b) promote partnerships, exchange of know-how and joint operations in
  areas such as development of products, markets and eco-tourism;

  (c) capacity building in human resources, improvement in service
  standards, and institutional structures; and

  (d) regional cooperation in tourism promotion.

  Infrastructure</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="24422">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development and management of infrastructure, as a means to overcome
  the supply-side constraints and strengthen regional integration.

  2. The Community support and cooperation for infrastructural
  development shall take account of priority development areas as
  articulated in the respective ESA States’ national and regional
  development programmes.

  3. The scope of cooperation in infrastructure will cover the
  development of physical infrastructure, namely transport, energy,
  information and communication technology.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Transport" article_identifier="24423">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development and management of transport. The objectives in this area
  are to:

  (a) Develop, restructure, rehabilitate upgrade and modernise the ESA
  region’s transport systems on a sustainable basis.

  (b) Improve the movement of people and flow of goods and provide
  better access to markets through road, air, maritime, inland water and
  rail transport.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) improve management of transport systems;

  (b) improve and develop the state of infrastructure at all levels,
  including the development of inter-modal infrastructure networks;

  (c) capacity building in human resources, improvement in service
  standards, and institutional structures;

  (d) technology development and transfer, innovation, information
  exchange and networks, and marketing;

  (e) encourage EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint ventures between
  economic operators;

  (f) improve safety and reliability of the transport sector, including
  the management of hazardous goods and emergency response; and

  (g) support to the development of regional transport policies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Energy" article_identifier="24424">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the energy
  sector as a vehicle for supporting the ESA economies’ competitiveness
  at the regional and global levels. The objectives in this area are to:

  (a) improve the access of ESA States to modern, efficient, reliable,
  diversified and sustainable and renewable sources of clean energy at
  competitive prices;

  (b) enhance the production, distribution and management capacity of
  energy nationally and regionally; and

  (c) promote regional energy cooperation.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) enhance the production and distribution capacity of existing
  energy sources, in particular hydro, petroleum and biomass;

  (b) expand and diversify the energy mix to include other potential
  sources of energy that are socially and environmentally acceptable and
  that reduce dependency on oil;

  (c) support the development of energy infrastructure, including for
  rural areas;

  (d) support the development of appropriate energy regulatory and
  policy reforms, including commercialisation and privatisation;

  (e) promote regional interconnectivity and cooperation in the
  production and distribution of energy;

  (f) capacity building in human resources, improvement in management,
  service standards, and institutional structures;

  (g) support the creation of a conducive environment for attracting
  investment in the sector;

  (h) technology development and transfer, research and development
  (R&amp;D), innovation, information exchange, development of databases
  and networks;

  (i) encourage EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint ventures between
  economic operators.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Information And Communications Technology (Ict)" article_identifier="24425">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development of ICT as a key sector in the modern society to foster
  competitiveness and innovation, as well as for the smooth transition
  towards the information society. The objective in this area is to
  develop the ICT sector and promote its contribution to other
  socio-economic sectors.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) facilitate connectivity at the national, regional and global
  levels;

  (b) disseminate new information and communication technologies;

  (c) support the development of the legal and regulatory frameworks on
  ICT;

  (d) technology development, transfer and applications, R&amp;D,
  innovation, information exchange and networks, and marketing;

  (e) capacity building in human resources, improvement in service
  standards, and institutional structures;

  (f) encourage and facilitate EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint
  ventures between economic operators;

  (g) promote and support the development of niche markets for
  ICT-enabled services.

  Natural resources and environment</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="24426">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  sustainable management of natural resources and environment.
  Cooperation in this area shall take account of differentiated and
  trans-boundary needs of ESA States.

  2. The scope of cooperation in natural resources and environment will
  cover natural assets, including water resources, and environment,
  including biodiversity, as well as enhancing the linkages between
  trade and environment. It will also cover support for the
  implementation of international environmental agreements, conventions
  and treaties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Water Resources" article_identifier="24427">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  development of water resources (including irrigation, hydropower and
  water supply) for the improvement of the livelihoods of the
  populations. The objectives in this area are:

  (a) the sustainable development and management of water resources in
  the region;

  (b) regional cooperation for the sustainable utilisation of
  trans-boundary water resources.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) development of infrastructure of water resources in the region;

  (b) development of the legal and regulatory frameworks;

  (c) promotion of integrated water management;

  (d) capacity building in human resources, improvement in service
  standards, water management and institutional structures;

  (e) encourage and facilitate EU-ESA partnerships, linkages, regional
  water partnerships and joint ventures between economic operators;

  (f) technology development, transfer and applications, R&amp;D,
  innovation, information exchange and networks;

  (g) water pollution control, purification and conservation, wastewater
  treatment and sanitation; and

  (h) promotion of sustainable irrigation schemes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Environment" article_identifier="24428">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the
  protection and sustainable management of the environment and
  implementation of trade-related environmental policies. The objectives
  in this area are to:

  (a) protect, restore and conserve the environment and biodiversity:
  flora, fauna and microbial genetic resources, including their
  ecosystems;

  (b) develop new ESA industries related to the environment; and

  (c) reduce environmental degradation, including clean air and
  desertification.

  Areas of cooperation

  2. Subject to the provisions of Article 36, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, including by facilitating support, in the following areas:

  (a) support the implementation of international environmental
  agreements, conventions and treaties;

  (b) strengthen and promote sustainable environmental management
  systems;

  (c) sustainable utilisation of biodiversity, forestry and wildlife
  resources;

  (d) reinforcing institutional and legal frameworks and the capacity to
  develop, implement, administer and enforce environmental laws,
  regulations, standards and policies;

  (e) capacity building in human resources and institutional structures
  to comply with environmental and biodiversity requirements;

  (f) encourage and facilitate EU-ESA partnerships, linkages and joint
  ventures between economic operators;

  (g) mitigation of natural disasters, prevention of environmental
  disasters and the loss of biodiversity;

  (h) technology development and adaptation, transfer and applications,
  R&amp;D and innovation;

  (i) protection and management of coastal and marine resources and
  domestic and wild indigenous biological resources;

  (j) support the development of alternative environmentally friendly
  activities and livelihoods;

  (k) support the production and facilitate trade of goods and services
  for which eco-labelling is important;

  (l) exchange of information and networking on products and their
  requirements in terms of production process, transport, marketing and
  labelling;

  (m) support the development of infrastructure facilities on
  environmentally-friendly products;

  (n) integration of local communities in the management of
  biodiversity, forestry and wildlife resources;

  (o) waste management and disposal of industrial and toxic wastes; and

  (p) sustainable management of forests and similar mechanisms.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Financial Undertakings" article_identifier="24429">1. The EC Party shall put at the disposal of ESA financial assistance
  to contribute to implement the programmes and projects to be developed
  under the areas of cooperation identified in this Agreement and
  relevant chapters and under the detailed Development Matrix.

  2. The Parties agree to establish adequate joint institutional
  arrangements to effectively monitor the implementation of the
  development cooperation of this Agreement. Such arrangements shall
  include the establishment of a Joint Development Committee.

  3. The Parties agree that the institutional arrangements shall remain
  flexible to adapt to the evolving national and regional needs.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER V" name="Areas For Future Negotiations" chapter_identifier="2929">
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Rendez-Vous Clause" article_identifier="24430">Building on the Cotonou Agreement and taking account of the progress
  made in the negotiations of a comprehensive EPA, the Parties agree to
  continue negotiations in accordance with Article 3 with a view to
  concluding a full and comprehensive EPA covering the following areas:

  (a) customs and trade facilitation;

  (b) outstanding trade and market access issues, including rules of
  origin and other related issues and trade defence measures, including
  outermost regions;

  (c) technical barriers to trade and sanitary and phytosanitary
  measures;

  (d) trade in services;

  (e) trade related issues namely:

  (i) competition policy;

  (ii) investment and private sector development;

  (iii) trade, environment and sustainable development;

  (iv) intellectual property rights;

  (v) transparency in public procurement;

  (f) agriculture;

  (g) current payments and capital payments;

  (h) development issues;

  (i) cooperation and dialogue on good governance in the tax and
  judicial area;

  (j) an elaborated dispute settlement mechanism, institutional
  arrangements; and

  (k) any other areas that the Parties find necessary, including
  consultations under Article 12 of the Cotonou Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER VI" name="Dispute Avoidance, Settlement, Institutional, General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="2930">
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Consultations" article_identifier="24431">1. The Parties shall endeavour to resolve any dispute concerning the
  interpretation and application of this Agreement by entering into
  consultations in good faith with the aim of reaching an agreed
  solution.

  2. A Party shall seek consultations by means of a written request to
  the other Party, identifying the measure at issue and the provisions
  of the Agreement that it considers the measure not to be in conformity
  with.

  3. Consultations shall be held within 40 days of the date of the
  submission of the request. The consultations shall be deemed concluded
  within 60 days of the date of the submission of the request, unless
  both Parties agree to continue consultations. The consultations shall
  remain confidential.

  4. Consultations on matters of urgency, including those regarding
  perishable or seasonal goods shall be held within 15 days of the date
  of the submission of the request, and shall be deemed concluded within
  30 days of the date of the submission of the request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="24432">1. If consultations do not succeed in settling the dispute within the
  60 days or 30 days referred to in Article 54, either Party may request
  settlement of the dispute by arbitration. To this end, each Party
  shall appoint an arbitrator within thirty days of the request for
  arbitration by notifying the other Party and the EPA Committee. The
  request for arbitration shall identify the measure at issue and the
  provisions of the Agreement that the complaining Party considers the
  measure not to be in conformity with. In the event of failure to do
  so, either Party may ask the Secretary General of the Permanent Court
  of Arbitration to appoint the second arbitrator.

  2. The two arbitrators shall in turn appoint a third arbitrator within
  thirty days. In the event of failure to do so, either Party may ask
  the Secretary General of the Permanent Court of Arbitration to appoint
  the third arbitrator.

  3. Unless the arbitrators decide otherwise, the procedure applied
  shall be laid down in the optional arbitration regulation of the
  Permanent Court of Arbitration for International Organisations and
  States. The arbitrators shall take a decision by majority vote within
  90 days and in matters of urgency should endeavour to take a decision
  within 60 days.

  4. Each Party to the dispute shall be bound to take the measures
  necessary to carry out the decision of the arbitrators.

  5. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the procedure set out in Article 98 of
  the Cotonou Agreement shall be applicable in the event of a dispute
  concerning development finance cooperation as provided for by the
  Cotonou Agreement.

  General exceptions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="General Exception Clause" article_identifier="24433">Subject to the requirement that such measures are not applied in a
  manner which would constitute a means of arbitrary or unjustifiable
  discrimination between the Parties where like conditions prevail, or a
  disguised restriction on international trade, nothing in this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement by
  the EC Party, the ESA States or a Signatory ESA State of measures
  which:

  (a) are necessary to protect public morals or to maintain public order
  and public security;

  (b) are necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health;

  (c) are necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations which
  are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement, including
  those relating to:

  (i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or to deal
  with the effects of a default on contracts;

  (ii) the protection of the privacy of individuals in relation to the
  processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of
  confidentiality of individual records and accounts;

  (iii) safety;

  (iv) customs enforcement; or

  (v) protection of intellectual property rights.

  (d) relate to the importation or exportation of gold or silver;

  (e) are necessary to the protection of national treasures of artistic,
  historic or archaeological value;

  (f) relate to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources if
  such measures are made effective in conjunction with restrictions on
  domestic production or consumption of goods, domestic supply or
  consumption of services and on domestic investors;

  (g) relate to the products of prison labour; or

  (h) are essential to the acquisition or distribution of products in
  general or local short supply, provided that any such measures shall
  be consistent with the principle that all parties are entitled to an
  equitable share of the international supply of such products, and that
  any such measures, which are inconsistent with the other provisions of
  this Agreement, shall be discontinued as soon as the conditions giving
  rise to them have ceased to exist.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="24434">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed:

  (a) to require the EC Party or a Signatory ESA State to furnish any
  information the disclosure of which it considers contrary to its
  essential security interests;

  (b) to prevent the EC Party or a Signatory ESA State from taking any
  action which it considers necessary for the protection of its
  essential security interests:

  (i) relating to fissionable and fusionable materials or the materials
  from which they are derived;

  (ii) relating to economic activities carried out directly or
  indirectly for the purpose of supplying or provisioning a military
  establishment;

  (iii) connected with the production of or trade in arms, munitions and
  war materials;

  (iv) relating to government procurement indispensable for national
  security or for national defence purposes; or

  (v) taken in time of war or other emergency in international
  relations.

  (c) to prevent the EC Party or a Signatory ESA State from taking any
  action in order to carry out obligations it has accepted for the
  purpose of maintaining international peace and security.

  2. The Parties shall inform each other to the fullest extent possible
  of measures taken under paragraphs 1(b) and (c) and of their
  termination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Taxation" article_identifier="24435">1. Nothing in this Agreement or in any arrangement adopted under this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the EC Party or a Signatory
  ESA State from distinguishing, in the application of the relevant
  provisions of their fiscal legislation, between taxpayers who are not
  in the same situation, in particular with regard to their place of
  residence or with regard to the place where their capital is invested.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement or in any arrangement adopted under this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement of
  any measure aimed at preventing the avoidance or evasion of taxes
  pursuant to the tax provisions of agreements to avoid double taxation
  or other tax arrangements or domestic fiscal legislation.

  3. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations
  of the EC Party or a Signatory ESA State under any tax convention. In
  the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and any such
  convention, that convention shall prevail to the extent of the
  inconsistency.

  Institutional, general and final provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Relations Between This Agreement And Comprehensive Epa" article_identifier="24436">In case there is any inconsistency between the comprehensive EPA and
  this Interim Agreement, the comprehensive EPA shall prevail to the
  extent of such inconsistency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Outermost Regions Of The European Community" article_identifier="24437">1. Taking account of the geographical proximity of the outermost
  regions of the EC and the ESA States and in order to reinforce
  economic and social links between these regions and the ESA States,
  the Parties shall endeavour to facilitate cooperation in all areas
  covered by this Agreement as well as to build and improve on existing
  trade in goods and services, promote investment and encourage
  transport and communication links between the outermost regions and
  the ESA States.

  2. The objectives enunciated in paragraph 1 shall also be pursued,
  wherever possible, through fostering the joint participation of the
  ESA States and the outermost regions in framework and specific
  programmes of the EC in areas covered by this Agreement.

  3. The EC Party shall endeavour to ensure coordination between the
  different financial instruments of the EC’s cohesion and development
  policies in order to foster cooperation between ESA States and the
  outermost regions of the EC in the areas covered by this Agreement.

  4. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent the EC Party from applying
  existing measures aimed at addressing the structural social and
  economic situation of the outermost regions pursuant to Article 299(2)
  of the Treaty establishing the European Community.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Definition Of The Parties And Fulfilment Of Obligations" article_identifier="24438">1. The Contracting Parties of this Agreement shall be the Union of
  Comoros, the Republic of Madagascar, the Republic of Mauritius, the
  Republic of Seychelles, the Republic of Zambia and the Republic of
  Zimbabwe hereinafter referred to as the "ESA States", on the
  one part, and the EC or its Member States or the EC and its Member
  States within their respective areas of competence as derived from the
  Treaty establishing the European Community, and hereinafter referred
  to as the "EC Party", on the other part for which this
  Agreement has entered into force or is provisionally applied.

  2. For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise expressly
  provided, the ESA States agree to act collectively. In cases where
  individual action is provided for or required to exercise the rights
  and/or comply with obligations under this Agreement, reference is made
  to "Signatory ESA State".

  3. The Parties or the Signatory ESA State(s) as the case may be shall
  adopt any general or specific measures required for them to fulfil
  their obligations under this Agreement and shall ensure that they
  comply with the objectives laid down in this Agreement.

  4. A Signatory ESA State which is not subject to the rights and
  obligations set out in Chapter II shall nevertheless be subject to and
  enjoy the rights and obligations arising from other Chapters of this
  Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Entry Into Force, Denunciation And Duration" article_identifier="24439">1. This Agreement shall be signed, ratified or approved in accordance
  with the applicable constitutional or internal rules and procedures of
  the respective Parties.

  2. This Agreement shall enter into force the first day of the first
  month following the deposit of the last instrument of ratification,
  acceptance or approval.

  3. Notifications of ratification, acceptance or approval shall be sent
  to the Secretary General of the Council of the European Union and to
  the Secretary General of the Common Market of the Eastern and Southern
  Africa, who shall be the depositories of this Agreement.

  4. Pending entry into force of the Agreement, the EC Party and the
  Signatory ESA States agree to apply the provisions of this Agreement
  which fall within their respective competences ("provisional
  application"). This may be effected either by provisional
  application where possible or by ratification of this Agreement.

  5. Provisional application shall be notified to the depositaries. This
  Agreement shall be applied provisionally 10 days after the last
  receipt of notification of provisional application from the EC or of
  ratification or provisional application from all Signatory ESA States
  listed in Annex II.

  6. Notwithstanding paragraphs 2 and 4, the EC Party and Signatory ESA
  States may unilaterally take steps to apply the agreement, before
  provisional application, to the extent feasible.

  7. The EC Party or a Signatory ESA State(s) may give written notice to
  the other of its intention to denounce this Agreement.

  8. Denunciation shall take effect one month after notification to the
  other Party.

  9. This Agreement shall remain in force until the comprehensive EPA
  enters into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Territorial Application" article_identifier="24440">This Agreement shall apply, on the one hand, to the territories in
  which the Treaty establishing the European Community is applied and
  under the conditions laid down in that Treaty, and, on the other hand,
  to the territories of Signatory ESA States. References in this
  Agreement to "territory" shall be understood in this sense.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Epa Committee" article_identifier="24441">1. An EPA Committee is hereby established.

  2. The EPA Committee shall be responsible for the administration of
  all matters under this Agreement, including development cooperation as
  provided for under Article 36 and for the fulfilment of any of the
  tasks mentioned in this Agreement.

  3. The EPA Committee shall be composed of representatives of the
  Parties. Each Party determines the organisation of its representation.

  4. The EPA Committee shall adopt its rules of procedure within three
  months of entry into force of the Interim Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Relationships With Other Agreements" article_identifier="24442">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall prejudice the application of
  measures deemed appropriate as provided for under Articles 11b, 96 and
  97 of the Cotonou Agreement and according to procedures set by these
  Articles.

  2. In the case of any inconsistency between the provisions of this
  Agreement and the provisions of Title II of Part 3 of the Cotonou
  Agreement, with the exception of the development cooperation
  provisions contained therein, the provisions of this Agreement shall
  prevail.

  3. The Parties acknowledge that some Signatory ESA States are not
  members of the WTO. Accordingly, references in this Agreement to WTO
  agreements (including the definitions provided therein) and WTO bodies
  or Committees shall not be construed as imposing on a Signatory ESA
  State that is not a member of the WTO any obligations arising from
  such WTO agreements or decisions of such bodies or Committees beyond
  the obligations expressly taken by such Signatory ESA State under this
  Agreement. Consequently, in the event of inconsistency between
  provisions of WTO agreements or decisions of WTO bodies or Committees
  on the one part and provisions of this Agreement, the latter shall
  always prevail in respect of Signatory ESA States who are not members
  of the WTO.

  4. The Parties agree that nothing in this Agreement requires them or
  the Signatory ESA States to act in a manner inconsistent with their
  WTO obligations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Accession" article_identifier="24443">1. Any of the following ESA States namely, the Republic of Djibouti,
  the State of Eritrea, the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia, the
  Republic of Malawi, the Republic of Sudan, may accede to this
  Agreement with the agreement of the Parties. This Agreement shall
  enter into force with respect to the acceding state in accordance with
  the applicable legal procedures of the EC Party and the ESA States and
  the acceding country. The EC shall endeavour to apply this Agreement
  to the acceding country as soon as possible.

  2. Any request for accession to this Agreement made by a State in the
  ESA region not listed in paragraph 1 shall be presented to the EPA
  Committee for determination.

  3. The EPA Committee may lay down the conditions and specific
  arrangements of the State referred to in paragraph 2 for its
  accession.

  4. This Agreement shall enter into force in relation to an acceding
  state on the date its instrument of accession is deposited.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Accession Of New Member States To The European Union" article_identifier="24444">1. The EPA Committee shall be advised of any request made by a third
  state to become a member of the EU. During the negotiations between
  the EU and the applicant State, the EC Party shall provide the ESA
  States with any relevant information and they in turn shall convey
  their concerns to the EC Party so that it can take them fully into
  account. The ESA States shall be notified by the EC Party of any
  accession to the EU.

  2. Any new Member State of the EU shall accede to this Agreement from
  the date of its accession by means of a clause to that effect in the
  act of accession. If the act of accession to the EU does not provide
  for such automatic accession to this Agreement, the EU Member State
  concerned shall accede by depositing an act of accession with the two
  depositaries, which shall arrange for certified copies to be sent to
  the ESA States.

  3. The Parties shall review the effects of the accession of new EU
  Member States on this Agreement. The EPA Committee may decide on any
  transitional or amending measures that might be necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Amendments" article_identifier="24445">1. Any amendments to this Agreement shall be adopted by the EPA
  Committee and shall enter into force when ratified.

  2. The EPA Committee shall adopt any transitional measures that may be
  required in respect of the amended provisions until they come into
  force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Authentic Texts" article_identifier="24446">This Agreement is drawn up in duplicate in the Bulgarian, Czech,
  Danish, Dutch, English, Estonian, Finnish, French, German, Greek,
  Hungarian, Italian, Latvian, Lithuanian, Maltese, Polish, Portuguese,
  Romanian, Slovak, Slovenian, Spanish and Swedish languages, each of
  these texts being equally authentic.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Annexes" article_identifier="24447">The Annexes and Protocols to this Agreement shall form an integral
  part thereof and may be reviewed and or amended by the EPA Committee.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="2931">
      <article article_identifier="24448">Съставено в Гранд Бей на двадесет и девети август две хиляди и девета
  година.

  Hecho en Grand Baie a veintinueve de agosto de dos mil nueve.

  V Grand Baie dne dvacátého devátého srpna dva tisíce devět.

  Udfærdiget i Grand Baie, den niogtyvende august to tusinde og ni.

  Geschehen zu Grand Baie am neunundzwanzigsten August zweitausendneun.

  Sõlmitud Grand Baies, kahe tuhande üheksanda aasta augusti kahekümne
  üheksandal päeval.

  Έγινε στην Grand Baie, στις είκοσι εννέα Αυγούστου δύο χιλιάδες εννιά.

  Done at Grand Baie on the twenty-ninth day of August in the year two
  thousand and nine.

  Fait à Grand Baie, le vingt-neuf août deux mille neuf.

  Fatto a Grand Baie, addì ventinove agosto duemilanove.

  Grand Baie, divi tūkstoši devītā gada divdesmit devītajā augustā.

  Priimta Grand Baie du tūkstančiai devintų metų rugpjūčio dvidešimt
  devintą dieną.

  Kelt Grand Baie-ben, a 2009. év augusztus hónapjának huszonkilencedik
  napján.

  Magħmul fi Grand Baie fid- disgħa u għoxrin jum ta’ Awwissu fis-sena
  elfejn u disgħa.

  Gedaan te Grand Baie, op de negenentwintigste dag van augustus in het
  jaar tweeduizend negen.

  Sporządzono w Grand Baie dnia dwudziestego dziewiątego sierpnia dwa
  tysiące dziewiątego roku.

  Feito em Grand Baie aos vinte e nove de Agosto de dois mil e nove.

  Încheiat la Grand Baie, la douăzeci și nouă august două mii nouă.

  V Grand Baie dvadsiateho deviateho augusta dvetisícdeväť.

  V Grand Baieju, devetinvajsetega avgusta dvatisočdevet.

  Tehty Grand Baiessa kahdentenakymmenentenäyhdeksäntenä päivänä
  elokuuta vuonna kaksituhattayhdeksän.

  Som skedde i Grand Baie den tjugonionde augusti år tjugohundranio.

  Pour l’Union des Comores

  Pour la République de Madagascar

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  For the Republic of Mauritius

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Pour la République des Seychelles

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  For the Republic of Zambia

  For the Republic of Zimbabwe

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  За Европейската общност

  Por la Comunidad Europea

  Za Evropské společenství

  For Det Europæiske Fællesskab

  Für die Europäische Gemeinschaft

  Euroopa Ühenduse nimel

  Για την Ευρωπαϊκή Κοινότητα

  For the European Community

  Pour la Communauté européenne

  Per la Comunità europea

  Eiropas Kopienas vārdā

  Europos bendrijos vardu

  az Európai Közösség részéről

  Għall-Komunità Ewropea

  Voor de Europese Gemeenschap

  W imieniu Wspólnoty Europejskiej

  Pela Comunidade Europeia

  Pentru Comunitatea Europeană

  Za Európske spoločenstvo

  za Evropsko skupnost

  Euroopan yhteisön puolesta

  På Europeiska gemenskapens vägnar

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  [1] For this calculation official data by the WTO on leading exporters
  in world merchandise trade (excluding intra-EU trade) shall be used.

  [2] For the purpose of this Article agricultural products are those
  covered by Annex I of the WTO Agreement on Agriculture.

  --------------------------------------------------</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
