<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Malaysia</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>22</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>20</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2005-12-13</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2006-07-13</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2006-07-12</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2021-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MYS</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MYS</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/malaysia/epa/content.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/policy/economy/fta/malaysia.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="271">
      <article article_identifier="2204">AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT OF JAPAN AND THE 
GOVERNMENT OF MALAYSIA FOR AN ECONOMIC PARTNERSHIP 


Preamble 


The Government of Japan and the Government of 
Malaysia, 


Recognising that a dynamic and rapidly changing global 
environment brought about by globalisation and 
technological progress presents various economic and 
strategic challenges and opportunities to the Countries; 


Conscious of their longstanding friendship and strong 
economic and political ties, that have developed through 
many years of fruitful and mutually beneficial co-operation 
between the Countries; 


Believing that such bilateral relationship will be 
enhanced by forging mutually beneficial economic 
partnership through co-operation, trade liberalisation and 
trade facilitation; 


Reaffirming that the economic partnership will provide 
a useful framework for enhanced co-operation and serve the 
common interests of the Countries in various fields as 
agreed in this Agreement and lead to the improvement of 
economic efficiency and the development of trade, 
investment and human resources; 


Recognising that such partnership would create larger 
and new market, and enhance the attractiveness and vibrancy 
of their markets; 


Recalling Article XXIV of the General Agreement on 
Tariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General 
Agreement on Trade in Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B, 
respectively, to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the 
World Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 
1994; 


Bearing in mind the Framework for Comprehensive 
Economic Partnership between Japan and the Association of 
Southeast Asian Nations (hereinafter referred to as 
“ASEAN”) signed in Bali, Indonesia on 8 October 2003; 


Convinced that this Agreement would open a new era for 
the relationship between the Countries; and 


Determined to establish a legal framework for an 
economic partnership between the Countries; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="272">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="2205">The objectives of this Agreement, to be pursued in 
accordance with its provisions, are: 



(a) 	to liberalise and facilitate trade in goods and 
services between the Countries; 



(b) 	to mutually improve investment opportunities and 
business environment, and ensure protection for 
investments and investment activities; 



(c) 	to establish a framework to enhance closer cooperation on socio-economic partnership, inter 
alia, by way of exchange of information, skills 
and technology in fields as agreed in this 
Agreement; 



(d) 	to ensure protection of intellectual property and 
to promote co-operation in the field thereof; 



(e) 	to encourage effective control of and promote cooperation in the field of anti-competitive 
activities; and 



(f) 	to create effective procedures for the 
implementation and application of this Agreement 
and for the resolution of disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="2206">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise 
specified: 



(a) 	the term “Countries” means Japan and Malaysia and 
the term “Country” means either Japan or 
Malaysia; 



(b) 	the term “GATS” means the General Agreement on 
Trade in Services in Annex 1B to the Marrakesh 
Agreement Establishing the World Trade 
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994, 
as may be amended; 



(c) 	the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement 
on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the 
Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade 
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994, 
as may be amended. For the purposes of this 
Agreement, references to articles in the GATT 
1994 include the interpretative notes; 



(d) 	the term “Governments” means the Government of 
Japan and the Government of Malaysia and the term 
“Government” means either the Government of Japan 
or the Government of Malaysia; 



(e) 	the term “Harmonized System (HS)” means the 
Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding 
System set out in the Annex to the International 
Convention on the Harmonized Commodity 
Description and Coding System, as may be amended, 
and adopted and implemented by the Countries in 
their respective laws; 



(f) 	the term “Japan” means all the territory of 
Japan, including its territorial sea, in which 
the laws and regulations of Japan are in force, 
and all the area beyond its territorial sea, 
including the sea-bed and subsoil thereof, over 
which Japan exercises sovereign rights or 
jurisdiction in accordance with international law 
and the laws and regulations of Japan; 



(g) 	the term “Malaysia” means the territories of the 
Federation of Malaysia, the territorial waters of 
Malaysia and the sea-bed and subsoil of the 
territorial waters, and the airspace above such 
areas, and includes any area extending beyond the 
limits of the territorial waters of Malaysia, and 
the sea-bed and subsoil of any such area, which 
has been or may hereafter be designated under the 
laws of Malaysia and in accordance with 
international law as an area over which Malaysia 
has sovereign rights or jurisdiction for the 
purposes of exploring and exploiting the natural 
resources, whether living or non-living; and 



(h) 	the term “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh 
Agreement Establishing the World Trade 
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994, 
as may be amended. 

Note: 	Nothing in subparagraphs (f) and (g) of this 
Article shall affect the rights and obligations 
of the Countries under international law, 
including those under the United Nations 
Convention on the Law of the Sea.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Transparency" article_identifier="2207">1. Each Country shall make publicly available its laws, 
regulations, administrative procedures and administrative 
rulings and judicial decisions of general application as 
well as international agreements to which the Country is a 
party, with respect to any matter covered by this 
Agreement. 



2. Each Government shall make easily available to the 
public, the names and addresses of the competent 
authorities responsible for laws, regulations, 
administrative procedures and administrative rulings, 
referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. 



3. Each Government shall, upon the request by the other 
Government, within a reasonable period of time, respond to 
specific questions from, and provide information to, the 
other Government in the English language with respect to 
matters referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. 



4. When introducing or changing its Country’s laws, 
regulations or administrative procedures that significantly 
affect the implementation and operation of this Agreement, 
each Government shall endeavour to provide, except in 
emergency situations, a reasonable interval between the 
time when such laws, regulations or administrative 
procedures are published or made publicly available and the 
time when they enter into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Public Comment" article_identifier="2208">Each Government shall, in accordance with the laws and 
regulations of the Country, endeavour to: 



(a) 	make public in advance regulations of general 
application that affect any matter covered by 
this Agreement; and 



(b) 	provide a reasonable opportunity for comments by 
the public and give consideration to those 
comments before adoption of such regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="2209">1. Where the administrative decisions which pertain to or 
affect the implementation and operation of this Agreement 
are taken by the competent authorities of a Government, the 
competent authorities shall, in accordance with the laws 
and regulations of the Country, endeavour to: 



(a) 	inform the applicant of the decision within a 
reasonable period of time after the submission of 
an application considered complete under the laws 
and regulations of the Country, taking into 
account the established standard period of time 
referred to in paragraph 3 of this Article; and 



(b) 	provide, within a reasonable period of time, 
information concerning the status of the 
application, at the request of the applicant. 

2. The competent authorities shall, in accordance with 
the laws and regulations of the Country, establish 
standards for taking administrative decisions in response 
to submitted applications. The competent authorities shall 
endeavour to: 



(a) 	make such standards as specific as possible; and 



(b) 	make such standards publicly available except 
when it would extraordinarily raise 
administrative difficulties for the Government. 

3. The competent authorities shall, in accordance with 
the laws and regulations of the Country, endeavour to: 



(a) 	establish standard periods of time between 
receipt of applications by the competent 
authorities and administrative decisions taken in 
response to submitted applications; and 



(b) 	make such periods of time publicly available, if 
it is established. 

4. The competent authorities shall, prior to any final 
decision which imposes obligations on or restricts rights 
of a person, endeavour to provide that person with: 



(a) 	a reasonable notice, including a description of 
the nature of the measure, specific provisions 
upon which such measure will be based, and the 
facts which may be a cause of taking such 
measure; and 



(b) 	a reasonable opportunity to present facts and 
arguments in support of position of such person, 

provided that time, nature of the measure and public 
interest permit and in accordance with the laws and 
regulations of the Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="2210">1. Each Country shall maintain judicial tribunals or 
procedures for the purpose of prompt review and, where 
warranted, correction of actions taken by the Government 
regarding matters covered by this Agreement. Such 
tribunals or procedures shall be independent of the 
authorities entrusted with the administrative enforcement 
of such actions. 



2. Each Country shall ensure that the parties in any such 
tribunals or procedures are provided with the right to: 



(a) 	a reasonable opportunity to support or defend 
their respective positions; and 



(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions 
of record. 


3. Each Country shall ensure, subject to appeal or 
further review as provided in its laws and regulations, 
that such decision is implemented by the relevant 
authorities with respect to the action at issue which is 
taken by the Government.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Administrative Guidance" article_identifier="2211">1. Where a competent authority of a Government renders 
administrative guidance with regard to any matter covered 
by this Agreement, such competent authority shall ensure 
that the administrative guidance does not exceed the scope 
of its competence and shall not require the person 
concerned to comply with its administrative guidance 
without voluntary co-operation. 



2. Such competent authority shall ensure, in accordance 
with the laws and regulations of its Country, that the 
person concerned not be treated unfavourably solely on 
account of non-compliance of such person with such 
administrative guidance. 



3. Such competent authority shall, in accordance with the 
laws and regulations of its Country, provide to the person 
concerned in writing, upon the request of such person, the 
purposes and contents of the administrative guidance. 



4. For the purposes of this Article, the term 
“administrative guidance” means guidance, recommendations, 
advice by a competent authority of either Government which 
require a person to do or refrain from doing any act but 
does not create, impose limitations on or in any way affect 
rights and obligations of such person in order to pursue 
administrative objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="2212">1. Each Government shall undertake, in accordance with 
the laws and regulations of its Country, to observe the 
confidentiality of information provided by the other 
Government. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article, the 
information provided under this Agreement may be 
transmitted to a third party subject to the prior written 
consent of the providing Government. 



3. Nothing in this Agreement shall require any Government 
to provide confidential information, the disclosure of 
which would impede law enforcement, or otherwise be 
contrary to the public interest, or which would prejudice 
legitimate commercial interests of particular enterprises, 
public or private. 



4. In the event of termination of this Agreement, the 
Countries agree that the provision of this Article shall 
continue to apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Taxation" article_identifier="2213">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, the 
provisions of this Agreement shall not apply to any 
taxation measures. 



2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and 
obligations of either Country under any tax convention. In 
the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and 
any such convention, that convention shall prevail to the 
extent of the inconsistency. 



3. Articles 3 and 8 shall apply to taxation measures, to 
the extent that the provisions of this Agreement are 
applicable to such taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="2214">1. For the purposes of Chapters 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7 other 
than Article 82, Articles XX and XXI of the GATT 1994 are 
incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis 
mutandis. 



2. For the purposes of Chapter 7 other than Article 82 
and Chapter 8, Articles XIV and XIV bis of the GATS are 
incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis 
mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="2215">1. The Countries reaffirm their rights and obligations 
under the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which 
both Countries are parties. 



2. In the event of any inconsistency between this 
Agreement and the WTO Agreement, the WTO Agreement shall 
prevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 



3. In the event of any inconsistency between this 
Agreement and any agreements other than the WTO Agreement, 
to which both Countries are parties, the Countries shall 
immediately consult with each other with a view to finding 
a mutually satisfactory solution, taking into consideration 
general principles of international law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="2216">The Governments shall conclude a separate agreement 
setting forth the details and procedures for the 
implementation of this Agreement (hereinafter referred to 
in this Agreement as “the Implementing Agreement”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="2217">1. A Joint Committee shall be established under this 
Agreement. 



2. 	The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing the implementation and operation of 
this Agreement; 



(b) 	submitting a report to the Countries through the 
contact points referred to in Article 15 on the 
implementation and operation of this Agreement; 



(c) 	considering and recommending to the Countries any 
amendments to this Agreement; 



(d) 	supervising and coordinating the work of all Sub-
Committees established under this Agreement; 



(e) 	adopting: 


(i) 	the Operational Procedures referred to in 
Chapter 3; and 


(ii) any necessary decisions; and 


(f) 	carrying out other functions as the Countries may 
agree. 


3. 	The Joint Committee: 



(a) 	shall be co-chaired by senior officials of the 
Governments, unless the Countries agree to 
convene the meeting at ministerial level; and 



(b) 	may establish and delegate its responsibilities 
to Sub-Committees. 


4. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules and 
procedures and financial arrangements. 



5. The Joint Committee shall convene its inaugural 
meeting within one year after this Agreement enters into 
force. Its subsequent meetings shall be held at such 
frequency as the Countries may agree upon. The Joint 
Committee shall convene alternately in Japan and Malaysia, 
unless the Countries agree otherwise. Special meetings of 
the Joint Committee may be convened, within 30 days upon 
the request of either Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Sub-Committees" article_identifier="2218">The following Sub-Committees shall be established on 
the date of entry into force of this Agreement: 



(a) 	Sub-Committee on Trade in Goods; 



(b) 	Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin; 



(c) 	Sub-Committee on Customs Procedures; 

(d) 

Sub-Committee on Technical Regulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment Procedures; 
(e) 

Sub-Committee on Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures; 
(f) 

Sub-Committee on Investment; 
(g) 

Sub-Committee on Trade in Services; 
(h) 

Sub-Committee on Intellectual Property; 
(i) 

Sub-Committee on Improvement of Business Environment; and 
(j) 

Sub-Committee on Co-operation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Communications" article_identifier="2219">Communications between the Countries on any matter 
relating to this Agreement shall be facilitated through the 
following contact points: 



(a) 	in the case of Japan, the Ministry of Foreign 
Affairs of Japan; and 



(b) 	in the case of Malaysia, the Ministry of Foreign 
Affairs of Malaysia.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="273">
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2220">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “bilateral safeguard measure” means a 
bilateral safeguard measure provided for in 
paragraph 1 of Article 23; 



(b) 	the term “customs duty” means any customs or 
import duty and a charge of any kind, imposed in 
connection with the importation of a good, but 
does not include any: 


(i) 	charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed 
consistently with the provisions of 
paragraph 2 of Article III of the GATT 1994, 
in respect of the like goods or, directly 
competitive or substitutable goods of the 
Country or in respect of goods from which 
the imported goods have been manufactured or 
produced in whole or in part; 


(ii) 	anti-dumping or countervailing duty applied 
pursuant to a Country’s law and applied 
consistently with the provisions of Article 
VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on 
Implementation of Article VI of the General 
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994, as may 
be amended, and the Agreement on Subsidies 
and Countervailing Measures in Annex 1A to 
the WTO Agreement, as may be amended; or 


(iii) 	fees or other charges commensurate with the 
cost of services rendered; 


(c) 	the term “customs value of goods” means the value 
of goods for the purposes of levying ad valorem 
customs duties on imported goods; 



(d) 	the term “domestic industry” means the producers 
as a whole of the like or directly competitive 
goods operating in the territory of a Country, or 
those whose collective output of the like or 
directly competitive goods constitutes a major 
proportion of the total domestic production of 
those goods; 



(e) 	the term “export subsidies” means export 
subsidies listed in Article 9 of the Agreement on 
Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as 
may be amended (hereinafter referred to in this 
Chapter as “the Agreement on Agriculture”); 



(f) 	the term “originating goods” means goods which 
qualify as originating goods under the provisions 
of Chapter 3; 



(g) 	the term “provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure” means a provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure provided for in subparagraph 9(a) of 
Article 23; 



(h) 	the term “serious injury” means a significant 
overall impairment in the position of a domestic 
industry; and 



(i) 	the term “threat of serious injury” means serious 
injury that, on the basis of facts and not merely 
on allegation, conjecture or remote possibility, 
is clearly imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="2221">The classification of goods in trade between the 
Countries shall be in conformity with the Harmonized 
System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="2222">Each Country shall accord national treatment to the 
goods of the other Country in accordance with Article III 
of the GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="2223">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
each Country shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties 
on originating goods of the other Country in accordance 
with its Schedule in Annex 1. 



2. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
neither Country shall increase any customs duty on 
originating goods of the other Country from the rate to be 
applied in accordance with its Schedule in Annex 1. 



3. On the request of either Country, the Countries shall 
negotiate on issues such as improving market access 
conditions on originating goods designated for negotiation 
in the Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the terms 
and conditions set out in such Schedule.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="2224">For the purposes of determining the customs value of 
goods traded between the Countries, provisions of Part I of 
the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of the 
General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to 
the WTO Agreement, as may be amended (hereinafter referred 
to in this Agreement as “the Agreement on Customs 
Valuation”), shall apply mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Export Subsidy" article_identifier="2225">Neither Country shall in accordance with the Agreement 
on Agriculture introduce or maintain any export subsidies 
on any agricultural good which is listed in Annex 1 to the 
Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Non-Tariff Measures" article_identifier="2226">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
each Country shall not introduce or maintain any non-tariff 
measures on the importation of any good of the other 
Country or on the exportation or sale for export of any 
good destined for the other Country which are inconsistent 
with its obligations under the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="2227">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, if an 
originating good of the other Country, as a result of the 
elimination or reduction of a customs duty in accordance 
with Article 19, is being imported into the territory of a 
Country in such increased quantities, in absolute terms or 
relative to domestic production, and under such conditions 
that the imports of that originating good constitute a 
substantial cause of serious injury, or threat thereof, to 
a domestic industry of the latter Country, the latter 
Country may, as a bilateral safeguard measure, to the 
minimum extent necessary to prevent or remedy the serious 
injury and to facilitate adjustment: 



(a) 	suspend the further reduction of any rate of 
customs duty on the originating good provided for 
in this Chapter; or 



(b) 	increase the rate of customs duty on the 
originating good to a level not to exceed the 
lesser of: 

(i) 	the most-favoured-nation applied rate of 
customs duty in effect at the time when the 
bilateral safeguard measure set out in this 
paragraph is taken; and 


(ii) 	the most-favoured-nation applied rate of 
customs duty in effect on the day 
immediately preceding the date of entry into 
force of this Agreement. 



2. Each Country shall not apply bilateral safeguard 
measures on an originating good imported up to the limit of 
quota quantities granted under tariff rate quotas applied 
in accordance with its Schedule in Annex 1. 



3. 	(a) A Country may take a bilateral safeguard measure 
only after an investigation has been carried out 
by the competent authorities of that Country in 
accordance with the same procedures as those 
provided for in Article 3 and paragraph 2 of 
Article 4 of the Agreement on Safeguards in Annex 
1A to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended 
(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “the 
Agreement on Safeguards”). 


(b) 	The investigation referred to in subparagraph (a) 
shall in all cases be completed within one year 
following its date of initiation. 


4. The following conditions and limitations shall apply 
with regard to a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) 	A Country shall immediately deliver a written 
notice to the other Country upon: 


(i) 	initiating an investigation referred to in 
subparagraph 3(a) of this Article relating 
to serious injury, or threat thereof, and 
the reasons for it; and 


(ii) 	taking a decision to apply or extend a 
bilateral safeguard measure. 


(b) 	The Country making the written notice referred to 
in subparagraph (a) shall provide the other 
Country with all pertinent information, which 
shall include: 


(i) 	in the written notice referred to in 
subparagraph (a)(i), the reason for the 
initiation of the investigation, a precise 
description of an originating good subject 
to the investigation and its subheading or a 
more detailed level of the Harmonized 
System, the period subject to the 
investigation and the date of initiation of 
the investigation; and 


(ii) 	in the written notice referred to in 
subparagraph (a)(ii), evidence of serious 
injury or threat thereof caused by the 
increased imports of the originating good, a 
precise description of the originating good 
subject to the proposed bilateral safeguard 
measure and its subheading or a more 
detailed level of the Harmonized System, a 
precise description of the bilateral 
safeguard measure, the proposed date of its 
introduction and its expected duration. 


(c) 	A Country proposing to apply or extend a 
bilateral safeguard measure shall provide 
adequate opportunity for prior consultations with 
the other Country with a view to reviewing the 
information arising from the investigation 
referred to in subparagraph 3(a) of this Article, 
exchanging views on the bilateral safeguard 
measure and reaching an agreement on compensation 
set out in paragraph 5 of this Article. 



(d) 	No bilateral safeguard measure shall be 
maintained except to the extent and for such time 
as may be necessary to prevent or remedy serious 
injury and to facilitate adjustment, provided 
that such time shall not exceed a period of four 
years. However, in very exceptional 
circumstances, a bilateral safeguard measure may 
be maintained for up to a total maximum period of 
five years. In order to facilitate adjustment in 
a situation where the expected duration of a 
bilateral safeguard measure is over one year, the 
Country maintaining the bilateral safeguard 
measure shall progressively liberalise the 
bilateral safeguard measure at regular intervals 
during the period of application. 



(e) 	No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied 
again to the import of a particular originating 
good which has been subject to such a bilateral 
safeguard measure, for a period of time equal to 
the duration of the previous bilateral safeguard 
measure or one year, whichever is longer. 



(f) 	Upon the termination of a bilateral safeguard 
measure, the rate of customs duty shall be the 
rate which would have been in effect but for the 
bilateral safeguard measure. 


5. 	(a) A Country proposing to apply or extend a 
bilateral safeguard measure shall provide to the 
other Country mutually agreed adequate means of 
trade compensation in the form of concessions of 
customs duties whose levels are substantially 
equivalent to the value of the additional customs 
duties expected to result from the bilateral 
safeguard measure. 



(b) 	If the Countries are unable to agree on the 
compensation within 30 days after the 
commencement of the consultation pursuant to 
subparagraph 4(c) of this Article, the Country 
against whose originating good the bilateral 
safeguard measure is taken shall be free to 
suspend the application of concessions of customs 
duties under this Agreement, which are 
substantially equivalent to the bilateral 
safeguard measure. 



(c) 	The right of suspension provided for in 
subparagraph (b) shall not be exercised for the 
first 18 months that a bilateral safeguard 
measure is in effect, provided that the bilateral 
safeguard measure has been taken as a result of 
an absolute increase in imports and that such a 
bilateral safeguard measure conforms to the 
provisions of this Article. The Country 
exercising the right of suspension may suspend 
the application of concessions of customs duties 
only for the minimum period necessary to achieve 
the substantially equivalent effects and only 
while the bilateral safeguard measure is 
maintained. 


6. Nothing in this Chapter shall prevent a Country from 
applying safeguard measures to an originating good in 
accordance with: 



(a) 	Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on 
Safeguards; or 



(b) 	Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture. 


7. Each Country shall ensure the consistent, impartial 
and reasonable administration of its laws and regulations 
relating to the bilateral safeguard measure. 



8. Each Country shall adopt or maintain equitable, 
timely, transparent and effective procedures relating to 
bilateral safeguard measure. 



9. 	(a) In critical circumstances, where delay would 
cause damage which it would be difficult to 
repair, a Country may take a provisional 
bilateral safeguard measure, which shall take the 
form of the measure set out in subparagraph 1(a) 
or (b) of this Article pursuant to a preliminary 
determination that there is clear evidence that 
increased imports of an originating good have 
caused or are threatening to cause serious injury 
to a domestic industry. 



(b) 	The Country shall deliver a written notice to the 
other Country prior to applying a provisional 
bilateral safeguard measure. Consultations 
between the Countries on the application of the 
provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall be 
initiated immediately after the provisional 
bilateral safeguard measure is taken. 



(c) 	The duration of the provisional bilateral 
safeguard measure shall not exceed 200 days. 
During that period, the pertinent requirements of 
paragraph 3 of this Article shall be met. The 
duration of the provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure shall be counted as a part of the period 
referred to in subparagraph 4(d) of this Article. 



(d) 	Paragraph 2, subparagraph 4(f) and paragraphs 7 
and 8 of this Article shall be applied mutatis 
mutandis to the provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure. The customs duty imposed as a result of 
the provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall 
be refunded if the subsequent investigation 
referred to in subparagraph 3(a) of this Article 
does not determine that increased imports of the 
originating good have caused or threatened to 
cause serious injury to a domestic industry. 


10. Written notice referred to in subparagraph 4(a) and 
subparagraph 9(b) of this Article and any other 
communication between the Countries shall be done in the 
English language. 



11. The Countries shall review the provisions of this 
Article, if necessary, after 10 years of the date of entry 
into force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="2228">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent 
a Country from taking any measure for balance-of-payments 
purposes. A Country taking such measure shall do so in 
accordance with the conditions established under Article 
XII and Section B of Article XVIII of the GATT 1994 and the 
Understanding on the Balance-of-Payments Provisions of the 
General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to 
the WTO Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude the use by a 
Country of exchange controls or exchange restrictions in 
accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the 
International Monetary Fund, as may be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Goods" article_identifier="2229">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Trade in Goods (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(c) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments; 
and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Co-Operation In The Field Of Automotive Industry" article_identifier="2230">The Countries shall co-operate, with the participation 
of their respective automotive industries, to further 
enhance competitiveness of the automotive industry in 
Malaysia.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="274">
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2231">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “competent governmental authority” means 
the authority of each Country that is responsible 
for the issuing of the certificate of origin or 
for the designation of the certification entities 
or bodies. In the case of Japan, the Ministry of 
Economy, Trade and Industry, and in the case of 
Malaysia, the Ministry of International Trade and 
Industry; 



(b) 	the term “customs authority” means the authority 
that, according to the legislation of each 
Country or a third State, is responsible for the 
administration and enforcement of its customs 
laws and regulations. In the case of Japan, the 
Ministry of Finance, and in the case of Malaysia, 
the Royal Malaysian Customs of the Ministry of 
Finance; 



(c) 	the term “exporter” means a person located in the 
territory of an exporting Country who exports a 
good from the territory of the exporting Country; 



(d) 	the terms “factory ships of the Country” and 
“vessels of the Country” respectively mean 
factory ships and vessels: 


(i) which are registered in the Country; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of the Country; 


(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 51 
percent by nationals of the Country, or by a 
juridical person with its head office in the 
territory of the Country, of which the 
representatives, chairman of the board of 
directors, and the majority of the members 
of such board are nationals of the Country, 
and of which at least 51 percent of the 
equity interest is owned by nationals or 
juridical persons of the Country; and 


(iv) 	of which at least 75 percent of the total of 
the master, officers and crew are nationals 
of the Countries or third States which are 
member countries of the ASEAN; 


(e) 	the term “fungible originating goods of a 
Country” or “fungible originating materials of a 
Country” respectively means originating goods or 
materials of a Country that are interchangeable 
for commercial purposes, whose properties are 
essentially identical; 



(f) 	the term “Generally Accepted Accounting 
Principles” means the recognised consensus or 
substantial authoritative support within a 
Country at a particular time as to which economic 
resources and obligations should be recorded as 
assets and liabilities, which changes in assets 
and liabilities should be recorded, how the 
assets and liabilities and changes in them should 
be measured, what information should be disclosed 
and how it should be disclosed, and which 
financial statements should be prepared. These 
standards may be broad guidelines of general 
application as well as detailed practices and 
procedures; 



(g) 	the term “importer” means a person who imports a 
good into the territory of the importing Country; 



(h) 	the term “indirect material” means a good used in 
the production, testing or inspection of another 
good but not physically incorporated into the 
good, or a good used in the maintenance of 
buildings or the operation of equipment 
associated with the production of another good, 
including: 


(i) 	fuel and energy; 


(ii) 	tools, dies and moulds; 


(iii) 	spare parts and goods used in the 
maintenance of equipment and buildings; 



(iv) 	lubricants, greases, compounding materials 
and other goods used in production or used 
to operate equipment and buildings; 


(v) 	gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safety 
equipment and supplies; 


(vi) 	equipment, devices and supplies used for 
testing or inspecting the goods; 

(vii) 	catalysts and solvents; and 


(viii) 	any other goods that are not incorporated 
into the good but whose use in the 
production of the good can reasonably be 
demonstrated to be a part of that 
production; 


(i) 	the term “material” means a good that is used in 
the production of another good; 



(j) 	the term “originating material of a Country” 
means an originating good of a Country which is 
used in the production of another good in the 
territory of the Country, including that which is 
considered as an originating material of the 
Country pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article 29; 



(k) 	the term “packing materials and containers for 
shipment” means goods that are used to protect a 
good during transportation, other than packaging 
materials and containers for retail sale referred 
to in Article 37; 



(l) 	the term “preferential tariff treatment” means 
the rate of customs duties applicable to an 
originating good of the exporting Country in 
accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 19; and 



(m) 	the term “production” means methods of obtaining 
goods including manufacturing, assembling, 
processing, raising, growing, breeding, mining, 
extracting, harvesting, fishing, trapping, 
gathering, collecting, hunting and capturing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="2232">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, a 
good shall qualify as an originating good of a Country 
where: 



(a) 	the good is wholly obtained or produced entirely 
in the territory of the Country, as defined in 
paragraph 2 of this Article; 



(b) 	the good is produced entirely in the territory of 
the Country exclusively from originating 
materials of the Country; or 



(c) 	the good satisfies the product specific rules set 
out in Annex 2, as well as all other applicable 
requirements of this Chapter, when the good is 
produced entirely in the territory of the Country 
using non-originating materials. 

2. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a) of this Article, 
the following goods shall be considered as being wholly 
obtained or produced entirely in the territory of a 
Country: 



(a) 	live animals born and raised in the territory of 
the Country; 



(b) 	animals obtained by hunting, trapping, fishing, 
gathering or capturing in the territory of the 
Country; 



(c) 	goods obtained from live animals in the territory 
of the Country; 



(d) 	plants and plant products harvested, picked or 
gathered in the territory of the Country; 



(e) 	minerals and other naturally occurring 
substances, not included in subparagraphs (a) 
through (d), extracted or taken in the territory 
of the Country; 



(f) 	goods of sea-fishing and other goods taken by 
vessels of the Country from the sea outside the 
territorial sea of a Country; 



(g) 	goods produced on board factory ships of the 
Country outside the territorial sea of the 
Country from the goods referred to in 
subparagraph (f); 



(h) 	goods taken from the seabed or subsoil beneath 
the seabed outside the territorial sea of the 
Country, provided that the Country has rights to 
exploit such seabed or subsoil in accordance with 
the provisions of the United Nations Convention 
on the Law of the Sea; 



(i) 	articles collected in the territory of the 
Country which can no longer perform their 
original purpose in the territory of the Country 
nor are capable of being restored or repaired and 
which are fit only for disposal or for the 
recovery of parts or raw materials; 



(j) 	scrap and waste derived from manufacturing or 
processing operations or from consumption in the 
territory of the Country and fit only for 
disposal or for the recovery of raw materials; 



(k) 	parts or raw materials recovered in the territory 
of the Country from articles which can no longer 
perform their original purpose nor are capable of 
being restored or repaired; and 



(l) 	goods obtained or produced in the territory of 
the Country exclusively from the goods referred 
to in subparagraphs (a) through (k). 


3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c) of this Article, 
the product specific rules set out in Annex 2 requiring 
that the materials used undergo a change in tariff 
classification or a specific manufacturing or processing 
operation shall apply only to non-originating materials. 



4. 	(a) For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c) of this 
Article, the product specific rules set out in 
Annex 2 using the value-added method require that 
the qualifying value content of a good, 
calculated in accordance with subparagraph (b) of 
this Article, is not less than the percentage 
specified by the rule for the good. 

(b) 	For the purposes of calculating the qualifying 
value content of a good, the following formula 
shall be applied: 


F.O.B. – V.N.M. 


Q.V.C. = --------------- x 100 


F.O.B. 


 Where: 


Q.V.C. is the qualifying value content of a 
good, expressed as a percentage; 


F.O.B. is, except as provided for in 
paragraph 5 of this Article, the free-on-board 
value of a good payable by the buyer of the good 
to the seller of the good, regardless of the mode 
of shipment, not including any internal excise 
taxes reduced, exempted, or repaid when the good 
is exported; and 


V.N.M. is the value of non-originating 
materials used in the production of a good. 


5. F.O.B. referred to in subparagraph 4(b) of this 
Article shall be the value: 



(a) 	adjusted to the first ascertainable price paid 
for the good from the buyer to the producer of 
the good, if there is free-on-board value of a 
good, but it is unknown and cannot be 
ascertained; or 



(b) 	determined in accordance with Articles 1 through 
8 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if there 
is no free-on-board value of the good. 

6. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value 
content of a good under subparagraph 4(b) of this Article, 
the value of a non-originating material used in the 
production of the good in the territory of a Country: 



(a) 	shall be determined in accordance with the 
Agreement on Customs Valuation, and shall include 
freight, insurance where appropriate, packing and 
all the other costs incurred in transporting the 
material to the importation port in the territory 
of the Country where the producer of the good is 
located; or 



(b) 	if such value is unknown and cannot be 
ascertained, shall be the first ascertainable 
price paid for the material in the territory of 
the Country, but may exclude all the costs 
incurred in the territory of the Country in 
transporting the material from the warehouse of 
the supplier of the material to the place where 
the producer is located such as freight, 
insurance and packing as well as any other known 
and ascertainable cost incurred in the territory 
of the Country. 


7. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value 
content of a good under subparagraph 4(b) of this Article 
in determining whether the good qualifies as an originating 
good of a Country, V.N.M. of the good shall not include the 
value of non-originating materials used in the production 
of originating materials of the Country which are used in 
the production of the good. 



8. For the purposes of subparagraph 5(b) or 6(a) of this 
Article, in applying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to 
determine the value of a good or non-originating material, 
the Agreement on Customs Valuation shall apply mutatis 
mutandis to domestic transactions or to the cases where 
there is no transaction of the good or non-originating 
material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="2233">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good 
qualifies as an originating good of a Country, an 
originating good of the other Country which is used as a 
material in the production of the good in the territory of 
the former Country may be considered as an originating 
material of the former Country. 



2. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value 
content of a good under subparagraph 4(b) of Article 28 in 
determining whether the good qualifies as an originating 
good of a Country, the value of a non-originating material 
produced in the territory of either Country and to be used 
in the production of the good may be limited to the value 
of non-originating materials used in the production of such 
non-originating material, provided that the good qualifies 
as an originating good of that Country under subparagraph 
1(c) of Article 28.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="2234">For the application of the product specific rules set 
out in Annex 2, non-originating materials used in the 
production of a good that do not satisfy an applicable rule 
for the good shall be disregarded, provided that the 
totality of such materials does not exceed specific 
percentages in value, weight or volume of the good and such 
percentages are set out in the product specific rule for 
the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="2235">A good shall not be considered to satisfy the 
requirement of change in tariff classification or specific 
manufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2 
solely by reason of: 



(a) 	operations to ensure the preservation of products 
in good condition during transport and storage 
(such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine) and 
other similar operations; 



(b) 	changes of packaging and breaking up and assembly 
of packages; 



(c) 	disassembly; 



(d) 	placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simple 
packaging operations; 



(e) 	collection of parts and components classified as 
a good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules 
for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 



(f) 	mere making-up of sets of articles; or 



(g) 	any combination of operations referred to in 
subparagraphs (a) through (f).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Consignment Criteria" article_identifier="2236">1. An originating good of the other Country shall be 
deemed to meet the consignment criteria when it is: 



(a) 	transported directly from the territory of the 
other Country; or 



(b) 	transported through third States for the purpose 
of transit or temporary storage in warehouses in 
such third States, provided that it does not 
undergo operations other than unloading, 
reloading or any other operation to preserve it 
in good condition. 

2. If the originating good of the other Country does not 
meet the consignment criteria referred to in paragraph 1 of 
this Article, that good shall not be considered as the 
originating good of the other Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Unassembled Or Disassembled Goods" article_identifier="2237">1. Where a good satisfies the requirements of the 
relevant provisions of Articles 28 through 31 and is 
imported into the territory of a Country from the territory 
of the other Country in a disassembled form but is 
classified as an assembled good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of 
the General Rules for the Interpretation of the Harmonized 
System, such a good shall be considered as an originating 
good of the other Country. 



2. A good assembled in the territory of a Country from 
unassembled or disassembled materials, which were imported 
into the territory of the Country and classified as an 
assembled good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules 
for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System, shall be 
considered as an originating good of the Country, provided 
that the good would have satisfied the applicable 
requirements of the relevant provisions of Articles 28 
through 31 had each of the non-originating materials among 
the unassembled or disassembled materials been imported 
into the territory of the Country separately and not as an 
unassembled or disassembled form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="2238">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good 
qualifies as an originating good of a Country, where 
fungible originating materials of the Country and fungible 
non-originating materials that are commingled in an 
inventory are used in the production of the good, the 
origin of the materials may be determined pursuant to an 
inventory management method under the Generally Accepted 
Accounting Principles in the territory of the Country. 



2. Where fungible originating goods of a Country and 
fungible non-originating goods are commingled in an 
inventory and, prior to exportation do not undergo any 
production process or any operation in the territory of the 
Country where they were commingled other than unloading, 
reloading or any other operation to preserve them in good 
condition, the origin of the good may be determined 
pursuant to an inventory management method under the 
Generally Accepted Accounting Principles in the territory 
of the Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="2239">Indirect materials shall be, without regard to where 
they are produced, considered to be originating materials 
of a Country where a good is produced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Accessories, Spare Parts And Tools" article_identifier="2240">1. In determining whether all the non-originating 
materials used in the production of a good undergo the 
applicable change in tariff classification or a specific 
manufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2, 
accessories, spare parts or tools delivered with the good 
that form part of the good's standard accessories, spare 
parts or tools, shall be disregarded, provided that: 



(a) 	the accessories, spare parts or tools are not 
invoiced separately from the good, without regard 
of whether they are separately described in the 
invoice; and 



(b) 	the quantities and value of the accessories, 
spare parts or tools are customary for the good. 

2. If the good is subject to a qualifying value content 
requirement, the value of the accessories, spare parts or 
tools shall be taken into account as the value of 
originating materials of a Country where the good is 
produced or non-originating materials, as the case may be, 
in calculating the qualifying value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Packaging Materials And Containers For Retail Sale" article_identifier="2241">1. In determining whether all the non-originating 
materials used in the production of a good undergo the 
applicable change in tariff classification or a specific 
manufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2, 
packaging materials and containers for retail sale, which 
are classified with the good pursuant to Rule 5 of the 
General Rules for the Interpretation of the Harmonized 
System, shall be disregarded. 



2. If the good is subject to a qualifying value content 
requirement, the value of such packaging materials and 
containers for retail sale shall be taken into account as 
the value of originating materials of a Country where the 
good is produced or non-originating materials, as the case 
may be, in calculating the qualifying value content of the 
good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Packing Materials And Containers For Shipment" article_identifier="2242">Packing materials and containers for shipment shall be: 



(a) 	disregarded in determining whether all the non-
originating materials used in the production of a 
good undergo the applicable change in tariff 
classification or a specific manufacturing or 
processing operation set out in Annex 2; and 



(b) 	without regard to where they are produced, 
considered to be originating materials of a 
Country where the good is produced, in 
calculating the qualifying value content of the 
good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Claim For Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="2243">1. The importing Country shall require a certificate of 
origin for an originating good of the exporting Country 
from importers who claim the preferential tariff treatment 
for the good. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article, the 
importing Country shall not require a certificate of origin 
from importers for: 



(a) 	an importation of a consignment of originating 
goods of the exporting Country whose aggregate 
customs value does not exceed 1000 United States 
dollars or its equivalent amount in the Country’s 
currency, or such higher amount as it may 
establish; or 



(b) 	an importation of an originating good of the 
exporting Country, for which the importing 
Country has waived the requirement for a 
certification of origin. 


3. Where an originating good of the exporting Country is 
imported through third States, the importing Country may 
require importers, who claim the preferential tariff 
treatment for the good, to submit: 



(a) 	a copy of through bill of lading; or 



(b) 	a certificate or any other information given by 
the customs authorities of such third States or 
other relevant entities, which evidences that it 
has not undergone operations other than 
unloading, reloading or any other operation to 
preserve it in good condition in those third 
States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="2244">1. The certificate of origin referred to in paragraph 1 
of Article 39 shall be issued by the competent governmental 
authority of the exporting Country on request having been 
made in writing by the exporter or its authorised agent. 
Such certificate of origin shall include minimum data 
specified in Annex 3. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, the competent 
governmental authority of the exporting Country may 
designate other entities or bodies to be responsible for 
the issuance of the certificate of origin, under the 
authorisation given in accordance with the applicable laws 
and regulations of the exporting Country. 



3. Where the competent governmental authority of the 
exporting Country designates other entities or bodies to 
carry out the issuance of the certificate of origin, the 
exporting Country shall notify in writing the other Country 
of its designees. 



4. For the purposes of this Chapter, upon the entry into 
force of this Agreement, the Countries shall establish a 
format of the certificate of origin in the English language 
in the Operational Procedures referred to in Article 50. 



5. The certificate of origin shall be completed in the 
English language. 



6. The issued certificate of origin shall be applicable 
to a single importation of an originating good of the 
exporting Country into the territory of the importing 
Country and be valid for 12 months from the date of 
issuance. 



7. Where the exporter is not the producer of a good, the 
exporter may request a certificate of origin on the basis 
of: 



(a) 	a declaration provided by the exporter to the 
competent governmental authority or its designees 
based on the information provided by the producer 
of the good to that exporter; or 



(b) 	a declaration voluntarily provided by the 
producer of the good directly to the competent 
governmental authority or its designees by the 
request of the exporter. 


8. The certificate of origin shall be issued only after 
the exporter who requests a certificate of origin, or the 
producer of a good in the territory of the exporting 
Country referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of this Article, 
proves to the competent governmental authority or its 
designees that the good to be exported qualifies as an 
originating good of the exporting Country. 



9. The competent governmental authority of the exporting 
Country shall provide the other Country with specimen 
signatures and impressions of stamps used in the offices of 
the competent governmental authority of the exporting 
Country or its designees. 



10. Each Country shall ensure that the competent 
governmental authority or its designees shall keep a record 
of the certificates of origin issued for a period of five 
years after the date on which the certificate was issued. 
Such record will include all antecedents, which were 
presented to prove the qualification as an originating good 
of the exporting Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Advance Rulings" article_identifier="2245">The importing Country shall endeavour to, prior to the 
importation of a good, issue a written advance ruling as to 
whether the good to be imported qualifies as an originating 
good of the exporting Country to importers of the good of 
the exporting Country or their authorised agents and 
exporters, and producers of the good in the territory of 
the exporting Country or their authorised agents, where a 
written application is made with all the necessary 
information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Obligations Regarding Exportations" article_identifier="2246">Each Country shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, ensure that the exporter to whom a certificate 
of origin has been issued, or the producer of a good in the 
territory of the exporting Country referred to in 
subparagraph 7(b) of Article 40: 



(a) 	shall notify in writing the competent 
governmental authority of the exporting Country 
or its designees without delay when he knows that 
such good does not qualify as an originating good 
of the exporting Country; and 



(b) 	shall keep the records relating to the origin of 
a good for five years after the date on which the 
certificate of origin was issued.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Request For Checking Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="2247">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good 
imported from the territory of the other Country under 
preferential tariff treatment qualifies as an originating 
good of the other Country, the relevant authority of the 
importing Country may request information relating to the 
origin of the good from the competent governmental 
authority of the exporting Country on the basis of a 
certificate of origin, where it has reasonable doubt as to 
the authenticity of the certificate of origin or the 
accuracy of the information included in the certificate of 
origin. 


Note: The term “relevant authority of the importing 


Country” referred to in Articles 43 through 46 


means: 



(a) 	in the case of Japan, the customs authority; and 



(b) 	in the case of Malaysia, the Ministry of 
International Trade and Industry. 


2. For the purposes of paragraph 1 of this Article, the 
competent governmental authority of the exporting Country 
shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, provide 
the information requested within a period of three months 
from the date of receipt of the request. 


If the relevant authority of the importing Country 
considers necessary, it may require additional information 
relating to the origin of the good. If additional 
information is requested by the relevant authority of the 
importing Country, the competent governmental authority of 
the exporting Country shall, in accordance with its laws 
and regulations, provide the information requested within a 
period of two months from the date of receipt of the 
request. 


3. For the purposes of paragraph 2 of this Article, the 
competent governmental authority of the exporting Country 
may request the exporter to whom a certificate of origin 
has been issued, or the producer of the good in the 
territory of the exporting Country referred to in 
subparagraph 7(b) of Article 40, to provide the former with 
the information requested.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Verification Visit" article_identifier="2248">1. If the relevant authority of the importing Country is 
not satisfied with the outcome of the request for checking 
pursuant to Article 43, it may request the exporting 
Country: 



(a) 	to collect and provide information relating to 
the origin of the good and check, for that 
purpose, the facilities used in the production of 
the good, through a visit by its competent 
governmental authority along with the relevant 
authority of the importing Country to the 
premises of the exporter to whom a certificate of 
origin has been issued, or the producer of the 
good in the territory of the exporting Country 
referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 40; 
and 



(b) 	during or after the visit, to provide information 
relating to the origin of the good in the 
possession of the competent governmental 
authority or its designee. 


2. When requesting the exporting Country to conduct a 
visit pursuant to paragraph 1 or 6 of this Article, the 
importing Country shall deliver a written communication 
with such request to the exporting Country at least 40 days 
in advance of the proposed date of the visit, the receipt 
of which is to be confirmed by the latter Country. The 
competent governmental authority of the exporting Country 
shall request the written consent of the exporter, or the 
producer of the good in the territory of the exporting 
Country whose premises are to be visited. 



3. The communication referred to in paragraph 2 of this 
Article shall include: 



(a) 	the identity of the relevant authority issuing 
the communication; 



(b) 	the name of the exporter, or the producer of the 
good in the territory of the exporting Country 
whose premises are requested to be visited; 



(c) 	the proposed date and place of the visit; 



(d) 	the objective and scope of the proposed visit, 
including specific reference to the good subject 
of the verification referred to in the 
certificate of origin; and 



(e) 	the names and titles of the officials of the 
relevant authority of the importing Country to be 
present during the visit. 


4. The exporting Country shall respond in writing to the 
importing Country, within 30 days of the receipt of the 
communication referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article, 
if it accepts or refuses to conduct a visit requested 
pursuant to paragraph 1 or 6 of this Article. 



5. The competent governmental authority of the exporting 
Country shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, 
provide within 45 days or any other mutually agreed period 
from the last day of the visit, to the relevant authority 
of the importing Country the information obtained pursuant 
to paragraph 1 or 6 of this Article. 



6. 	(a) In cases where the relevant authority of the 
importing Country considers as exceptional, that 
relevant authority may, before or during the 
request for checking referred to in Article 43, 
put forward the exporting Country a request 
referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. 

(b) 	Where the request referred to in subparagraph (a) 
is made, Article 43 shall not be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Determination Of Origin And Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="2249">1. The relevant authority of the importing Country may 
deny preferential tariff treatment to a good for which an 
importer claims preferential tariff treatment where the 
good does not qualify as an originating good of the 
exporting Country or where the importer fails to comply 
with any of the relevant requirements of this Chapter. 



2. The competent governmental authority of the exporting 
Country shall, when it cancels the decision to issue the 
certificate of origin, promptly notify the cancellation to 
the exporter to whom the certificate of origin has been 
issued, and to the relevant authority of the importing 
Country except where the certificate has been returned to 
the competent governmental authority. The relevant 
authority of the importing Country may determine that the 
good does not qualify as an originating good of the 
exporting Country and may deny preferential tariff 
treatment when it receives the notification. 



3. The relevant authority of the importing Country may 
determine that a good does not qualify as an originating 
good of the exporting Country and may deny preferential 
tariff treatment, and a written determination thereof shall 
be sent to the competent governmental authority of the 
exporting Country: 



(a) 	where the competent governmental authority of the 
exporting Country fails to respond to the request 
within the period referred to in paragraph 2 of 
Article 43 or paragraph 5 of Article 44; 



(b) 	where the exporting Country refuses to conduct a 
visit, or that Country fails to respond to the 
communication referred to in paragraph 2 of 
Article 44 within the period referred to in 
paragraph 4 of Article 44; or 



(c) 	where the information provided to the relevant 
authority of the importing Country pursuant to 
Article 43 or 44, is not sufficient to prove that 
the good qualifies as an originating good of the 
exporting Country. 


4. After carrying out the procedures outlined in Article 
43 or 44 as the case may be, the relevant authority of the 
importing Country shall provide the competent governmental 
authority of the exporting Country with a written 
determination of whether or not the good qualifies as an 
originating good of the exporting Country, including 
findings of fact and the legal basis for the determination. 
The competent governmental authority of the exporting 
Country shall inform such determination by the relevant 
authority of the importing Country to the exporter, or the 
producer of the good in the territory of the exporting 
Country, whose premises were subject to the visit referred 
to in Article 44.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="2250">1. Each Country shall maintain, in accordance with its 
laws and regulations, the confidentiality of information 
provided to it as confidential pursuant to this Chapter, 
and shall protect that information from disclosure that 
could prejudice the competitive position of the persons 
providing the information. 



2. Information obtained by the relevant authority of the 
importing Country pursuant to this Chapter: 



(a) 	may only be used by such authority for the 
purposes of this Chapter; and 



(b) 	shall not be used by the importing Country in any 
criminal proceedings carried out by a court or a 
judge, unless the information is requested to the 
other Country and provided to the former Country, 
through the diplomatic channels or other channels 
established in accordance with the applicable 
laws of the requested Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Penalties And Measures Against False Declaration" article_identifier="2251">1. Each Country shall establish or maintain, in 
accordance with its laws and regulations, appropriate 
penalties or other sanctions against its exporters to whom 
a certificate of origin has been issued and its producers 
of the goods in the territory of the exporting Country 
referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 40, for 
providing false declaration or documents to its competent 
governmental authority or its designees prior to the 
issuance of certificate of origin. 



2. Each Country shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate 
against its exporters to whom a certificate of origin has 
been issued and its producers of the goods in the territory 
of the exporting Country referred to in subparagraph 7(b) 
of Article 40, for failing to notify in writing to the 
competent governmental authority of the exporting Country 
or its designees without delay after having known, after 
the issuance of certificate of origin, that such good does 
not qualify as an originating good of the exporting Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="2252">1. Communications between the importing Country and the 
exporting Country shall be conducted in the English 
language. 



2. For the application of the relevant product specific 
rules set out in Annex 2 and the determination of origin, 
any applicable valuation method under the Generally 
Accepted Accounting Principles in the territory of the 
exporting Country shall be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="2253">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Rules of Origin (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring: 


(i) 	the implementation and operation of this 
Chapter; 


(ii) 	any amendments to Annexes 2 and 3, proposed 
by either Country; and 


(iii) 	the Operational Procedures referred to in 
Article 50; 


(b) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(c) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments; 
and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Operational Procedures" article_identifier="2254">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement, 
the Joint Committee shall adopt the Operational Procedures 
that provide detailed regulations pursuant to which the 
customs authorities, the competent governmental authorities 
of the Countries defined in Article 27 and the relevant 
authorities of the Countries shall implement their 
functions under this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="275">
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Scope" article_identifier="2255">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures 
required for the clearance of goods traded between the 
Countries. 



2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Countries in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of each Country 
and within the competence and available resources of their 
respective customs authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2256">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “customs authority” means the customs 
authority as defined in subparagraph (b) of 
Article 27; and 



(b) 	the term “customs laws” means such laws and 
regulations administered and enforced by the 
customs authority of each Country concerning the 
importation, exportation, and transit of goods, 
as they relate to customs duties, charges, and 
other taxes, or to prohibitions, restrictions, 
and other similar controls with respect to the 
movement of controlled items across the boundary 
of the customs territory of each Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Transparency" article_identifier="2257">1. Each Country shall ensure that all relevant 
information of general application pertaining to its 
customs laws is publicly available in the Country. 



2. At the request of the interested person of the 
Countries, each Country shall endeavour to provide 
information relating to the specific customs matters raised 
by the interested person and pertaining to its customs 
laws. Each Country shall supply not only the information 
specifically requested but also any other pertinent 
information relating to customs matters which it considers 
the interested person should be made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="2258">1. Both Countries shall endeavour to apply customs 
procedures in a predictable, consistent and transparent 
manner. 



2. For prompt customs clearance of goods traded between 
the Countries, each Country shall: 



(a) 	make use of information and communications 
technology; 



(b) 	simplify its customs procedures; 



(c) 	harmonise its customs procedures, as far as 
possible, with relevant international standards 
and recommended practices such as those made 
under the auspices of the Customs Co-operation 
Council; and 



(d) 	promote co-operation, wherever appropriate, 
between: 

(i) 	its customs authority and other national 
authorities; and 


(ii) 	its customs authority and the trading 
communities of the Country. 


3. Each Country shall provide affected parties in its 
territory with accessible processes of administrative and 
judicial review in relation to the action taken by the 
Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Temporary Admission And Goods In Transit" article_identifier="2259">1. Each Country shall continue to facilitate the 
procedures for the temporary admission of goods traded 
between the Countries in accordance with the Customs 
Convention on the A.T.A. Carnet for the Temporary Admission 
of Goods, as may be amended (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the A.T.A. Convention”). 



2. Each Country shall continue to facilitate customs 
clearance of goods in transit from or to the territory of 
the other Country in accordance with paragraph 3 of Article 
V of the GATT 1994. 



3. The Countries shall endeavour to promote, through 
seminars and courses, the use of A.T.A. carnets pursuant to 
the A.T.A. Convention for the temporary admission of goods 
and the facilitation of customs clearance of goods in 
transit in the territories of the Countries or third 
States. 



4. For the purposes of this Article, the term “temporary 
admission” means customs procedures under which certain 
goods may be brought into a customs territory 
conditionally, relieved totally or partially from the 
payment of customs duties. Such goods shall be imported 
for a specific purpose, and shall be intended for re-
exportation within a specified period and without having 
undergone any change except normal depreciation due to the 
use made of them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Co-Operation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="2260">1. The Countries shall co-operate and exchange 
information with each other on customs matters. 



2. The co-operation and exchange of information on 
customs matters shall be implemented as provided for in the 
Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Capacity Building" article_identifier="2261">The area of co-operation pursuant to paragraph 2 of 
Article 56 shall include capacity building, such as 
training, technical assistance and exchange of experts.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Sub-Committee On Customs Procedures" article_identifier="2262">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Customs Procedures (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	identifying areas to be improved for facilitating 
trade between the Countries; 



(c) 	reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to 
the Joint Committee; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. The composition of the Sub-Committee shall be 
specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="276">
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="2263">1. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures as defined 
in the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A 
to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended (hereinafter 
referred to in this Agreement as “TBT Agreement”), and 
adopted by the Countries that may directly or indirectly 
affect trade in goods between the Countries. It shall not 
apply to purchasing specifications prepared by governmental 
bodies for production or consumption requirements of 
governmental bodies and sanitary and phytosanitary measures 
as defined in the Agreement on the Application of Sanitary 
and Phytosanitary Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement, as may be amended (hereinafter referred to in 
this Agreement as “SPS Agreement”). 



2. The Countries shall develop co-operation and conduct 
consultation in the field of technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures. 



3. The Countries, recognising the rights and obligations 
as referred to in Article 60, shall establish a framework 
under this Chapter for joint efforts of the Countries to 
ensure that technical regulations do not create unnecessary 
obstacles to the trade in goods between the Countries and 
for possible mutual recognition arrangements between the 
Countries in the most appropriate and cost-effective 
manner.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="2264">The Countries reaffirm their rights and obligations 
relating to technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures under the TBT Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Technical Regulations" article_identifier="2265">1. The Countries shall, where appropriate and consistent 
with their rights and obligations under the TBT Agreement, 
endeavour to work towards harmonisation of their respective 
technical regulations based on international standards, 
recommendations and guidelines. 



2. Each Country shall give positive consideration to 
accepting as equivalent technical regulations of the other 
Country, even if these regulations differ from its own, 
provided it is satisfied that these regulations adequately 
fulfil the objectives of its own regulations. 



3. A Country shall, upon the request of the other Country 
and where appropriate, explain the reasons why it has not 
accepted a technical regulation of the other Country as 
equivalent to its own. 



4. The Countries may co-operate with each other in the 
context of their participation in international 
standardising bodies to ensure that international standards 
developed within such organisations that are likely to 
become a basis for technical regulations are trade 
facilitating and do not create unnecessary obstacles to 
trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Acceptance Of Results Of Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="2266">1. Each Country shall ensure, whenever possible, that 
results of the conformity assessment procedures in the 
territory of the other Country are accepted, even when 
those procedures differ from its own, provided it is 
satisfied that the procedures offer an assurance of 
conformity with applicable technical regulations or 
standards equivalent to its own procedures. The Countries 
recognise that prior consultations may be necessary in 
order to arrive at a mutually satisfactory understanding 
with regard to such matters as provided for in paragraphs 



1.1 and 1.2 of Article 6 of the TBT Agreement. 



2. A Country shall, upon the request of the other Country 
and where appropriate, explain the reasons why it has not 
accepted the results of conformity assessment procedures in 
the territory of the other Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Mutual Recognition Arrangements" article_identifier="2267">1. Each Country, upon the request of the other Country, 
shall enter into negotiations for possible mutual 
recognition arrangements on the results of conformity 
assessment procedures, conducted by conformity assessment 
bodies of the exporting Country to assess conformity to 
importing Country’s requirements, in the sectors which both 
Countries agree upon. 



2. With a view to facilitating the negotiation for 
possible mutual recognition arrangements referred to in 
paragraph 1 of this Article: 



(a) 	the Countries shall take into consideration that 
a broad range of mechanisms exist to facilitate 
the acceptance of the results of conformity 
assessment procedures; 



(b) 	the Countries shall, recognising the existence of 
differences in the structure and operation of 
conformity assessment procedures in their 
respective territories, endeavour to make 
compatible the conformity assessment procedures 
to the greatest extent practicable; and 



(c) 	in order to build confidence in the reliability 
of results of conformity assessment procedures 
conducted by conformity assessment bodies of the 
other Country, a Country may consult with the 
other Country, as appropriate, on such matters as 
the technical competence of the conformity 
assessment bodies of the other Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Co-Operation" article_identifier="2268">1. Both Countries shall develop co-operation in the field 
of technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures. Such co-operation may include: 



(a) 	joint studies, seminars and symposia; 



(b) 	establishing or improving of infrastructure in 
calibration, testing, inspection, certification 
and accreditation to meet relevant international 
standards, recommendations and guidelines; 



(c) 	where appropriate, effectively using the existing 
framework for mutual recognition developed by 
relevant regional and international bodies; 



(d) 	research and development; 



(e) 	exchange of information; 



(f) 	exchange of Government officials for training 
purposes; and 



(g) 	technical assistance and co-operation in 
connection with the Countries’ compliance with 
the TBT Agreement. 

2. The implementation of this Article shall be subject to 
the availability of funds and the applicable laws and 
regulations of each Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="2269">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Technical Regulations, Standards and 
Conformity Assessment Procedures (hereinafter referred to 
in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	exchanging information on technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures; 



(b) 	exchanging lists of conformity assessment bodies 
registered or accredited by relevant registration 
or accreditation authorities of each Country; 



(c) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(d) 	undertaking consultation on issues related to 
technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures; 



(e) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(f) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(g) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall convene its inaugural meeting 
within one year after this Agreement enters into force and 
subsequently meet at such times as may be agreed by the 
Countries. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues as 
may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments, 
and may invite representatives of relevant 
entities other than the Governments with the 
necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be 
discussed; and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="2270">Each Government shall designate an enquiry point to 
answer all reasonable enquiries from the other Government 
regarding technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures and, if appropriate, provide the 
other Government with other relevant information which it 
considers the other Government should be made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="2271">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="277">
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Scope" article_identifier="2272">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary and 
phytosanitary (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as 
“SPS”) measures under the SPS Agreement, that may, directly 
or indirectly, affect trade in goods between the Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="2273">The Countries reaffirm their rights and obligations 
relating to SPS measures under the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Sub-Committee On Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="2274">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures 
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-
Committee”) established in accordance with Article 14 shall 
be: 



(a) 	exchanging information on such matters as 
occurrences of SPS incidents in the territories 
of the Countries and third States, and change or 
introduction of SPS related regulations and 
standards of the Countries, which may, directly 
or indirectly, affect trade in goods between the 
Countries; 



(b) 	notifying to either Country of information on 
potential SPS risks recognised by the other 
Country; 



(c) 	undertaking science-based consultation to 
identify and address specific issues that may 
arise from the application of SPS measures with 
the objective to achieve mutually acceptable 
solutions; 



(d) 	reviewing the implementation and operation of 
this Chapter; 



(e) 	reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to 
the Joint Committee; and 



(f) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. Both Countries, through the Sub-Committee, shall cooperate in the areas of SPS measures including capacity 
building, technical assistance and exchange of experts 
subject to the availability of appropriated funds and the 
applicable laws and regulations of each Country. 



3. The Sub-Committee shall convene its inaugural meeting 
within one year after this Agreement enters into force and 
subsequently meet at such times as may be agreed by the 
Countries. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues as 
may be agreed by the Countries. 



4. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments; 
and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments. 


5. The Sub-Committee may, if necessary, establish ad hoc 
technical working groups as its subsidiary bodies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="2275">Each Government shall designate an enquiry point to 
answer all reasonable enquiries from the other Government 
regarding SPS measures referred to in Article 68 and, if 
appropriate, provide the other Government with the relevant 
information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="2276">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="278">
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Scope" article_identifier="2277">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or 
maintained by a Country relating to: 



(a) 	investors of the other Country; and 



(b) 	investments of investors of the other Country in 
the former Country. 

2. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter 
and Chapter 8: 



(a) 	with respect to matters covered by Articles 75, 
76 and 79, Chapter 8 shall prevail to the extent 
of inconsistency; and 



(b) 	with respect to matters not falling under 
subparagraph (a), this Chapter shall prevail to 
the extent of inconsistency. 

3. Nothing in this Chapter shall impose any obligation on 
either Country regarding measures pursuant to immigration 
laws and regulations. 


Note: 	In respect of Malaysia, measures referred to in 
this paragraph include those pursuant to the 
immigration policies endorsed by the Cabinet, 
and announced and made publicly available in a 
written form by the Government of Malaysia.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2278">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	an enterprise is: 


(i) 	“owned” by an investor if more than 50 
percent of the equity interests in it is 
beneficially owned by the investor; and 


(ii) 	“controlled” by an investor if the investor 
has the power to name a majority of its 
directors or otherwise to legally direct its 
actions; 


(b) 	the term “enterprise of a Country” means any 
legal entity duly constituted or organised under 
the law of a Country, whether for profit or 
otherwise, and whether privately-owned or 
controlled or governmentally-owned or controlled, 
including any corporation, trust, partnership, 
joint venture, sole proprietorship, association, 
organisation, company or branch; 



(c) 	the term “financial services” shall have the same 
meaning as in subparagraph 5(a) of the Annex on 
Financial Services of the GATS; 



(d) 	the term “freely usable currency” means any 
currency that is widely used to make payments for 
international transactions and widely traded in 
the international principal exchange markets as 
defined under the Articles of Agreement of the 
International Monetary Fund, as may be amended; 



(e) 	the term “investments” means every kind of asset 
owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by 
an investor of a Country, including: 

(i) 	an enterprise; 


(ii) 	shares, stocks or other forms of equity 
participation in an enterprise, including 
rights derived therefrom; 


(iii) 	bonds, debentures, loans and other forms of 
debt, including rights derived therefrom; 



(iv) 	rights under contracts, including turnkey, 
construction, management, production or 
revenue-sharing contracts; 


(v) 	claims to money and claims to any 
performance under contract having a 
financial value; 


(vi) 	intellectual property rights, including 
copyrights, patent rights, and rights 
relating to utility models, trademarks, 
industrial designs, layout-designs of 
integrated circuits, new plant varieties, 
trade names, indications of source or 
geographical indications, undisclosed 
information, which are conferred pursuant to 
the laws and regulations of each Country; 

(vii) 	rights conferred pursuant to laws and 
regulations or contracts such as 
concessions, licences, authorisations and 
permits; and 


(viii) 	any other tangible and intangible, movable 
and immovable property, and any related 
property rights, such as mortgages, liens 
and pledges; 


Investments also include profits, capital gains, 
dividends, royalties, interests, fees and other 
current incomes accruing from investments. A 
change in the form in which assets are invested 
does not affect their character as investments. 


Note 1: 	Where an asset lacks the characteristics 
of an investment, that asset is not an 
investment regardless of the form it may 
take. The characteristics of an 
investment include the commitment of 
capital, the expectation of gain or 
profit, or the assumption of risk. 


Note 2: 	Whether a particular right conferred 
pursuant to laws and regulations or 
contracts, as referred to in 
subparagraph (vii), has the 
characteristics of an investment depends 
on such factors as the nature and extent 
of the rights that the holder has under 
the domestic law of the Country. For 
greater certainty, the foregoing is 
without prejudice to whether any asset 
associated with such right has the 
characteristics of an investment. 


Note 3: 	Investments do not include an order or 
judgment entered in a judicial or 
administrative action. 



(f) 	the term “investor of a Country” means a natural 
person of a Country or an enterprise of a 
Country, except branch of an enterprise of a 
third State which is located in the Country; 



(g) 	the term “natural person of a Country” means a 
natural person who resides in a Country or 
elsewhere and who under the law of the Country: 


(i) 	in respect of Japan, is a national of Japan; 
and 


(ii) 	in respect of Malaysia, is a national of 
Malaysia or has the right of permanent 
residence in Malaysia; and 


(h) 	the term “portfolio investment” means: 

(i) 	shares, stocks or other forms of equity 
participation in an enterprise traded in a 
securities exchange, which amount to less 
than 10 percent of the total capital of such 
enterprise; or 


(ii) 	debt securities, such as bonds, notes and 
financial derivatives, the original maturity 
of which is less than 12 months, unless such 
debt securities are arising out of intra-
company debt transactions between an 
investor of a Country and an enterprise in 
the other Country of which 10 percent or 
more of the shares, stocks, or other forms 
of equity are directly or indirectly owned 
by the investor, or which is directly or 
indirectly controlled by the investor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="2279">1. Each Country shall accord to investors of the other 
Country and to their investments treatment no less 
favourable than that it accords in like circumstances to 
its own investors and to their investments with respect to 
the establishment, acquisition, expansion, management, 
operation, maintenance, use, possession, liquidation, sale, 
or other disposition of investments (hereinafter referred 
to in this Chapter as “investment activities”). 



2. This Article shall not apply to the establishment, 
acquisition and expansion of portfolio investments. 



3. Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 1 of this 
Article, each Country may prescribe special formalities in 
connection with the establishment of investments by 
investors of the other Country in the former Country such 
as the compliance with registration requirements, provided 
that such special formalities do not impair the substance 
of the rights under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="2280">Each Country shall accord to investors of the other 
Country and to their investments treatment no less 
favourable than that it accords in like circumstances to 
investors of a third State and to their investments, with 
respect to investment activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="2281">Each Country shall accord to investments of investors 
of the other Country fair and equitable treatment and full 
protection and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Access To The Courts Of Justice" article_identifier="2282">Each Country shall in that Country accord to investors 
of the other Country treatment no less favourable than the 
treatment which it accords in like circumstances to its own 
investors or investors of a third State with respect to 
access to its courts of justice and administrative 
tribunals and agencies, both in pursuit and in defence of 
such investors’ rights. 


Note: 	This Article shall apply in respect of taxation 
measures, where Article 81 applies to taxation 
measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Prohibition Of Performance Requirements" article_identifier="2283">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, the Annex to the 
Agreement on Trade-Related Investment Measures in Annex 1A 
to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended, is incorporated 
into and forms part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 



2. The Countries shall enter into further consultations, 
at the earliest possible time. The aim of such 
consultations is to review issues pertaining to prohibition 
of performance requirements within five years from the date 
of entry into force of this Agreement. 



3. The aim of consultations referred to in paragraph 2 of 
this Article may include the review of reservations 
relating to prohibition of performance requirements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Reservations And Exceptions" article_identifier="2284">1. Articles 75 and 76 and paragraph 1 of Article 79 shall 
not apply to: 



(a) 	any existing non-conforming measure that is 
maintained by the following, as set out in 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities listed in 
Annex 4 and indicated with an asterisk (“*”): 


(i) 	the central government of a Country; or 


(ii) 	a prefecture of Japan or a state of 
Malaysia, as set out in Annex 4 in 
accordance with paragraph 5 of this Article; 


(b) 	any existing non-conforming measure that is 
maintained by a local government of a Country 
other than prefectures and states referred to in 
subparagraph (a)(ii); 



(c) 	the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs 


(a) and (b); or 


(d) 	an amendment or modification of any measure 
referred to in subparagraphs (a) and (b), 
provided that the amendment or modification does 
not decrease the level of conformity of the 
measure, as it existed immediately before the 
amendment or modification, with Articles 75 and 
76 and paragraph 1 of Article 79. 


2. Each Country reserves the right to adopt or maintain 
any measure not conforming with the obligations imposed by 
Articles 75 and 76 and paragraph 1 of Article 79, for 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities listed in Annex 4 other 
than those referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. 



3. Any amendment or modification of an existing measure 
or adoption of a new measure for sectors, sub-sectors or 
activities referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article, 
shall not be more restrictive to existing investors and 
existing investments than the measure applied to such 
investors and investments immediately before such amendment 
or modification or adoption, unless such sectors, sub-
sectors or activities are indicated with the symbol “+” in 
Annex 4. 



4. 	For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) 	the terms “existing investors” and “existing 
investments” mean respectively investors whose 
investments are present in a Country, and 
investments that are present in a Country, 
immediately before the modification or amendment 
of existing measures, or adoption of new 
measures; and 



(b) 	any expansion or diversification of existing 
investments by existing investors after the 
modification or amendment of existing measures or 
adoption of new measures shall not be regarded as 
existing investments to the extent of such 
expansion or diversification. 


5. Each Country shall set out in Annex 4, within six 
months after the entry into force of this Agreement, any 
existing non-conforming measure, with an asterisk (“*”), 
maintained by a prefecture or a state as referred to in 
subparagraph 1(a)(ii) of this Article and shall notify 
thereof the other Country by a diplomatic note. 



6. Neither Country may, under any measure adopted 
pursuant to paragraph 2 of this Article after the entry 
into force of this Agreement, require an investor of the 
other Country, by reason of its nationality, to sell or 
otherwise dispose of an investment existing at the time the 
measure becomes effective, unless otherwise specified in 
the initial approval by the relevant authority. 



7. In cases where a Country makes an amendment or 
modification of existing measures or adopts new measures 
with respect to sectors, sub-sectors or activities listed 
in Annex 4: 



(a) 	that Country shall notify the other Country to 
the extent possible, the amendment or 
modification or new measures, and whenever 
possible prior to implementation, if not, as soon 
as possible thereafter; and 



(b) 	that Country upon the request by the other 
Country shall hold consultation in good faith 
with that other Country with a view to achieving 
mutual satisfaction. 


8. Notwithstanding the provisions of this Article, each 
Country may, in exceptional financial, economic or 
industrial circumstances, adopt exceptional measure 
inconsistent with Articles 75 and 76 and paragraph 1 of 
Article 79 in the sectors, sub-sectors or activities listed 
in Annex 4 with an asterisk (“*”), provided that such 
Country shall, to the extent possible prior to the entry 
into force of the measure, or as soon as possible 
thereafter: 



(a) 	notify the other Country of the elements of the 
measure; and 



(b) 	hold, upon the request by the other Country, 
consultations in good faith with the other 
Country with a view to achieving mutual 
satisfaction and take appropriate action 
thereafter. 


9. Each Country shall endeavour, where appropriate, to 
reduce or eliminate the reservations specified in Annex 4. 



10. Articles 75, 76 and 79 shall not apply to any measure 
that a Country adopts or maintains with respect to 
government procurement. 



11. Articles 75 and 76 shall not apply to any measure 
covered by an exception to, or derogation from, the 
obligations under Articles 3 and 4 of the Agreement on 
Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights in 
Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended 
(hereinafter referred to as “the TRIPS Agreement”), as 
specifically provided in those Articles and in Article 5 of 
the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="2285">1. Neither Country shall take any measures of or 


equivalent to expropriation or nationalisation against the 
investments in that Country of investors of the other 
Country (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as 
“expropriation”) except: 



(a) 	for a lawful or public purpose; 



(b) 	on a non-discriminatory basis; 



(c) 	in accordance with due process of law; and 



(d) 	upon payment of prompt, adequate and effective 
compensation. 

2. Such compensation shall be equivalent to the fair 
market value of the expropriated investments: 



(a) 	at the time when or immediately before the 
expropriation was publicly announced; or 



(b) 	when the expropriation occurred, 

whichever is the earlier. 



3. The fair market value shall not reflect any change in 
market value occurring because the expropriation had become 
publicly known earlier. 



4. The compensation shall be paid without delay and shall 
carry an appropriate interest, taking into account the 
length of time from the time of expropriation until the 
time of payment. It shall be: 



(a) 	effectively realisable; 



(b) 	freely transferable; and 



(c) 	freely convertible at the market exchange rate 
prevailing on the date of the expropriation into 
the currency of the Country of the investors 
concerned and freely usable currencies. 


5. This Article shall apply to taxation measures, to the 
extent that such taxation measures constitute 
expropriation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="2286">1. Each Country shall accord to investors of the other 
Country that have suffered loss or damage relating to their 
investment activities in the former Country due to armed 
conflict or state of emergency such as revolution, 
insurrection, civil disturbance or any other similar event 
in the former Country, treatment, as regards restitution, 
indemnification, compensation or any other settlement, that 
is no less favourable than that which it accords to its own 
investors or to investors of a third State, whichever is 
more favourable to the investors of the other Country. 



2. Any payments made pursuant to paragraph 1 of this 
Article shall be effectively realisable, freely convertible 
and freely transferable.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Transfers" article_identifier="2287">1. Each Country shall allow all transfers to be made into 
and out of that Country freely and without delay in any 
freely usable currency. Such transfers shall include: 



(a) 	the initial capital and additional amounts to 
maintain or increase investments; 



(b) 	profits, capital gains, dividends, royalties, 
interest, fees and other current incomes accruing 
from investments of the investors of the other 
Country; 



(c) 	proceeds from the total or partial sale or 
liquidation of investments of investors of the 
other Country; 



(d) 	payments made under a contract including loan 
payments in connection with investments; 



(e) 	earnings, remuneration and other compensation of 
personnel from the other Country who work in 
connection with investments in the former 
Country; 



(f) 	payments made in accordance with Articles 81 and 
82; and 



(g) 	payments arising out of the settlement of a 
dispute under Article 85. 


2. Each Country shall allow transfers referred to in 
paragraph 1 of this Article to be made in a freely usable 
currency at the market rate of exchange prevailing on the 
date of the transfer. 



3. Subject to paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, each 
Country shall accord to the transfer referred to in 
paragraph 1 of this Article treatment no less favourable 
than that accorded to the transfer originating from 
investments made by investors of any third State. 



4. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, a 
Country may delay or prevent a transfer referred to in 
paragraph 1 of this Article through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good-faith application of its laws 
relating to: 



(a) 	bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of the 
rights of creditors; 



(b) 	issuing, trading or dealing in securities; 



(c) 	criminal or penal offences; 



(d) 	ensuring compliance with orders or judgments in 
adjudicatory proceedings; or 



(e) 	obligations of investors arising from social 
security and public retirement plans.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="2288">1. If a Country or its designated agency makes a payment 
to any of its investors pursuant to an indemnity, guarantee 
or insurance contract, pertaining to an investment of that 
investor within the other Country, the other Country shall: 



(a) 	recognise the assignment, to the former Country 
or its designated agency, of any right or claim 
of the investor that formed the basis of such 
payment; and 



(b) 	recognise the right of the former Country or its 
designated agency to exercise by virtue of 
subrogation any such right or claim to the same 
extent as the original right or claim of the 
investor. 

2. Articles 81, 82 and 83 shall apply mutatis mutandis as 
regards payment to be made to the Country or its designated 
agency mentioned in paragraph 1 of this Article by virtue 
of such assignment of right or claim, and the transfer of 
such payment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Settlement Of Investment Disputes Between A Country And An Investor Of The Other Country" article_identifier="2289">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, an “investment 
dispute” is a dispute between a Country and an investor of 
the other Country that has incurred loss or damage by 
reason of, or arising out of, an alleged breach of any 
right conferred by this Chapter with respect to the 
investments of the investor of the other Country. 


Note: 	This Article shall apply in respect of taxation 
measures, where Article 81 applies to taxation 
measures. 


2. Nothing in this Article shall be construed so as to 
prevent an investor who is a party to an investment dispute 
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “disputing 
investor”) from seeking administrative or judicial 
settlement within the Country that is a party to the 
investment dispute (hereinafter referred to in this Article 
as “disputing Country”). 



3. An investment dispute shall, as far as possible, be 
settled amicably through consultations between the parties 
to the investment dispute. 



4. If the investment dispute cannot be settled through 
such consultations within five months from the date on 
which the disputing investor requested for the 
consultations in writing and if the disputing investor 
concerned has not submitted the investment dispute for 
resolution under administrative or judicial settlement, the 
disputing investor may: 



(a) 	submit the investment dispute to the Kuala Lumpur 
Regional Centre for Arbitration (hereinafter 
referred to as “KLRCA”) for settlement by 
conciliation or arbitration; 



(b) 	submit the investment dispute to conciliation or 
arbitration in accordance with the provisions of 
the Convention on the Settlement of Investment 
Disputes between States and Nationals of Other 
States done at Washington, March 18, 1965, as may 
be amended; 



(c) 	submit the investment dispute to arbitration 
under the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations 
Commission on International Trade Law, adopted by 
the United Nations Commission on International 
Trade Law on April 28, 1976, as may be amended; 
or 



(d) 	if agreed with the disputing Country, submit the 
investment dispute to arbitration in accordance 
with other arbitration rules. 


5. The applicable arbitration rules shall govern the 
arbitration referred to in this Article except to the 
extent modified in this Article. 



6. The disputing investor who intends to submit the 
investment dispute to conciliation or arbitration pursuant 
to paragraph 4 of this Article shall give to the disputing 
Country written notice of intent to do so at least 90 days 
before the claim is submitted. The notice of intent shall 
specify: 



(a) 	the name and address of the disputing investor; 



(b) 	the specific measures of the disputing Country at 
issue and a brief summary of the factual and 
legal basis of the dispute sufficient to present 
the problem clearly, including the provisions of 
this Chapter alleged to have been breached; and 



(c) 	the dispute settlement procedures set forth in 
paragraph 4 of this Article which the disputing 
investor will seek. 


7. Each Country hereby consents to the submission of 
investment disputes by a disputing investor to conciliation 
or arbitration chosen by the disputing investor as provided 
for in paragraph 4 of this Article. If more than three 
years have elapsed since the date the disputing investor 
knew or ought to have known, whichever is the earlier, of 
the loss or damage which, it is alleged, has been incurred 
by the disputing investor, the consent above shall be 
invalidated. 



8. Notwithstanding paragraph 4 of this Article and 
subject to the laws of the disputing Country, the disputing 
investor may initiate or continue an action that seeks 
interim injunctive relief that does not involve the payment 
of damages before an administrative tribunal or a court of 
justice. 



9. Unless the disputing investor and the disputing 
Country (hereinafter referred to as “the disputing 
parties”) agree otherwise, an arbitral tribunal established 
under subparagraphs 4(a), (b) and (c) of this Article shall 
comprise three arbitrators, one arbitrator appointed by 
each of the disputing parties and the third, who shall be 
the presiding arbitrator, appointed by agreement of the 
disputing parties. If the disputing investor or the 
disputing Country fails to appoint an arbitrator within 60 
days from the date on which the investment dispute was 
submitted to arbitration, the Director of KLRCA, in the 
case of arbitration referred to in subparagraph 4(a) of 
this Article, or the Secretary-General of the International 
Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (hereinafter 
referred to in this Article as “ICSID”), in the case of 
arbitration referred to in subparagraphs 4(b) and (c) of 
this Article, on the request of either of the disputing 
parties, shall appoint, in his or her discretion, the 
arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed from the KLRCA 
or ICSID Panel of Arbitrators respectively subject to the 
requirement of paragraphs 10 and 11 of this Article. 



10. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the 
third arbitrator shall not be of the same nationality as 
the disputing investor, nor be a national of the disputing 
Country, nor have his or her usual place of residence in 
either of the Countries, nor be employed by either of the 
disputing parties, nor have dealt with the investment 
dispute in any capacity. 



11. In the case of arbitration referred to in 
subparagraphs 4(a), (b) and (c) of this Article, each of 
the disputing parties may indicate up to three 
nationalities, the appointment of arbitrators of which is 
unacceptable to it. In this event, the Director of KLRCA, 
in the case of arbitration referred to in subparagraph 4(a) 
of this Article, or the Secretary-General of ICSID, in the 
case of arbitration referred to in subparagraphs 4(b) and 

(c) of this Article, may not appoint as arbitrator any 
person whose nationality is indicated by any of the 
disputing parties. 



12. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the 
arbitration shall be held in the disputing Country. 



13. On written notice to the disputing parties, the 
Country other than the disputing Country may make 
submission to the arbitral tribunal on a question of 
interpretation of this Agreement. 



14. 	The award shall include: 



(a) 	a judgment whether or not there has been a breach 
by the disputing Country of any rights conferred 
by this Chapter in respect of the disputing 
investor and its investments; and 



(b) 	a remedy if there has been such breach. The 
remedy shall be limited to one or both of the 
following: 

(i) 	payment of monetary damages and applicable 
interest; and 


(ii) 	restitution of property, in which case the 
award shall provide that the disputing 
Country may pay monetary damages and any 
applicable interest in lieu of restitution. 


Costs may also be awarded in accordance with the 
applicable arbitration rules. 



15. The award rendered in accordance with paragraph 14 of 
this Article shall be final and binding upon the disputing 
parties. The disputing Country shall carry out without 
delay the provisions of any such award and provide in the 
disputing Country for the enforcement of such award in 
accordance with its relevant laws and regulations. 



16. Neither Country shall, in respect of an investment 
dispute which one of its investors shall have submitted to 
arbitration in accordance with paragraph 4 of this Article, 
give diplomatic protection, or bring an international claim 
before another forum, unless the other Country shall have 
failed to abide by and comply with the award rendered in 
such investment dispute. Diplomatic protection, for the 
purposes of this paragraph, shall not include informal 
diplomatic exchanges for the sole purpose of facilitating a 
settlement of the investment dispute. 



17. This Article shall not apply to any dispute arising 
between a Country and an investor of the other Country on 
any right or privileges conferred or created by Articles 75 
and 79. 



18. An investor of a Country whose investments are not 
made in compliance with the laws and regulations of the 
other Country which are not inconsistent with this 
Agreement: 



(a) 	shall not be entitled to submit an investment 
dispute to conciliation or arbitration referred 
to in paragraph 4 of this Article; and 



(b) 	shall not resort to dispute settlement procedures 
under Chapter 13 as a means to settle the 
investment disputes between the investor and the 
other Country. 

Note: 	For the purposes of this paragraph, in respect 
of Malaysia, investments that are not made in 
compliance with the laws and regulations 
include investments that are not made in 
compliance with national policies endorsed by 
the Cabinet and announced and made publicly 
available in a written form by the Government 
of Malaysia.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Facilitation Of Movement Of Investors" article_identifier="2290">1. Subject to its immigration laws and regulations 
relating to entry, stay and authorisation to work, each 
Country shall grant entry, temporary stay and authorisation 
to work to investors, and executives, managers and members 
of the board of directors of an enterprise of the other 
Country, for the purpose of establishing, developing, 
administering or advising on the operation in the former 
Country of an investment to which they, or an enterprise of 
the other Country that employs such executives, managers 
and members of the board of directors, have committed or 
are in the process of committing a substantial amount of 
capital or other resources, so long as they continue to 
meet the requirements of this Article. 


Note: 	In respect of Malaysia, its obligations under 
this paragraph are also subject to the 
immigration policies, relating to entry, stay 
and authorisation to work, endorsed by the 
Cabinet, and announced and made publicly 
available in a written form by the Government 
of Malaysia. 


2. Each Country shall, to the extent possible, make 
publicly available, requirements and procedures for 
application for a renewal of the period of temporary stay, 
a change of status of temporary stay or an issuance of a 
work permit for a natural person of the other Country who 
has been granted entry and temporary stay with respect to 
an investment. Each Country shall endeavour to facilitate 
the procedures to the extent possible, in accordance with 
its laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="2291">In cases where a Country takes any measure pursuant to 
Article 10 that does not conform with the obligations of 
the provisions of this Chapter other than the provisions of 
Article 82, that Country shall so notify the other Country, 
to the extent possible prior to the entry into force of the 
measure, or if not, as soon thereafter as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="2292">1. A Country may adopt or maintain measures not 
conforming with its obligations under Article 75 relating 
to cross-border capital transactions and Article 83: 



(a) 	in the event of serious balance-of-payments and 
external financial difficulties or threat 
thereof; or 



(b) 	in cases where, in exceptional circumstances, 
movements of capital cause or threaten to cause 
serious difficulties for macroeconomic management 
in particular, monetary and exchange rate 
policies. 

2. 	Measures referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article: 



(a) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, as 
may be amended, as applicable; 



(b) 	shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the 
circumstances set out in paragraph 1 of this 
Article; 



(c) 	shall be temporary and shall be eliminated as 
soon as conditions permit or be phased out 
progressively as the situation specified in 
paragraph 1 of this Article improves; and 



(d) 	shall be promptly notified to the other Country. 

3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be regarded as altering 
the rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Country 
as a party to the Articles of Agreement of the 
International Monetary Fund, as may be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Prudential Measures" article_identifier="2293">Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Chapter, 
a Country shall not be prevented from taking measures 
relating to financial services for prudential reasons, 
including measures for the protection of investors, 
depositors, policy holders or persons to whom a fiduciary 
duty is owed by an enterprise supplying financial services, 
or to ensure the integrity and stability of the financial 
system. Where such measures do not conform with the 
provisions of this Chapter, they shall not be used as a 
means of avoiding the Country’s commitments or obligations 
under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Environmental Measures" article_identifier="2294">Each Country shall not encourage investments by 
investors of the other Country by relaxing its 
environmental measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="2295">1. A Country may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an 
investor of the other Country that is an enterprise of the 
other Country and to an investment of such investor if 
investors of a third State own or control the enterprise, 
and the denying Country: 



(a) 	does not maintain diplomatic relations with the 
third State; or 



(b) 	adopts or maintains measures with respect to the 
third State that prohibit transactions with the 
enterprise or that would be violated or 
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were 
accorded to the enterprise or to its investments. 

2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, a 
Country may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an 
investor of the other Country that is an enterprise of the 
other Country and to investments of such investor if 
investors of a third State own or control the enterprise 
and the enterprise has no substantial business activities 
in the Country under whose law it is constituted or 
organised.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Co-Operation In Promotion And Facilitation Of Investments" article_identifier="2296">1. Both Countries shall co-operate in promoting and 
facilitating investments between the Countries through ways 
such as: 



(a) 	discussing effective ways on investment promotion 
activities and capacity building; 



(b) 	facilitating the provision and exchange of 
investment information including information on 
their laws, regulations and policies to increase 
awareness on investment opportunities; and 



(c) 	encouraging and supporting investment promotion 
activities of each Country or their business 
sectors. 

2. The implementation of this Article shall be subject to 
the availability of funds and the applicable laws and 
regulations of each Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Sub-Committee On Investment" article_identifier="2297">1. For the purposes of effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Investment (hereinafter referred to in this 
Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in accordance 
with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	exchanging information on any matters related to 
this Chapter; 



(b) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter and the reservations 
set out in Annex 4; 



(c) 	undertaking consultation to review the issues 
pertaining to the prohibition of performance 
requirements; 



(d) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter, 
including issues related to co-operation in the 
promotion and facilitation of investments; 



(e) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(f) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments; 
and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="279">
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="2298">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Country 
affecting trade in services. 



2. 	This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) 	in respect of air transport services, measures 
affecting traffic rights, however granted; or to 
measures affecting services directly related to 
the exercise of traffic rights, other than 
measures affecting: 


(i) 	aircraft repair and maintenance services; 


(ii) 	the selling and marketing of air transport 
services; and 


(iii) computer reservation system services; 


(b) 	cabotage in maritime transport services; 



(c) 	subsidies provided by a Country or a state 
enterprise thereof, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance; and 



(d) 	measures affecting natural persons seeking access 
to the employment market of a Country, or 
measures regarding nationality or citizenship, or 
residence or employment on a permanent basis. 


3. Articles 96, 97 and 101 shall not apply to any measure 
by a Country with respect to government procurement. 



4. Article 101 shall not apply to any measure by a 
Country pursuant to immigration laws and regulations. 



5. This Chapter shall not prevent a Country from applying 
measures to regulate the entry of natural persons of the 
other Country into, or their temporary stay in, its 
territory, including those measures necessary to protect 
the integrity of, and to ensure the orderly movement of 
natural persons across, its borders, provided that such 
measures are not applied in such a manner as to nullify or 
impair the benefits accruing to the other Country under the 
terms of a specific commitment. 


Note: 	The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural 
persons of a certain nationality or citizenship 
and not for those of others shall not be 
regarded as nullifying or impairing benefits 
under a specific commitment. 


6. Annex 5 provides supplementary provisions to this
definitions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2299">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “aircraft repair and maintenance 
services” means such activities when undertaken 
on an aircraft or a part thereof while it is 
withdrawn from service and does not include so-
called line maintenance; 



(b) 	the term “commercial presence” means any type of 
business or professional establishment, including 
through: 

(i) 	the constitution, acquisition or maintenance 
of a juridical person; or 


(ii) 	the creation or maintenance of a branch or a 
representative office, 


within a Country for the purposes of supplying a 
service; 



(c) 	the term “computer reservation system services” 
means services provided by computerized systems 
that contain information about air carriers’ 
schedules, availability, fares and fare rules, 
through which reservations can be made or tickets 
may be issued; 



(d) 	the term “juridical person” means any legal 
entity duly constituted or otherwise organised 
under applicable law, whether for profit or 
otherwise, and whether privately-owned or 
governmentally-owned, including any corporation, 
trust, partnership, joint venture, sole 
proprietorship or association; 



(e) 	the term “juridical person of the other Country” 
means a juridical person which is either: 

(i) 	constituted or otherwise organised under the 
law of the other Country and is engaged in 
substantive business operations in the other 
Country; or 


(ii) 	in the case of the supply of a service 
through commercial presence, owned or 
controlled by: 


(AA) natural persons of the other Country; 
or 


(BB) juridical persons of the other Country 
identified under subparagraph (i) of 
this paragraph; 



(f) 	a juridical person is: 


(i) 	“owned” by persons of a Country or a third 
State if more than 50 percent of the equity 
interest in it is owned by such persons; 


(ii) 	“controlled” by persons of a Country or a 
third State if such persons have the power 
to name a majority of its directors or 
otherwise to legally direct its actions; and 


(iii) 	“affiliated” with another person when it 
controls, or is controlled by, that other 
person; or when it and the other person are 
both controlled by the same person; 


(g) 	the term “measure” means any measure by a 
Country, whether in the form of a law, 
regulation, rule, procedure, decision, 
administrative action or any other form; 


Note: 	The term “measure” shall include taxation 
measures to the extent covered by the 
GATS. 


(h) 	the term “measures by a Country” means measures 
taken by: 


(i) 	central or local governments and 
authorities; and 


(ii) 	non-governmental bodies in the exercise of 
powers delegated by central or local 
governments or authorities; 


(i) 	the term “measures by a Country affecting trade 
in services” includes measures in respect of: 


(i) the purchase, payment or use of a service; 


(ii) 	the access to and use of, in connection with 
the supply of a service, services which are 
required by a Country to be offered to the 
public generally; and 


(iii) 	the presence, including commercial presence, 
of persons of a Country for the supply of a 
service in the other Country; 


(j) 	the term “monopoly supplier of a service” means 
any person, public or private, which in the 
relevant market of a Country is authorised or 
established formally or in effect by that Country 
as the sole supplier of that service; 



(k) 	the term “natural person of the other Country” 
means a natural person who resides in the other 
Country or elsewhere and who under the law of the 
other Country: 


(i) 	in respect of Japan, is a national of Japan; 
and 


(ii) 	in respect of Malaysia, is a national of 
Malaysia or has the right of permanent 
residence in Malaysia; 


(l) 	the term “sector” of a service means: 


(i) 	with reference to a specific commitment, one 
or more, or all, sub-sectors of that 
service, as specified in a Country’s 
Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6; 
or 


(ii) 	otherwise, the whole of that service sector, 
including all of its sub-sectors; 


(m) 	the term “selling and marketing of air transport 
services” means opportunities for the air carrier 
concerned to sell and market freely its air 
transport services including all aspects of 
marketing such as market research, advertising 
and distribution. These activities do not 
include the pricing of air transport services nor 
the applicable conditions; 



(n) 	the term “service consumer” means any person that 
receives or uses a service; 



(o) 	the term “service of the other Country” means a 
service which is supplied: 


(i) 	from or in the other Country, or in the case 
of maritime transport, by a vessel 
registered under the laws of the other 
Country, or by a person of the other Country 
which supplies the service through the 
operation of a vessel or its use in whole or 
in part; or 


(ii) 	in the case of the supply of a service 
through commercial presence or through the 
presence of natural persons, by a service 
supplier of the other Country; 


(p) 	the term “services” includes any service in any 
sector except services supplied in the exercise 
of governmental authority; 



(q) 	the term “service supplied in the exercise of 
governmental authority” means any service which 
is supplied neither on a commercial basis nor in 
competition with one or more service suppliers; 



(r) 	the term “service supplier” means any person that 
supplies a service; 


Note: 	Where the service is not supplied directly 
by a juridical person but through other 
forms of commercial presence such as a 
branch or a representative office, the 
service supplier (i.e. the juridical 
person) shall, nonetheless, through such 
presence be accorded the treatment 
provided for service suppliers under this 
Chapter. Such treatment shall be extended 
to the presence through which the service 
is supplied and need not be extended to 
any other parts of the supplier located 
outside the Country where the service is 
supplied. 


(s) 	the term “service supplier of the other Country” 
means any natural person of the other Country or 
juridical person of the other Country, that 
supplies a service; 



(t) 	the term “state enterprise” means an enterprise 
owned or controlled by a Country; 



(u) 	the term “supply of a service” includes the 
production, distribution, marketing, sale and 
delivery of a service; 



(v) 	the term “trade in services” means the supply of 
a service: 


(i) 	from within one Country into the other 
Country (“cross-border supply mode”); 


(ii) 	in one Country to the service consumer of 
the other Country (“consumption abroad 
mode”); 


(iii) 	by a service supplier of one Country, 
through commercial presence in the other 
Country (“commercial presence mode”); and 


(iv) 	by a service supplier of one Country, 
through presence of natural persons of that 
Country in the other Country (“presence of 
natural persons mode”); and 


(w) 	the term “traffic rights” means the rights for 
scheduled and non-scheduled services to operate 
and/or to carry passengers, cargo and mail for 
remuneration or hire from, to, within, or over 
the territory of a Country, including points to 
be served, routes to be operated, types of 
traffic to be carried, capacity to be provided, 
tariffs to be charged and their conditions, and 
criteria for designation of airlines, including 
such criteria as number, ownership and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Market Access" article_identifier="2300">1. With respect to market access through the modes of 
supply defined in paragraph (v) of Article 95, each Country 
shall accord services and service suppliers of the other 
Country treatment no less favourable than that provided for 
under the terms, limitations and conditions agreed and 
specified in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 


6. 


Note: 	If a Country undertakes a market-access 
commitment in relation to the supply of a 
service through the mode of supply referred to 
in subparagraph (v)(i) of Article 95 and if the 
cross-border movement of capital is an 
essential part of the service itself, that 
Country is thereby committed to allow such 
movement of capital. If a Country undertakes a 
market-access commitment in relation to the 
supply of a service through the mode of supply 
referred to in subparagraph (v)(iii) of Article 
95, it is thereby committed to allow related 
transfers of capital into that Country. 


2. In sectors where market-access commitments are 
undertaken, the measures which a Country shall not maintain 
or adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision or 
on the basis of its entirety, unless otherwise specified in 
its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6, are 
defined as: 



(a) 	limitations on the number of service suppliers 
whether in the form of numerical quotas, 
monopolies, exclusive service suppliers or the 
requirements of an economic needs test; 



(b) 	limitations on the total value of service 
transactions or assets in the form of numerical 
quotas or the requirement of an economic needs 
test; 



(c) 	limitations on the total number of service 
operations or on the total quantity of service 
output expressed in terms of designated numerical 
units in the form of quotas or the requirement of 
an economic needs test; 


Note: 	This subparagraph does not cover measures 
of a Country which limit inputs for the 
supply of services. 


(d) 	limitations on the total number of natural 
persons that may be employed in a particular 
service sector or that a service supplier may 
employ and who are necessary for, and directly 
related to, the supply of a specific service in 
the form of numerical quotas or the requirement 
of an economic needs test; 



(e) 	measures which restrict or require specific types 
of legal entity or joint venture through which a 
service supplier may supply a service; and 



(f) 	limitations on the participation of foreign 
capital in terms of maximum percentage limit on 
foreign shareholding or the total value of 
individual or aggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="2301">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of Specific 
Commitments in Annex 6, and subject to any conditions and 
qualifications set out therein, each Country shall accord 
to services and service suppliers of the other Country, in 
respect of all measures affecting the supply of services, 
treatment no less favourable than that it accords to its 
own like services and service suppliers. 


Note: 	Specific commitments assumed under this Article 
shall not be construed to require either 
Country to compensate for any inherent 
competitive disadvantages which result from the 
foreign character of the relevant services or 
service suppliers. 


2. A Country may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 of 
this Article by according to services and service suppliers 
of the other Country, either formally identical treatment 
or formally different treatment to that it accords to its 
own like services and service suppliers. 



3. Formally identical or formally different treatment 
shall be considered to be less favourable if it modifies 
the conditions of competition in favour of services or 
service suppliers of a Country compared to like services or 
service suppliers of the other Country. 



4. A Country shall not invoke the preceding paragraphs of 
this Article under Chapter 13 with respect to a measure of 
the other Country that falls within the scope of an 
international agreement between them relating to the 
avoidance of double taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Additional Commitments" article_identifier="2302">The Countries may negotiate commitments with respect 
to measures affecting trade in services not subject to 
scheduling under Articles 96 and 97, including those 
regarding qualifications, standards or licensing matters. 
Such commitments shall be inscribed in a Country’s Schedule 
of Specific Commitments in Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Schedule Of Specific Commitments" article_identifier="2303">1. Each Country shall set out in a schedule the specific 
commitments it undertakes under Articles 96, 97 and 98. 
Schedules of Specific Commitments shall be annexed to this 
Agreement as Annex 6. 



2. With respect to sectors where the specific commitments 
are undertaken, each Schedule of Specific Commitments in 
Annex 6 shall specify: 



(a) 	terms, limitations and conditions on market 
access; 



(b) 	conditions and qualifications on national 
treatment; 



(c) 	undertakings relating to additional commitments; 
and 



(d) 	where appropriate, the time-frame for 
implementation of such commitments. 


3. With respect to sectors or sub-sectors where the 
specific commitments are undertaken in Annex 6 and which 
are indicated with “SS”, any terms, limitations, conditions 
and qualifications, referred to in subparagraphs 2(a) and 

(b) of this Article, other than those based on measures 
pursuant to immigration laws and regulations, shall be 
limited to those based on non-conforming measures, which 
are in effect on the date of entry into force of this 
Agreement. 


4. Measures inconsistent with both Articles 96 and 97 
shall be inscribed in the column relating to Article 96. 
This inscription will be considered to provide a condition 
or qualification to Article 97 as well.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Modification Of Schedules" article_identifier="2304">1. Each Country may modify or withdraw any commitments in 
its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6. 



2. The modifying Country shall notify its intention of 
such modification or withdrawal to the other Country and 
thereafter enter into negotiations in line with 
subparagraph 2(a) of Article XXI of the GATS, to maintain a 
general level of mutually advantageous commitments not less 
favourable to trade than that provided for in its Schedule 
of Specific Commitments in Annex 6 prior to such 
negotiations. 



3. Such modification or withdrawal shall be approved by 
the Countries in accordance with their respective legal 
procedures, and shall enter into force on the date to be 
agreed upon by the Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="2305">1. Each Country shall accord to services and service 
suppliers of the other Country treatment no less favourable 
than that it accords to like services and service suppliers 
of any third State. 



2. The provision of paragraph 1 of this Article shall not 
apply to any measure by a Country with respect to sectors, 
sub-sectors or activities, as set out in its Schedule in 
Annex 7. 



3. If a Country has entered into an agreement on trade in 
services with a third State or enters into such an 
agreement after this Agreement comes into force, with 
respect to sectors, sub-sectors or activities included in 
its Schedule in Annex 7, it shall, upon the request of the 
other Country, consider according to services and service 
suppliers of the other Country, treatment no less 
favourable than that it accords to like services and 
service suppliers of that third State pursuant to such an 
agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Authorisation, Licensing Or Qualification" article_identifier="2306">With a view to ensuring that any measure by a Country 
relating to the authorisation, licensing or qualification 
of service suppliers of the other Country does not 
constitute an unnecessary barrier to trade in services, 
each Country shall endeavour to ensure that such measure: 



(a) 	is based on objective and transparent criteria, 
such as competence and the ability to supply the 
service; 



(b) 	is not more burdensome than necessary to ensure 
the quality of the service; and 



(c) 	does not constitute a disguised restriction on 
the supply of the service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="2307">1. A Country may recognise the education or experience 
obtained, requirements met, or licences or certifications 
granted in the other Country for the purposes of the 
fulfilment, in whole or in part, of its standards or 
criteria for the authorisation, licensing or certification 
of service suppliers of the other Country. 



2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1 of this 
Article, which may be achieved through harmonisation or 
otherwise, may be based upon an agreement or arrangement 
between the Countries or may be accorded unilaterally. 



3. Where a Country recognises, by agreement or 
arrangement between the Country and a third State or 
unilaterally, the education or experience obtained, 
requirements met or licences or certifications granted in 
the third State: 


(a) 	nothing in Article 101 shall be construed to 
require the Country to accord such recognition to 
the education or experience obtained, 
requirements met or licences or certifications 
granted in the other Country; and 



(b) 	the Country shall accord the other Country an 
adequate opportunity to demonstrate that the 
education or experience obtained, requirements 
met or licences or certifications granted in the 
other Country should also be recognised.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Transparency" article_identifier="2308">1. Each Country shall, upon the request by the other 
Country, provide in the English language, as appropriate, 
the other Country with information on its laws and 
regulations and any amendment thereof affecting Articles 96 
and 97. 



2. Each Country shall provide, as appropriate, the other 
Country with copies of its publicly released guidelines or 
policy statements affecting Articles 96 and 97 in relation 
to its specific commitments as set out in Annex 6. 



3. Each Country shall provide, as appropriate, the other 
Country with copies of its annual reports or any other 
publication that are made generally available to the 
public. 

Note: 	The information provided by the Countries under this 
Article will be supplied solely for the purposes of 
transparency, and shall not be construed to affect 
any rights and obligations of the Countries under 
this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="2309">1. Each Country shall ensure that any monopoly supplier 
of a service in the Country does not, in the supply of the 
monopoly service in the relevant market, act in a manner 
inconsistent with the Country’s commitments under this 
Chapter. 



2. Where a Country’s monopoly supplier competes, either 
directly or through an affiliated company, in the supply of 
a service outside the scope of its monopoly rights and 
which is subject to that Country’s specific commitments, 
the Country shall ensure that such a supplier does not 
abuse its monopoly position to act in the Country in a 
manner inconsistent with such commitments. 



3. The provisions of this Article shall also apply to 
cases of exclusive service suppliers, where a Country, 
formally or in effect: 



(a) 	authorises or establishes a small number of 
service suppliers; and 



(b) 	substantially prevents competition among those 
suppliers in the Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Emergency Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="2310">1. The Countries shall initiate discussions within one 
year from the entry into force of this Agreement to develop 
mutually acceptable guidelines and procedures for the 
application of emergency safeguard measures within five 
years of the entry into force of this Agreement. 



2. 	(a) Notwithstanding the provision of paragraph 1 of 
this Article, if a Country deems itself to be 
affected by the negative impact caused by its 
specific commitments in Annex 6, the Country may 
request to hold a consultation with the other 
Country to deal with such situation and the other 
Country shall respond to the request in good 
faith. 

(b) 	In the consultation, the Countries shall 
endeavour to reach a mutually acceptable solution 
within a reasonable time.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="2311">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article 
108, a Country shall not apply restrictions on 
international transfers and payments for current 
transactions relating to trade in services. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and 
obligations of the Countries as members of the 
International Monetary Fund (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the Fund”) under the Articles of Agreement 
of the International Monetary Fund, as may be amended, 
including the use of exchange actions which are in 
conformity with the Articles of Agreement of the 
International Monetary Fund, as may be amended, provided 
that a Country shall not impose restrictions on any capital 
transactions inconsistently with its commitments under this
108, or at the request of the Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="2312">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and 
external financial difficulties or threat thereof, a 
Country may adopt or maintain restrictions on trade in 
services, including on payments or transfers for 
transactions. 



2. The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1 of this 
Article: 



(a) 	shall ensure that the other Country is treated as 
favourably as any third State; 



(b) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, as 
may be amended; 



(c) 	shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial, 
economic and financial interests of the other 
Country; 



(d) 	shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the 
circumstances described in paragraph 1 of this 
Article; and 



(e) 	shall be temporary and be phased out 
progressively as the situation specified in 
paragraph 1 of this Article improves. 


3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a 
Country may give priority to the supply of services which 
are more essential to its economic or development 
programmes. However, such restrictions shall not be 
adopted or maintained for the purposes of protecting a 
particular service sector. 



4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph 
1 of this Article, or any changes therein, shall be 
promptly notified to the other Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="2313">A Country may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a 
service supplier of the other Country where the Country 
establishes that the service is being supplied by a 
juridical person that is owned or controlled by persons of 
a third State, and that denying Country: 



(a) 	does not maintain diplomatic relations with the 
third State; or 



(b) 	adopts or maintains measures with respect to the 
third State that prohibit transactions with the 
juridical person or that would be violated or 
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were 
accorded to the juridical person.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Services" article_identifier="2314">1. For the purpose of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Trade in Services (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14, shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing commitments, with respect to measures 
affecting trade in services in this Chapter, with 
a view to achieving further liberalisation on a 
mutually advantageous basis and securing an 
overall balance of rights and obligations; 



(b) 	reviewing the implementation and operation of 
this Chapter; 



(c) 	reviewing and discussing the issues concerning 
the effective implementation of Articles 103 and 
106; 



(d) 	reporting the outcome of discussions of the Sub-
Committee to the Joint Committee; and 



(e) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 


2. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments, 
and may invite representatives of relevant 
entities other than the Governments with the 
necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be 
discussed; and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall hold its inaugural meeting 
within one year after this Agreement enters into force. 
The subsequent meeting of the Sub-Committee shall be held 
at such frequency as the Countries may agree upon. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall establish a working group on 
financial services (hereinafter referred to in this Article 
as “the Working Group”). The details and procedures of the 
Working Group shall be specified in Annex 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Review Of Commitments" article_identifier="2315">1. The Countries shall review commitments on trade in 
services with the first review within five years from the 
date of entry into force of this Agreement, with the aim of 
improving the overall commitments undertaken by the 
Countries under this Agreement. 



2. In reviewing the commitments in accordance with 
paragraph 1 of this Article, the Countries shall take into 
account paragraph 1 of Article IV of the GATS.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="280">
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="2316">1. The Countries shall grant and ensure adequate, 
effective and non-discriminatory protection of intellectual 
property, promote efficiency and transparency in 
administration of intellectual property protection system, 
and provide for measures for the enforcement of 
intellectual property rights against infringement, 
counterfeiting and piracy, in accordance with the 
provisions of this Chapter and the international agreements 
to which both Countries are parties. 



2. Intellectual property referred to in this Chapter 
shall mean all categories of intellectual property: 



(a) 	that are subject of Articles 119 through 124; 
and/or 



(b) 	that are under the TRIPS Agreement and/or the 
relevant international agreements referred to in 
the TRIPS Agreement. 


3. The Countries recognise the importance of 
international agreements which provide for the 
international standards of protection of intellectual 
property. 



4. The Countries reaffirm their commitment to comply with 
the obligations set out in the international agreements 
relating to intellectual property to which both Countries 
are parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Definitions" article_identifier="2317">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “Nice Agreement” means the Nice 
Agreement Concerning the International 
Classification of Goods and Services for the 
Purposes of the Registration of Marks of June 15, 
1957, as amended and as may be amended; and 



(b) 	the term “Strasbourg Agreement” means the 
Strasbourg Agreement Concerning the International 
Patent Classification of March 24, 1971, as 
amended and as may be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="2318">Each Country shall accord to nationals of the other 
Country treatment no less favourable than the treatment it 
accords to its own nationals with regard to the protection 
of intellectual property in accordance with Articles 3 and 
5 of the TRIPS Agreement. The obligation under this 
Article does not apply to the protection of new plant 
varieties in respect of the measure as set out in the 
reservation No. 1 of Schedule of Japan in Annex 4. 


Note: 	For the purposes of Articles 114 and 115, 
“nationals” shall have the same meaning as in the 
TRIPS Agreement, and “protection” shall include 
matters affecting the availability, acquisition, 
scope, maintenance and enforcement of intellectual 
property rights as well as those matters affecting 
the use of intellectual property rights specifically 
addressed in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="2319">Each Country shall accord to nationals of the other 
Country treatment no less favourable than the treatment it 
accords to the nationals of a third State with regard to 
the protection of intellectual property in accordance with 
Articles 4 and 5 of the TRIPS Agreement. The obligation 
under this Article does not apply to the protection of new 
plant varieties in respect of the measure as set out in the 
reservation No. 1 of Schedule of Japan in Annex 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Streamlining And Harmonisation Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="2320">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administration 
of intellectual property protection system, each Country 
shall take appropriate measures to streamline its 
administrative procedures concerning intellectual property. 



2. Applications for and grants of patents and 
publications thereof shall be classified in accordance with 
the international patent classification system established 
under the Strasbourg Agreement. Applications for 
registrations of, and registrations of, trademarks for 
goods and services and publications thereof shall be 
classified in accordance with the international 
classification system of goods and services established 
under the Nice Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Transparency" article_identifier="2321">For the purposes of further promoting transparency in 
administration of intellectual property protection system, 
each Country shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, take appropriate measures to: 



(a) 	in cases other than those provided for in 
paragraph (b) of this Article and paragraph 5 of 
Article 119, publish information on at least 
grants of patents and registrations of utility 
models, industrial designs and trademarks, and 
make available to the public information 
contained in the dossiers thereof; 



(b) 	publish information on applications for 
registrations of, and registrations of, new plant 
varieties, and make available to the public 
information contained in the dossiers thereof; 



(c) 	make available to the public information on 
applications for the suspension by the competent 
authorities of the release of goods infringing 
intellectual property rights as a border measure; 
and 



(d) 	make available to the public information on its 
efforts to provide effective enforcement of 
intellectual property rights and other 
information with regard to intellectual property 
protection system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="2322">The Countries shall take necessary measures to enhance 
public awareness of protection of intellectual property 
including educational and dissemination projects on the use 
of intellectual property as well as on the enforcement of 
intellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Patents" article_identifier="2323">1. Patents shall be available for any inventions, whether 
products or processes, in all fields of technology, 
provided that they are new, involve an inventive step and 
are capable of industrial application in accordance with 
Article 27 of the TRIPS Agreement. 



2. Each Country shall ensure that any patent application 
shall not be rejected solely on the ground that the subject 
matter claimed in the application is a micro-organism. 



3. Each Country shall ensure that any applicant for a 
patent application may file a request to the competent 
authority that his application for a patent be examined, 
where appropriate, in preference to other applications, 
subject to reasonable grounds. 



4. Each Country shall ensure that an application for a 
patent is examined upon the request of the applicant, where 
appropriate, in preference to other applications, if the 
applicant has filed an application for a patent of the same 
invention or substantially the same invention in the other 
Country. Each Country may require the applicant to furnish 
a result of relevant prior art search or examination result 
for the invention together with the request. 



5. Each Country shall publish patent applications, in 
accordance with its laws and regulations, after the 
expiration of a period of 18 months from the filing date 
or, where priority is claimed, the priority date.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="2324">1. Each Country shall provide for the protection of 
independently created industrial designs that are new or 
original in accordance with Article 25 of the TRIPS 
Agreement. 



2. Each Country shall ensure that a claimed industrial 
design shall not be new, if it is made available to the 
public through telecommunication line before the filing 
date of the application for the registration of industrial 
design or, where priority is claimed, the priority date of 
the application, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations. 



3. Each Country shall endeavour to provide that a claimed 
industrial design shall not be new, if it is publicly known 
or described in a publication made available to the public 
in the other Country before the filing date of the 
application for the registration of industrial design in 
the former Country or, where priority is claimed, the 
priority date of the application, in accordance with its 
laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Trademarks For Goods And Services" article_identifier="2325">1. Each Country shall ensure that the owner of a 
registered trademark shall have the exclusive right to 
prevent all third parties not having the owner’s consent 
from using in the course of trade identical or similar 
signs for goods or services which are identical or similar 
to those in respect of which the trademark is registered, 
where such use would result in a likelihood of confusion. 



2. Each Country shall refuse or cancel the registration 
of a trademark, which is identical or similar to a 
trademark well-known in either Country as indicating the 
goods or services of the owner of the well-known trademark, 
if use of that trademark is for unfair intentions, inter 
alia, intention to gain an unfair profit or intention to 
cause damage to the owner of the well-known trademark 
whether or not such use would result in a likelihood of 
confusion.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Copyright And Related Rights" article_identifier="2326">1. Each Country shall provide to authors, performers and 
producers of phonograms the exclusive right of authorising 
the making available to the public of their works, 
performances fixed in phonograms and phonograms, 
respectively, by wire or wireless means, in such a way that 
members of the public may access them from a place and at a 
time individually chosen by them. 



2. Each Country shall provide for appropriate measures 
concerning limitations on liability for service providers: 



(a) 	in case where a service provider provides a 
necessary deterrent to the transmission of 
information through telecommunication systems or 
networks controlled or operated by the service 
provider which it believes to be the infringement 
of copyright or related rights; and 



(b) 	in case where the infringement of copyright or 
related rights occurs by the transmission of 
information through telecommunication systems or 
networks controlled or operated by a service 
provider and where the service provider is 
technically unable to deter the transmission or 
has difficulty in finding the infringement of 
copyright or related rights. 


3. Each Country shall take necessary measures to promote 
the development of the collective management organisations 
for copyright and related rights in that Country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="New Plant Varieties" article_identifier="2327">1. The Countries recognise the importance of protecting 
new plant varieties in a manner consistent with 
internationally harmonised system. For this purpose, each 
Country shall ensure that rights relating to new plant 
varieties are adequately protected. 



2. Each Country shall, having due regard to the concerns 
of the other Country, endeavour to protect as many plant 
genera or species as possible in a manner stated in 
paragraph 1 of this Article within the shortest period of 
time.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="2328">1. Each Country shall provide for effective protection 
against unfair competition. 



2. Any act of competition contrary to honest practices in 
industrial or commercial matters constitutes an act of 
unfair competition. The following acts of unfair 
competition, in particular, shall be prohibited: 



(a) 	all acts of such a nature as to create confusion 
by any means whatever with the establishment, the 
goods, the services, or the industrial or 
commercial activities, of a competitor; 



(b) 	false allegations in the course of trade of such 
a nature as to discredit the establishment, the 
goods, the services, or the industrial or 
commercial activities, of a competitor; 



(c) 	indications or allegations the use of which in 
the course of trade is liable to mislead the 
public as to the nature, the characteristics, the 
suitability for their purpose, or the quantity, 
of the goods or the services, or the 
manufacturing process of the goods; 



(d) 	acts of assigning, leasing, displaying for the 
purpose of assignment or lease, exporting or 
importing goods which imitate the configuration 
of another person's goods except as provided for 
in the laws and regulations of each Country; and 



(e) 	acts of acquiring or holding right to use domain 
names identical with or similar to a specific 
indication of goods or services of another 
person, or using the domain name, with intention 
to gain unfair profit or intention of causing 
damage to that other person. 


3. Each Country shall ensure in its laws and regulations 
adequate and effective protection of undisclosed 
information in accordance with Article 39 of the TRIPS 
Agreement. 



4. Each Country shall establish appropriate remedies to 
prevent or punish acts of unfair competition. In 
particular, each Country shall ensure that any person that 
considers its business interests to be affected by an act 
of unfair competition may bring legal action and request 
suspension or prevention of the act, destruction of the 
goods which constitute the act, removal of facilities used 
for the act, or any damages which result from the act.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Enforcement – Border Measures" article_identifier="2329">1. Each Country shall, in accordance with Article 51 of 
the TRIPS Agreement, provide for procedures concerning the 
suspension by the competent authorities of the release of 
goods infringing trademarks or copyrights or related 
rights. Each Country may also provide for corresponding 
procedures concerning the suspension by the competent 
authorities of the release of goods infringing other 
intellectual property rights, inter alia, patents, utility 
models, industrial designs or rights relating to new plant 
varieties. 



2. Where a Country has determined to suspend the release 
of goods infringing intellectual property rights, the 
competent authorities of that Country shall inform the 
right holder of that intellectual property of the names and 
addresses of the consignor and the importer. 



3. Each Country shall ensure that the competent 
authorities do not allow the re-exportation of the goods 
infringing trademarks or copyrights or related rights other 
than in exceptional circumstances.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Enforcement – Civil Remedies" article_identifier="2330">Each Country shall ensure that the right holder of 
intellectual property has the right to claim against the 
infringer damages adequate to compensate for the injury the 
right holder has suffered because of an infringement of 
that person’s intellectual property right by an infringer 
who knowingly, or with reasonable grounds to know, engaged 
in infringing activity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Enforcement – Criminal Remedies" article_identifier="2331">Each Country shall provide for criminal procedures and 
penalties to be applied in cases of wilful trademark 
counterfeiting or copyright piracy on a commercial scale. 
Each Country shall, to the extent possible, endeavour to 
provide for criminal procedures and penalties to be applied 
in cases of wilful infringement of other intellectual 
property rights on a commercial scale.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Co-Operation" article_identifier="2332">1. The Countries, recognising the growing importance of 
protection of intellectual property in pursuing further 
promotion of trade and investment between the Countries, 
subject to the availability of funds and the applicable 
laws and regulations of each Country, shall co-operate in 
the field of intellectual property. Costs of co-operation 
under this Article shall be borne in an equitable manner to 
be mutually agreed upon between the Countries. 



2. Areas and forms of co-operation under this Article 
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement. 



3. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Sub-Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="2333">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Intellectual Property (hereinafter referred to 
in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in 
accordance with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	discussing any issues related to intellectual 
property with a view to enhancing protection of 
intellectual property and enforcement of 
intellectual property rights and to promoting 
efficient and transparent administration of 
intellectual property protection system, such as: 


(i) 	requirement of attestation or other 
certification; 


(ii) 	general power of attorney system; 


(iii) 	improvement of administration of modified 
substantive examination; 


(iv) 	industrial design protection system 
including deferment of publication; and 


(v) 	multi-class trademark application system; 


(c) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments, 
and may invite representatives of relevant 
entities other than the Governments with the 
necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be 
discussed; and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="2334">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article 73 of the 
TRIPS Agreement is incorporated into and forms part of this 
Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Controlling Anti-Competitive Activities" chapter_identifier="281">
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Measures Against Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="2335">1. Each Country shall, in accordance with its applicable 
laws and regulations, take measures which it considers 
appropriate against anti-competitive activities for the 
efficient functioning of its market. 



2. Each Country shall, when necessary, endeavour to 
review and improve or adopt laws and regulations to 
effectively control anti-competitive activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Co-Operation On Controlling Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="2336">1. The Countries shall, in accordance with their 
respective laws and regulations, co-operate in the field of 
controlling anti-competitive activities subject to their 
respective available resources. 



2. The details and procedures of co-operation under this 
Article shall be specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="2337">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Improvement Of Business Environment" chapter_identifier="282">
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="2338">1. Each Government shall, in accordance with the laws and 
regulations of its Country, take appropriate measures to 
further improve the business environment for the benefit of 
the enterprises of the other Country conducting their 
business activities in the Country. 



2. The Governments shall, in accordance with the laws and 
regulations of their respective Countries, promote cooperation to further improve the business environment in 
their respective Countries and take necessary measures 
including establishing such mechanisms as provided for in 
Articles 135 and 137. 

1. For the purposes of effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Improvement of Business Environment 
(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “the Sub-
Committee”) established in accordance with Article 14 shall</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Sub-Committee On Improvement Of Business Environment" article_identifier="2339">be: 




(a) 

addressing issues in relation to the improvement 




of business environment that the Sub-Committee 




considers appropriate, taking into account, as 




necessary, the findings reported by a Liaison 




Office on Improvement of Business Environment 




(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as 




“Liaison Office”) established in accordance with 




Article 137, and in co-operation with other 




relevant Sub-Committee(s) with a view to avoiding 




unnecessary overlap with the works of other 




relevant Sub-Committee(s);   


(b) 

reporting the findings and making recommendations 




to the Countries, including the measures to be 




taken by the Governments, regarding such 




functions as referred to in subparagraph (a). 




The Sub-Committee may consult with the Joint 




Committee prior to the submission of 




recommendations to the Countries; 


(c) 

where appropriate, reviewing the implementation 




of the recommendations referred to in 




subparagraph (b); 


(d) 

making available, where appropriate, to 




enterprises of the Countries the recommendations 




referred to in subparagraph (b) and the results 




of the review referred to in subparagraph (c) in 




an appropriate manner; 


(e) 

reporting the recommendations referred to in 




subparagraph (b) and other findings in relation 




to the implementation and operation of this 




Chapter to the Joint Committee; and 
(f) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 


13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Countries. 



3. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments, 
and may invite representatives of the business 
sector and other business-related organisations 
with the necessary expertise relevant to the 
issues to be discussed; and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments. 


4. The other details of the Sub-Committee shall be set 
forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Recommendations From The Sub-Committee" article_identifier="2340">The Countries shall take into consideration the 
recommendations referred to in subparagraph 1 (b) of 
Article 135.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="Liaison Office On Improvement Of Business Environment" article_identifier="2341">1. Each Country shall designate and maintain a Liaison 
Office for the purposes of this Chapter. 



2. The functions and other details of the Liaison Office 
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="2342">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Co-Operation" chapter_identifier="283">
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="2343">1. The Governments shall, in accordance with the 
applicable laws and regulations of their respective 
Countries, promote co-operation under this Agreement for 
their mutual benefits in order to liberalise and facilitate 
trade and investment between the Countries and to promote 
the well-being of the peoples of the Countries. For this 
purpose, the Governments shall co-operate and, where 
necessary and appropriate, encourage and facilitate cooperation between parties other than the Governments. 



2. 	The main objectives of this Chapter are as follows: 



(a) 	to enhance socio-economic development; 



(b) 	to strengthen economic competitiveness; 



(c) 	to advance human resource development; 



(d) 	to promote sustainable development; and 



(e) 	to improve overall well-being of the peoples of 
both Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Fields Of Co-Operation" article_identifier="2344">The fields of co-operation under this Chapter shall 
include: 



(a) 	agriculture, forestry, fisheries and plantation; 



(b) 	education and human resource development; 



(c) 	information and communications technology; 



(d) 	science and technology; 



(e) 	small and medium enterprises; 



(f) 	tourism; 



(g) 	environment; and 



(h) 	other fields to be mutually agreed upon by the 
Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Areas And Forms Of Co-Operation" article_identifier="2345">Areas and forms of co-operation under this Chapter 
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Costs Of Co-Operation" article_identifier="2346">1. The implementation of co-operation under this Chapter 
shall be subject to the availability of funds and the 
applicable laws and regulations of each Country. 



2. Costs of co-operation under this Chapter shall be 
borne in an equitable manner to be mutually agreed upon 
between the Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Sub-Committee On Co-Operation" article_identifier="2347">1. For the purposes of effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the functions of the Sub-
Committee on Co-operation (hereinafter referred to in this 
Article as “the Sub-Committee”) established in accordance 
with Article 14 shall be: 



(a) 	exchanging information on the field of cooperation; 



(b) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(c) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(d) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee regarding issues relating to the 
implementation of this Chapter, including the 
measures to be taken by the Countries; 



(e) 	identifying ways for further co-operation between 
the Countries; 



(f) 	supervising the functions and activities of the 
working group to be established pursuant to 
paragraph 5 of this Article; 



(g) 	establishing its own rules of administrative 
procedures; and 



(h) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee in accordance with Article 

13. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall respect existing consultation 
mechanisms between the Countries for Official Development 
Assistance and, as appropriate, share information and 
coordinate with such mechanisms to ensure effective and 
efficient implementation of co-operative activities and 
projects. 



3. The Sub-Committee shall convene its inaugural meeting 
within one year after this Agreement enters into force and 
subsequently meet at such times as may be agreed by the 
Countries. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues as 
may be agreed by the Countries. 



4. 	The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	composed of representatives of the Governments, 
and may, by consensus, invite representatives of 
relevant entities other than the Governments with 
the necessary expertise relevant to the issues to 
be discussed; and 



(b) 	co-chaired by officials of the Governments. 


5. The Sub-Committee may establish a working group for 
each field of co-operation under the Sub-Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="2348">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="284">
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Scope" article_identifier="2349">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, this 
Chapter shall apply with respect to the settlement of 
disputes between the Countries concerning the 
interpretation or application of this Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights of 
the Countries to have recourse to dispute settlement 
procedures available under any other international 
agreement to which both Countries are parties. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of this Article, once a 
dispute settlement procedure has been initiated under this 
Chapter or under any other international agreement to which 
both Countries are parties with respect to a particular 
dispute, that procedure shall be used to the exclusion of 
any other procedure for that particular dispute. However, 
this shall not apply if substantially separate and distinct 
rights or obligations under different international 
agreements are in dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Consultations" article_identifier="2350">1. Either Country may make a request in writing 
consultations to the other Country concerning any matter on 
the interpretation or application of this Agreement. 



2. When a Country requests consultations pursuant to 
paragraph 1 of this Article, the other Country shall reply 
to the request and enter into consultations in good faith 
within 30 days after the date of receipt of the request, 
with a view to reaching a prompt and mutually satisfactory 
resolution of the matter. In a case of consultations 
regarding perishable goods, the requested Country shall 
enter into consultations within 15 days after the date of 
receipt of the request. 



3. The requesting Country shall set out the reasons for 
the request, including identification of the measure at 
issue and an indication of the legal basis for the 
complaint. 



4. The Countries shall make every effort to reach a 
mutually satisfactory resolution through consultations. 



5. Consultations shall be confidential and without 
prejudice to the rights of either Country in any further 
proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="2351">1. The Countries may at any time agree to good offices, 
conciliation or mediation. They may begin at any time and 
be terminated at the request of either Country at any time. 



2. If the Countries agree, procedures for good offices, 
conciliation or mediation may continue while procedures of 
the arbitral tribunal provided for in this Chapter are in 
progress. 



3. Proceedings involving good offices, conciliation or 
mediation and positions taken by the Countries during these 
proceedings, shall be confidential, and without prejudice 
to the rights of either Country in any further proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 148" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="2352">1. The complaining Country that requested consultations 
under Article 146 may request in writing the establishment 
of an arbitral tribunal to the Country complained against: 



(a) 	if the Country complained against does not enter 
into such consultations within 30 days after the 
date of receipt of the request for consultations 
under that Article; or 



(b) 	if the Countries fail to resolve the dispute 
through such consultations under that Article 
within 60 days after the date of receipt of the 
request for such consultations, 

provided that the complaining Country considers that any 
benefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under this 
Agreement is being nullified or impaired as a result of the 
failure of the Country complained against to carry out its 
obligations, or as a result of the application by the 
Country complained against of measures which are in 
conflict with the obligations of that Country, under this 
Agreement. 


2. Any request to establish an arbitral tribunal pursuant 
to this Article shall identify: 



(a) 	the legal basis of the complaint including the 
provisions of this Agreement alleged to have been 
breached and any other relevant provisions; and 



(b) 	the factual basis for the complaint. 


3. Each Country shall, within 30 days after the date of 
receipt of the request for the establishment of an arbitral 
tribunal, appoint one arbitrator who may be its national 
and propose up to three candidates to serve as the third 
arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. 
The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either 
Country, nor have his or her usual place of residence in 
either Country, nor be employed by either Country, nor have 
dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 



4. The Countries shall agree on and appoint the third 
arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of the 
request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal, 
taking into account the candidates proposed pursuant to 
paragraph 3 of this Article. If the Countries fail to 
agree on the third arbitrator, the Countries shall request 
the two arbitrators appointed pursuant to paragraph 3 of 
this Article to appoint the third arbitrator. If the 
arbitrators are not able to reach agreement on the third 
arbitrator within 30 days after the date of receipt of the 
request, the Director-General of the WTO may be requested 
by either Country to appoint the third arbitrator. 



5. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal 
shall be the date on which the chair is appointed. 



6. The arbitral tribunal should be composed of 
arbitrators with relevant technical or legal expertise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 149" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="2353">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article 


148: 



(a) 	should consult with the Countries as appropriate 
and provide adequate opportunities for the 
development of a mutually satisfactory 
resolution; 



(b) 	shall make its award in accordance with this 
Agreement and applicable rules of international 
law; 



(c) 	shall set out, in its award, its findings of law 
and fact, together with the reasons therefore; 
and 



(d) 	may, apart from giving its findings, include in 
its award suggested implementation options for 
the Countries to consider in conjunction with 
Article 152. 


2. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Countries, 
such relevant information as it considers necessary and 
appropriate. The Countries shall respond promptly and 
fully to any request by an arbitral tribunal for such 
information as the arbitral tribunal considers necessary 
and appropriate. 



3. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from any 
relevant source and may consult experts to obtain their 
opinion on certain aspects of the matter. With respect to 
factual issues concerning a scientific or other technical 
matter raised by a Country, the arbitral tribunal may 
request advisory reports in writing from an expert or 
experts. The arbitral tribunal may, at the request of a 
Country or on its own initiative, select, in consultation 
with the Countries, no fewer than two scientific or 
technical experts who shall assist the arbitral tribunal 
throughout its proceedings, but who shall not have the 
right to vote in respect of any decision to be made by the 
arbitral tribunal, including its award.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 150" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="2354">1. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 



2. The venue for the proceedings of the arbitral tribunal 
shall be decided by mutual consent of the Countries, 
failing which it shall alternate between the Countries. 



3. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the 
documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 



4. Notwithstanding paragraph 3 of this Article, either 
Country may make public statements as to its views 
regarding the dispute, but shall treat as confidential, 
information and written submissions submitted by the other 
Country to the arbitral tribunal which that other Country 
has designated as confidential. Where a Country has 
provided information or written submissions designated to 
be confidential, the other Country may request a non-
confidential summary of the information or written 
submissions which may be disclosed publicly. The Country 
to whom such a request is made may agree to such a request 
and submit such a summary, or refuse the request without 
needing to ascribe any reasons or justification. 



5. The Countries shall be given the opportunity to attend 
any of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the 
proceeding. Any information or written submissions 
submitted by a Country to the arbitral tribunal, including 
any comments on the descriptive part of the draft award and 
responses to questions put by the arbitral tribunal, shall 
be made available to the other Country. 



6. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted 
without the presence of the Countries, and in the light of 
the information provided and the statements made. 



7. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 90 days after the 
date of its establishment, submit to the Countries its 
draft award, including both descriptive part and its 
findings and conclusions, for the purposes of enabling the 
Countries to review precise aspects of the draft award. 
When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit 
its draft award within the aforementioned 90 days period, 
it may extend that period with the consent of the 
Countries. A Country may submit comments in writing to the 
arbitral tribunal on the draft award within 15 days after 
the date of submission of the draft award. 



8. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award, within 30 
days after the date of submission of the draft award. 



9. The arbitral tribunal shall attempt to make its 
decisions, including its award, by consensus but may also 
make such decisions, including its award, by majority vote. 



10. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and 
binding on the Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 151" name="Suspension And Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="2355">1. Where the Countries agree, the arbitral tribunal may 
suspend its work at any time for a period not to exceed 12 
months. In the event of such a suspension, the time-frames 
set out in paragraphs 7 and 8 of Article 150 and paragraph 
8 of Article 152 shall be extended by the amount of time 
that the work was suspended. The proceedings of the 
arbitral tribunal shall be resumed at any time upon the 
request of either Country. If the work of the arbitral 
tribunal has been suspended for more than 12 months, the 
authority for establishment of the arbitral tribunal shall 
lapse unless the Countries agree otherwise. 



2. The Countries may agree to terminate the proceedings 
of the arbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of 
the award to the Countries by jointly so notifying the 
chair of the arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 152" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="2356">1. The Country complained against shall promptly comply 
with the award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant to 
Article 150. 



2. The Country complained against shall, within 20 days 
after the date of issuance of the award, notify the 
complaining Country of the period of time for implementing 
the award. If the complaining Country considers the period 
of time notified to be unacceptable, it may request to the 
Country complained against consultations with a view to 
reaching a mutually satisfactory implementation period. If 
no satisfactory implementation period has been agreed 
within 20 days after the date of receipt of the request, 
the complaining Country may refer the matter to an arbitral 
tribunal. 



3. If the Country complained against considers it 
impracticable to comply with the award within the 
implementation period as determined pursuant to paragraph 2 
of this Article, the Country complained against shall, no 
later than the expiry of that implementation period, enter 
into consultations with the complaining Country, with a 
view to developing mutually satisfactory resolution, 
through compensation or any alternative arrangement. If no 
satisfactory resolution has been agreed within 20 days 
after the date of expiry of that implementation period, the 
complaining Country may notify the Country complained 
against that it intends to suspend the application to the 
Country complained against of concessions or other 
obligations under this Agreement. 



4. If the complaining Country considers that the Country 
complained against has failed to comply with the award 
within the implementation period as determined pursuant to 
paragraph 2 of this Article, it may refer the matter to an 
arbitral tribunal. 



5. If the arbitral tribunal to which the matter is 
referred pursuant to paragraph 4 of this Article confirms 
that the Country complained against has failed to comply 
with the award within the implementation period as 
determined pursuant to paragraph 2 of this Article, the 
complaining Country may, within 30 days after the date of 
such confirmation by the arbitral tribunal, notify the 
Country complained against that it intends to suspend the 
application to the Country complained against of 
concessions or other obligations under this Agreement. 



6. Suspension of the application of concessions or other 
obligations under paragraphs 3 and 5 of this Article may 
only be implemented at least 30 days after the date of 
notification in accordance with those paragraphs. Such 
suspension shall: 



(a) 	not be effected if, in respect of the dispute to 
which the suspension relates, consultations, or 
proceedings before an arbitral tribunal are in 
progress; 



(b) 	be temporary, and be discontinued when the 
Countries reach a mutually satisfactory 
resolution or where compliance with the original 
award is effected; 



(c) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification 
or impairment that is attributable to the failure 
to comply with the original award; and 



(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to 
which the nullification or impairment relates, 
unless it is not practicable or effective to 
suspend the application of concessions or 
obligations in such sector or sectors. 


7. If the Country complained against considers that the 
requirements for the suspension of the application to it of 
concessions or other obligations under this Agreement by 
the complaining Country set out in paragraph 3, 5 or 6 of 
this Article have not been met, it may request 
consultations with the complaining Country. The 
complaining Country shall enter into consultations within 
10 days after the date of receipt of the request. If the 
Countries fail to resolve the matter within 30 days after 
the date of receipt of the request for consultations 
pursuant to this paragraph, the Country complained against 
may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal. 



8. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the 
purposes of this Article shall, wherever possible, have as 
its arbitrators, the arbitrators of the original arbitral 
tribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators to 
the arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes 
of this Article shall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 3 
and 4 of Article 148. Unless the Countries agree to a 
different period, such arbitral tribunal shall issue its 
award within 60 days after the date when the matter is 
referred to it. The award of the arbitral tribunal 
established under this Article shall be binding on the 
Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 153" name="Expenses" article_identifier="2357">Unless the Countries agree otherwise, the expenses of 
the arbitral tribunal, including the remuneration of its 
arbitrators, shall be borne by the Countries in equal 
shares.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="285">
      <article number="ARTICLE 154" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="2358">The table of contents and headings of the Chapters and 
the Articles of this Agreement are inserted for convenience 
of reference only and shall not affect the interpretation 
of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 155" name="General Review" article_identifier="2359">The Countries shall undertake a general review of the 
implementation and operation of this Agreement in the fifth 
calendar year following the calendar year in which this 
Agreement enters into force, and every five years 
thereafter, unless otherwise agreed by both Countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 156" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="2360">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall form an 
integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 157" name="Amendment" article_identifier="2361">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between the 
Countries. 



2. Such amendment shall be approved by the Countries in 
accordance with their respective legal procedures, and 
shall enter into force on the date to be agreed upon by the 
Countries. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of this Article, 
amendments relating only to Annex 2 or 3 may be made by 
diplomatic notes exchanged between the Governments. 



4. Amendments shall not affect the rights and obligations 
of the Countries provided for under this Agreement until 
the amendments enter into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 158" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="2362">This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth 
day after the date on which the Governments exchange 
diplomatic notes informing each other that the legal 
procedures of their respective Countries necessary for 
entry into force of this Agreement have been completed. It 
shall remain in force unless terminated as provided for in 
Article 159.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 159" name="Termination" article_identifier="2363">1. Either Country may terminate this Agreement by giving 
one year’s advance notice in writing to the other Country. 



2. The other Country may request in writing consultations 
concerning any matter that would arise from the termination 
within 45 days after the date of receipt of the notice 
referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. 



3. The requested Country shall enter into consultations 
in good faith with a view to reaching an equitable 
agreement within 30 days after the date of receipt of the 
request referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="286">
      <article article_identifier="2364">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly 
authorised by their respective Governments, have signed 
this Agreement. 


DONE at Kuala Lumpur, on this thirteenth day of 
December in the year 2005 in duplicate in the English 
language. 


For the Government For the Government 
of Japan: of Malaysia:</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
