<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Chile - Japan</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>3</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>3</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2007-03-27</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2007-09-03</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2007-08-24</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2022-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">CHL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">CHL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>South America; East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/latin/chile/joint0703/agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">https://www.direcon.gob.cl/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/AAEE-Chile-Japón_baja.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/policy/economy/fta/chile.html</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://www.direcon.gob.cl/detalle-de-acuerdos/?idacuerdo=6253</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="26">
      <article article_identifier="216">AGREEMENT BETWEEN JAPAN AND THE REPUBLIC OF CHILE 
FOR A STRATEGIC ECONOMIC PARTNERSHIP 


Preamble 


Japan and the Republic of Chile (hereinafter referred 
to as “Chile”), 


 Conscious of their longstanding friendship and strong 
economic and political ties that have developed through 
many years of fruitful and mutually beneficial cooperation 
between the Parties; 


 Recognizing that creating a clearly established and 
secured trade and investment framework through mutually 
advantageous rules to govern trade and investment between 
the Parties would enhance the competitiveness of their 
economies, make their markets more efficient, and ensure 
predictable commercial environment for further expansion of 
trade and investment between them; 


 Recognizing that an adequate protection of 
intellectual property and the effective enforcement of 
competition laws will encourage trade and investment 
between the Parties; 


 Believing that a strategic economic partnership 
between the Parties will bring economic and social 
benefits, create new and better opportunities for 
employment, improve the living standards of peoples, and 
provide a catalyst for the liberalization of trade and 
investment in the Asia-Pacific region and broader 
cooperation at international fora; 


 Convinced that economic development, social 
development and environmental protection are interdependent 
and mutually reinforcing pillars of sustainable development 
and that the strategic economic partnership can play an 
important role in promoting sustainable development; 


 Recognizing the rights of the Parties to regulate in 
order to meet national policy objectives; and 


 Determined to establish a legal framework for 
promoting and developing the strategic economic partnership 
on the basis of the rights and obligations of the Parties 
under the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade 
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994 and other 
international agreements to which both Parties are parties; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="27">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Establishment Of A Free-Trade Area" article_identifier="217">The Parties hereby establish a free-trade area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Objectives" article_identifier="218">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 



(a) 	liberalize trade in goods between the Parties, in 
conformity with Article XXIV of the GATT 1994; 



(b) 	liberalize trade in services between the Parties, 
in conformity with Article V of the GATS; 



(c) 	increase investment opportunities and strengthen 
protection for investments and investment 
activities in the Parties; 



(d) 	enhance opportunities for suppliers of the 
Parties to participate in government procurement 
in the Parties; 



(e) 	provide an adequate protection of intellectual 
property and promote cooperation in the field 
thereof; 



(f) 	promote cooperation and coordination for the 
effective enforcement of competition laws and 
regulations in each Party; 



(g) 	improve business environment in the Parties; and 



(h) 	create effective procedures to prevent and 
resolve disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="219">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations 
under the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which 
both Parties are parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Publication" article_identifier="220">1. Each Party shall ensure that its laws, regulations and 
administrative rulings of general application with respect 
to any matter covered by this Agreement are promptly 
published or otherwise made publicly available in such a 
manner as to enable interested persons and the other Party 
to become acquainted with them. 



2. Each Party shall, upon the request by the other Party, 
within a reasonable period of time, respond to specific 
questions from, and provide information to, the other Party 
with respect to matters referred to in paragraph 1, through 
contact points referred to in Article 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Notification" article_identifier="221">Where a Party considers that any measure that it 
proposes to take might materially affect the implementation 
and operation of this Agreement or otherwise substantially 
affect the other Party’s interests under this Agreement, 
the former Party shall notify the other Party, to the 
extent practicable, of such measure, through contact points 
referred to in Article 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Public Comment" article_identifier="222">To the extent practicable, each Party shall, in 
accordance with its laws and regulations: 



(a) 	make public in advance administrative regulations 
of general application that it proposes to adopt 
and that affect any matter covered by this 
Agreement; and 



(b) 	provide a reasonable opportunity for comments by 
the public before adoption of such regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="223">Where administrative decisions which pertain to or 
affect the implementation and operation of this Agreement 
are taken by the competent authorities of a Party, the 
competent authorities shall, in accordance with the laws 
and regulations of the Party: 



(a) 	inform the applicant of the decision within a 
reasonable period of time after the submission of 
the application considered complete under the 
laws and regulations of the Party; 



(b) 	provide, within a reasonable period of time, 
information concerning the status of the 
application, at the request of the applicant; and 



(c) 	afford the applicant a reasonable opportunity to 
present facts and arguments in support of its 
positions prior to any final administrative 
decisions, when time, the nature of the 
proceeding, and the public interest permit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="224">1. Each Party shall establish or maintain judicial or 
administrative tribunals or procedures for the purpose of 
the prompt review and, where warranted, correction of 
administrative actions regarding matters covered by this 
Agreement. Such tribunals or procedures shall be impartial 
and independent of the office or authority entrusted with 
administrative enforcement of such actions and shall not 
have any substantial interest in the outcome of the matter. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that, in any such tribunals or 
procedures, the parties to the proceedings are provided 
with the right to: 



(a) 	a reasonable opportunity to support or defend 
their respective positions; and 



(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions 
of record. 


3. Each Party shall ensure, subject to appeal or further 
review as provided in its laws and regulations, that such 
decision is implemented by the offices or authorities with 
respect to the administrative action at issue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="225">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, maintain the confidentiality of information 
provided in confidence by the other Party pursuant to this 
Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party to 
provide confidential information, the disclosure of which 
would impede the enforcement of its laws and regulations, 
or otherwise be contrary to the public interest, or which 
would prejudice legitimate commercial interests of 
particular enterprises, public or private.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="226">Each Party shall designate a contact point to 
facilitate communications between the Parties on any matter 
covered by this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="General Definitions" chapter_identifier="28">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="227">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise 
specified: 



(a) 	the term “Agreement on Customs Valuation” means 
the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of 
the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 
in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 



(b) 	the term “Area” means: 

(i) 	with respect to Japan, the territory of 
Japan, and all the area beyond its 
territorial sea, including the sea-bed and 
subsoil thereof, over which Japan exercises 
sovereign rights or jurisdiction in 
accordance with international law and the 
laws and regulations of Japan; and 


(ii) 	with respect to Chile, the land, maritime 
and air space under its sovereignty, and the 
exclusive economic zone and the continental 
shelf within which it exercises sovereign 
rights and jurisdiction in accordance with 
international law and its domestic law; 


Note: 	Nothing in subparagraph (b) shall affect 
the rights and obligations of the Parties 
under international law, including those 
under the United Nations Convention on the 
Law of the Sea. 



(c) 	the term “Commission” means the Commission 
established under Article 189; 



(d) 	the term “customs authority” means the authority 
that, according to the legislation of each Party 
or non-Parties, is responsible for the 
administration and enforcement of customs laws 
and regulations: 


(i) 	with respect to Japan, the Ministry of 
Finance; and 


(ii) 	with respect to Chile, the National Customs 
Service (Servicio Nacional de Aduanas); 


(e) 	the term “days” means calendar days, including 
weekends and holidays; 



(f) 	the term “enterprise” means any corporation, 
company, association, partnership, trust, joint 
venture, sole-proprietorship or other entity 
constituted or organized under applicable law, 
whether for profit or otherwise, and whether 
privately-owned or controlled or governmentally-
owned or controlled; 



(g) 	the term “enterprise of a Party” means an 
enterprise constituted or organized under the law 
of a Party; 



(h) 	the term “existing” means in effect on the date 
of entry into force of this Agreement; 



(i) 	the term “GATS” means the General Agreement on 
Trade in Services in Annex 1B to the WTO 
Agreement;  



(j) 	the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement 
on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement. For the purposes of this Agreement, 
references to articles in the GATT 1994 include 
the interpretative notes; 



(k) 	the term “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the 
Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding 
System set out in the Annex to the International 
Convention on the Harmonized Commodity 
Description and Coding System, and adopted and 
implemented by the Parties in their respective 
laws; 



(l) 	the term “measure” means any measure by a Party, 
whether in the form of a law, regulation, rule, 
procedure, practice, decision, administrative 
action or any other form; 



(m) 	the term “natural person of a Party” means a 
natural person who, under the laws and 
regulations of a Party: 


(i) 	with respect to Japan, is a national of 
Japan; and 


(ii) 	with respect to Chile, is a national of 
Chile or a permanent resident in Chile; 


(n) 	the term “originating good” means a good which 
qualifies as an originating good under the 
provisions of Chapter 4; 



(o) 	the term “Parties” means Japan and Chile and the 
term ”Party” means either Japan or Chile; 



(p) 	the term “person” means a natural person or an 
enterprise; 



(q) 	the term “SPS Agreement” means the Agreement on 
the Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary 
Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 



(r) 	the term “state enterprise” means an enterprise 
owned or controlled by a Party; 



(s) 	the term “TRIPS Agreement” means the Agreement on 
Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property 
Rights in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement; and 



(t) 	the term “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh 
Agreement Establishing the World Trade 
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="29">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="228">The classification of goods in trade between the 
Parties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="229">Each Party shall accord national treatment to the 
goods of the other Party in accordance with Article III of 
the GATT 1994, and to this end Article III of the GATT 1994 
is incorporated into and made part of this Agreement, 
mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="230">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
each Party shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties on 
originating goods of the other Party designated for such 
purposes in its Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the 
terms and conditions set out in such Schedule. 



2. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
neither Party shall increase any customs duty on 
originating goods of the other Party from the rate to be 
applied in accordance with its Schedule in Annex 1. 



3. Upon the request of either Party, the Parties shall 
negotiate on issues such as improving market access 
conditions on originating goods designated for negotiation 
in the Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the terms 
and conditions set out in such Schedule.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="231">For the purposes of determining the customs value of 
goods traded between the Parties, provisions of Part I of 
the Agreement on Customs Valuation shall apply mutatis 
mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Export Duties" article_identifier="232">Neither Party shall introduce or maintain any duties, 
or fees or other charges of any kind imposed on a good 
exported from the Party into the other Party, unless such 
duties, or fees or other charges are not in excess of those 
imposed on the like good destined for domestic consumption. 


Note: 	The term “fees or other charges of any kind” shall 
not include any fees or other charges commensurate 
with the cost of services rendered, which are 
consistent with the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Agricultural Export Subsidies" article_identifier="233">Taking full account of the objectives of eliminating 
export subsidies on any agricultural good within the 
framework of the World Trade Organization, neither Party 
shall introduce or maintain any export subsidies on any 
agricultural good which is listed in Annex 1 to the 
Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="234">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, 
each Party shall not introduce or maintain any prohibition 
or restriction other than customs duties on the importation 
of any good of the other Party or on the exportation or 
sale for export of any good destined to the other Party, 
which is inconsistent with its obligations under Article XI 
of the GATT 1994 and its relevant provisions under the WTO 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="235">1. Nothing in this Section shall be construed to prevent 
a Party from taking any measure for balance-of-payments 
purposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in 
accordance with the conditions established under Article 
XII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Balance-
of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement on Tariffs 
and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Section shall preclude the use by a 
Party of exchange controls or exchange restrictions in 
accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the 
International Monetary Fund.
Bilateral Safeguard Measures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="236">1. Subject to the provisions of this Section, a Party may 
take a bilateral safeguard measure, to the minimum extent 
necessary to prevent or remedy the serious injury to a 
domestic industry of that Party and to facilitate 
adjustment, if an originating good of the other Party, as a 
result of the elimination or reduction of a customs duty in 
accordance with Article 14, is being imported into the 
former Party in such increased quantities, in absolute 
terms, and under such conditions that the imports of that 
originating good constitute a substantial cause of serious 
injury, or threat thereof. 



2. 	A Party may, as a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) 	suspend the further reduction of any rate of 
customs duty on the originating good provided for 
in Section 1; or 



(b) 	increase the rate of customs duty on the 
originating good to a level not to exceed the 
lesser of: 

(i) 	the most-favored-nation applied rate of 
customs duty in effect when the bilateral 
safeguard measure is taken; and 


(ii) 	the most-favored-nation applied rate of 
customs duty in effect on the day 
immediately preceding the date of entry into 
force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Investigation Procedures" article_identifier="237">1. A Party may take a bilateral safeguard measure only 
after an investigation has been carried out by the 
competent authorities of that Party in accordance with the 
same procedures as those provided for in Article 3 and 
subparagraph 2(c) of Article 4 of the Agreement on 
Safeguards. 



2. The investigation referred to in paragraph 1 shall in 
all cases be completed within one year following its date 
of initiation. 



3. In the investigation referred to in paragraph 1 to 
determine whether increased imports of an originating good 
have caused or are threatening to cause serious injury to a 
domestic industry under the terms of this Section, the 
competent authorities of the Party who carry out the 
investigation shall evaluate all relevant factors of an 
objective and quantifiable nature having a bearing on the 
situation of that domestic industry, in particular, the 
rate and amount of the increase in imports of the 
originating good in absolute terms, the share of the 
domestic market taken by the increased imports of the 
originating good, and the changes in the level of sales, 
production, productivity, capacity utilization, profits and 
losses, and employment. 



4. The determination that increased imports of an 
originating good have caused or are threatening to cause 
serious injury to a domestic industry shall not be made 
unless the investigation referred to in paragraph 1 
demonstrates, on the basis of objective evidence, the 
existence of the causal link between increased imports of 
the originating good and serious injury or threat thereof. 
When factors other than the increased imports of the 
originating good are causing injury to the domestic 
industry at the same time, such injury shall not be 
attributed to the increased imports of the originating 
good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Conditions And Limitations" article_identifier="238">The following conditions and limitations shall apply 
with regard to a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) 	no bilateral safeguard measure shall be 
maintained except to the extent and for such time 
as may be necessary to prevent or remedy serious 
injury and to facilitate adjustment, provided 
that such time shall not exceed a period of three 
years. However, in very exceptional 
circumstances, a bilateral safeguard measure may 
be extended, provided that the total period of 
the bilateral safeguard measure, including such 
extensions, shall not exceed four years; 



(b) 	in order to facilitate adjustment in a situation 
where the expected duration of a bilateral 
safeguard measure is over one year, the Party 
maintaining the bilateral safeguard measure shall 
progressively liberalize the bilateral safeguard 
measure at regular intervals during the period of 
application; 



(c) 	no bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied 
again to the import of a particular originating 
good which has been subject to such a bilateral 
safeguard measure, for a period of time equal to 
the duration of the previous bilateral safeguard 
measure or one year, whichever is longer; 



(d) 	nothing in this Section shall prevent a Party 
from applying safeguard measures to an 
originating good of the other Party in accordance 
with: 


(i) 	Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the 
Agreement on Safeguards; or 


(ii) Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture; 


(e) 	no bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied 
to the import of a particular originating good 
which has been en route from a Party to the other 
Party at the time when the other Party notifies 
the former Party of the decision to apply such a 
bilateral safeguard measure pursuant to 
subparagraph 1(b) of Article 23; and 



(f) 	upon the termination of a bilateral safeguard 
measure, the rate of customs duty shall be the 
rate which would have been in effect if the 
bilateral safeguard measure had never been 
applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Notification" article_identifier="239">1. A Party shall immediately deliver a written notice to 
the other Party upon: 



(a) 	taking a decision to initiate an investigation 
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 21 relating 
to serious injury or threat thereof, and the 
reasons for it; and 



(b) 	taking a decision to apply, extend or liberalize 
a bilateral safeguard measure. 

2. The Party making the written notice referred to in 
paragraph 1 shall provide the other Party with all 
pertinent information, which shall include: 



(a) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraph 
1(a), the reason for the initiation of the 
investigation, a precise description of the 
originating good subject to the investigation and 
its subheading of the Harmonized System, the 
period subject to the investigation and the date 
of initiation of the investigation; and 



(b) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraph 
1(b), evidence of serious injury or threat 
thereof caused by the increased imports of the 
originating good, a precise description of the 
originating good subject to the proposed 
bilateral safeguard measure and its subheading of 
the Harmonized System, a precise description of 
the bilateral safeguard measure, and the proposed 
date of its introduction and its expected 
duration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Consultations And Compensation" article_identifier="240">1. A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral 
safeguard measure shall provide adequate opportunity for 
prior consultations with the other Party with a view to 
reviewing the information arising from the investigation 
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 21, exchanging views 
on the bilateral safeguard measure and reaching an 
agreement on compensation set out in this Article. 



2. A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral 
safeguard measure shall provide to the other Party mutually 
agreed adequate means of trade compensation in the form of 
concessions of customs duties whose levels are 
substantially equivalent to the value of the additional 
customs duties expected to result from the bilateral 
safeguard measure. 



3. If the Parties are unable to agree on the compensation 
within 30 days after the commencement of the consultation 
pursuant to paragraph 1, the Party against whose 
originating good the bilateral safeguard measure is taken 
shall be free to suspend the application of concessions of 
customs duties under this Agreement, which are 
substantially equivalent to the bilateral safeguard 
measure, after giving written notice of such suspension, 
together with the information regarding concessions to be 
suspended, to the other Party. The Party exercising the 
right of suspension may suspend the application of 
concessions of customs duties only for the minimum period 
necessary to achieve the substantially equivalent effects 
and only while the bilateral safeguard measure is 
maintained.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Provisional Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="241">1. In critical circumstances, where delay would cause 
damage which it would be difficult to repair, a Party may 
take a provisional bilateral safeguard measure, which shall 
take the form of the measure set out in subparagraph 2(a) 
or (b) of Article 20 pursuant to a preliminary 
determination that there is clear evidence that increased 
imports of an originating good of the other Party have 
caused or are threatening to cause serious injury to a 
domestic industry. 



2. A Party shall deliver a written notice to the other 
Party prior to applying a provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure. Consultations between the Parties on the 
application of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure 
shall be initiated immediately after the provisional 
bilateral safeguard measure is taken. 



3. The duration of a provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure shall not exceed 200 days. During that period, the 
pertinent requirements of Article 21 shall be met. The 
duration of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure 
shall be counted as a part of the period referred to in 
subparagraph (a) of Article 22. 



4. Subparagraph (f) of Article 22 and paragraphs 1 and 2 
of Article 26 shall be applied mutatis mutandis to a 
provisional bilateral safeguard measure. The customs duty 
imposed as a result of a provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure shall be refunded if the subsequent investigation 
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 21 does not determine 
that increased imports of an originating good of the other 
Party have caused or threatened to cause serious injury to 
a domestic industry.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="242">1. Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial and 
reasonable administration of its laws and regulations 
relating to bilateral safeguard measure. 



2. Each Party shall adopt or maintain equitable, timely, 
transparent and effective procedures relating to bilateral 
safeguard measure. 



3. The written notice referred to in paragraph 1 of 
Article 23, paragraph 3 of Article 24 and paragraph 2 of 
Article 25 and any other communication between the Parties 
shall be done in the English language. 



4. The Parties shall review the provisions of this 
Section, if necessary, after 10 years of the date of entry 
into force of this Agreement.
Other Provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Committee On Trade In Goods" article_identifier="243">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter and Chapter 4, the Parties hereby 
establish a Committee on Trade in Goods (hereinafter 
referred to in this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring: 


(i) 	the implementation and operation of this 
Chapter and Chapter 4; 


(ii) 	any amendments to Annexes 2 and 4, proposed 
by either Party; and 


(iii) 	the Operational Procedures referred to in 
Article 52; 


(b) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter and 
Chapter 4; 



(c) 	reporting the findings and the outcome of 
discussions of the Committee to the Commission; 
and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties. 



4. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties. 



5. A Working Group on Fish and Fishery Products shall be 
established under the Committee. Details of the Working 
Group shall be set forth in a separate agreement to be 
concluded between the Governments of the Parties for the 
implementation of this Agreement (hereinafter referred to 
as “the Implementing Agreement”). 

Note: 	In the case of Chile, the Implementing 
Agreement shall be implemented as an Executive 
Agreement (Acuerdo de Ejecución) in accordance 
with the Political Constitution of the Republic 
of Chile (Constitución Política de la República 
de Chile).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Definitions" article_identifier="244">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “Agreement on Agriculture” means the 
Agreement on Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement; 



(b) 	the term “Agreement on Safeguards” means the 
Agreement on Safeguards in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement; 



(c) 	the term “bilateral safeguard measure” means a 
bilateral safeguard measure provided for in 
paragraph 2 of Article 20; 



(d) 	the term “customs duty” means any customs or 
import duty and a charge of any kind, including 
any form of surtax or surcharge, imposed in 
connection with the importation of a good, but 
does not include any: 


(i) 	charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed 
consistently with the provisions of 
paragraph 2 of Article III of the GATT 1994, 
in respect of the like goods or, directly 
competitive or substitutable goods of the 
Party or in respect of goods from which the 
imported goods have been manufactured or 
produced in whole or in part; 


(ii) 	anti-dumping or countervailing duty applied 
pursuant to a Party’s law and applied 
consistently with the provisions of Article 
VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on 
Implementation of Article VI of the General 
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994, and the 
Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing 
Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 
or 


(iii) 	fees or other charges commensurate with the 
cost of services rendered; 


(e) 	the term “customs value of goods” means the value 
of goods for the purposes of levying ad valorem 
customs duties on imported goods; 



(f) 	the term “domestic industry” means the producers 
as a whole of the like or directly competitive 
goods operating in a Party, or those whose 
collective output of the like or directly 
competitive goods constitutes a major proportion 
of the total domestic production of those goods; 



(g) 	the term “export subsidies” means export 
subsidies described in subparagraph (e) of 
Article 1 of the Agreement on Agriculture; 



(h) 	the term “provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure” means a provisional bilateral safeguard 
measure provided for in paragraph 1 of Article 
25; 



(i) 	the term “serious injury” means a significant 
overall impairment in the position of a domestic 
industry; and 



(j) 	the term “threat of serious injury” means serious 
injury that, on the basis of facts and not merely 
on allegation, conjecture or remote possibility, 
is clearly imminent.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="30">
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="245">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, a 
good shall qualify as an originating good of a Party where: 



(a) 	the good is wholly obtained or produced entirely 
in the Party, as defined in paragraph 2; 



(b) 	the good is produced entirely in the Party 
exclusively from originating materials of the 
Party; 



(c) 	the good is produced entirely in the Party using 
non-originating materials, provided that the good 
satisfies the product specific rules set out in 
Annex 2, as well as all other applicable 
requirements of this Chapter; or 



(d) 	except for a good provided for in Chapters 61 
through 63 of the Harmonized System, the good is 
produced entirely in the Party, but one or more 
of the non-originating materials that are used in 
the production of the good do not undergo an 
applicable change in tariff classification 
because: 

(i) 	the good is imported into the Party in an 
unassembled or disassembled form but is 
classified as an assembled good pursuant to 
Rule 2(a) of the General Rules for the 
Interpretation of the Harmonized System; or 


(ii) 	the heading for the good provides for and 
specifically describes both the good itself 
and its parts and is not further subdivided 
into subheadings, or the subheading for the 
good provides for and specifically describes 
both the good itself and its parts, 


provided that the qualifying value content of the good, 
determined in accordance with Article 30, is not less than 
45 percent when the method referred to in subparagraph 1(a) 
of Article 30 is used or 30 percent when the method 
referred to in subparagraph 1(b) of Article 30 is used, 
unless otherwise provided for in Annex 2, and that the good 
satisfies all other applicable requirements of this 
Chapter. 


2. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a), the following 
goods shall be considered as being wholly obtained or 
produced entirely in a Party: 



(a) 	mineral goods extracted in the Party; 



(b) 	vegetable goods harvested in the Party; 



(c) 	live animals born and raised in the Party; 



(d) 	goods obtained from hunting, trapping or fishing 
in the Party; 



(e) 	goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 



(f) 	fish, shellfish and other marine species taken 
from the sea beyond the territorial seas of the 
Parties by vessels: 

(i) 	which are registered or recorded in the 
Party; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; 


(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 50 
percent by nationals of the Party, or by an 
enterprise with its head office in the 
Party, of which the representatives, 
chairman of the board of directors, and the 
majority of the members of such board are 
nationals of the Party, and of which at 
least 50 percent of the equity interest is 
owned by nationals or enterprises of the 
Party; 


(iv) 	of which the master and officers are all 
nationals of the Party; and 


(v) 	of which at least 75 percent of the crew are 
nationals of the Party; 


Note 1: 	Without prejudice to the rights and 
obligations of the Parties under 
international law, including those under 
the United Nations Convention on the Law 
of the Sea, subparagraph (f) shall not 
apply to fish, shellfish and other 
marine species taken from the exclusive 
economic zone of the other Party by the 
vessels referred to in that 
subparagraph. 


Note 2: 	The requirements of subparagraphs 
(f)(iii) through (v) shall not apply to 
vessels registered or recorded in Chile 
prior to June 30, 1991, provided for in 
Transitional Article 10 of the 
consolidated text of the Law 18.892, 
General Law on Fisheries and Aquiculture 
(Artículo 10 Transitorio del texto 
refundido, coordinado y sistematizado de 
la Ley 18.892, Ley General de Pesca y 
Acuicultura), and their successor 
vessels registered or recorded in 
accordance with that Law and other 
relevant provisions of Chilean law. 


(g) 	goods produced from the goods referred to in 
subparagraph (f) on board factory ships: 


(i) 	which are registered or recorded in the 
Party; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; 


(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 50 
percent by nationals of the Party, or by an 
enterprise with its head office in the 
Party, of which the representatives, 
chairman of the board of directors, and the 
majority of the members of such board are 
nationals of the Party, and of which at 
least 50 percent of the equity interest is 
owned by nationals or enterprises of the 
Party; 


(iv) 	of which the master and officers are all 
nationals of the Party; and 


(v) 	of which at least 75 percent of the crew are 
nationals of the Party; 


  Note: 	The requirements of subparagraphs (g)(iii) 
through (v) shall not apply to factory 
ships registered or recorded in Chile 
prior to June 30, 1991, provided for in 
Transitional Article 10 of the 
consolidated text of the Law 18.892, 
General Law on Fisheries and Aquiculture 
(Artículo 10 Transitorio del texto 
refundido, coordinado y sistematizado de 
la Ley 18.892, Ley General de Pesca y 
Acuicultura), and their successor vessels 
registered or recorded in accordance with 
that Law and other relevant provisions of 
Chilean law. 



(h) 	goods taken by the Party or a natural person or 
enterprise of the Party from the seabed or 
subsoil beneath the seabed outside the 
territorial sea of the Party, provided that the 
Party has rights to exploit such seabed or 
subsoil; 



(i) 	waste and scrap derived from: 


(i) 	production in the Party; or 


(ii) 	used goods collected in the Party, provided 
that such goods are fit only for the 
recovery of raw materials; and 


(j) 	goods produced in the Party exclusively from the 
goods referred to in subparagraphs (a) through 
(i), or from their derivatives, at any stage of 
production. 

3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c), the product 
specific rules set out in Annex 2 requiring that the 
materials used undergo a change in tariff classification or 
a specific manufacturing or processing operation shall 
apply only to non-originating materials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Qualifying Value Content" article_identifier="246">1. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(c) of Article 29, 
the qualifying value content of a good shall be calculated 
on the basis of one or the other of the following methods: 



(a) 	Method based on value of non-originating 
materials (“Build-down method”) 


TV - VNM 
QVC = ---------- x 100 
TV 


(b) 	Method based on value of originating materials 
(“Build-up method”) 

VOM 
QVC = ------ x 100 
TV 


 Where: 


QVC is the qualifying value content of the good, 
expressed as a percentage; 


TV is the transaction value of the good adjusted 
to F.O.B. basis, except as provided for in 
paragraph 2; 


VNM is the value of non-originating materials 
used by the producer in the production of the 
good determined pursuant to Article 31; and 


VOM is the value of originating materials used by 
the producer in the production of the good 
determined pursuant to Article 31. 


2. In the event that there is no transaction value or the 
transaction value of the good is unacceptable under Article 
1 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, the value of the 
good shall be determined in accordance with Articles 2 
through 7 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Value Of Materials" article_identifier="247">1. 	The value of a material: 



(a) 	shall be the transaction value of the material; 
or 



(b) 	in the event that there is no transaction value 
or the transaction value of the material is 
unacceptable under Article 1 of the Agreement on 
Customs Valuation, shall be determined in 
accordance with Articles 2 through 7 of the 
Agreement on Customs Valuation. 

2. 	The value of a material referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) 	shall include freight, insurance, packing and all 
other costs incurred in transporting the material 
to the importation port in the Party where the 
producer of the good is located; and 



(b) 	may include the cost of waste and spoilage 
resulting from the use of the material in the 
production of the good, less the value of 
reusable scrap or by-product. 

3. The value of a non-originating material shall not 
include, where the producer acquires the material in the 
Party where the producer is located, freight, insurance, 
packing and all other costs incurred in transporting the 
material from the warehouse of the supplier of the material 
to the place where the producer is located; as well as any 
other known and ascertainable cost incurred in the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="248">Non-originating materials used in the production of a 
good that do not undergo an applicable change in tariff 
classification shall be disregarded in determining whether 
the good qualifies as an originating good of a Party, 
provided that the totality of such materials does not 
exceed specific percentages in value, weight or volume of 
the good as set out in Annex 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="249">For the purposes of determining whether a good 
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, an originating 
good of the other Party which is used as a material in the 
production of the good in the former Party may be 
considered as an originating material of the former Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="250">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good 
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, where fungible 
materials consisting of originating materials of the Party 
and non-originating materials that are commingled in an 
inventory are used in the production of the good, the 
origin of the materials may be determined pursuant to an 
inventory management method recognized in the Generally 
Accepted Accounting Principles in the Party. 



2. Where fungible goods consisting of originating goods 
of a Party and non-originating goods are commingled in an 
inventory and, prior to exportation do not undergo any 
production process or any operation in the Party where they 
were commingled other than unloading, reloading and any 
other operation to preserve them in good condition, the 
origin of the good may be determined pursuant to an 
inventory management method recognized in the Generally 
Accepted Accounting Principles in the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Sets, Kits Or Composite Goods" article_identifier="251">1. Sets, kits and composite goods classified pursuant to 
Rule 3 of the General Rules for the Interpretation of the 
Harmonized System shall qualify as originating goods of the 
exporting Party, where every good contained in the sets, 
kits or composite goods satisfies the applicable rule of 
origin for each of them under this Chapter. 



2. Paragraph 1 shall prevail over the product specific 
rules set out in Annex 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="252">Indirect materials shall be, without regard to where 
they are produced, considered to be originating materials 
of the Party where the good is produced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Accessories, Spare Parts And Tools" article_identifier="253">Accessories, spare parts or tools delivered with a 
good that form part of the good’s standard accessories, 
spare parts or tools, shall be disregarded in determining 
whether the good qualifies as an originating good of a 
Party, provided that: 



(a) 	the accessories, spare parts or tools are not 
invoiced separately from the good, without regard 
of whether they are separately described in the 
invoice; and 



(b) 	the quantities and value of the accessories, 
spare parts or tools are customary for the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Packaging Materials And Containers For Retail Sale" article_identifier="254">Packaging materials and containers in which a good is 
packaged for retail sale shall, if classified with the good 
pursuant to Rule 5 of the General Rules for the 
Interpretation of the Harmonized System, be disregarded in 
determining whether the good qualifies as an originating 
good of a Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Packing Materials And Containers For Shipment" article_identifier="255">Packing materials and containers for shipment shall be 
disregarded in determining whether the good qualifies as an 
originating good of a Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="256">1. A good shall not be considered to be an originating 
good of the exporting Party merely by reason of: 



(a) 	operations to ensure the preservation of products 
in good condition during transport and storage; 



(b) 	changes of packaging and breaking up and assembly 
of packages; 



 (c) 	disassembly; 



(d) 	placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simple 
packaging operations; 



(e) 	collection of parts and components classified as 
a good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules 
for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 



(f) 	mere making-up of sets of articles; or 



(g) 	any combination of operations referred to in 
subparagraphs (a) through (f). 

2. Paragraph 1 shall prevail over the product specific 
rules set out in Annex 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Consignment Criteria" article_identifier="257">1. An originating good of a Party shall be deemed to meet 
the consignment criteria when it is: 



(a) 	transported directly from the Party to the other 
Party; or 



(b) 	transported through one or more non-Parties for 
the purpose of transit or temporary storage in 
warehouses in such non-Parties, provided that it 
does not undergo operations other than unloading, 
reloading and any other operation to preserve it 
in good condition. 

2. If an originating good of a Party does not meet the 
consignment criteria referred to in paragraph 1, that good 
shall not be considered as an originating good of the 
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Exhibitions" article_identifier="258">Notwithstanding Article 41, an originating good of a 
Party imported into the other Party after an exhibition in 
a non-Party shall continue to qualify as an originating 
good of the former Party when it: 



(a) 	remained under the control of the customs 
authority of the non-Party while it was in the 
non-Party; and 



 (b) 	was transported: 

(i) directly to and from the non-Party; or 


(ii) 	through other non-Parties for the purpose of 
transit or temporary storage in warehouses 
in such other non-Parties, provided that it 
did not undergo operations other than 
unloading, reloading and any other operation 
to preserve it in good condition.
Certificate of Origin and Related Procedures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Claim For Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="259">1. The customs authority of the importing Party shall 
require a certificate of origin for an originating good of 
the exporting Party from importers who claim the 
preferential tariff treatment for the good. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the customs authority of 
the importing Party shall not require a certificate of 
origin from importers for: 



(a) 	an importation of originating goods of the 
exporting Party whose total customs value does 
not exceed 1000 United States of America dollars 
or its equivalent amount in the Party’s currency, 
or such higher amount as it may establish; or 



(b) 	an importation of originating goods of the 
exporting Party, for which the customs authority 
of the importing Party has waived the requirement 
for a certificate of origin, 

provided that the importation does not form part of one or 
more importations that may reasonably be considered to have 
been undertaken or arranged for the purpose of avoiding the 
certification requirements of this Article and Article 46. 


3. In the case where an originating good of the exporting 
Party is imported after an exhibition in a non-Party, the 
customs authority of the importing Party may require 
importers, who claim the preferential tariff treatment for 
the good, to submit: 



(a) 	a certificate or any other information given by 
the customs authority of that non-Party or other 
relevant entities, which evidences that the good 
meets the requirements of subparagraph (a) of 
Article 42; and 



(b) 	(i) a copy of through bill of lading; or 

(ii) 	if the good was transported through other 
non-Parties, a certificate or any other 
information given by the customs authorities 
of such other non-Parties or other relevant 
entities, which evidences that the good has 
not undergone operations other than 
unloading, reloading and any other operation 
to preserve it in good condition in those 
other non-Parties. 


4. Where an originating good of the exporting Party is 
imported through one or more non-Parties except for the 
case referred to in paragraph 3, the customs authority of 
the importing Party may require importers, who claim the 
preferential tariff treatment for the good, to submit: 



(a) 	a copy of through bill of lading; or 



(b) 	a certificate or any other information given by 
the customs authorities of such non-Parties or 
other relevant entities, which evidences that the 
good has not undergone operations other than 
unloading, reloading and any other operation to 
preserve it in good condition in those non-
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="260">1. A certificate of origin shall be issued by the 
competent authority specified in Annex 3(hereinafter 
referred to in this Chapter as “competent authority”) of 
the exporting Party on request having been made in writing 
by the exporter. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, the competent 
authority of the exporting Party may designate public or 
private entities or bodies to be responsible for the 
issuance of certificate of origin in accordance with the 
applicable laws and regulations of the exporting Party. 



3. Where the competent authority of the exporting Party 
designates public or private entities or bodies to carry 
out the issuance of certificate of origin, the exporting 
Party shall notify in writing the other Party of its 
designees. 



4. For the purposes of this Chapter, upon the entry into 
force of this Agreement, a format of certificate of origin 
shall be established in the English language in the 
Operational Procedures referred to in Article 52. A 
certificate of origin shall include minimum data specified 
in Annex 4. 



5. A certificate of origin shall be completed in the 
English language. 



6. An issued certificate of origin shall be applicable to 
an importation of originating goods of the exporting Party 
into the importing Party and be valid for one year from the 
date of issuance. 



7. Where the exporter of a good is not the producer of 
the good in the exporting Party, the exporter may request a 
certificate of origin on the basis of: 



(a) 	a declaration provided by the exporter to the 
competent authority of the exporting Party or its 
designees based on the information provided by 
the producer of the good to that exporter; or 



(b) 	a declaration voluntarily provided by the 
producer of the good directly to the competent 
authority of the exporting Party or its designees 
by the request of the exporter. 


8. A certificate of origin shall be issued only after the 
exporter who requests the certificate of origin, or the 
producer of a good in the exporting Party referred to in 
subparagraph 7(b), proves to the competent authority of the 
exporting Party or its designees that the good to be 
exported qualifies as an originating good of the exporting 
Party. The competent authority of the exporting Party or 
its designees may, in accordance with the applicable laws 
and regulations of the exporting Party, require such 
exporter or producer to provide information relating to the 
origin of the good. 



9. The competent authority of the exporting Party shall 
provide the importing Party with impressions of stamps used 
by the competent authority of the exporting Party or its 
designees. 



10. Each Party shall ensure that the competent authority 
of the exporting Party or its designees shall keep a record 
of issued certificates of origin for a period of five years 
after the date on which the certificate of origin was 
issued. Such record will include all antecedents, which 
were presented to prove the qualification as an originating 
good of the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Obligations Regarding Exportations" article_identifier="261">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, ensure that the exporter to whom a certificate 
of origin has been issued, or the producer of a good in the 
exporting Party referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 


44: 



(a) 	shall notify in writing the competent authority 
of the exporting Party or its designees without 
delay when such exporter or producer knows that 
such good does not qualify as an originating good 
of the exporting Party; and 



(b) 	shall keep the records relating to the origin of 
the good for five years after the date on which 
the certificate of origin was issued.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Obligations Regarding Importations" article_identifier="262">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, the 
customs authority of the importing Party shall require an 
importer who claims preferential tariff treatment for a 
good imported from the other Party to: 



(a) 	make a written declaration, based on a valid 
certificate of origin, that the good qualifies as 
an originating good of the exporting Party; 



(b) 	have the certificate of origin in its possession 
at the time the declaration is made; 



(c) 	provide the certificate of origin on the request 
of the customs authority of the importing Party; 
and 



(d) 	promptly make a corrected declaration and pay any 
duties owing where the importer has reason to 
believe that the certificate of origin on which a 
declaration was based contains information that 
is not correct. 

2. Each Party shall ensure that, in the case in which the 
importer at the time of importation does not have a 
certificate of origin in its possession, the importer may, 
in accordance with the laws and regulations of the 
importing Party, provide the customs authority of the 
importing Party with the certificate of origin issued in 
accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 44 and, if required, 
such other documentation relating to the importation of the 
good, within a period not exceeding one year after the time 
of importation. 


Note: 	In the case of importation into Chile, any 
excess customs duties shall be refunded to the 
importer referred to in paragraph 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Request For Checking Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="263">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good 
imported from the exporting Party under preferential tariff 
treatment qualifies as an originating good of the exporting 
Party, the customs authority of the importing Party may 
request information relating to the origin of the good from 
the competent authority of the exporting Party on the basis 
of a certificate of origin, where it has reasonable doubt 
as to the authenticity of the certificate of origin or the 
accuracy of the information included in the certificate of 
origin. 



2. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the competent 
authority of the exporting Party shall, in accordance with 
the laws and regulations of the exporting Party, provide 
the information requested within a period of three months 
from the date of receipt of the request. If the customs 
authority of the importing Party considers necessary, it 
may require additional information relating to the origin 
of the good. If additional information is requested by the 
customs authority of the importing Party, the competent 
authority of the exporting Party shall, in accordance with 
the laws and regulations of the exporting Party, provide 
the information requested within a period of two months 
from the date of receipt of the request. 



3. For the purposes of paragraph 2, the competent 
authority of the exporting Party may request the exporter 
to whom the certificate of origin has been issued, or the 
producer of the good in the exporting Party referred to in 
subparagraph 7(b) of Article 44, to provide the former with 
the information requested. 



4. The request of information in accordance with 
paragraph 1 shall not preclude the use of the verification 
method provided for in Article 48.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Verification Visit" article_identifier="264">1. The customs authority of the importing Party may 
request the competent authority of the exporting Party to: 



(a) 	collect and provide information relating to the 
origin of a good and check, for that purpose, the 
facilities used in the production of the good, 
through a visit by the competent authority of the 
exporting Party along with the customs authority 
of the importing Party to the premises of the 
exporter to whom the certificate of origin has 
been issued, or the producer of the good in the 
exporting Party referred to in subparagraph 7(b) 
of Article 44; and 



(b) 	provide information relating to the origin of the 
good in the possession of the competent authority 
of the exporting Party or its designees during 
the visit pursuant to subparagraph (a). 


2. When requesting the competent authority of the 
exporting Party to conduct a visit pursuant to paragraph 1, 
the customs authority of the importing Party shall deliver 
a written communication with such request to the competent 
authority of the exporting Party at least 40 days in 
advance of the proposed date of the visit, the receipt of 
which is to be confirmed by the competent authority of the 
exporting Party. The competent authority of the exporting 
Party shall request the written consent of the exporter, or 
the producer of the good in the exporting Party whose 
premises are to be visited. 



3. The communication referred to in paragraph 2 shall 
include: 



(a) 	the identity of the customs authority issuing the 
communication; 



(b) 	the name of the exporter, or the producer of the 
good in the exporting Party whose premises are 
requested to be visited; 



(c) 	the proposed date and place of the visit; 



(d) 	the objective and scope of the proposed visit, 
including specific reference to the good subject 
of the verification referred to in the 
certificate of origin; and 



(e) 	the names and titles of the officials of the 
customs authority of the importing Party to be 
present during the visit. 


4. The competent authority of the exporting Party shall 
respond in writing to the customs authority of the 
importing Party, within 30 days of the receipt of the 
communication referred to in paragraph 2, if it accepts or 
refuses to conduct the visit requested pursuant to 
paragraph 1. 



5. The competent authority of the exporting Party shall, 
in accordance with the laws and regulations of the 
exporting Party, provide within 45 days or any other 
mutually agreed period from the last day of the visit, to 
the customs authority of the importing Party the 
information obtained pursuant to paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Determination Of Origin And Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="265">1. The customs authority of the importing Party may deny 
preferential tariff treatment to a good for which an 
importer claims preferential tariff treatment where the 
good does not qualify as an originating good of the 
exporting Party or where the importer fails to comply with 
any of the relevant requirements of this Chapter. 



2. The competent authority of the exporting Party shall, 
when it cancels the decision to issue the certificate of 
origin, promptly notify the cancellation to the exporter to 
whom the certificate of origin has been issued, and to the 
customs authority of the importing Party except where the 
certificate of origin has been returned to the competent 
authority of the exporting Party. The customs authority of 
the importing Party may determine that the good does not 
qualify as an originating good of the exporting Party and 
may deny preferential tariff treatment when it receives the 
notification. 



3. The customs authority of the importing Party may 
determine that a good does not qualify as an originating 
good of the exporting Party and may deny preferential 
tariff treatment, and a written determination thereof shall 
be sent to the competent authority of the exporting Party: 



(a) 	where the competent authority of the exporting 
Party fails to respond to the request within the 
period referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 47 
or paragraph 5 of Article 48; 



(b) 	where the competent authority of the exporting 
Party refuses to conduct a visit, or fails to 
respond to the communication referred to in 
paragraph 2 of Article 48 within the period 
referred to in paragraph 4 of Article 48; or 



(c) 	where the information provided to the customs 
authority of the importing Party pursuant to 
Article 47 or 48, is not sufficient to prove that 
the good qualifies as an originating good of the 
exporting Party. 


4. After carrying out the procedures outlined in Article 
47 or 48 as the case may be, the customs authority of the 
importing Party shall provide the competent authority of 
the exporting Party with a written determination of whether 
or not the good qualifies as an originating good of the 
exporting Party, including findings of fact and the legal 
basis for the determination, within 45 days from the date 
of receipt of the information provided by the competent 
authority of the exporting Party pursuant to Article 47 or 

48. The competent authority of the exporting Party shall 
inform such determination by the customs authority of the 
importing Party to the exporter, or the producer of the 
good in the exporting Party, whose premises were subject to 
the visit referred to in Article 48.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Penalties And Measures Against False Declaration" article_identifier="266">1. Each Party shall establish or maintain, in accordance 
with its laws and regulations, appropriate penalties or 
other sanctions against its exporters to whom a certificate 
of origin has been issued and the producers of a good in 
the exporting Party referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of 
Article 44, for providing false declaration or documents to 
the competent authority of the exporting Party or its 
designees prior to the issuance of certificate of origin. 



2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate 
against its exporters to whom a certificate of origin has 
been issued and the producers of a good in the exporting 
Party referred to in subparagraph 7(b) of Article 44, for 
failing to notify in writing to the competent authority of 
the exporting Party or its designees without delay after 
having known, after the issuance of certificate of origin, 
that such good does not qualify as an originating good of 
the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Transitional Provision For Goods In Transit Or Storage" article_identifier="267">An importer may not claim preferential tariff 
treatment for a good which, on the date of entry into force 
of this Agreement, is in transport from the exporting Party 
to the importing Party or in temporary storage in 
warehouses, except that: 



(a) 	the good otherwise satisfies all applicable 
requirements of this Chapter; and 



(b) 	the importer provides, in accordance with the 
laws and regulations of the importing Party, the 
customs authority of the importing Party with the 
certificate of origin issued retrospectively and, 
if required, such other documentation relating to 
the importation of the good, within a period not 
exceeding four months after the entry into force 
of this Agreement.
Other Provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Operational Procedures" article_identifier="268">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement, 
the Commission shall adopt the Operational Procedures that 
provide detailed regulations pursuant to which the customs 
authorities, the competent authorities and other relevant 
authorities of the Parties shall implement their functions 
under this Chapter and Chapter 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="269">1. Communications between the importing Party and the 
exporting Party shall be conducted in the English language. 



2. For the application of the relevant product specific 
rules set out in Annex 2 and the determination of origin, 
the Generally Accepted Accounting Principles in the 
exporting Party shall be applied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Definitions" article_identifier="270">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “exporter” means a person located in an 
exporting Party who exports goods from the 
exporting Party; 



(b) 	the term “F.O.B.” means free on board, regardless 
of the mode of transportation, at the point of 
direct shipment by the seller to the buyer; 



(c) 	the term “fungible goods” or “fungible materials” 
respectively means goods or materials that are 
interchangeable for commercial purposes, whose 
properties are essentially identical; 



(d) 	the term “Generally Accepted Accounting 
Principles” means the recognized consensus or 
substantial authoritative support within a Party 
at a particular time as to which economic 
resources and obligations should be recorded as 
assets and liabilities, which changes in assets 
and liabilities should be recorded, how the 
assets and liabilities and changes in them should 
be measured, what information should be disclosed 
and how it should be disclosed, and which 
financial statements should be prepared. These 
standards may be broad guidelines of general 
application as well as detailed practices and 
procedures; 



(e) 	the term “importer” means a person who imports 
goods into the importing Party; 



(f) 	the term “indirect materials” means goods used in 
the production, testing or inspection of another 
good but not physically incorporated into the 
good, or goods used in the maintenance of 
buildings or the operation of equipment 
associated with the production of another good, 
including: 


(i) 	fuel and energy; 


(ii) tools, dies and moulds; 


(iii) 	spare parts and goods used in the 
maintenance of equipment and buildings; 



(iv) 	lubricants, greases, compounding materials 
and other goods used in production or used 
to operate equipment and buildings; 


(v) 	gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safety 
equipment and supplies; 


(vi) 	equipment, devices and supplies used for 
testing or inspection; 

(vii) 	catalysts and solvents; and 


(viii) 	any other goods that are not incorporated 
into another good but whose use in the 
production of the good can reasonably be 
demonstrated to be a part of that 
production; 


(g) 	the term “material” means a good that is used in 
the production of another good; 



(h) 	the term “originating material of a Party” means 
an originating good of a Party which is used in 
the production of another good in the Party, 
including that which is considered as an 
originating material of the Party pursuant to 
Article 33; 



(i) 	the term “packing materials and containers for 
shipment” means goods that are used to protect a 
good during its transportation, other than 
packaging materials and containers for retail 
sale referred to in Article 38; 



(j) 	the term “preferential tariff treatment” means 
the rate of customs duties applicable to an 
originating good of the exporting Party in 
accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 14; 



(k) 	the term “producer” means a person who engages in 
the production of goods or materials; 



(l) 	the term “production” means methods of obtaining 
goods including manufacturing, assembling, 
processing, raising, growing, breeding, mining, 
extracting, harvesting, fishing, trapping, 
gathering, collecting, hunting and capturing; 



(m) 	the term “transaction value of a good” means the 
price actually paid or payable for a good with 
respect to a transaction of the producer of the 
good, pursuant to the principles of Article 1 of 
the Agreement on Customs Valuation, adjusted in 
accordance with the principles of paragraphs 1, 3 
and 4 of Article 8 of the Agreement on Customs 
Valuation, regardless of whether the good is sold 
for export. For the purposes of this definition, 
the seller referred to in the Agreement on 
Customs Valuation shall be the producer of the 
good; and 



(n) 	the term “transaction value of a material” means 
the price actually paid or payable for a material 
with respect to a transaction of the producer of 
the good, pursuant to the principles of Article 1 
of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, adjusted 
in accordance with the principles of paragraphs 
1, 3 and 4 of Article 8 of the Agreement on 
Customs Valuation, regardless of whether the 
material is sold for export. For the purposes of 
this definition, the seller referred to in the 
Agreement on Customs Valuation shall be the 
supplier of the material, and the buyer referred 
to in the Agreement on Customs Valuation shall be 
the producer of the good.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="31">
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Scope" article_identifier="271">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures 
required for the clearance of goods traded between the 
Parties. 



2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of each Party and 
within the available resources of their respective customs 
authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Transparency" article_identifier="272">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant information 
of general application pertaining to its customs laws and 
administrative procedures is readily available to any 
interested person, with maximum use of information and 
communications technology. 



2. When information that has been made available must be 
revised due to changes in its customs laws, each Party 
shall, whenever possible, make the revised information 
publicly available sufficiently in advance of the entry 
into force of the changes. 



3. Each Party shall endeavor to provide the other Party 
with advance notice of any significant modification of its 
policy with regard to customs procedures that is likely to 
substantially affect the implementation and operation of 
this Agreement. 



4. At the request of any interested person of the 
Parties, each Party shall endeavor to provide, as quickly 
and as accurately as possible, information relating to the 
specific customs matters raised by the interested person 
and pertaining to its customs laws. 



5. Each Party shall designate one or more enquiry points 
to answer reasonable enquiries from any interested person 
of the Parties concerning customs matters, and shall make 
publicly available, including through the Internet, the 
names and addresses of such enquiry points.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="273">1. Both Parties shall apply their respective customs 
procedures in a predictable, consistent and transparent 
manner. 



2. To expedite customs clearance, while ensuring 
effective enforcement against illicit trafficking of goods, 
each Party shall: 



(a) 	endeavor to make use of information and 
communications technology, taking into account 
international standards; 



(b) 	adopt or maintain accessible information and 
communications technology systems, allowing the 
authorized or registered person to send 
declarations to its customs authority; 



(c) 	adopt or maintain simplified customs procedures; 



(d) 	harmonize its customs procedures, as far as 
possible, with relevant international standards 
and recommended practices such as those made 
under the auspices of the Customs Co-operation 
Council; and 



(e) 	promote cooperation, wherever appropriate, 
between its customs authority and: 

(i) 	other national authorities of the Party; 


(ii) the trading communities of the Party; and 


(iii) the customs authorities of non-Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="274">1. The Parties shall cooperate with each other in the 
field of customs procedures. 



2. Such cooperation shall be implemented as provided for 
in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Penalties" article_identifier="275">Each Party shall adopt or maintain appropriate 
sanctions or other measures against violations of its 
customs laws.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Committee On Customs Procedures" article_identifier="276">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Customs Procedures (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing the implementation and operation of 
this Chapter; 



(b) 	reporting the findings of the Committee to the 
Commission; 



(c) 	identifying areas, relating to this Chapter, to 
be improved for facilitating trade in goods 
between the Parties; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties. 



4. The composition of the Committee shall be specified in 
the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Definition" article_identifier="277">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “customs 
laws” of a Party means the laws and regulations of a Party 
relating to the importation, exportation, transit or 
storage of goods, and any other related matters, falling 
under the competence of the customs authority of the Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="32">
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Scope" article_identifier="278">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary and 
phytosanitary (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as 
"SPS") measures of the Parties under the SPS Agreement, 
that may, directly or indirectly, affect trade in goods 
between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="279">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations 
relating to SPS measures under the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="280">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which is 
able to answer all reasonable enquiries from the other 
Party regarding SPS measures and, if appropriate, to 
provide their relevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Working Group On Sps Measures" article_identifier="281">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Working Group on SPS measures (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “Working Group”). 



2. The functions of the Working Group shall be: 



(a) 	exchange of information on such matters as 
occurrences of SPS incidents in the Parties and 
non-Parties, and change or introduction of SPS-
related regulations and standards of the Parties, 
which may, directly or indirectly, affect trade 
in goods between the Parties; 



(b) 	science-based consultations to identify and 
address specific issues that may arise from the 
application of SPS measures; 



(c) 	consulting cooperative efforts between the 
Parties in international fora in relation to SPS 
measures; and 



(d) 	discussing technical cooperation between the 
Parties on SPS measures. 


3. The Working Group shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties with responsibility for SPS 
measures. 



4. The Working Group shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="282">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="33">
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Scope" article_identifier="283">1. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures as defined 
in the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A 
to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to in this 
Chapter as “TBT Agreement”). 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to purchasing 
specifications prepared by governmental bodies for 
production or consumption requirements of governmental 
bodies and sanitary and phytosanitary measures as defined 
in the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="284">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations 
relating to technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures under the TBT Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="285">1. For the purposes of ensuring that technical 
regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures 
do not create unnecessary obstacles to trade in goods 
between the Parties, the Parties shall, where possible, 
cooperate in the field of technical regulations, standards 
and conformity assessment procedures. 



2. The forms of cooperation pursuant to paragraph 1 may 
include the following: 



(a) 	conducting joint studies and holding seminars, in 
order to enhance mutual understanding of 
technical regulations, standards and conformity 
assessment procedures in the Parties; 



(b) 	exchanging information on technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures; 
and 



(c) 	contributing, where appropriate, jointly to the 
activities related to technical regulations, 
standards and conformity assessment procedures in 
international and regional fora. 


3. The implementation of this Article shall be subject to 
the availability of appropriated funds and the applicable 
laws and regulations of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="286">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Technical Regulations, Standards and 
Conformity Assessment Procedures (hereinafter referred to 
in this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) coordinating cooperation pursuant to Article 69; 



(b) 	reviewing the implementation and operation of 
this Chapter; 



(c) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter 
with the objective of obtaining mutually 
acceptable solutions; 



(d) 	reporting, where appropriate, the findings of the 
Committee to the Commission; and 



(e) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties. 



4. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="287">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="34">
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Scope" article_identifier="288">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or 
maintained by a Party relating to: 



(a) 	investors of the other Party; 



(b) 	investments of investors of the other Party in 
the Area of the former Party; and 



(c) 	with respect to Articles 77 and 87, all 
investments in the Area of the former Party. 


2. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter 
and another Chapter, the other Chapter shall prevail to the 
extent of the inconsistency. 



3. This Chapter shall not apply to measures adopted or 
maintained by a Party to the extent that they are covered 
by Chapter 10. 



4. This Chapter is subject to Annex 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="289">Each Party shall accord to investors of the other 
Party and to their investments made in the Area of the 
former Party, treatment no less favorable than that it 
accords, in like circumstances, to its own investors and to 
their investments with respect to investment activities in 
its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="290">Each Party shall accord to investors of the other 
Party and to their investments made in the Area of the 
former Party, treatment no less favorable than that it 
accords, in like circumstances, to investors of a non-Party 
and to their investments with respect to investment 
activities in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="291">Each Party shall accord to investments made in its 
Area by investors of the other Party, treatment in 
accordance with customary international law, including fair 
and equitable treatment and full protection and security. 


Note 1: 	Article 75 prescribes the customary international 
law minimum standard of treatment of aliens as the 
minimum standard of treatment to be afforded to 
investments made in the Area of a Party by 
investors of the other Party. The customary 
international law minimum standard of treatment of 
aliens refers to all customary international law 
principles that protect the economic rights and 
interests of aliens. The concepts of “fair and 
equitable treatment” and “full protection and 
security” do not require treatment in addition to 
or beyond that which is required by the customary 
international law minimum standard of treatment of 
aliens. 


Note 2: 	A determination that there has been a breach of 
another provision of this Agreement, or of a 
separate international agreement, does not 
establish that there has been a breach of Article 


75. 


Note 3: 	Each Party shall accord to investors of the other 
Party, non-discriminatory treatment with regard to 
access to the courts of justice and administrative 
tribunals and agencies of the former Party in 
pursuit and in defense of rights of such 
investors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="292">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other 
Party that have suffered loss relating to their investments 
made in the Area of the former Party due to armed conflict, 
revolution, insurrection, civil disturbance or any other 
similar event, treatment, as regards restitution, 
indemnification, compensation or any other settlement, that 
is no less favorable than that it accords to its own 
investors or to investors of a non-Party. 



2. Any payments as a means of settlement referred to in 
paragraph 1 shall be fully realizable, freely transferable 
and freely convertible at the market exchange rate into the 
currency of the Party of the investors concerned and freely 
usable currencies. 



3. Paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply to any subsidies 
including grants, government supported loans, guarantees 
and insurance as provided for in subparagraph 5(b) of 
Article 79.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Performance Requirements" article_identifier="293">1. Neither Party may impose or enforce any of the 
following requirements, or enforce any commitment or 
undertaking, in connection with investment activities of an 
investor of a Party or of a non-Party in its Area: 



(a) 	to export a given level or percentage of goods or 
services; 



(b) 	to achieve a given level or percentage of 
domestic content; 



(c) 	to purchase, use or accord a preference to goods 
produced or services supplied in its Area, or to 
purchase goods or services from persons in its 
Area; 



(d) 	to relate in any way the volume or value of 
imports to the volume or value of exports or to 
the amount of foreign exchange inflows associated 
with investments of the investor; 



(e) 	to restrict sales of goods or services in its 
Area that investments of the investor produce or 
supply by relating such sales in any way to the 
volume or value of its exports or foreign 
exchange earnings; 



(f) 	to transfer technology, a production process or 
other proprietary knowledge to a person in its 
Area except when: 


(i) 	the requirement is imposed or the commitment 
or undertaking is enforced by a court of 
justice, administrative tribunal or 
competition authority to remedy a practice 
determined after judicial or administrative 
process to be anti-competitive under its 
competition laws and regulations; or 


(ii) 	the requirement concerns the transfer of 
intellectual property rights which is 
undertaken in a manner not inconsistent with 
the TRIPS Agreement; or 


(g) 	to supply to a specific region or the world 
market exclusively from its Area, the goods that 
the investor produces or the services that the 
investor supplies. 

2. Neither Party may condition the receipt or continued 
receipt of an advantage, in connection with investment 
activities of an investor of a Party or of a non-Party in 
its Area, on compliance with any of the following 
requirements: 



(a) 	to achieve a given level or percentage of 
domestic content; 



(b) 	to purchase, use or accord a preference to goods 
produced in its Area, or to purchase goods from 
persons in its Area; 



(c) 	to relate in any way the volume or value of 
imports to the volume or value of exports or to 
the amount of foreign exchange inflows associated 
with investments of the investor; or 



(d) 	to restrict sales of goods or services in its 
Area that investments of the investor produce or 
supply by relating such sales in any way to the 
volume or value of its exports or foreign 
exchange earnings. 

3. 	(a) Nothing in paragraph 2 shall be construed to 
prevent a Party from conditioning the receipt or 
continued receipt of an advantage, in connection 
with investment activities of an investor of a 
Party or of a non-Party in its Area, on 
compliance with a requirement to locate 
production, supply a service, train or employ 
workers, construct or expand particular 
facilities, or carry out research and 
development, in its Area. 



(b) 	Subparagraphs 1(a), 1(b), 1(c), 2(a) and 2(b) 
shall not apply to qualification requirements for 
goods or services with respect to export 
promotion and foreign aid programs. 



(c) 	Subparagraphs 1(b), 1(c), 1(f), 1(g), 2(a) and 
2(b) shall not apply to government procurement. 



(d) 	Subparagraphs 2(a) and 2(b) shall not apply to 
requirements imposed by an importing Party 
relating to the content of goods necessary to 
qualify for preferential tariffs or preferential 
quotas. 

4. Paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply to any requirement 
other than the requirements set out in those paragraphs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Senior Management And Boards Of Directors" article_identifier="294">1. Neither Party may require that an enterprise of that 
Party that is an investment made in its Area by an investor 
of the other Party appoint, to senior management positions, 
individuals of any particular nationality. 



2. A Party may require that a majority of the board of 
directors, or any committee thereof, of an enterprise of 
that Party that is an investment made in its Area by an 
investor of the other Party, be of a particular 
nationality, or resident in the former Party, provided that 
the requirement does not materially impair the ability of 
the investor to exercise control over its investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Non-Conforming Measures" article_identifier="295">1. Articles 73, 74, 77 and 78 shall not apply to: 


(a) 	any existing non-conforming measure that is 
maintained by: 


(i) 	with respect to Chile: 



(A) 	the national government, as set out in 
its Schedule in Annex 6; or



   (B) 	a local government; and 

   Note: 	“The national government” includes 
regional governments. 


(ii) with respect to Japan: 



(A) 	the central government or a prefecture, 
as set out in its Schedule in Annex 6; 
or 



(B) 	a local government other than 
prefectures; 


(b) 	the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraph 
(a); or 



(c) 	an amendment or a modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraph 
(a), to the extent that the amendment or 
modification does not decrease the conformity of 
the measure, as it existed immediately before the 
amendment or modification, with Articles 73, 74, 
77 and 78. 


2. Articles 73, 74, 77 and 78 shall not apply to any 
measure that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities, as set out in its 
Schedule in Annex 7. 



3. Neither Party may, under any measure adopted after the 
date of entry into force of this Agreement and covered by 
its Schedule in Annex 7, require an investor of the other 
Party, by reason of its nationality, to sell or otherwise 
dispose of an investment that exists at the time the 
measure becomes effective. 



4. Articles 73 and 74 shall not apply to any measure that 
is an exception to, or derogation from, the obligations 
under the TRIPS Agreement. 



5. 	Articles 73, 74 and 78 shall not apply to: 



 (a) 	government procurement; or 



(b) 	subsidies provided by a Party or a state 
enterprise, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Notification" article_identifier="296">1. In the case where a Party makes an amendment or a 
modification to any existing non-conforming measure as set 
out in its Schedule in Annex 6, the Party shall notify the 
other Party, as soon as possible, of such amendment or 
modification. 



2. In the case where a Party adopts any measure after the 
entry into force of this Agreement, with respect to 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities as set out in its 
Schedule in Annex 7, the Party shall, to the extent 
possible, notify the other Party of such measure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Transfers" article_identifier="297">1. Each Party shall allow all transfers relating to 
investments made in its Area by an investor of the other 
Party to be made freely and without delay into and out of 
its Area. Such transfers shall include: 



(a) 	the initial capital and additional amounts to 
maintain or increase such investments; 



(b) 	profits, dividends, interest, capital gains, 
royalty payments, management fees, technical 
assistance fees and other fees; 



(c) 	proceeds from the sale or liquidation of all or 
any part of such investments; 



(d) 	payments made under a contract, including 
payments made pursuant to a loan agreement; 



(e) 	payments made pursuant to paragraphs 1 and 2 of 
Article 76 and Article 82; and 



(f) 	payments arising under Section 2. 


2. Each Party shall allow transfers referred to in 
paragraph 1 to be made in a freely usable currency at the 
market rate of exchange prevailing on the date of each 
transfer. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, a Party may delay 
or prevent a transfer through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good-faith application of its laws 
relating to: 



(a) 	bankruptcy, insolvency, or the protection of the 
rights of creditors; 



(b) 	issuing, trading or dealing in securities or 
derivatives; 



(c) 	criminal or penal offenses; 



(d) 	reports or record keeping of transfers of 
currency or other monetary instruments; or 



(e) 	ensuring compliance with orders or judgments in 
judicial or administrative proceedings. 


4. 	This Article is subject to Annex 8.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="298">1. Neither Party may expropriate or nationalize 
investments made in its Area by investors of the other 
Party either directly or indirectly through measures 
equivalent to expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter 
referred to as “expropriation”), except: 



(a) 	for a public purpose; 



(b) 	on a non-discriminatory basis; 



(c) 	on payment of prompt, adequate and effective 
compensation in accordance with paragraphs 2 
through 4; and 



(d) 	in accordance with due process of law and Article 

75. 



2. The compensation shall be equivalent to the fair 
market value of the expropriated investments at the time 
when the expropriation was officially announced or when the 
expropriation occurred, whichever is the earlier. The fair 
market value shall not reflect any change in market value 
occurring because the expropriation had become publicly 
known prior to such official announcement or occurrence of 
the expropriation. The compensation shall be paid without 
delay and be fully realizable and freely transferable. 



3. If payment is made in a freely usable currency, the 
compensation paid shall include interest, at a commercially 
reasonable rate for that currency, accrued from the date of 
expropriation until the date of payment. 



4. If a Party elects to pay in a currency other than a 
freely usable currency, the compensation paid, converted 
into the currency of payment at the market rate of exchange 
prevailing on the date of payment, shall be no less than 
the sum of the following: 



(a) 	the fair market value on the date of 
expropriation, converted into a freely usable 
currency at the market rate of exchange 
prevailing on that date; and 



(b) 	interest, at a commercially reasonable rate for 
that freely usable currency, accrued from the 
date of expropriation until the date of payment. 


5. This Article shall not apply with respect to the grant 
of compulsory licenses concerning intellectual property 
rights in accordance with the TRIPS Agreement. 

Note: 	For greater certainty, Article 82 shall be 
interpreted in accordance with Annex 9.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="299">1. If a Party or its designated agency makes a payment to 
any of its investors pursuant to an indemnity, guarantee or 
insurance contract, pertaining to an investment made by 
that investor within the Area of the other Party, the other 
Party shall: 



(a) 	recognize the assignment, to the former Party or 
its designated agency, of any right of the 
investor that formed the basis of such payment; 
and 



(b) 	recognize the right of the former Party or its 
designated agency to exercise by virtue of 
subrogation such right to the same extent as the 
original right of the investor. 

2. For greater certainty, the investor shall continue to 
be entitled to exercise its rights that have not been 
subrogated pursuant to paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Special Formalities And Information Requirements" article_identifier="300">1. Nothing in Article 73 shall be construed to prevent a 
Party from adopting or maintaining a measure that 
prescribes special formalities in connection with 
investment activities of investors of the other Party and 
their investments made in the Area of the former Party, 
such as the compliance with registration requirements, or 
requirements that investors be residents of the Party or 
that investments be legally constituted under the laws and 
regulations of the Party, provided that such formalities do 
not materially impair the protections afforded by the Party 
to investors of the other Party and their investments 
pursuant to this Chapter. 



2. Notwithstanding Articles 73 and 74, a Party may 
require investors of the other Party, or their investments 
made in its Area, to provide information concerning those 
investments solely for informational or statistical 
purposes. The Party shall protect such information that is 
confidential from any disclosure that would prejudice the 
competitive position of the investors or their investments. 
Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to prevent a 
Party from otherwise obtaining or disclosing information in 
connection with the equitable and good-faith application of 
its law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="301">1. A Party may adopt or maintain measures not conforming 
with its obligations under Articles 73 and 81, regarding 
payments and transfers related to an investment: 



(a) 	in the event of serious balance-of-payments and 
external financial difficulties or threat 
thereof; or 



(b) 	in cases where, in exceptional circumstances, 
movements of capital cause or threaten to cause 
serious difficulties for macroeconomic 
management, in particular, monetary and exchange 
rate policies. 

2. 	Measures referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(b) 	shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the 
circumstances set out in paragraph 1; 



(c) 	shall be temporary and eliminated as soon as 
conditions permit; 



(d) 	shall be promptly notified to the other Party; 
and 



(e) 	shall avoid unnecessary damages to the 
commercial, economic and financial interests of 
the other Party. 

3. Nothing in this Article shall be regarded as altering 
the rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party as 
a party to the Articles of Agreement of the International 
Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="302">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an 
investor of the other Party that is an enterprise of the 
other Party and to its investments if the enterprise is 
owned or controlled by an investor of a non-Party and the 
denying Party: 



(a) 	does not maintain diplomatic relations with the 
non-Party; or 



(b) 	adopts or maintains measures with respect to the 
non-Party that prohibit transactions with the 
enterprise or that would be violated or 
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were 
accorded to the enterprise or to its investments. 

2. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an 
investor of the other Party that is an enterprise of the 
other Party and to its investments if the enterprise is 
owned or controlled by an investor of a non-Party or of the 
denying Party and the enterprise has no substantial 
business activities in the Area of the other Party, subject 
to prior notification to and consultation with the other 
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Environmental Measures" article_identifier="303">Each Party recognizes that it is inappropriate to 
encourage investments by investors of the other Party by 
relaxing its environmental measures. To this effect each 
Party should not waive or otherwise derogate from such 
environmental measures as an encouragement for 
establishment, acquisition or expansion of investments in 
its Area. 

Settlement of Investment Disputes 
between a Party and an Investor of the Other Party</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Consultation And Negotiation" article_identifier="304">In the event of an investment dispute between a Party 
and an investor of the other Party, they should initially 
seek to resolve the dispute through consultation and 
negotiation, which may include the use of non-binding, 
third-party procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Submission Of A Claim To Arbitration" article_identifier="305">1. In the event that an investment dispute cannot be 
settled by consultation and negotiation: 



(a) 	the investor of a Party, on its own behalf, may 
submit to arbitration under this Section a claim: 


(i) that the other Party has breached an 
obligation under Section 1; and 


(ii) 	that the investor has incurred loss or 
damage by reason of, or arising out of, that 
breach; and 


(b) 	the investor of a Party, on behalf of an 
enterprise of the other Party that is a juridical 
person that such investor owns or controls 
directly or indirectly, may submit to arbitration 
under this Section a claim: 

(i) that the other Party has breached an 
obligation under Section 1; and 


(ii) 	that the enterprise has incurred loss or 
damage by reason of, or arising out of, that 
breach. 



2. An investment made by an investor of a Party may not 
submit a claim to arbitration under this Section. 



3. 	For greater certainty: 



(a) 	no claim may be submitted to arbitration under 
this Section that alleges a violation of any 
provision of this Agreement other than an 
obligation under Section 1; and 



(b) 	an investor of a Party may not submit a claim to 
arbitration under this Section in relation to any 
act or fact that took place or any situation that 
ceased to exist before the date of entry into 
force of this Agreement. 


4. At least 90 days before submitting any claim to 
arbitration under this Section, an investor of a Party 
shall deliver to the other Party a written notice of its 
intention to submit the claim to arbitration (hereinafter 
referred to as “notice of intent”). The notice of intent 
shall specify: 



(a) 	the name and address of the investor and, in the 
case of subparagraph 1(b), the name, address, and 
place of incorporation of the enterprise; 



(b) 	the provision of Section 1 alleged to have been 
breached; 



(c) 	the legal and factual basis for that claim; and 



(d) 	the relief sought and the approximate amount of 
damages claimed. 


5. Provided that six months have elapsed since the events 
giving rise to the claim, an investor of a Party may submit 
a claim referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) 	under the ICSID Convention, provided that both 
Parties are parties to the ICSID Convention; 



(b) 	under the ICSID Additional Facility Rules, 
provided that either Party, but not both, is a 
party to the ICSID Convention; 



(c) 	under the UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules; or 



(d) 	if the disputing parties agree, to any other 
arbitration institution or under any other 
arbitration rules. 


6. A claim shall be deemed submitted to arbitration under 
this Section when the claimant’s notice of or request for 
arbitration (hereinafter referred to in this Section as 
“notice of arbitration”): 



(a) 	referred to in paragraph (1) of Article 36 of the 
ICSID Convention is received by the Secretary-
General; 



(b) 	referred to in Article 2 of Schedule C of the 
ICSID Additional Facility Rules is received by 
the Secretary-General; 



(c) 	referred to in Article 3 of the UNCITRAL 
Arbitration Rules, together with the statement of 
claim referred to in Article 18 of the UNCITRAL 
Arbitration Rules, is received by the respondent; 
or 



(d) 	under any other arbitration institution or 
arbitration rules selected under subparagraph 
5(d) is received by the respondent, unless 
otherwise specified by such institution or in 
such rules. 


7. The claimant shall provide with the notice of 
arbitration: 



(a) 	the name of the arbitrator that the claimant 
appoints; or 



(b) 	the claimant’s written consent for the Secretary-
General to appoint the claimant’s arbitrator. 


8. The arbitration rules applicable under paragraph 5, 
which are in effect on the date the claim is submitted to 
arbitration under this Section, shall govern the 
arbitration except to the extent modified by this Section.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Consent To Arbitration" article_identifier="306">1. Each Party consents to the submission of a claim to 
arbitration in accordance with the procedures set out in 
this Section. 



2. The consent under paragraph 1 and the submission of a 
claim to arbitration under this Section shall satisfy the 
requirements of: 


(a) 	Chapter II of the ICSID Convention and the ICSID 
Additional Facility Rules for written consent of 
the parties; and 



(b) 	Article II of the New York Convention for an 
agreement in writing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Conditions And Limitations On Consent" article_identifier="307">1. No claim may be submitted to arbitration under this 
Section if more than three years have elapsed from the date 
on which the investor in the case of subparagraph 1(a) of 
Article 89 or the enterprise in the case of subparagraph 
1(b) of Article 89 first acquired, or should have first 
acquired, knowledge of the breach alleged under paragraph 1 
of Article 89 and knowledge that such investor or 
enterprise had incurred loss or damage. 



2. No claim may be submitted to arbitration under this 
Section unless: 



(a) in the case of subparagraph 1(a) of Article 89: 


(i) 	the claimant consents in writing to 
arbitration in accordance with the 
procedures set out in this Section; 


(ii) 	the claimant waives in writing any right to 
initiate before any administrative tribunal 
or court under the law of either Party, or 
other dispute settlement procedures, any 
proceedings with respect to any measure 
alleged to constitute a breach referred to 
in paragraph 1 of Article 89; and 


(iii) 	the claimant has not initiated any 
proceedings before any administrative 
tribunal or court referred to in 
subparagraph (ii). For greater certainty, 
if the investor elects to initiate such 
proceedings, that election shall be 
definitive and the investor may not 
thereafter submit the claim to arbitration 
under this Section; and 


(b) in the case of subparagraph 1(b) of Article 89: 

(i) 	both the claimant and the enterprise consent 
in writing to arbitration in accordance with 
the procedures set out in this Section; 


(ii) 	both the claimant and the enterprise waive 
in writing any right to initiate before any 
administrative tribunal or court under the 
law of either Party, or other dispute 
settlement procedures, any proceedings with 
respect to any measure alleged to constitute 
a breach referred to in paragraph 1 of 
Article 89; and 


(iii) 	the claimant or the enterprise referred to 
in subparagraph (ii) has not initiated any 
proceedings before any administrative 
tribunal or court referred to in 
subparagraph (ii). For greater certainty, 
if the investor or the enterprise elects to 
initiate such proceedings, that election 
shall be definitive and neither the investor 
nor the enterprise may thereafter submit the 
claim to arbitration under this Section. 


3. Notwithstanding subparagraphs 2(a)(ii), 2(a)(iii), 
2(b)(ii) and 2(b)(iii), the claimant or the enterprise 
referred to in subparagraphs 2(b)(ii) and 2(b)(iii) may 
initiate or continue an action that seeks interim 
injunctive relief that does not involve the payment of 
monetary damages before an administrative tribunal or court 
under the law of the respondent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Establishment Of A Tribunal" article_identifier="308">1. Unless the disputing parties otherwise agree, a 
Tribunal shall comprise three arbitrators, one arbitrator 
appointed by each of the disputing parties and the third, 
who shall be the presiding arbitrator, appointed by 
agreement of the disputing parties. 



2. If an arbitrator or arbitrators are not appointed 
pursuant to paragraph 1 within 75 days from the date on 
which the claim was submitted to arbitration, the 
Secretary-General may be requested by either disputing 
party to appoint the arbitrator or arbitrators not yet 
appointed from the ICSID Panel of Arbitrators subject to 
the requirements of paragraph 3. 



3. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the 
presiding arbitrator shall not be a national of either 
Party, nor have his or her usual place of residence in 
either Party, nor be employed by either disputing party, 
nor have dealt with the claim in any capacity. 



4. The date of establishment of a Tribunal shall be the 
date on which all the arbitrators have been appointed and 
accepted such appointment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Governing Law" article_identifier="309">1. Subject to paragraph 2, when a claim is submitted to 
arbitration under this Section, a Tribunal shall decide the 
issues in dispute in accordance with this Agreement and 
applicable rules of international law. 



2. An interpretation of a provision of this Agreement 
adopted by the Commission shall be binding on a Tribunal, 
and any award must be consistent with that interpretation. 
Such interpretation shall be made publicly available 
through the means that each Party considers appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Interpretation Of Annexes" article_identifier="310">1. Where a respondent asserts as a defense that the 
measure alleged to be a breach is within the scope of a 
non-conforming measure set out in Annex 6 or 7, the 
Tribunal shall, on request of the respondent, request the 
Commission to adopt an interpretation on the issue. The 
Commission shall adopt and submit in writing its 
interpretation to the Tribunal within 60 days of delivery 
of the request. 



2. The interpretation adopted and submitted by the 
Commission under paragraph 1 shall be binding on the 
Tribunal, and any award must be consistent with that 
interpretation. If the Commission fails to submit an 
interpretation within the aforementioned 60 days period, 
the Tribunal shall decide the issue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Participation In Arbitration" article_identifier="311">1. On written notice to the disputing parties, the Party 
other than the respondent may make submissions to the 
Tribunal on a question of interpretation of this Agreement. 



2. The Party other than the respondent shall be entitled 
to receive from the respondent, a copy of: 



(a) 	the evidence that has been tendered to the 
Tribunal; and 



(b) 	the written argument of the disputing parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Place Of Arbitration" article_identifier="312">Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, a 
Tribunal shall hold an arbitration in a country that is a 
party to the New York Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Preliminary Questions" article_identifier="313">1. 

(a) 

A Tribunal shall address and decide as a 




preliminary question any objection by the 




respondent that, as a matter of law, the Tribunal 




may not make an award against the respondent in 




accordance with Article 103, provided that the 




respondent so requests as soon as possible after 




the Tribunal is established, and in no event 




later than the date the Tribunal fixes for the 




respondent to submit its counter-memorial. In 




deciding such objection, the Tribunal shall 




assume to be true the factual allegations of the 




claimant in support of any claim in the notice of 




arbitration. The Tribunal may also consider any 




relevant facts not in dispute. 


(b) 

Subparagraph (a) shall not prejudice the 




authority of the Tribunal to address as a 




preliminary question any objection other than the 




objection referred to in subparagraph (a), such 




as an objection that the dispute is not within 




the competence of the Tribunal. 


(c) 

On receipt of the objection referred to in 




subparagraph (a), the Tribunal shall suspend any 




proceedings on the merits, establish a schedule 




for considering the objection consistent with any 




schedule it has established for considering any 




other preliminary question, and issue a decision 




or award on the objection, stating the grounds 
therefor. 



2. In the event that the respondent so requests within 45 
days after the date of establishment of the Tribunal, the 
Tribunal shall address and decide on an expedited basis the 
objection referred to in subparagraph 1(a) or any objection 
that the dispute is not within the competence of the 
Tribunal. The Tribunal shall suspend any proceedings on 
the merits and issue a decision or award on the objection, 
stating the grounds therefor, no later than 150 days, or 
180 days if a hearing is held or under extraordinary 
circumstances, after the date of the request. 



3. When it decides a respondent’s objection pursuant to 
paragraph 1 or 2, the Tribunal may, if warranted, award to 
the prevailing disputing party reasonable costs including 
attorneys’ fees incurred in submitting or opposing the 
objection. In determining whether such an award is 
warranted, the Tribunal shall consider whether the 
claimant’s claim was frivolous or whether the respondent’s 
objection was frivolous, and shall provide the disputing 
parties a reasonable opportunity to comment. 



4. The respondent does not waive its right to make any 
objection or argument on the merits merely because the 
respondent did or did not make a request pursuant to 
paragraph 1 or 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Insurance Or Guarantee Contracts" article_identifier="314">In an arbitration under this Section, the respondent 
may not assert, as a defense, counterclaim, right of set-
off or otherwise, that the claimant has received or will 
receive indemnification or other compensation for all or
guarantee contract.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Interim Measures Of Protection" article_identifier="315">A Tribunal may order an interim measure of protection 
to preserve the rights of a disputing party, or to 
facilitate the conduct of arbitral proceedings, including 
an order to preserve evidence in the possession or control 
of a disputing party. A Tribunal may not order attachment 
or enjoin the application of the measure alleged to 
constitute a breach referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 


89.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Expert Report" article_identifier="316">Without prejudice to the appointment of other kinds of 
experts where authorized by the applicable arbitration 
rules, a Tribunal, at the request of a disputing party or, 
except as the disputing parties agree otherwise, on its own 
initiative, may appoint one or more experts in the fields 
of environmental, health, safety or other scientific 
matters to report to it in writing on any factual issue 
concerning matters of their expertise raised by a disputing 
party in a proceeding, subject to such terms and conditions 
as the disputing parties may agree.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Consolidation Of Multiple Claims" article_identifier="317">1. When a disputing party considers that two or more 
claims submitted to arbitration under paragraph 1 of 
Article 89 have a question of law or fact in common and 
arise out of the same events or circumstances, the 
disputing party may seek a consolidation order in 
accordance with the terms of paragraphs 2 through 10. 



2. A disputing party that seeks a consolidation order 
under this Article shall deliver, in writing, a request to 
the Secretary-General to establish a Tribunal under this 
Article. The request shall specify: 



(a) 	the names and addresses of all the disputing 
parties sought to be covered by the order; 



(b) 	the nature of the order sought; and 



(c) 	the grounds on which the order is sought. 


3. Unless the Secretary-General finds within 60 days 
after receiving a request under paragraph 2 that the claims 
do not satisfy the requirements set out in paragraph 1, a 
Tribunal shall be established under this Article. 



4. Unless all the disputing parties sought to be covered 
by the order otherwise agree, a Tribunal established under 
this Article shall comprise three arbitrators: 



(a) 	one arbitrator appointed by agreement of the 
claimants; 



(b) 	one arbitrator appointed by the respondent; and 



(c) 	the presiding arbitrator appointed by the 
Secretary-General, provided, however, that the 
presiding arbitrator shall not be a national of 
either Party, nor have his or her usual place of 
residence in either Party, nor be employed by any 
disputing party, nor have dealt with the claims 
in any capacity. 


5. If, within 60 days after the Secretary-General 
receives a request under paragraph 2, the respondent fails 
or the claimants fail to appoint an arbitrator in 
accordance with paragraph 4, the Secretary-General may be 
requested by any disputing party sought to be covered by 
the order, to appoint the arbitrator or arbitrators not yet 
appointed. If the respondent fails to appoint an 
arbitrator, the arbitrator to be appointed by the 
Secretary-General shall be a national of the respondent, 
and if the claimants fail to appoint an arbitrator, the 
arbitrator to be appointed by the Secretary-General shall 
be a national of the Party other than the respondent. 



6. Where a claimant that has submitted a claim to 
arbitration under paragraph 1 of Article 89 considers that 
such a claim raises a question of law or fact in common to, 
and arises out of the same events or circumstances as, 
claims upon which the consolidation under paragraph 2 has 
been requested, but has not been named in such request, the 
claimant may make a written request to the Tribunal 
established under this Article that the claimant be covered 
by any order made under paragraph 7, and shall specify in 
the request: 



(a) 	the name and address of the claimant; 



(b) 	the nature of the order sought; and 



(c) 	the grounds on which the order is sought. 


7. Where a Tribunal established under this Article is 
satisfied that two or more claims that have been submitted 
to arbitration under paragraph 1 of Article 89 have a 
question of law or fact in common, and arise out of the 
same events or circumstances, the Tribunal may, in the 
interest of fair and efficient resolution of the claims, 
and after hearing the disputing parties, by order: 



(a) 	assume jurisdiction over, and hear and determine 
together, all or part of the claims; or 



(b) 	assume jurisdiction over, and hear and determine 
one or more of the claims, the determination of 
which it believes would assist in the resolution 
of the others. 


8. A Tribunal established under this Article shall 
conduct its proceedings in accordance with the UNCITRAL 
Arbitration Rules, except as modified by this Section. 



9. A Tribunal established under Article 92 shall not have 
jurisdiction to decide a claim, or a part of a claim, over 
which a Tribunal established under this Article has assumed 
jurisdiction. 



10. On application of a disputing party, a Tribunal 
established under this Article, pending its decision as to 
whether to make an order under paragraph 7, may order the 
adjourning of the proceedings of a Tribunal established 
under Article 92. 



11. For greater certainty, the provisions of this Section 
other than this Article shall apply with respect to a 
Tribunal established under this Article except to the 
extent modified by this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Proposed Award" article_identifier="318">A Tribunal shall, at the request of a disputing party, 
submit to the disputing parties a proposed award, before 
making an award, except an award issued pursuant to Article 


97. The disputing parties may submit to the Tribunal 
written comments on the proposed award within 60 days after 
the date of submission of the proposed award. The Tribunal 
shall consider such comments and make an award within 105 
days of the date of submission of the proposed award.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Award" article_identifier="319">1. Where a Tribunal makes an award against the 
respondent, the Tribunal may award, separately or in 
combination, only: 



(a) 	monetary damages and any applicable interest; and 



(b) 	restitution of property, in which case the award 
shall provide that the respondent may pay 
monetary damages and any applicable interest in 
lieu of restitution. 

A Tribunal may also award costs including attorneys’ 
fees in accordance with this Section and the applicable 
arbitration rules. 


2. Subject to paragraph 1, in the case of subparagraph 
1(b) of Article 89: 



(a) 	an award of monetary damages and any applicable 
interest shall provide that the sum be paid to 
the enterprise; and 



(b) 	an award of restitution of property shall provide 
that restitution be made to the enterprise. 


3. 	A Tribunal may not award punitive damages. 



4. An award made by a Tribunal shall have no binding 
force except between the disputing parties and in respect 
of the particular case. 



5. Subject to paragraph 7, a disputing party shall abide 
by and comply with an award without delay. 



6. If the respondent fails to abide by or comply with an 
award, the Party other than the respondent may request the 
establishment of an arbitral tribunal pursuant to Article 

178. 	The requesting Party may seek in such proceedings: 



(a) 	a determination that the failure to abide by or 
comply with the award is inconsistent with the 
obligations of this Agreement; and 



(b) 	a recommendation that the respondent abide by or 
comply with the award. 

7. A disputing party may not seek enforcement of an award 
until such award becomes final. An award becomes final 
when: 



(a) 	in the case of an award under the ICSID 
Convention: 


(i) 	120 days have elapsed from the date the 
award was made and no disputing party has 
requested revision or annulment of the 
award; or 


(ii) 	revision or annulment proceedings have been 
completed; and 


(b) 	in the case of an award under the ICSID 
Additional Facility Rules, the UNCITRAL 
Arbitration Rules, or the rules selected pursuant 
to subparagraph 5(d) of Article 89: 

(i) 	90 days have elapsed from the date the award 
was made and no disputing party has 
commenced a proceeding to revise or annul 
the award; or 


(ii) 	an application to revise or annul the award 
has been dismissed or allowed and there is 
no further appeal. 


8. Each Party shall provide for the enforcement of an 
award in its Area in accordance with its relevant laws and 
regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Service Of Documents" article_identifier="320">1. Notices and other documents relating to arbitration 
under this Section shall be served on a Party by delivery 
to: 



(a) 	with respect to Japan, the Ministry of Foreign 
Affairs; and 



(b) 	with respect to Chile, the Ministry of Foreign 
Affaires, Legal Affaires Directorate (Dirección 
de Asuntos Jurídicos del Ministerio de Relaciones 
Exteriores de la República de Chile). 

2. The Commission shall make publicly available the 
addresses of the authorities referred to in paragraph 1.
Definitions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Definitions" article_identifier="321">1. 	For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “claimant” means an investor of a Party 
that submits a claim to arbitration under Section 
2; 



(b) 	the term “disputing parties” means the claimant 
and the respondent; 



(c) 	the term “disputing party” means either the 
claimant or the respondent; 



(d) 	the term “freely usable currency” means freely 
usable currency as defined under the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(e) 	the term “ICSID” means the International Centre 
for Settlement of Investment Disputes; 



(f) 	the term “ICSID Additional Facility Rules” means 
the Rules Governing the Additional Facility for 
the Administration of Proceedings by the 
Secretariat of the International Centre for 
Settlement of Investment Disputes; 



(g) 	the term “ICSID Convention” means the Convention 
on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between 
States and Nationals of other States, done at 
Washington, March 18, 1965; 



(h) 	the term “investment” means every kind of asset 
that  an investor owns or controls, directly or 
indirectly, which has the characteristics of an 
investment. Forms that an investment may take 
include: 

Note 1: 	The characteristics of an investment 
include the commitment of capital or 
other resources, the expectation of gain 
or profit, or the assumption of risk. 


Note 2: 	An investment does not include an order 
or judgment entered in a judicial or 
administrative action. 


(i) 	an enterprise and a branch of an enterprise; 


(ii) 	shares, stocks, and other forms of equity 
participation in an enterprise; 


(iii) 	bonds, debentures, loans and other debt 
instruments, but do not include a debt 
instrument of a Party or of a state 
enterprise; 



(iv) futures, options and other derivatives; 


(v) 	rights under contracts, including turnkey, 
construction, management, production or 
revenue-sharing contracts; 


(vi) 	intellectual property rights; 

(vii) 	rights conferred pursuant to domestic law, 
such as concessions, licenses, 
authorizations and permits; and 


(viii) 	other tangible or intangible, movable or 
immovable property, and any related property 
rights, such as leases, mortgages, liens and 
pledges; 



(i) 	the term “investment activities” means 
establishment, acquisition, expansion, 
management, conduct, operation, maintenance, use, 
enjoyment and sale or other disposition of 
investments; 



(j) 	the term “investor of a Party” means a natural 
person or an enterprise of a Party, or the Party 
or state enterprise thereof, that attempts to 
make, is making, or has made investments in the 
Area of the other Party; 



(k) 	the term “New York Convention” means the United 
Nations Convention on the Recognition and 
Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards, done at 
New York, June 10, 1958; 



(l) 	the term “respondent” means a Party against which 
a claim is submitted to arbitration under Section 
2; 



(m) 	the term “Secretary-General” means the Secretary-
General of ICSID; 



(n) 	the term “Tribunal” means an arbitration tribunal 
established under Article 92 or 101; and 



(o) 	the term “UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules” means the 
arbitration rules of the United Nations 
Commission on International Trade Law, approved 
by the United Nations General Assembly on 
December 15, 1976. 

2. 	For the purposes of this Chapter, an enterprise is: 



(a) 	“owned” by an investor if more than 50 percent of 
the equity interests in it is beneficially owned 
by the investor; and 



(b) 	“controlled” by an investor if the investor has 
the power to name a majority of its directors or 
otherwise to legally direct its actions in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of a 
Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Cross-Border Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="35">
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Scope" article_identifier="322">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or 
maintained by a Party affecting cross-border trade in 
services by service suppliers of the other Party. Such 
measures include measures affecting: 



(a) 	the supply of a service; 


Note: 	The measures affecting the supply of a 
service include those affecting the 
provision of any financial security as a 
condition for the supply of a service. 


(b) 	the purchase or use of, or payment for, a 
service; 



(c) 	the access to and the use of services offered to 
the public generally, including distribution, 
transport or telecommunications networks, in 
connection with the supply of a service; and 



(d) 	the presence in its Area of a service supplier of 
the other Party. 

2. 	This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) 	cabotage in maritime transport services; 



(b) 	financial services, as defined in Article 128; 



(c) 	in respect of air transport services, measures 
affecting traffic rights, however granted; or 
measures affecting services directly related to 
the exercise of traffic rights, other than 
measures affecting: 


(i) 	aircraft repair and maintenance services; 


(ii) 	the selling and marketing of air transport 
services; and 


(iii) computer reservation system services; 


 (d) 	government procurement; 



(e) 	subsidies provided by a Party or a state 
enterprise, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance; 



(f) 	measures affecting natural persons of a Party 
seeking access to the employment market of the 
other Party, or measures regarding nationality or 
citizenship, or residence or employment on a 
permanent basis; and 



(g) 	services supplied in the exercise of governmental 
authority.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="323">Each Party shall accord to services and service 
suppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorable 
than that it accords, in like circumstances, to its own 
services and service suppliers. 


Note: 	For greater certainty, nothing in this Article shall 
be construed to require either Party to compensate 
for any inherent competitive disadvantages which 
result from the foreign character of the relevant 
services or service suppliers.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="324">Each Party shall accord to services and service 
suppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorable 
than that it accords, in like circumstances, to services 
and service suppliers of any non-Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Local Presence" article_identifier="325">Neither Party shall require a service supplier of the 
other Party to establish or maintain a representative 
office or any form of enterprise, or to be resident, in its 
Area as a condition for the cross-border supply of a 
service. 


Note: 	The term “cross-border supply of a service” has the 
same meaning as the term “cross-border trade in 
services”.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Non-Conforming Measures" article_identifier="326">1. 	Articles 107, 108 and 109 shall not apply to: 



(a) 	any existing non-conforming measure that is 
maintained by: 


(i) 	with respect to Chile: 



(A) 	the national government, as set out in 
its Schedule in Annex 6; or



   (B) 	a local government; and 

(ii) with respect to Japan: 



(A) 	the central government or a prefecture, 
as set out in its Schedule in Annex 6; 
or 



(B) 	a local government other than 
prefectures; 


(b) 	the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraph 
(a); or 



(c) 	an amendment or a modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraph 
(a), to the extent that the amendment or 
modification does not decrease the conformity of 
the measure, as it existed immediately before the 
amendment or modification, with Articles 107, 108 
and 109. 

   Note: 	“The national government” includes 
regional governments. 


2. Articles 107, 108 and 109 shall not apply to any 
measure that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities, as set out in its 
Schedule in Annex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Notification" article_identifier="327">1. In the case where a Party makes an amendment or a 
modification to any existing non-conforming measure as set 
out in its Schedule in Annex 6, the Party shall notify the 
other Party, as soon as possible, of such amendment or 
modification. 



2. In the case where a Party adopts any measure after the 
entry into force of this Agreement, with respect to 
sectors, sub-sectors or activities as set out in its 
Schedule in Annex 7, the Party shall, to the extent 
possible, notify the other Party of such measure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Authorization, Qualification, Technical Standard And Licensing" article_identifier="328">With a view to ensuring that any measure adopted or 
maintained by a Party in any services sector relating to 
the authorization, qualification requirements and 
procedures, technical standards and licensing requirements 
of service suppliers of the other Party does not constitute 
an unnecessary barrier to cross-border trade in services, 
each Party shall endeavor to ensure that such measure: 



(a) 	is based on objective and transparent criteria, 
such as the competence and ability to supply the 
service; 



(b) 	is not more burdensome than necessary to ensure 
the quality of the service; and 



(c) 	does not constitute a disguised restriction on 
the supply of the service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="329">1. A Party may recognize the education or experience 
obtained, requirements met, or licenses or certifications 
granted in the other Party for the purposes of the 
fulfillment, in whole or in part, of its standards or 
criteria for the authorization, licensing or certification 
of service suppliers of the other Party. 



2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1, which may be 
achieved through harmonization or otherwise, may be based 
upon an agreement or arrangement between the Parties or may 
be accorded unilaterally. 



3. Where a Party recognizes, by agreement or arrangement 
between the Party and a non-Party or unilaterally, the 
education or experience obtained, requirements met, or 
licenses or certifications granted in the non-Party: 



(a) 	nothing in Article 108 shall be construed to 
require the Party to accord such recognition to 
the education or experience obtained, 
requirements met, or licenses or certifications 
granted in the other Party; and 



(b) 	the Party shall accord the other Party an 
adequate opportunity to demonstrate that the 
education or experience obtained, requirements 
met, or licenses or certifications granted in the 
other Party should also be recognized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="330">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and 
external financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party 
may adopt or maintain restrictions on cross-border trade in 
services, including on payments or transfers for 
transactions. 



2. 	The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) 	shall be applied on the basis of national 
treatment and most-favored-nation treatment; 



(b) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) 	shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial, 
economic and financial interests of the other 
Party; 



(d) 	shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the 
circumstances described in paragraph 1; and 



(e) 	shall be temporary and be phased out 
progressively as the situation specified in 
paragraph 1 improves. 


3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a 
Party may give priority to the cross-border supply of 
services which are more essential to its economic or 
development programs. However, such restrictions shall not 
be adopted or maintained for the purposes of protecting a 
particular service sector. 



4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph 
1, or any changes therein, shall be promptly notified to 
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="331">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a 
service supplier of the other Party that is an enterprise 
of the other Party, where the former Party establishes that 
the enterprise is owned or controlled by persons of a non-
Party, and the former Party: 



(a) 	does not maintain diplomatic relations with the 
non-Party; or 



(b) 	adopts or maintains measures with respect to the 
non-Party that prohibit transactions with the 
enterprise or that would be violated or 
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were 
accorded to the enterprise. 

2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, a 
Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a service 
supplier of the other Party that is an enterprise of the 
other Party where the former Party establishes that the 
enterprise is owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party 
and has no substantial business activities in the Area of 
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Definitions" article_identifier="332">1. 	For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “aircraft repair and maintenance 
services” means such activities when undertaken 
on an aircraft or a part thereof while it is 
withdrawn from services and does not include so-
called line maintenance; 



(b) 	the term “computer reservation system services” 
means services provided by computerized systems 
that contain information about air carriers’ 
schedules, availability, fares and fare rules, 
through which reservations may be made or tickets 
may be issued; 



(c) 	the term “cross-border trade in services” means 
the supply of a service: 

(i) 	from the Area of a Party into the Area of 
the other Party; 


(ii) 	in the Area of a Party by a natural person 
or an enterprise of that Party to a natural 
person or an enterprise of the other Party; 
and 


(iii) 	by a natural person of a Party in the Area 
of the other Party, 


but does not include the supply of services by an 
investment of an investor of a Party, as defined 
in Article 105, in the Area of the other Party; 



(d) 	the term “measure adopted or maintained by a 
Party” means any measure adopted or maintained 
by: 


(i) 	any level of government or authority of a 
Party; and 


(ii) 	non-governmental bodies in the exercise of 
powers delegated by any level of government 
or authority of a Party; 


(e) 	the term “service supplied in the exercise of 
governmental authority” means any service which 
is supplied neither on a commercial basis nor in 
competition with one or more service suppliers; 



(f) 	the term “service supplier” means a person that 
seeks to supply or supplies a service; 



(g) 	the term “supply of a service” includes the 
production, distribution, marketing, sale and 
delivery of a service; 



(h) 	the term “the selling and marketing of air 
transport services” means opportunities for the 
air carrier concerned to sell and market freely 
its air transport services including all aspects 
of marketing such as market research, advertising 
and distribution. These activities do not 
include the pricing of air transport services nor 
the applicable conditions; and 



(i) 	the term “traffic rights” means the rights for 
scheduled and non-scheduled services to operate 
and/or to carry passengers, cargo and mail for 
remuneration or hire from, to, within, or over a 
Party, including points to be served, routes to 
be operated, types of traffic to be carried, 
capacity to be provided, tariffs to be charged 
and their conditions, and criteria for 
designation of airlines, including such criteria 
as number, ownership and control. 

2. 	For the purposes of this Chapter, an enterprise is: 



(a) 	“owned” by a person if more than 50 percent of 
the equity interests in it is beneficially owned 
by the person; and 



(b) 	“controlled” by a person if the person has the 
power to name a majority of its directors or 
otherwise to legally direct its actions in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of a 
Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Financial Services" chapter_identifier="36">
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Scope" article_identifier="333">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or 
maintained by a Party relating to: 



(a) 	financial institutions of the other Party; 



(b) 	investors of the other Party, and investments of 
such investors, in financial institutions in the 
Area of the former Party; and 



(c) 	cross-border trade in financial services. 


2. Articles 81 through 86, 114 and 115 shall apply to 
measures described in paragraph 1, mutatis mutandis. For 
greater certainty, no other provision of Chapter 8 or 9 
shall apply to measures described in paragraph 1. 



3. 	This Chapter is subject to Annex 5. 



4. 	This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) 	measures adopted or maintained by a Party 
relating to: 


(i) 	activities conducted by the central bank or 
monetary authority of the Party or by any 
other public entity in pursuit of monetary 
or exchange rate policies; 


(ii) 	activities or services forming part of a 
public retirement plan or statutory system 
of social security, unless the Party allows 
any of such activities or services to be 
conducted by its financial institutions in 
competition with a public entity or a 
financial institution; or 


(iii) 	activities or services conducted for the 
account or with the guarantee or using the 
financial resources of the Party, including 
its public entities, unless the Party allows 
any of such activities or services to be 
conducted by its financial institutions in 
competition with a public entity or a 
financial institution; 


 (b) 	government procurement; 



(c) 	subsidies provided by a Party or a state 
enterprise thereof, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance; and 



(d) 	measures affecting natural persons of a Party 
seeking access to the employment market of the 
other Party, or measures regarding nationality or 
citizenship, or residence or employment on a 
permanent basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="334">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule in Annex 10, 
subject to any conditions and qualifications set out 
therein, each Party shall accord to investors of the other 
Party treatment no less favorable than that it accords to 
its own investors, in like circumstances, with respect to 
the establishment, acquisition, expansion, management, 
conduct, operation, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale or 
other disposition of financial institutions and investments 
in financial institutions in its Area. 



2. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule in Annex 10, 
subject to any conditions and qualifications set out 
therein, each Party shall accord to financial institutions 
of the other Party and to investments of investors of the 
other Party in financial institutions treatment no less 
favorable than that it accords to its own financial 
institutions, and to investments of its own investors in 
financial institutions, in like circumstances, with respect 
to the establishment, acquisition, expansion, management, 
conduct, operation, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale or 
other disposition of financial institutions and 
investments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Market Access For Financial Institutions" article_identifier="335">1. With respect to market access for financial 
institutions, each Party shall accord to financial 
institutions of the other Party and investors of the other 
Party who seek to establish financial institutions in the 
Area of the former Party treatment no less favorable than 
that provided for under the terms, limitations and 
conditions specified in its Schedule in Annex 10. 



2. In sectors where market-access commitments are 
undertaken, the measures which a Party shall not maintain 
or adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision or 
on the basis of its entire Area, unless otherwise specified 
in its Schedule in Annex 10, are defined as: 


(a) 	limitations on the number of financial 
institutions whether in the form of numerical 
quotas, monopolies, exclusive financial 
institutions or the requirements of an economic 
needs test; 



(b) 	limitations on the total value of financial 
service transactions or assets in the form of 
numerical quotas or the requirement of an 
economic needs test; 



(c) 	limitations on the total number of financial 
service operations or on the total quantity of 
financial service output expressed in terms of 
designated numerical units in the form of quotas 
or the requirement of an economic needs test; 


Note: 	Subparagraph (c) does not cover measures 
of a Party which limit inputs for the 
supply of financial services. 


(d) 	limitations on the total number of natural 
persons that may be employed in a particular 
financial service sector or that a financial 
institution may employ and who are necessary for, 
and directly related to, the supply of a specific 
financial service in the form of numerical quotas 
or the requirement of an economic needs test; and 



(e) 	measures which restrict or require specific types 
of legal entity or joint venture through which a 
financial institution may supply a financial 
service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Cross-Border Trade" article_identifier="336">1. Each Party shall permit, under terms and conditions 
that accord national treatment, cross-border financial 
service suppliers of the other Party to supply the 
financial services specified in its Schedule in Annex 11, 
subject to any terms and conditions set out therein. 



2. Each Party shall permit persons located in its Area, 
and its natural persons in the Area of the other Party, to 
purchase the financial services specified in its Schedule 
in Annex 12, subject to any terms and conditions set out 
therein, from cross-border financial service suppliers of 
the other Party located in the Area of the other Party. 
This obligation does not require a Party to permit cross-
border financial service suppliers of the other Party to do 
business or solicit in the Area of the former Party. The 
former Party may define “doing business” and “solicitation” 
for the purposes of this Article as long as such 
definitions are not inconsistent with its obligations under 
paragraph 1. 



3. A Party may require the registration of cross-border 
financial service suppliers of the other Party and of their 
financial instruments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="New Financial Services" article_identifier="337">1. Each Party shall permit financial institutions of the 
other Party to offer in its Area any new financial service 
in sectors or sub-sectors where commitments are undertaken 
in its Schedule in Annex 10 and subject to the terms, 
limitations, conditions and qualifications set out in that 
Schedule and provided that the introduction of this new 
financial service does not require the former Party to 
adopt a new law or modify an existing law. 



2. Each Party may determine the legal form through which 
the new financial service may be supplied and may require 
authorization for the supply of the new financial service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Treatment Of Certain Information" article_identifier="338">Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to require 
a Party to disclose information relating to the affairs and 
accounts of individual customers or any confidential or 
proprietary information in the possession of public 
entities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="339">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Chapter 
and Chapters 8 and 9, a Party shall not be prevented from 
adopting or maintaining measures for prudential reasons, 
including for the protection of investors, depositors, 
policy holders, or persons to whom a fiduciary duty is owed 
by a financial institution or cross-border financial 
service supplier, or to ensure the integrity and stability 
of the financial system. Where such measures do not 
conform with the provisions of this Agreement, they shall 
not be used as a means of avoiding the Party’s commitments 
or obligations under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Self-Regulatory Organizations" article_identifier="340">Where a Party requires a financial institution of the 
other Party to be a member of, participate in, or have 
access to, a self-regulatory organization to supply a 
financial service in the Area of the former Party, the 
former Party shall ensure that such organization accords 
national treatment to the financial institution of the 
other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Payment And Clearing Systems" article_identifier="341">Under terms and conditions that accord national 
treatment, each Party shall grant to financial institutions 
of the other Party established in its Area access to 
payment and clearing systems operated by public entities, 
and to official funding and refinancing facilities 
available in the normal course of ordinary business. This 
Article is not intended to confer access to the Party’s 
lender of last resort facilities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Committee On Financial Services" article_identifier="342">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Financial Services (hereinafter referred to in 
this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(c) 	reporting the findings of the Committee to the 
Commission; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. 	The Committee shall be composed of: 



(a) 	with respect to Japan, officials from the 
Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Financial 
Services Agency; and 



(b) 	with respect to Chile, officials from the 
Ministry of Finance (Ministerio de Hacienda). 


4. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="343">1. The consultations under Article 177 on prudential 
issues and other financial matters shall be participated in 
by: 



(a) 	with respect to Japan, officials from the 
Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Financial 
Services Agency; and 



(b) 	with respect to Chile, officials from the 
Ministry of Finance (Ministerio de Hacienda). 


2. A Party shall not be required to disclose information 
or refrain from taking any action with respect to specific 
regulatory, supervisory, administrative or enforcement 
matters, solely by reason of the consultations under 
Article 177. 



3. The arbitral tribunal established under Article 178 
for disputes arising under this Chapter shall be composed 
entirely of arbitrators who have expertise or experience in 
financial services law or practice, which may include the 
laws and regulations of financial institutions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Definitions" article_identifier="344">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “cross-border financial service supplier 
of a Party” means a person of a Party that is 
engaged in the business of supplying financial 
services within the Area of the Party and that 
seeks to supply or supplies financial services 
through the cross-border supply of financial 
services; 


Note: 	The term “cross-border supply of financial 
services” has the same meaning as the term 
“cross-border trade in financial 
services”. 


(b) 	the term “cross-border trade in financial 
services” means the supply of a financial 
service: 

(i) 	from the Area of a Party into the Area of 
the other Party; 


(ii) 	in the Area of a Party by a person of that 
Party to a person of the other Party; and 


(iii) 	by a natural person of a Party in the Area 
of the other Party, 


but does not include the supply of a financial 
service by an investment of an investor of a 
Party, in the Area of the other Party; 



(c) 	the term “financial institution” means any 
enterprise that is authorized to do business and 
regulated or supervised as a financial 
institution under the law of the Party in which 
it is located; 



(d) 	the term “financial institution of the other 
Party” means a financial institution located in a 
Party that is owned or controlled by persons of 
the other Party; 



(e) 	the term “financial service” means any service of 
a financial nature. Financial services include 
all insurance and insurance-related services, and 
all banking and other financial services 
(excluding insurance).  Financial services 
include the following activities: 

(i) Insurance and Insurance-Related Services 


   (A) 	direct insurance (including coinsurance): 


    (AA) life; and 


    (BB) non-life; 



   (B) 	reinsurance and retrocession; 



   (C) 	insurance intermediation, such as 
brokerage and agency; and 



(D) 	services auxiliary to insurance, such 
as consultancy, actuarial, risk 
assessment and claim settlement 
services; and 

(ii) 	Banking and Other Financial Services 
(Excluding Insurance)



   (A) 	acceptance of deposits and other 
repayable funds from the public; 



   (B) 	lending of all types, including 
consumer credit, mortgage credit, 
factoring and financing of commercial 
transactions; 



   (C) 	financial leasing; 



   (D) 	all payment and money transmission 
services, including credit, charge and 
debit cards, travelers checks and 
bankers drafts; 



   (E) 	guarantees and commitments; 



(F) 	trading for own account or for account 
of customers, whether on an exchange, 
in an over-the-counter market or 
otherwise, the following: 

    (AA) money market instruments 
(including checks, bills, 
certificates of deposits); 


    (BB) foreign exchange; 


    (CC) derivative products including, 
but not limited to, futures and 
options;


    (DD) exchange rate and interest rate 
instruments, including products 
such as swaps, forward rate 
agreements; 


    (EE) transferable securities; and


    (FF) other negotiable instruments and 
financial assets, including 
bullion; 



(G) 	participation in issues of all kinds of 
securities, including underwriting and 
placement as agent (whether publicly or 
privately) and provision of services 
related to such issues; 



   (H) 	money broking; 



   (I) 	asset management, such as cash or 
portfolio management, all forms of 
collective investment management, 
pension fund management, custodial, 
depository and trust services; 



   (J) 	settlement and clearing services for 
financial assets, including securities, 
derivative products, and other 
negotiable instruments; 



   (K) 	provision and transfer of financial 
information, and financial data 
processing and related software by 
suppliers of other financial services; 
and 



   (L) 	advisory, intermediation, and other 
auxiliary financial services on all the 
activities listed in subparagraphs (A) 
through (K), including credit reference 
and analysis, investment and portfolio 
research and advice, advice on 
acquisitions and on corporate 
restructuring and strategy; 

(f) 	the term “investment” means an investment as 
defined in subparagraph 1(h) of Article 105, 
except that, with respect to loans and debt 
instruments referred to in that subparagraph: 


(i) 	a loan to or debt instrument issued by a 
financial institution is an investment only 
where it is treated as regulatory capital by 
the Party in which the financial institution 
is located; and 


(ii) 	a loan granted by or debt instrument owned 
by a financial institution, other than a 
loan to or debt instrument of a financial 
institution referred to in subparagraph (i), 
is not an investment;


  for greater certainty, 


(iii) 	a loan to, or a debt instrument issued by, a 
Party or a state enterprise thereof is not 
an investment; and 


(iv) 	a loan granted by or debt instrument owned 
by a cross-border financial service 
supplier, other than a loan to or debt 
instrument issued by a financial institution 
referred to in subparagraph (i), is an 
investment under Chapter 8 if such loan or 
debt instrument meets the criteria for 
investments set out in subparagraph 1(h) of 
Article 105; 



(g) 	the term “investor of a Party” means an investor 
of a Party as defined in subparagraph 1(j) of 
Article 105; 



(h) 	the term “new financial service” means a service 
of a financial nature, including services related 
to existing and new products or the manner in 
which a product is delivered, that is not 
supplied by any financial service supplier in the 
Area of a Party but which is supplied in the Area 
of the other Party; 



 (i) 	the term “person of a Party” means a natural 
person or an enterprise of a Party and, for 
greater certainty, does not include a branch of 
an enterprise of a non-Party; 



(j) 	the term “public entity” means the Government, 
the central bank or monetary authority of a 
Party, or any entity owned or controlled by a 
Party, that is principally engaged in carrying 
out governmental functions or activities for 
governmental purposes, not including an entity 
principally engaged in supplying financial 
services on commercial terms or a private entity, 
performing functions normally performed by a 
central bank or monetary authority, when 
exercising those functions; and 



(k) 	the term “self-regulatory organization” means any 
non-governmental body, including any securities 
or futures exchange or market, clearing agency, 
or any other organization or association, that 
exercises its own or delegated regulatory or 
supervisory authority over financial 
institutions.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Entry And Temporary Stay Of Nationals For Business Purposes" chapter_identifier="37">
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="General Principles" article_identifier="345">1. This Chapter reflects the preferential trading 
relationship between the Parties, the mutual desire of the 
Parties to facilitate entry and temporary stay of nationals 
for business purposes on a reciprocal basis and to 
establish transparent criteria and procedures for entry and 
temporary stay, and the need to ensure border security and 
to protect the domestic labor force and permanent 
employment in either Party. 



2. Each Party shall apply its measures relating to the 
provisions of this Chapter in accordance with paragraph 1, 
and, in particular, shall apply expeditiously those 
measures so as to avoid unduly impairing or delaying trade 
in goods or services or conduct of investment activities 
under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Scope" article_identifier="346">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting the 
entry and temporary stay of nationals of a Party who enter 
the other Party for business purposes. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting 
nationals of a Party seeking access to the employment 
market of the other Party, nor shall it apply to measures 
regarding nationality or citizenship, or residence or 
employment on a permanent basis. 



3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applying 
measures to regulate the entry of nationals of the other 
Party into, or their temporary stay in, the former Party, 
including those measures necessary to protect the integrity 
of, and to ensure the orderly movement of natural persons 
across, its borders, provided that such measures are not 
applied in such a manner as to nullify or impair the 
benefits accruing to the other Party under the terms of the 
categories set out in Annex 13. 

Note: 	The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural 
persons of a certain nationality and not for 
those of others shall not be regarded as 
nullifying or impairing benefits under the 
terms of a specific category.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Grant Of Entry And Temporary Stay" article_identifier="347">Each Party shall grant entry and temporary stay to 
nationals of the other Party in accordance with this 
Chapter including the provisions of Annex 13.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Provision Of Information" article_identifier="348">Each Party shall: 



(a) 	provide to the other Party such materials as will 
enable that other Party to become acquainted with 
its measures relating to this Chapter; 



(b) 	make publicly available in the Parties, 
explanatory material in a consolidated document 
regarding the requirements for entry and 
temporary stay under this Chapter, no later than 
one year after the date of entry into force of 
this Agreement; and 



(c) 	to the extent possible, upon request by the other 
Party, make available to the other Party, in 
accordance with its laws and regulations, data 
respecting the granting of entry and temporary 
stay under this Chapter to nationals of the other 
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="349">1. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter unless: 



(a) 	the matter involves a pattern of practice; and 



(b) 	the nationals of a Party concerned have exhausted 
the administrative remedies, where available, 
regarding the particular matter. 

2. The remedies referred to in subparagraph 1(b) shall be 
deemed to be exhausted if a final determination in the 
matter has not been issued by the competent authority of 
the other Party within one year after the date of the 
institution of the administrative remedy, and the failure 
to issue such determination is not attributable to delay 
caused by the nationals.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Measures Pursuant To Immigration Laws And Regulations" article_identifier="350">Except for this Chapter and Chapters 1, 2, 16, 17, 18 
and 19, nothing in this Agreement shall impose any 
obligation on either Party regarding measures pursuant to 
immigration laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Definitions" article_identifier="351">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “entry and temporary stay” means entry 
into and stay in a Party by a national of the 
other Party without the intent to establish 
permanent residence; and 



(b) 	the term “immigration laws and regulations” means 
any laws and regulations affecting the entry and 
temporary stay of nationals.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="38">
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Scope" article_identifier="352">1. This Chapter shall apply to any measures adopted or 
maintained by a Party relating to government procurement, 
by any contractual means, including through such methods as 
purchase or as lease, rental or hire purchase, with or 
without an option to buy: 



(a) 	by entities specified in Part 1 of Annex 14; 



(b) 	of goods specified in Part 2 of Annex 14, 
services specified in Part 3 of Annex 14, or 
construction services specified in Part 4 of 
Annex 14; and 



(c) 	where the value of the contracts to be awarded is 
estimated to be not less than the thresholds 
specified in Part 5 of Annex 14 at the time of 
publication of a notice of procurement. 


2. Paragraph 1 is subject to the General Notes set out in 
Part 6 of Annex 14. 



3. Neither Party shall prepare, design or otherwise 
structure any government procurement contract in order to 
avoid the obligations under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="National Treatment And Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="353">1. With respect to any laws, regulations, procedures and 
practices regarding government procurement covered by this 
Chapter, each Party shall provide immediately and 
unconditionally to the goods, services and suppliers of the 
other Party, treatment no less favorable than that it 
accords to its own goods, services and suppliers. 



2. With respect to any laws, regulations, procedures and 
practices regarding government procurement covered by this 
Chapter, each Party shall ensure: 



(a) 	that its entities do not treat a locally-
established supplier less favorably than another 
locally-established supplier on the basis of the 
degree of affiliation to, or ownership by, a 
natural person or an enterprise of the other 
Party; and 



(b) 	that its entities do not discriminate against a 
locally-established supplier on the basis that 
the goods or services offered by that supplier 
for a particular procurement are goods or 
services of the other Party. 


3. This Article shall not apply to customs duties and 
charges of any kind imposed on or in connection with 
importation, the method of levying such duties and charges, 
other import regulations, including restrictions and 
formalities, nor to measures affecting trade in services 
other than laws, regulations, procedures and practices 
regarding government procurement covered by this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Valuation Of Contracts" article_identifier="354">In determining the value of contracts for the purposes 
of implementing this Chapter: 



(a) 	valuation shall take into account all forms of 
remuneration, including any premiums, fees, 
commissions and interest receivable; 



(b) 	the selection of the valuation method by an 
entity shall not be used, nor shall any 
procurement requirement be divided, with the 
intention of avoiding the application of this 
Chapter; and 



(c) 	in cases where an intended procurement specifies 
the need for option clauses, the basis for 
valuation shall be the total value of the maximum 
permissible procurement, inclusive of optional 
purchases.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Prohibition Of Offsets" article_identifier="355">Each Party shall ensure that its entities do not, in 
the qualification and selection of suppliers, goods or 
services, or in the evaluation of tenders and award of 
contracts, impose, seek or consider offsets. For the 
purposes of this Article, offsets means conditions 
considered, sought or imposed by an entity prior to or in 
the course of its procurement process that encourage local 
development or improve its Party’s balance of payments 
accounts, by means of requirements of local content, 
licensing of technology, investment, counter-trade or 
similar requirements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Technical Specifications" article_identifier="356">1. Technical specifications laying down the 
characteristics of the goods or services to be procured, 
such as quality, performance, safety and dimensions, 
symbols, terminology, packaging, marking and labeling, or 
the processes and methods for their production and 
requirements relating to conformity assessment procedures 
prescribed by procuring entities, shall not be prepared, 
adopted or applied with a view to, or with the effect of, 
creating unnecessary obstacles to trade. 



2. Any technical specifications prescribed by procuring 
entities shall, where appropriate: 



(a) 	be specified in terms of performance rather than 
design or descriptive characteristics; and 



(b) 	be based on international standards, where such 
exist; otherwise, on national technical 
regulations, recognized national standards, or 
building codes. 


3. Each Party shall ensure that its entities do not 
prescribe technical specifications that require or refer to 
a particular trademark or trade name, patent, design or 
type, specific origin or producer or supplier, unless there 
is no sufficiently precise or intelligible way of 
describing the procurement requirements and provided that, 
in such cases, words such as “or equivalent” are included 
in the tender documentation. 



4. Each Party shall ensure that its entities do not seek 
or accept, in a manner which would have the effect of 
precluding fair competition, advice which may be used in 
the preparation or adoption of any technical specifications 
for a specific procurement from a person that may have a 
commercial interest in the procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Tendering Procedures" article_identifier="357">1. Each Party shall ensure that the tendering procedures 
of its entities are applied in a non-discriminatory manner 
and in compliance with this Chapter. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that its entities do not 
provide to any supplier information with regard to a 
specific procurement in a manner which would have the 
effect of precluding competition.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Qualification Of Suppliers" article_identifier="358">1. In the process of qualifying suppliers, each Party 
shall ensure that its entities do not discriminate against 
suppliers of the other Party. Qualification procedures 
shall be consistent with the following: 



(a) 	any conditions for participation in tendering 
procedures shall be published in adequate time to 
enable interested suppliers to initiate and, to 
the extent that it is compatible with efficient 
operation of the procurement process, complete 
the qualification procedures; 



(b) 	any conditions for participation in tendering 
procedures shall be limited to those which are 
essential to ensure the potential supplier’s 
capability to fulfill the contract in question; 



(c) 	the process of, and the time required for, 
qualifying suppliers shall not be used in order 
to keep suppliers of the other Party off a 
suppliers’ list or from being considered for a 
particular intended procurement.  Entities shall 
recognize as qualified suppliers such suppliers 
of the other Party who meet the conditions for 
participation in a particular intended 
procurement. Suppliers requesting to participate 
in a particular intended procurement who may not 
yet be qualified shall also be considered, 
provided there is sufficient time to complete the 
qualification procedure; 



(d) 	entities may maintain permanent lists of 
qualified suppliers. The entities shall ensure: 


(i) 	that suppliers may apply for qualification 
at any time; and 


(ii) 	that all qualified suppliers so requesting 
are included in the lists within a 
reasonably short time; 


(e) 	if, after publication of the notice of 
procurement under paragraph 1 of Article 143, a 
supplier not yet qualified requests to 
participate in an intended procurement, the 
entity shall promptly start procedures for 
qualification; and 



(f) 	any supplier having requested to become a 
qualified supplier shall be advised by the 
entities concerned of the decision in this 
regard. 

2. Nothing in paragraph 1 shall preclude the exclusion of 
any supplier on grounds such as bankruptcy, liquidation or 
insolvency, or false declarations relating to a 
procurement, provided that such an action is consistent 
with the national treatment and non-discrimination 
provisions of this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Notice Of Procurement" article_identifier="359">1. For each case of intended procurement, each Party 
shall ensure that its entities make publicly available in 
advance in the appropriate publication listed in Part 7 of 
Annex 14, a notice of procurement inviting interested 
suppliers to participate in that procurement, except as 
provided for in Article 147. 



2. The information in each notice of procurement shall 
include a description of the intended procurement, any 
conditions that suppliers must fulfill to participate in 
the procurement, the name of the entity, the address where 
all documents relating to the procurement may be obtained 
and the time-limits for submission of tenders. 



3. Each Party shall endeavor to ensure that its entities 
make publicly available notices of procurement in a timely 
manner through means which offer the widest possible and 
non-discriminatory access to interested suppliers. These 
means may be accessible free of charge, through a single 
electronic point of access. 



4. If, after making publicly available a notice of 
procurement in any case of intended procurement, but before 
the time set for opening or receipt of tenders as specified 
in the notice or the tender documentation, it becomes 
necessary to amend or re-issue the notice, the amendment or 
the re-issued notice shall be made publicly available in 
the same manner as the original notice. Any significant 
information given to one supplier with respect to a 
particular intended procurement shall be given 
simultaneously to all other suppliers concerned in adequate 
time to permit the suppliers to consider such information 
and to respond to it.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Time-Limits For Tendering" article_identifier="360">Each Party shall ensure that: 



(a) 	any prescribed time-limit is adequate to allow 
suppliers of the other Party as well as domestic 
suppliers to prepare and submit tenders before 
the closing of the tendering procedures; and 



(b) 	in determining any such time-limit, its entities, 
consistent with their own reasonable needs, take 
into account such factors as the complexity of 
the intended procurement, the extent of 
subcontracting anticipated, the normal time for 
transmitting tenders by mail from foreign as well 
as domestic points and the delays of making 
publicly available notices of procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Tender Documentation" article_identifier="361">1. Tender documentation provided to suppliers shall 
contain all information necessary to permit them to submit 
responsive tenders. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that its entities make tender 
documentation accessible, or, upon request, forward the 
tender documentation, to any supplier participating in the 
tendering procedure, and reply promptly to any reasonable 
request for explanations relating thereto. 



3. Each Party shall endeavor to ensure that its entities 
reply promptly to any reasonable request for relevant 
information submitted by a supplier participating in the 
tendering procedure, on condition that such information 
does not give that supplier an advantage over its 
competitors in the procedure for the award of the contract. 
The information provided to a supplier may be provided to 
any other suppliers that are invited to tender.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Awarding Of Contracts" article_identifier="362">1. To be considered for award, a tender must, at the time 
of opening, conform to the essential requirements of the 
notice of procurement or tender documentation and be from a 
supplier which complies with the conditions for 
participation. If an entity has received a tender 
abnormally lower or otherwise exceptionally more 
advantageous than other tenders submitted, it may enquire 
with the tenderer to ensure that the tenderer can comply 
with the conditions of participation and be capable of 
fulfilling the terms of the contract. 



2. Unless in the public interest an entity decides not to 
issue the contract, the entity shall make the award to the 
tenderer who has been determined to be fully capable of 
undertaking the contract and whose tender is either the 
lowest tender or determined to be the most advantageous in 
terms of the specific evaluation criteria set forth in the 
notice of procurement or tender documentation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Other Tendering Procedures" article_identifier="363">1. Articles 141 through 146 need not apply in the 
following conditions, provided that the tendering under 
this Article is not used by entities of a Party with a view 
to avoiding maximum possible competition or in a manner 
which would constitute a means of discrimination against 
the suppliers of the other Party or protection to domestic 
producers or suppliers: 



(a) 	in the absence of tenders in response to the 
tender pursuant to Articles 141 through 146, or 
when the tenders submitted have been collusive in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of the 
former Party, or not in conformity with the 
essential requirements in the tender, or from 
suppliers who do not comply with the conditions 
for participation provided for in accordance with 
this Chapter, on condition that the requirements 
of the initial tender are not substantially 
modified in the contract as awarded; 



(b) 	when, for works of art or for reasons connected 
with the protection of exclusive rights, such as 
patents or copyrights, or in the absence of 
competition for technical reasons, the goods or 
services can be supplied only by a particular 
supplier and no reasonable alternative or 
substitute exists; 



(c) 	in so far as is strictly necessary when, for 
reasons of extreme urgency brought about by 
events unforeseeable by the entity, the goods or 
services could not be obtained in time by means 
of the tendering procedures pursuant to Articles 
141 through 146; 



(d) 	for additional deliveries by the original 
supplier that are intended either as parts 
replacement for existing supplies, or 
installations, or as the extension of existing 
supplies, services, or installations, where a 
change of supplier would compel the entity to 
procure goods or services not meeting 
requirements of interchangeability with existing 
equipment, software, services or installations; 



(e) 	when an entity procures prototypes or a first 
good or service which are developed at its 
request in the course of, and for, a particular 
contract for research, experiment, study or 
original development; 


Note: 	Original development of a first good or 
service may include limited production or 
supply in order to incorporate the results 
of field testing and to demonstrate that 
the good or service is suitable for 
production or supply in quantity to 
acceptable quality standards. It does not 
extend to quantity production or supply to 
establish commercial viability or to 
recover research and development costs. 


(f) 	when additional construction services which were 
not included in the initial contract but which 
were within the objectives of the original tender 
documentation have, due to unforeseeable 
circumstances, become necessary to complete the 
construction services described therein, provided 
that the total value of contracts awarded for 
additional construction services may not exceed 
50 percent of the amount of the initial contract; 



(g) 	for new construction services consisting of the 
repetition of similar construction services which 
conform to a basic project for which an initial 
contract was awarded in accordance with Articles 
141 through 146 and for which the entity has 
indicated in the notice of procurement concerning 
the initial construction service, that the 
tendering procedures under this Article might be 
used in awarding contracts for such new 
construction services; 



(h) 	for goods purchased on a commodity market; 



(i) 	for purchases made under exceptionally 
advantageous conditions which only arise in the 
very short term. This provision is intended to 
cover unusual disposals by enterprises which are 
not normally suppliers, or disposal of assets of 
businesses in liquidation or receivership. It is 
not intended to cover routine purchases from 
regular suppliers; and 



(j) 	in the case of contracts awarded to the winner of 
design contest provided that the contest has been 
organized in a manner which is consistent with 
the principles of this Chapter and that the 
contest is judged by an independent jury with a 
view to design contracts being awarded to the 
winners. 

2. Each Party shall ensure that, whenever it is necessary 
for its entities to resort to the tendering procedures 
under paragraph 1, the entities maintain a record or 
prepare a written report providing specific justification 
for such procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 148" name="Post-Award Information" article_identifier="364">1. Each Party shall ensure that its entities make 
publicly available, in an appropriate publication listed in 
Part 7 of Annex 14, after the award of each contract, 
information such as: 



(a) 	the nature and quantity of goods or services in 
the contract award; 



(b) 	the name and address of the entity awarding the 
contract;  



(c) 	the date of award; 



(d) 	the name and address of the winning tenderer; 



(e) 	the value of the winning award; and 



(f) 	the type of procedure used. 

2. Each Party shall ensure that its entities, on request 
from a supplier of a Party, promptly provide information 
including: 



(a) 	pertinent information concerning the reasons why 
the supplier’s application to qualify was 
rejected, why its existing qualification was 
brought to an end and why it was not selected; 
and 



(b) 	when the supplier is an unsuccessful tenderer, 
pertinent information concerning the reasons why 
its tender was not selected and on the 
characteristics and relative advantages of the 
tender selected as well as the name of the 
winning tenderer. 

3. Where a supplier of a Party is an unsuccessful 
tenderer, the Party may seek, without prejudice to the 
provisions under Chapter 16, such additional information on 
the contract award, as may be necessary to ensure that the 
procurement was made fairly and impartially. The other 
Party shall provide information on both the characteristics 
and relative advantages of the winning tender and the 
contract price. Normally this latter information may be 
disclosed by the former Party provided it exercises this 
right with discretion. In cases where release of this 
information would prejudice competition in future tenders, 
this information shall be confidential and not be disclosed 
except after consultation with and agreement of the other 
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 149" name="Challenge Procedures" article_identifier="365">1. In the event of a complaint by a supplier that there 
has been a breach of this Chapter in the context of a 
government procurement, the procuring entity shall accord 
impartial and timely consideration to any such complaint, 
in a manner that is not prejudicial to obtaining corrective 
measures under the challenge system. 



2. Each Party shall provide non-discriminatory, timely, 
transparent and effective procedures enabling suppliers to 
challenge alleged breaches of this Chapter arising in the 
context of procurements in which they have, or have had, an 
interest. 



3. Each Party shall provide its challenge procedures in 
writing and make them generally available. 



4. Each Party shall ensure that documentation relating to 
all aspects of the process concerning government 
procurement covered by this Chapter shall be retained at 
least for three years. 



5. The interested supplier may be required to initiate a 
challenge procedure and notify the procuring entity within 
specified time-limits from the time when the basis of the 
complaint is known or reasonably should have been known, 
but in no case within a period of less than 10 days. 



6. Challenges shall be heard by an impartial and 
independent reviewing authority with no interest in the 
outcome of the government procurement and the members of 
which are secure from external influence during the term of 
appointment. A reviewing authority which is not a court 
shall either be subject to judicial review or shall have 
procedures which provide at least the following: 



(a) 	participants can be heard before an opinion is 
given or a decision is reached; 



(b) 	participants can be represented and accompanied; 



(c) 	participants shall have access to all 
proceedings;  



(d) 	proceedings can take place in public; 



(e) 	opinions or decisions are given in writing with a 
statement describing the basis for the opinions 
or decisions; 



(f) 	witnesses can be presented; and 



(g) 	documents are disclosed to the reviewing 
authority. 


7. 	Challenge procedures shall provide for: 



(a) 	rapid interim measures to correct breaches of 
this Chapter and to preserve commercial 
opportunities. Such action may result in 
suspension of the procurement process. However, 
procedures may provide that overriding adverse 
consequences for the interests concerned, 
including the public interest, may be taken into 
account in deciding whether such measures should 
be applied; 



(b) 	an assessment and, where appropriate, a decision 
on the justification of the challenge; and 



(c) 	where appropriate, correction of breaches of this 
Chapter or compensation for the loss or damages 
suffered, which may be limited to costs for 
tender preparation or protest. 


8. With a view to the preservation of the commercial and 
other interests involved, the challenge procedure shall 
normally be completed within a reasonable time.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 150" name="Use Of Electronic Communications In Procurement" article_identifier="366">1. The Parties shall seek to provide opportunities for 
government procurement to be undertaken through the 
Internet or a comparable computer-based telecommunications 
network. 



2. In order to facilitate commercial opportunities for 
its suppliers under this Chapter, each Party shall endeavor 
to adopt or maintain a single electronic portal for access 
to comprehensive information on government procurement 
supply opportunities in its Area, and information on 
measures relating to government procurement shall be 
available. 



3. The Parties shall encourage, to the extent possible, 
the use of electronic means for the provision of tender 
documents and the receipt of tenders. 



4. The Parties shall endeavor to ensure the adoption of 
policies and procedures for the use of electronic means in 
government procurement that: 



(a) 	protect documentation from unauthorized and 
undetected alteration; and 



(b) 	provide appropriate levels of security for data 
on, and passing through, the procuring entity’s 
network.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 151" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="367">Subject to the requirement that such measures are not 
applied in a manner that would constitute a means of 
arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination between the 
Parties where the same conditions prevail, or a disguised 
restriction on trade, nothing in this Chapter shall be 
construed to prevent a Party from imposing, enforcing or 
maintaining measures: 



(a) 	necessary to protect public morals, order or 
safety;  



(b) 	necessary to protect human, animal or plant life 
or health; 



(c) 	necessary to protect intellectual property; or 



(d) 	relating to goods or services of handicapped 
persons, of philanthropic institutions, or of 
prison labor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 152" name="Rectifications Or Modifications" article_identifier="368">1. A Party shall notify the other Party of its 
rectifications, or in exceptional cases, other 
modifications relating to Annex 14 along with the 
information as to the likely consequences of the change for 
the mutually agreed coverage provided in this Chapter. 



2. If the rectifications or other modifications are of a 
purely formal or minor nature, notwithstanding Article 197, 
they shall become effective provided that no objection from 
the other Party has been raised within 30 days. In other 
cases, both Parties shall consult the proposal and any 
claim for compensatory adjustments with a view to 
maintaining a balance of rights and obligations and a 
comparable level of mutually agreed coverage provided in 
this Chapter prior to such rectification or other 
modification. 



3. In the event of an agreement between the Parties not 
being reached, the Party which has received such 
notification may have recourse to the dispute settlement 
procedure under Chapter 16. 

Note: 	Notwithstanding any other provision of this Chapter, 
a Party may undertake reorganizations of its 
entities, including programs through which the 
procurement of such entities is decentralized or the 
corresponding government functions cease to be 
performed by any government entity, whether or not 
subject to this Chapter. In cases of 
reorganizations, compensation need not be proposed. 
Neither Party shall undertake such reorganizations 
to avoid the obligations of this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 153" name="Privatization Of Entities" article_identifier="369">When government control at the central or national 
government level over an entity specified in Part 1 of 
Annex 14 has been effectively eliminated, notwithstanding 
that the government may possess holding thereof or appoint 
member of the board of directors thereto, this Chapter 
shall no longer apply to that entity and compensation need 
not be proposed. A Party shall notify the other Party of 
the name of such entity before elimination of government 
control or as soon thereafter as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 154" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="370">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an 
enterprise of the other Party if the enterprise is owned or 
controlled by persons of a non-Party and the former Party: 



(a) 	does not maintain diplomatic relations with the 
non-Party; or 



(b) 	adopts or maintains measures with respect to the 
non-Party that prohibit transactions with the 
enterprise or that would be violated or 
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were 
accorded to the enterprise. 

2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, a 
Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a supplier 
of the other Party that is an enterprise of the other Party 
where the denying Party establishes that the enterprise is 
owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party and has no 
substantial business activities in the Area of the other 
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 155" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="371">In the event that after the entry into force of this 
Agreement a Party offers a non-Party additional advantages 
of access to its government procurement market beyond what 
the other Party has been provided with under this Chapter, 
the former Party shall, upon request of the other Party, 
enter into negotiations with the other Party with a view to 
extending those advantages to the other Party on a 
reciprocal basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 156" name="Committee On Government Procurement" article_identifier="372">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Government Procurement (hereinafter referred 
to in this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	analyzing available information on each Party’s 
government procurement market; 



(c) 	reporting the findings of the Committee to the 
Commission; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties. 



4. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 157" name="Definition" article_identifier="373">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “supplier” 
means a person that provides or could provide goods or 
services to an entity.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="39">
      <article number="ARTICLE 158" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="374">1. The Parties shall ensure adequate, effective and nondiscriminatory protection of intellectual property, promote 
efficiency and transparency in administration of 
intellectual property protection system, and provide for 
measures for adequate and effective enforcement of 
intellectual property rights against infringement, 
counterfeiting and piracy, in accordance with the 
provisions of this Chapter and the international agreements 
to which both Parties are parties. 



2. The Parties may take appropriate measures to prevent 
the abuse of intellectual property rights by right holders 
or the resort to practices which unreasonably restrain 
trade or adversely affect the international transfer of 
technology, provided that such measures are consistent with 
the provisions of this Agreement and the TRIPS Agreement. 



3. The Parties affirm their existing rights and 
obligations under the TRIPS Agreement and other 
multilateral agreements relating to intellectual property 
to which both Parties are parties. Nothing in this Chapter 
shall derogate from existing rights and obligations that 
the Parties have under the TRIPS Agreement or other 
multilateral agreements relating to intellectual property 
to which both Parties are parties. 



4. For the purposes of this Chapter, intellectual 
property refers to all categories of intellectual property: 



(a) 	that are subject of Articles 161 through 163; 
and/or 



(b) 	that are under the TRIPS Agreement and/or the 
relevant international agreements referred to in 
the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 159" name="Streamlining Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="375">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administration 
of intellectual property system, each Party shall take 
measures to streamline its administrative procedures 
concerning intellectual property. 



2. Each Party shall use a classification for patents and 
utility models in accordance with the Strasbourg Agreement 
Concerning the International Patent Classification, of 
March 24, 1971, as amended. Each Party shall use a 
classification of goods and services in accordance with the 
Nice Agreement Concerning the International Classification 
of Goods and Services for the Purposes of the Registration 
of Marks, of June 15, 1957, as amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 160" name="Transparency" article_identifier="376">For the purposes of further promoting transparency in 
administration of intellectual property system, each Party 
shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, take 
appropriate measures to make available to the public 
information on its efforts to provide effective enforcement 
of intellectual property rights and other information with 
regard to intellectual property system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 161" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="377">Each Party shall afford an opportunity for interested 
parties to oppose to an application for registration of or 
a registration of, and to request the cancellation of the 
registration of, a trademark, in accordance with its laws 
and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 162" name="New Varieties Of Plants" article_identifier="378">Each Party shall become a party, if it is not a party, 
to the 1991 Act of International Convention for the 
Protection of New Varieties of Plants, by January 1, 2009.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 163" name="Geographical Indications" article_identifier="379">1. The Parties agree that indications for wines and 
spirits listed in Annex 15 are geographical indications 
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 22 of the TRIPS 
Agreement, and shall abide by the obligations under the 
relevant provisions of the TRIPS Agreement with respect to 
the protection of geographical indications. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of Article 197, 
modifications to Annex 15 proposed by both Parties may be 
adopted by the Commission pursuant to subparagraph 1(d)(i) 
of Article 190. The adopted modifications shall be 
confirmed by an exchange of diplomatic notes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 164" name="Enforcement" article_identifier="380">1. Each Party shall provide for procedures concerning the 
suspension by its customs authority of the release of the 
goods infringing patents, utility models, industrial 
designs, trademarks, or copyrights or related rights, which 
are destined for importation into, or exportation from, the 
Party. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that its judicial authorities 
have the authority to order the infringer to pay the right 
holder damages adequate to compensate for the injury the 
right holder has suffered because of an infringement of 
that person’s intellectual property right by an infringer 
who knowingly, or with reasonable grounds to know, engaged 
in infringing activity. 



3. Each Party shall provide for criminal procedures and 
penalties to be applied in cases of trademark 
counterfeiting or copyright piracy, committed willfully and 
on a commercial scale. Remedies available shall include 
imprisonment and/or monetary fines sufficient to provide a 
deterrent, consistently with the level of penalties applied 
for crimes of a corresponding gravity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 165" name="Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="381">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Intellectual Property (hereinafter referred to 
in this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) 	discussing any issues related to intellectual 
property, such as: 


(i) 	areas and forms of cooperation in the field 
of intellectual property; 


(ii) 	enforcement of intellectual property rights; 


(iii) geographical indications; and 


(iv) 	public awareness concerning protection of 
intellectual property; 


(c) 	reporting the findings of the Committee to the 
Commission; and 



(d) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties. 



4. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="40">
      <article number="ARTICLE 166" name="General Provision" article_identifier="382">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and 
regulations and in a manner consistent with this Chapter, 
take measures which it considers appropriate against anticompetitive activities so as to avoid that the benefits of 
the liberalization of trade and investment may be 
diminished or nullified by such activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 167" name="Cooperation On Controlling Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="383">The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective 
laws and regulations, cooperate in the field of controlling 
anti-competitive activities subject to their respective 
available resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 168" name="Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="384">Each Party shall apply its competition laws and 
regulations in a manner which does not discriminate between 
persons in like circumstances on the basis of their 
nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 169" name="Procedural Fairness" article_identifier="385">Each Party shall implement administrative and judicial 
procedures in a fair manner to control anti-competitive 
activities, pursuant to its relevant laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 170" name="Transparency" article_identifier="386">Each Party shall promote transparency of the 
implementation of its competition laws and regulations and 
its competition policy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 171" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="387">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in 
Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Improvement Of Business Environment" chapter_identifier="41">
      <article number="ARTICLE 172" name="Consultations For The Improvement Of Business Environment" article_identifier="388">The Parties, confirming their interest in creating a 
more favorable business environment with a view to 
promoting trade and investment activities by their private 
enterprises, shall from time to time have consultations in 
order to address issues concerning the improvement of 
business environment in the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 173" name="Committee On Improvement Of Business Environment" article_identifier="389">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and 
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a 
Committee on Improvement of Business Environment 
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Committee shall be: 



(a) 	discussing ways and means to improve business 
environment in the Parties; 



(b) 	making, as needed, recommendations to the Parties 
on appropriate measures to be taken by the 
Parties; 



(c) 	receiving information on the implementation of 
such recommendations from the relevant 
authorities of the Governments of the Parties; 



(d) 	making public, as needed, such recommendations in 
an appropriate manner; 



(e) 	reporting the findings of the Committee to the 
Commission; and 



(f) 	carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Commission in accordance with Article 190. 


3. The Committee shall be composed of government 
officials of the Parties. 



4. The Committee may, by consensus, invite 
representatives of relevant entities other than the 
governmental agencies of the Parties with the necessary 
expertise related to the issues to be discussed. 



5. The Committee shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties. 



6. The Committee shall cooperate with other relevant 
committees or working groups with a view to avoiding 
unnecessary overlap with the works of such committees or 
working groups.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 174" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="390">The dispute settlement procedure provided for in 
Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 16" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="42">
      <article number="ARTICLE 175" name="Scope" article_identifier="391">Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, this 
Chapter shall apply with respect to the avoidance or 
settlement of disputes between the Parties concerning the 
implementation, interpretation or operation of this 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 176" name="Choice Of Dispute Settlement Procedure" article_identifier="392">1. Where a dispute regarding any matter arises under both 
this Agreement and the WTO Agreement, the complaining Party 
may select the dispute settlement procedure in which to 
settle the dispute. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, once the complaining 
Party has requested the establishment of an arbitral 
tribunal under this Chapter or a panel under Article 6 of 
the Understanding on Rules and Procedures Governing the 
Settlement of Disputes in Annex 2 to the WTO Agreement with 
respect to a particular dispute, the arbitral tribunal or 
panel selected shall be used to the exclusion of the other 
procedure for that particular dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 177" name="Consultations" article_identifier="393">1. Either Party may request in writing consultations with 
the other Party concerning any matter on the 
implementation, interpretation or operation of this 
Agreement, including a matter relating to a measure that 
the other Party proposes to take (hereinafter referred to 
in this Chapter as “proposed measure”). 



2. The requesting Party shall set out the reasons for the 
request, including identification of the measure at issue 
and an indication of the legal basis for the complaint, and 
provide sufficient information to enable a full examination 
of the matter. 



3. The Parties shall make every effort to arrive at a 
mutually satisfactory resolution of the matter through 
consultations under this Article. 



4. The consultations under this Article shall be 
confidential and without prejudice to the rights of either 
Party in any further proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 178" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="394">1. The complaining Party that requested consultations 
under Article 177 may request in writing the establishment 
of an arbitral tribunal, if the Parties fail to resolve the 
matter within: 



(a) 	45 days after the date of receipt of the request 
for consultations; or 



(b) 	30 days after the date of receipt of the request 
for consultations in cases of urgency, including 
those which concern perishable goods, 

provided that the complaining Party considers that any 
benefits accruing to it directly or indirectly under this 
Agreement are being nullified or impaired as a result of 
the failure of the Party complained against to carry out 
its obligations under this Agreement, or as a result of the 
application by the Party complained against of measures 
which are in conflict with its obligations under this 
Agreement. 



2. The request of the establishment of an arbitral 
tribunal referred to in paragraph 1 may also be made in 
case where the complaining Party considers that any 
benefits accruing to it directly or indirectly under 
Chapters 3 and 4 are being nullified or impaired as a 
result of the application by the Party complained against 
of measures which are not in conflict with its obligations 
under those Chapters. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, the establishment 
of an arbitral tribunal shall not be requested on any 
matter relating to a proposed measure. 



4. Any request to establish an arbitral tribunal pursuant 
to this Article shall identify: 



(a) 	the specific measure at issue; 



(b) 	the legal basis of the complaint including the 
provisions of this Agreement alleged to have been 
breached and any other relevant provisions; and 



(c) 	the factual basis for the complaint. 


5. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal 
shall be the date on which the chair is appointed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 179" name="Terms Of Reference Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="395">Unless the Parties otherwise agree within 20 days from 
the date of receipt of the request for the establishment of 
the arbitral tribunal, the terms of reference of the 
arbitral tribunal shall be: 


“To examine, in the light of the relevant provisions 
of this Agreement, the matter referred to in the request 
for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal pursuant to 
Article 178, to make findings of law and fact together with 
the reasons therefor and to issue an award for the 
resolution of the dispute.”</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 180" name="Composition Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="396">1. 	An arbitral tribunal shall comprise three arbitrators. 



2. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date of 
receipt of the request for the establishment of an arbitral 
tribunal, appoint one arbitrator who may be its national 
and propose up to three candidates to serve as the third 
arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. 
The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either 
Party, nor have his or her usual place of residence in 
either Party, nor be employed by either Party, nor have 
dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 



3. The Parties shall agree on and appoint the third 
arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of the 
request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal, 
taking into account the candidates proposed pursuant to 
paragraph 2. 



4. If a Party has not appointed an arbitrator pursuant to 
paragraph 2 or if the Parties fail to agree on and appoint 
the third arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 3, the 
arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed shall be chosen 
within seven days by lot from the candidates proposed 
pursuant to paragraph 2. 



5.	 All arbitrators shall: 



(a) 	have expertise or experience in law, 
international trade or other matters covered by 
this Agreement; 



(b) 	be chosen strictly on the basis of objectivity, 
reliability and sound judgment; 



(c) 	be independent of, and not be affiliated with or 
receives instructions from, the Government of 
either Party; and 



(d) 	comply with a code of conduct, to be provided in 
the Rules of Procedures referred to in Article 

187. 


6. If an arbitrator appointed under this Article dies, 
becomes unable to act or resigns, a successor shall be 
appointed within 15 days in accordance with the appointment 
procedure provided for in paragraphs 2, 3 and 4, which 
shall be applied, respectively, mutatis mutandis. The 
successor shall have all the powers and duties of the 
original arbitrator. The work of the arbitral tribunal 
shall be suspended for a period beginning on the date the 
original arbitrator dies, becomes unable to act or resigns 
and ending on the date the successor is appointed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 181" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="397">1. The function of an arbitral tribunal is to make an 
objective assessment of the dispute before it, including an 
examination of the facts of the case and the applicability 
of and conformity with this Agreement, and make such other 
findings and rulings necessary for the resolution of the 
dispute.  



2. The arbitral tribunal should consult with the Parties 
as appropriate and provide adequate opportunities for the 
development of a mutually satisfactory resolution.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 182" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="398">1. 	The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 



2. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend 
any of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the 
proceedings. Any information or written submissions 
submitted by a Party to the arbitral tribunal, including 
any comments on the draft award and responses to questions 
put by the arbitral tribunal, shall be made available to 
the other Party. 



3. The arbitral tribunal shall make its decisions, 
including its award, by consensus but may also make its 
decisions, including its award, by majority vote. 



4. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from any 
relevant source and may consult experts to obtain their 
opinion on certain aspects of the matter. 



5. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the 
documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 



6. Notwithstanding paragraph 5, either Party may make 
public statements as to its views regarding the dispute, 
but shall treat as confidential, information and written 
submissions submitted by the other Party to the arbitral 
tribunal which that other Party has designated as 
confidential. Where a Party has provided information or 
written submissions designated to be confidential, that 
Party shall, upon request of the other Party, provide a 
non-confidential summary of the information or written 
submissions which may be disclosed publicly. 



7. Each Party shall bear the cost of its appointed 
arbitrator and its own expenses. The cost of the chair of 
an arbitral tribunal and other expenses associated with the 
conduct of the proceedings shall be borne by the Parties in 
equal shares.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 183" name="Suspension Or Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="399">1. The Parties may agree that the arbitral tribunal 
suspends its work at any time for a period not exceeding 12 
months from the date of such agreement. In the event of 
such a suspension, the time-frames set out in paragraphs 2, 
5 and 7 of Article 184 and paragraph 7 of Article 186 shall 
be extended by the amount of time that the work was 
suspended. If the work of the arbitral tribunal has been 
suspended for more than 12 months, the authority for 
establishment of the arbitral tribunal shall lapse unless 
the Parties agree otherwise. 



2. The Parties may agree to terminate the proceedings of 
the arbitral tribunal by jointly so notifying the chair of 
the arbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of 
the award to the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 184" name="Award" article_identifier="400">1. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted 
without the presence of the Parties, and in the light of 
the information provided and the statements made, and the 
relevant provisions of this Agreement. 



2. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 120 days, or 
within 60 days in cases of urgency, including those which 
concern perishable goods, after the date of its 
establishment, submit to the Parties its draft award. 



3. The draft award shall contain both the descriptive 
part and the findings, conclusions and decisions of the 
arbitral tribunal, for the purposes of enabling the Parties 
to review precise aspects of the draft award. 



4. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot 
submit its draft award within the aforementioned 120 days 
or 60 days period, it may extend that period with the 
consent of the Parties. 



5. A Party may provide written comments to the arbitral 
tribunal on its draft award within 15 days after the date 
of submission of the draft award. 



6. After considering any written comments on the draft 
award, the arbitral tribunal may reconsider its draft award 
and make any further examination it considers appropriate. 



7. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award, within 30 
days after the date of submission of the draft award. 



8. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be available 
to the public within 15 days after the date of issuance, 
subject to the requirement to protect confidential 
information.  



9. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and 
binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 185" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="401">1. Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the Party 
complained against shall comply with the award of the 
arbitral tribunal referred to in Article 184 immediately. 
If this is not practicable, the Party complained against 
shall comply with the award within a reasonable period of 
time. 



2. The reasonable period of time referred to in paragraph 
1 shall be mutually determined by the Parties. Where the 
Parties fail to agree on the reasonable period of time 
within 45 days after the date of issuance of the award of 
the arbitral tribunal referred to in Article 184, either 
Party may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal, which 
shall determine the reasonable period of time. 



3. Where there is disagreement between the Parties as to 
whether the Party complained against has complied with the 
award of the arbitral tribunal referred to in Article 184 
within the reasonable period of time as determined pursuant 
to paragraph 2, either Party may refer the matter to an 
arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 186" article_identifier="402">Non-Implementation – 
Compensation and Suspension of Concessions 
or Other Obligations</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 187" name="Rules Of Procedures" article_identifier="403">The Commission shall adopt the Rules of Procedures 
which provide for the details of the rules and procedures 
of arbitral tribunals established under this Chapter, upon 
the entry into force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 188" name="Modification Of Rules And Procedures" article_identifier="404">Any time period, or other rules and procedures for 
arbitral tribunals, provided for in this Chapter, including 
the Rules of Procedures referred to in Article 187, may be 
modified by mutual consent of the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 17" name="Commission" chapter_identifier="43">
      <article number="ARTICLE 189" name="Establishment Of The Commission" article_identifier="405">The Parties hereby establish a Commission which shall 
be co-chaired by Ministers or senior officials of the 
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 190" name="Functions Of The Commission" article_identifier="406">1. 	The Commission shall: 



(a) 	review and monitor, and consider any matters 
relating to, the implementation, interpretation 
and operation of this Agreement; 



(b) 	consider and recommend to the Parties any 
amendments to this Agreement; 



(c) 	supervise and coordinate the work of all 
committees and working groups established under 
this Agreement; 



 (d) 	adopt: 


(i) 	modifications to Annex 15; 


(ii) 	the Operational Procedures referred to in 
Article 52; 


(iii) 	an interpretation of a provision of this 
Agreement referred to in Articles 93 and 94; 


(iv) 	the Rules of Procedures referred to in 
Article 187; and 


(v) 	any necessary decisions; and 


(e) 	carry out other functions as the Parties may 
agree. 

2. The Commission may establish committees and working 
groups, refer matters to any committee or working group for 
advice, delegate its responsibilities to any committee or 
working group, and consider matters raised by any committee 
or working group.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 191" name="Rules And Procedures Of The Commission" article_identifier="407">1. The Commission shall establish its rules and 
procedures. 



2. Decisions of the Commission shall be taken by mutual 
agreement. 



3. The Commission shall meet at such venues and times as 
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 18" name="Exceptions" chapter_identifier="44">
      <article number="ARTICLE 192" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="408">1. For the purposes of Chapters 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 other 
than Article 76, Article XX of the GATT 1994 is 
incorporated into and made part of this Agreement, mutatis 
mutandis. 



2. For the purposes of Chapters 8 other than Article 76, 
9, 10 and 11, Article XIV of the GATS, including its 
footnotes, is incorporated into and made part of this 
Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 193" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="409">Nothing in this Agreement other than Article 76 shall 
be construed: 



(a) 	to require a Party to furnish any information the 
disclosure of which it considers contrary to its 
essential security interests; 



(b) 	to prevent a Party from taking any actions which 
it considers necessary for the protection of its 
essential security interests: 


(i) 	relating to the traffic in arms, ammunition 
and implements of war and to such traffic in 
other goods and materials, or such supply of 
services, as is carried on directly or 
indirectly for the purpose of supplying or 
provisioning a military establishment; 


(ii) 	taken in time of war or other emergency in 
international relations; or 


(iii) 	relating to fissionable and fusionable 
materials or the materials from which they 
are derived; or 


(c) 	to prevent a Party from taking any action in 
pursuance of its obligations under the United 
Nations Charter for the maintenance of 
international peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 194" name="Taxation" article_identifier="410">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Article, 
nothing in this Agreement shall apply to taxation measures. 


Note: 	The term “taxation measures” shall not include: 



(a) 	a customs duty as defined in subparagraph (d) of 
Article 28; 



(b) 	an anti-dumping or countervailing duty referred 
to in subparagraph (d)(ii) of Article 28; and 



(c) 	fees or charges referred to in subparagraph 
(d)(iii) of Article 28. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and 
obligations of either Party under the provisions relating 
to any taxation measures in any other international 
agreements to which both Parties are parties. 



3. Article 13 shall apply to taxation measures to the 
same extent as Article III of the GATT 1994. 



4. Articles 107 and 108 shall apply to taxation measures 
to the same extent as covered by the GATS. 



5. 	(a) Article 82 shall apply to taxation measures 
except that no investor may invoke Article 82 as 
the basis for a claim under Article 89, where it 
has been determined pursuant to subparagraph (b) 
that the measure is not an expropriation. 


(b) 	The investor shall refer the issue, at the time 
that it delivers the notice of intent under 
Article 89, to the competent authorities of both 
Parties, through the contact points referred to 
in Article 10, to determine whether such measure 
is not an expropriation. If the competent 
authorities of both Parties do not consider the 
issue or, having considered it, fail to determine 
that the measure is not an expropriation within a 
period of 180 days of such referral, the investor 
may submit its claim to arbitration under Article 


89. 


(c) 	For the purposes of subparagraph (b), the term 
“competent authorities” means: 

(i) 	with respect to Japan, the Minister of 
Finance or his or her authorized 
representative, who shall consider the issue 
in consultation with the Minister of Foreign 
Affairs or his or her authorized 
representative; and 


(ii) 	with respect to Chile, the Director of the 
Internal Revenue Service, Ministry of 
Finance (Director del Servicio de Impuestos 
Internos, Ministerio de Hacienda).</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 19" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="45">
      <article number="ARTICLE 195" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="411">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall 
constitute an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 196" name="Headings" article_identifier="412">The headings of the Chapters, Sections and Articles of 
this Agreement are inserted for convenience of reference 
only and shall not affect the interpretation of this 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 197" name="Amendments" article_identifier="413">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between the 
Parties. 



2. Any amendment shall be approved by the Parties in 
accordance with their respective legal procedures. Such 
amendment shall enter into force on the date to be agreed 
upon by the Parties. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, amendments relating only 
to Annex 2 or 4 may be made by exchange of diplomatic 
notes. 

Note: 	In the case of Chile, the amendments under 
paragraph 3 shall be made as an Executive 
Agreement (Acuerdo de Ejecución) in accordance 
with the Political Constitution of the Republic 
of Chile (Constitución Política de la República 
de Chile).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 198" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="414">This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth 
day after the date of exchange of diplomatic notes 
informing each other that their respective legal procedures 
necessary for entry into force of this Agreement have been 
completed. It shall remain in force unless terminated as 
provided for in Article 199.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 199" name="Termination" article_identifier="415">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving 
one year’s advance notice in writing to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="46">
      <article article_identifier="416">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly 
authorized by their respective Governments, have signed 
this Agreement. 


DONE at Tokyo, on this twenty-seventh day of March in 
the year 2007 in duplicate in the English language. 


For Japan: For the Republic of Chile:</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
