<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Treaty on a Free Trade Area between members of the Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>762</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>413</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2011-10-18</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2012-09-20</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2013-06-06</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2020-12-30</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">ARM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KGZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">MDA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">TJK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">UKR</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">ARM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KGZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">MDA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">TJK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">UKR</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">99</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/762/TOA/English/FTA CIS_Text with protocols.docx</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/762/AnnexAndRelatedDocs/English/FTA CIS_Text with protocols.docx</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4130">
      <article article_identifier="35699">TREATY
  ON A FREE-TRADE AREA
  (St. Petersburg, October 18, 2011)
    The member states of the Commonwealth of Independent States,
    hereinafter referred to as the Parties,
  
    Taking into account the necessity of proper and efficient
    functioning of the free-trade area,
  
    For the purpose of formation of conditions for a free flow of goods;
  
    Understanding the necessity of being integrated into the world
    economy and international trade system;
  
    Being guided by a desire for a constant rise in the living standards
    of the population of its states,
  
    Proceeding from the assumption that provisions of this Treaty are
    applicable to trade in goods between the Parties,
  
    And recognizing generally accepted norms of international law and
    being guided by the norms of the WTO agreements, in particular GATT
    1994, including Article XXIV of GATT 1994,
  
    Have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4131">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Definitions" article_identifier="35700">Definitions used in this Treaty shall mean the following:
      WTO - World Trade Organisation,
    created in accordance with the Marrakech Agreement on Establishing
    the World Trade Organization, signed on April 15, 1994;
  GATT 1994 - General Agreement on
    Tariffs and Trade of 1994 contained in Annex 1A to the Agreement on
    the Establishment of a World Trade Organisation of April 15, 1994;
  payments equivalent to customs
    duties - payments collected at importation or exportation
    of goods, and also in other cases established by the national
    legislation of a Party analogous, by the purposes and economic
    effect, to customs duties which are not customs duties, a
    compensation for the value of services rendered in connection with
    the carrying out of procedures for importation or exportation and
    are not connected with the application of safeguard, antidumping,
    countervailing measures in mutual trade;
  import of goods - importation of
    goods onto the customs territory of a Party without the obligation
    on re-export;
  export of goods - exportation of
    goods from the customs territory of a Party without the obligation
    on re-import;
  re-export - exportation of a
    commodity originating from the customs territory of one of the
    Parties from the customs territory of another Party to third
    countries:
  authorized export - re-export of
    a commodity in whose respect a Party which is the country of origin
    of such commodity establishes or maintains customs duties in its
    export to third countries effectuated in the presence of a properly
    drawn up written permit issued by the authorised body of the country
    of origin of the goods;
  unauthorized re-export -
    re-export of a commodity in whose respect a Party which is the
    country of origin of such good establishes or maintains customs
    duties in its export to third countries effectuated without a
    properly drawn up written permit issued by the authorised body of
    the country of origin of the goods.
  
    2. When using in this Treaty references to provisions of GATT 1994
    or to any other international treaties concluded within the WTO, the
    terms contained therein "contracting Party/Parties" or
    "member/members" shall mean, respectively, Party/Parties
    as they are defined in the preamble
    of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Application Of Customs Duties And Payments Equivalent To Customs Duties" article_identifier="35701">1. A Party shall not apply customs duties and any other
    payments equivalent to customs
    duties with respect to export of goods intended for the
    customs territory of another Party, and/or to import of a good
    originating from the customs territory of another Party, except for
    the cases stipulated in Annex 1 to
    this Treaty.
  
    2. The Parties shall not increase the level of custom duties in
    mutual trade of goods mentioned in Annex
    1 to this Treaty.
  
    3. If a Party applying an export duty according to
    Annex 1 to this Treaty has abolished
    it or reduced its level with respect to a third country, then it is
    applicable with respect to the Parties. This applies without
    prejudice to the provisions of
    Article
    18 of this Treaty.
  
    4. Unless otherwise stipulated by this Treaty, customs duties shall
    not be applied in a manner which would lead to the increase of
    discrimination between Parties and third countries.
  
    5. If with respect to the goods mentioned in
    Annex 1 to this Treaty there is
    stipulated a mechanism of changing the rates of a duty depending on
    the change in economic, statistical or other indicators, except for
    the customs value of goods, then the Parties shall not change such
    mechanism in a way that would increase the level of tariff
    protection.
  
    6. A state which has acceded to this Treaty shall not apply any
    customs duties with respect to the export or import of goods
    originating from the customs territories of the other Parties and
    intended for the customs territories of the other Parties in a
    manner which would lead to an increase of the duty rate as compared
    with the one that was applied by the acceding state with respect to
    the other Parties as on the date of the
    entry into force
    of this Treaty, unless otherwise results from the procedure for
    establishing a duty which is used as on the date of entry into force
    of this Treaty.
  
    7. Nothing in this Article shall prevent any Party from collecting
    with respect to the import of goods:
  
    obligatory payment, equivalent in accordance with the provisions of
    Article 5 of this
    Treaty, to the internal tax levied on goods, if such goods are
    produced on the territory of this Party, or on goods from which the
    imported goods were fully or partly manufactured or produced, or a
    payment connected with the application of domestic taxes on imported
    goods in accordance with the provisions of Article 5 of this Treaty;
  
    duty to be applied in accordance with the provisions of
    Articles
    8 and
    9
    of this Treaty.
  
    8. None of the provision of this Article shall prevent a Party from
    collecting, with respect to the import or
    export of goods, any fees based on
    the cost of rendered services and to be applied in accordance with
    the provisions of paragraph 1 of Article VIII of GATT 1994.
  
    9. A Party shall not change methods and procedure for establishing
    and applying the fees stipulated by paragraph 7 of this Article in a
    manner which would lead to an increase of the size of the fee as
    compared with the size of the fee to be applied by the Party as on
    the date of entry into
    force of this Treaty without increasing the value of the
    services rendered unless such change is aimed at a fuller reflection
    of the level of the value of the services rendered.
  
    10. Within 30 days from the date of
    entry into force
    of this Treaty the Parties shall notify one another about the fees
    stipulated by paragraph8 of this Article.
  
    11. Incase if a Party applies zero or reduced rates of export duties
    on export to the customs territories of the other Parties as
    compared with the duty rates applied with respect to the export of
    goods intended for the customs territories of third countries, then
    such other Parties shall prohibit
    unauthorized re-export of such
    goods.
  
    In case if such prohibition has not been established or has not
    actually been applied, then a Party applying zero or reduced
    export-duty rates on export to the customs territories of other
    Parties may increase them to the level applied on export to the
    customs territories of third countries.
  
    12. The Parties may, within the framework of bilateral arrangements,
    agree on other methods of regulating the relations stipulated by
    paragraph11 of this Article not stipulating the introduction of
    prohibition on re-export.
  
    13. Within 30 days from the date of
    entry into force
    of this Treaty, each Party shall, in writing, notify the other
    Parties about the goods in whose export to third countries customs
    duties shall be collected, and also about the sizes of the rates
    (and, when applicable, about the mechanism for calculating the
    rates) of such customs duties.
  
    14. Any changes of the list of the goods mentioned in paragraph13 of
    this Article, as well as any changes of the rate sizes or of the
    mechanism for calculating the customs-duty rates mentioned in
    paragraph13 of this Article shall be notified, in writing, by each
    Party to other Parties not later than 30 days before the date of
    entry into force of such changes.
  
    15. The Parties have agreed to negotiate reduction and gradual
    abolition of export duties mentioned in
    Annex 1 to this Treaty. The first
    round of such negotiations shall take place within six months after
    the entry into
    force of this Treaty.
  
    The results of such negotiations shall be formalized by protocols.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Abolition Of Quantitative Restrictions In Mutual Trade" article_identifier="35702">1. None of the Parties shall establish and/or maintain on import of
    any goods from the territory of another Party or for export of any
    goods intended for the territory of another Party, any prohibitions
    or restrictions other than those permitted by Article XI of GATT
    1994, including by the Notes and supplementary provisions to that
    Article, and also by
    Articles
    8 and
    9
    of this Treaty.
  
    2.Prohibitions and restrictions which are subject to abolition in
    accordance with paragraph 1 of this Article and which are effective
    on the moment of entry
    into force of this Treaty, shall be abolished according to
    the schedule stipulated by Annex 2 to this Treaty which is an
    integral part thereof.
  
    3. A Party establishing certain quantitative restrictions
    permissible in accordance with paragraph1 of this Article, shall, in
    advance, inform the other Parties about the reasons for the
    establishment, forms and possible periods of application of such
    restrictions affecting interests of the Parties, with justification
    of such action.
  
    4. The Parties shall settle all issues arising in connection with
    the application of permissible quantitative restrictions by means of
    consultations.
  
    5. In selecting the measures in accordance with this Article, the
    Parties shall give priority to those of them which least negatively
    affect the achievement of purposes of this Treaty.
  
    6. In applying any quantitative restrictions, the Parties shall
    comply with the provisions stipulated by Article XIII of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Determination Of The Country Of Origin Of Goods" article_identifier="35703">1. For determining the country of origin of goods which originate
    from the Parties and are in trade turnover among them, the Parties
    shall be guided by the
    Rules
    for Determining the Country of Origin, which are an integral part of
    the
    Agreement
    on the Rules for Determining the Country of Origin of Goods in the
    Commonwealth of Independent States of November 20, 2009.
  
    2. The procedure for determining the country of origin of goods
    originating and imported onto the customs territories of the Parties
    from third countries, shall be governed by the national legislation
    of the Parties and by the international treaties ratified by the
    Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="National Regime" article_identifier="35704">The Parties shall grant national treatment to each other in
    accordance with Article III of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Government Procurement" article_identifier="35705">1. With respect to all laws, normative acts, procedures and practice
    concerning government procurement under paragraph 8(a) of Article
    III of GATT 1994 covered by the provisions of paragraph3 of this
    Article, each of the Parties shall grant, with respect to goods
    originating from the territory of any other Party and its related
    suppliers, a not less favorable treatment than the one which is
    granted to:
  
    1) domestic goods and suppliers;
  
    2) goods originating from the territory of any other Party and its
    suppliers.
  
    2. Provisions of paragraph1 of this Article shall not be applicable
    with respect to customs duties and any other payments equivalent to
    customs duties applied on import.
  
    3. Provisions of paragraph1 of this Article shall be applicable on a
    bi- or multilateral basis among the interested Parties.
  
    4. Within three months after the
    entry into force
    of this Treaty the interested Parties shall enter into negotiations
    for elaborating a Protocol to this Treaty determining the
    obligations of the Parties with respect to the rules and procedures
    regulating government procurement for the purposes of completing it
    within a three-year period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Freedom Of Transit" article_identifier="35706">1. Transit of goods and transport means within the framework of this
    Treaty shall be regulated in accordance with the provisions of
    Article V of GATT 1994.
  
    2. The following conditions are applied to transit of goods and
    transport means:
  
    1) goods being transited through the territory of a Party shall
    simultaneously:
  
    a) remain unchanged, except for changes due to natural deterioration
    or loss under normal conditions of transportation and storage;
  
    b) not be used for any purposes other than transit;
  
    c) be delivered to the customs authority of destination within the
    periods established by the customs authority of departure,
    proceeding from capacity of the transport means carrying a
    commodity, the planed rout and any other conditions of shipment;
  
    2) in cases where it does not contradict the provisions of this
    Treaty, a Party may, in accordance with its legislation, establish a
    list of certain types of goods whose transit is prohibited and also
    a list of certain types of goods whose transit requires special
    permits from authorised bodies of the Parties. The Parties shall
    notify each other about its lists;
  
    3) if transit is interrupted due to an accident or force majeure,
    then the carrier shall be guided by norms established by the
    national legislation of the Party on whose territory transit has
    been interrupted;
  
    4) customs authorities of the Parties shall mutually recognise
    national means of identification, other means of customs support,
    and also documents necessary for controlling the goods and transport
    vehicles carrying them, in accordance with international conventions
    ratified by the Parties, and/or with the arrangements reached among
    them;
  
    5) each Party shall grant the goods transiting across the territory
    of any other Party a regime not less favourable than the regime
    which would have been granted to such goods if they were transported
    from the place of origin to the place of destination without being
    transferred across the territory of such other Party.
  
    3. Provisions of this Article shall not extend to pipeline
    transport.
  
    4. Interested Parties shall enter into negotiations for elaborating
    an Agreement on the Transit by Pipeline Transport and shall complete
    such negotiations within six months after the
    entry into force
    of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Application Of Safeguard Measures In Mutual Trade" article_identifier="35707">1. Nothing in this Treaty shall restrict the right of a Party
    (customs union)
        For the purposes of Article 8 and Article 9 of this Treaty the
        customs union means union between the Parties which provides for
        the uniform application of safeguard, antidumping and
        countervailing measures.
       to apply any safeguard measures. Such measures with
    respect to industrial and agricultural goods shall be applied only
    in accordance with Article XIX of GATT 1994, the WTO Agreement on
    Safeguards and by this Treaty.
  
    2. When applying any safeguard measures, a Party (customs union)
    shall remove from the effect of such measures a commodity
    originating from the territory of another Party on condition that
    such commodity has been imported in such quantities and under such
    conditions which have not caused any injury and/or have not created
    a threat of causing injury to the domestic industry of this Party
    (customs union).
  
    Import originating from the territory of another Party shall be
    considered as not causing any injury and/or not threatening to cause
    injury to the domestic industry of a Party (customs union) if the
    other Party is not one of the five main suppliers of the imported
    commodity for the last three years and the following conditions are
    simultaneously met:
  
    during the recent three years the import volumes from the other
    Party have been decreasing or growing in smaller volumes (in
    absolute and relative indicators) as compared with the import from
    other countries;
  
    the price level of import of goods from the other Party is equal or
    higher than the price level of a domestic commodity producer of like
    or directly competitive goods on the internal market of the
    importing Party (customs union).
  
    3. If one of the Parties (customs union) intends to apply safeguard
    measures, then this Party (customs union) shall, not later than 30
    days before the completion of the investigation, inform about such
    intention the other Parties which may be affected by the application
    of a measure. Interested Parties shall conduct consultations for the
    purposes of finding a mutually acceptable solution.
  
    4. When choosing a type of safeguard measures, the Parties (customs
    union) shall give the priority to those measures which will cause
    the least injury to achieving the purposes of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Application Of Antidumping And Countervailing Measures In Mutual Trade" article_identifier="35708">1. Nothing in this Treaty prevents a Party (customs union) from
    applying, with respect to the import of a commodity originating from
    another Party, any antidumping or countervailing measures. Such
    measures with respect to industrial and agricultural goods must be
    applied only in accordance with Articles VI, XVI of GATT 1994, the
    WTO Agreement on the Application of Article VI of GATT 1994, the WTO
    Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures and with this
    Treaty.
  
    2. If one of the Parties (customs union) intends to apply any
    antidumping or countervailing measures, then this Party (customs
    union) shall, before the application of the measures, provide the
    other interested Parties with the relevant information about the
    main facts and findings reasoning the application of such measures.
    For the Parties to be able to protect their interests, such
    information shall be provided in advance but not later than 30 days
    before the completion of the investigation.
  
    3. A Party (customs union) which intends to apply or prolong certain
    antidumping or countervailing measures, shall provide adequate
    possibility for conducting preliminary consultations before the
    completion of the investigation by the interested Parties.
  
    4. When choosing a type of antidumping or countervailing measures,
    the Parties (customs union) shall give the priority to those
    measures which will cause the least damage to achieving the purposes
    of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Granting Of Subsidies" article_identifier="35709">1. The Parties shall grant subsidies in accordance with the
    provisions of Articles VI, XVI of GATT 1994 and of the WTO Agreement
    on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures.
  
    2. The Parties shall not maintain and shall not grant any prohibited
    subsidies under Article 3 of the WTO Agreement on Subsidies and
    Countervailing Measures, except for the measures stipulated in Annex
    3 to this Treaty, which is its integral part.
  
    3. The Parties shall refrain from granting any specific subsidies
    under Article 2 of the WTO Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing
    Measures which may cause a serious infringement of interests of
    other Parties and will entail negative consequences stipulated by
    Article 6 of the WTO Agreement on
    Subsidies and Countervailing Measures.
  
    4. Each Party shall ensure transparence of state aid to enterprises
    by means of annual information of the other Parties about the total
    amount and distribution of the aid rendered by the state and
    providing, upon the request of another Party, information about
    rendering of state aid in concrete cases and schemes of granting
    such aid.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Technical Barriers To Trade" article_identifier="35710">In mutual trade the Parties shall apply technical measures,
    including technical regulations, standards and procedures of
    conformity assessment, while being guided by the rules and
    principles of the WTO Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade.
  
    The Parties shall cooperate in the field of standardization,
    metrology, assessment (confirmation) of conformity, accreditation,
    state control (supervision) within the framework of the Interstate
    Council for Standardization, Metrology and Certification under the
    Agreement on Coordinated Policy in the Field of Standardization,
    Metrology and Certification of March 13, 1992.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="35711">In mutual trade the Parties shall be guided by the rules and
    principles of the WTO Agreement on the Application of Sanitary and
    Phytosanitary Measures, as well as international treaties in the
    relevant fields whose participants they are.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Payments" article_identifier="35712">1. The Parties shall not maintain ongoing restrictions and shall not
    establish new restrictions on international transfers and payments
    for the supply of goods within the framework of mutual trade in
    goods, except for the cases stipulated in Article 14 of this Treaty.
  
    2. Nothing in this Treaty shall affect the rights and obligations of
    the Parties ensuing from their membership in the International
    Monetary Fund in accordance with the
    Articles
    of the Agreement on the International Monetary Fund or with the
    provisions of the special currency agreement to be concluded by the
    Parties in accordance with paragraph 3 of this Article.
  
    3. If any state acceding to this Treaty is not a party to the
    Articles
    of the Agreement on the International Monetary Fund, then
    the Parties shall conclude with such state a special currency
    agreement establishing the payments procedure within the mutual
    trade in goods.
  
    If any Party withdraws from the International Monetary Fund, revokes
    or otherwise terminates its obligations under
    Article
    VIII of the
    Agreement
    on the International Monetary Fund, then such Party shall, as soon
    as possible, conclude the said special currency agreement with the
    other Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Restrictions For The Maintenance Of The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="35713">1. In the event of serious violations of the equilibrium of its
    balance of payments and serious external financial difficulties, any
    Party may establish or maintain certain restrictions that are not
    contradictory with the norms of Article XII of GATT 1994 and the
    Understanding on Balance-of-Payment Provisions of GATT 1994, on
    trade in goods with other Parties by applying measures stipulated by
    national legislation leading to restriction of quantity or value of
    goods permitted for import, including introduction of restrictions
    on payments and transfers related to trade in goods with the
    Parties.
  
    Restriction measures on mutual trade in goods, including limitations
    on payments and transfers, for the purposes mentioned in this
    paragraph, may be applied only if payments for delivery of goods
    imported by a Party within the framework of mutual trade, are made
    in currencies which form, as mentioned in paragraph 2 of this
    Article, the currency reserves of the Party applying such
    restrictive measures in mutual trade of goods.
  
    2.Restrictions with respect to import, including payments and
    transfers established, maintained or strengthened by a Party in
    accordance with this Article, shall not be more considerable than it
    is necessary for preventing an inevitable threat of a serious
    reduction of the currency reserves of such Party or for restoring a
    rational rate of growth of currency reserves of this Party.
  
    3. Any Party, having difficulties with balance of payments or
    external financial situation, primarily, to improve the situation,
    uses possibilities that are not affecting trade in goods, in
    particular, attracting external loans and other resources, and
    ensure proper use of such loans or resources.
  
    4. The Parties applying restrictions according to this Article:
  
    shall follow the
    Articles
    of the Agreement on the International Monetary Fund or the
    obligations stipulated in a special currency agreement;
  
    shall not excessively damage commercial, economic and financial
    interests of any other Party;
  
    shall not apply any measures beyond the necessary in connection with
    the state of the balance of payment;
  
    shall not create any discrimination among the Parties unless the
    restrictive measures of trade in goods are aimed at smoothing the
    balance between the currencies; in such case the measures shall not
    go beyond the limits of the necessary discrimination approach;
  
    shall gradually remove measures introduced in accordance with this
    Article - at the extent of mitigation of the circumstances which
    have caused their introduction;
  
    shall not unreasonably impede, in the introduction of certain
    measures in accordance with this Article, the importation of any
    goods in minimum commercial quantities whose exclusion from trade
    turnover would violate the usual channels of trade;
  
    shall not apply any restrictions which would prevent import of
    commercial samples or compliance with regulations on patents,
    trademarks, copyright or similar procedures.
  
    5. The measures whose application is allowed under this Article
    shall not include such measures as introduction or maintenance of
    duties, licensing and quoting, unless due to critical state of the
    balance of payments other measures can not stop sharp worsening of
    the situation with foreign accounts.
  
    6. In the introduction of measures restricting current payments and
    transfers, any Party applying such measures shall immediately inform
    the International Monetary Fund about the restriction of freedom of
    current operations in accordance with the provisions of
    Article
    VIII of the Agreement on the International Monetary Fund and
    shall conduct consultations with the International Monetary Fund for
    improving the situation with the balance of payments or the external
    financial situation, revealing economic problems which could lead to
    worsening of state of balance of payments of such Party, and for
    determining the optimality of the measures being taken.
  
    7. Any restrictions introduced or maintained by a Party in
    accordance with this Article, or any changes in such restrictions,
    shall be subject to urgent notification of the other Parties.
  
    8.If circumstances make it possible, no Party shall introduce any
    restrictions in accordance with this Article prior to consultations
    with the other Parties whose interests may be affected. If any
    restrictions have been introduced before consultations, then
    consultations shall be conducted in the shortest possible time.
  
    Consultations shall be conducted for the purposes of:
  
    assessing the character and scale of difficulties with the balance
    of payments and with the external financial situation of a Party
    introducing restrictive measures on trade in goods in accordance
    with this Article;
  
    assessing foreign-economic and trade situation in which such Party
    has found itself;
  
    identifying possible alternative improving measures which may be
    used.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="35714">Nothing in this Treaty shall be interpreted as impeding the
    application by any Party of measures referred to General Exceptions
    in accordance with Article XX of GATT 1994 with compliance of
    conditions set forth in the mentioned Article of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="35715">With respect to measures aimed at ensuring national security, the
    Parties shall apply the provisions of Article XXI of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Administration Issues" article_identifier="35716">The collection of fees, performance of the formalities connected
    with import and export and the application of the rules of trade are
    carried out in accordance with Articles VIII and X of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Agreements On Customs Unions, Free Trade And Cross-Border Trade" article_identifier="35717">1. This Treaty shall not impede the Parties to participate in
    agreements on customs union, free trade and/or cross-border trade in
    accordance with the WTO rules and, in particular, of Article XXIV of
    GATT 1994.
  
    2. Provisions of this Treaty shall be applied in relations among the
    participants of the Customs Union and the Common Economic Space so
    far as they are not contrary to:
  
    International agreements concluded by them within the framework of
    the Customs Union and the Common Economic Space, as well as,
    decisions, adopted on their basis by the bodies of the Customs
    Union;
  
    bilateral treaties concluded among the members of the Customs Union
    and the Common Economic Space.
  
    3. Participation of the Parties in the international treaties
    mentioned in paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, shall not restrict
    their rights and shall not release from the obligations under this
    Treaty before the other Parties, which are not participants of such
    treaties (Annex 6).
  
    4. In case if participation of one of the Parties in an agreement,
    stipulated by paragraph 1 of this Article, exercises considerable
    negative impact on mutual trade of the participants of this Treaty,
    by the request of any interested Party, the Parties shall conduct
    consultations in order to elaborate and implement measures aimed at
    restoring mutual trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Disputable Issues" article_identifier="35718">1. Parties shall take all necessary measures to fulfill their
    obligations under this Treaty.
  
    2. If one of the Parties considers that the other Party does not
    fulfill its obligations under this Treaty and such nonfulfillment of
    obligations damages or threatens to damage economic interests of the
    former Party, then both Parties shall conduct consultations for the
    purpose of reaching a mutually acceptable elimination of existing
    differences.
  
    If no agreement has been reached, then a dispute may, at the choice
    of the former Party, be submitted for consideration of the CIS
    Economic Court if both Parties are members to the
    Agreement
    on the Status of the Economic Court of the Commonwealth of
    Independent States of July 6, 1992, or to the commission of experts
    in accordance with the dispute settlement procedure stipulated by
    Annex 4 to this Treaty, which is its
    integral part.
  
    3. Disputes on issues which are in this Treaty to be settled by
    referring to the provisions of the WTO agreements, shall be resolved
    among the Parties which are WTO members in the procedure stipulated
    by the relevant WTO agreements. The provisions of this paragraph
    shall not impede the Parties which are WTO members to settle
    disputes in accordance with paragraph 2 of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Amendments And Supplements" article_identifier="35719">By mutual consent of the Parties, amendments and supplements may be
    introduced into this Treaty, which shall be its integral part and
    which shall be formalised by relevant protocols.
  
    Protocols shall enter into force in accordance with the procedure
    stipulated for entry
    into force of this Treaty, except for the protocols
    stipulated in paragraph 15 of Article 2 of this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Reservations" article_identifier="35720">Reservations to this Treaty shall not be permitted.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="35721">1. This Treaty shall enter into force upon the expiry of 30 days
    from the date of receipt by the depositary of a third notification
    on the fulfillment by its signatory Parties of the internal
    procedures necessary for its entry into force.
  
    2.With regard to other Parties that fulfill intrastate procedures
    later, this Treaty shall enter into force upon the expiry of 30 days
    from the date of receipt of relevant documents by the depositary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Correlation With Other International Obligations" article_identifier="35722">1. In relations among the Parties, for which this Treaty has entered
    into force, its provisions shall be applied while international
    treaties, specified in the list (Annex 5 to this Treaty which is its
    integral part), shall become ineffective.
  
    2. The Parties have agreed that from the date of entry into force of
    this Treaty, they will take measures for terminating bilateral
    international treaties existing between them in the manner and
    within the terms stipulated by such treaties, unless the Parties
    have not agreed otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Accession" article_identifier="35723">This Treaty, after its entry into force, shall be open for accession
    of any state by submitting the accession document to the depositary.
  
    For the CIS member state, this Treaty shall enter into force upon
    the expiry of 30 days from the date of receipt of the accession
    document by the depositary.
  
    For a state, which is not a CIS member, this Treaty shall enter into
    force upon the expiry of 30 days from the date of receipt by the
    depositary of the accession document as well as terms, agreed by the
    Parties, for accession to this Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Validity, Termination, Withdrawal" article_identifier="35724">1. This Treaty is concluded for an indefinite period.
  
    Each of the Parties may withdraw from this Treaty by sending to the
    depositary a written notification about such intention not later
    than twelve months before the withdrawal and having settled the
    financial and other obligations which have arisen during the effect
    of this Treaty.
  
    2. For the purposes of resolving the possible disputes and claims,
    including those of material character, the provisions of this Treaty
    shall continue being effective with respect to a Party which has
    terminated its participation up to the complete settlement of all
    the obligations.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4132">
      <article article_identifier="35725">Done in the city of St. Petersburg on October 18, 2011 in one
    original copy in Russian. The original copy is deposited at the
    Executive Committee of the Commonwealth of Independent States, which
    shall send its certified copy to each signatory state to this
    Treaty.
  
    /Signatures/</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
