<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Ukraine - Russian Federation</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>580</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>362</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1993-06-24</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1994-02-21</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2008-08-18</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>1994-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive>2012-09-20</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">UKR</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">UKR</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">762</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/580/TOA/English/FTA Ukraine - Russian Federation_ToA.doc</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/580/AnnexAndRelatedDocs/English/FTA Ukraine - Russian Federation Trade Info Annex.doc</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="577">
      <article article_identifier="27362">Free Trade Agreementbetween and Free Trade Agreementbetween the Government of and the Government
  of the 
  Date of signing: June 24, 1993

  Effective date: February 21, 1994

  Additionally see protocols

  of June 24, 1993,

  of November 14, `1997,

  of October 4, 2001

  The Government of Ukraine and the Government of the , referred to
  hereinafter as the Contracting Parties,

  taking into account the Multilateral Agreement on Coordinating Issues
  of Export Control over Raw Materials, Materials, Equipment,
  Technologies and Services that May be Used for the Development of
  Weapons of Mass Destruction and their Delivery by Missiles of July 26,
  2992,

  striving to develop trade and economic cooperation between Ukraine and
  the Russian Federation on the basis of equality and mutual benefit,
  proceeding from the sovereign right of each state to pursue an
  independent foreign economic policy and ensure the performance of
  corresponding international commitments and the execution of declared
  intentions,

  endeavoring to establish a single market of goods, services, capital
  and labor,

  have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="3250">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="27363">1. The Contracting Parties shall not apply customs duties, taxes and
  charges of equivalent effect on the export and/or import of
  commodities originating from the customs territory of one of the
  Contracting Parties and intended for the customs territory of another
  Contracting Party. Exclusion from the trade regime by a conciliated
  list of commodities shall be formalized by separate documents, which
  are an inseparable part of the present Agreement. The Contracting
  Parties shall conciliate the phased reduction of exclusions stipulated
  in the referred to documents.

  2. For the purposes of the present Agreement and for its validity
  period, the commodities originating from the territory of the
  Contracting Parties shall mean commodities that have been:

  a) completely manufactured on the territory of the Contracting Parties
  and/or

  b) processed on the territory of the Contracting Parties with the use
  of raw materials, materials and components originating from third
  countries and, therefore, changed their affiliation with the
  classification of foreign trade commodities (CFTC) based on the
  Harmonized System of Description and Coding of Commodities and the
  combined tariff-statistical classification of the European Union,
  proceeding from the first four digits and/or

  c) manufactured with the use of the raw materials, materials and
  components specified in subitem “b,” provided their aggregate value
  does not exceed the fixed share of the export price of the sold
  commodities.

  The Contracting Parties shall formalize the detailed rules for
  origination of commodities in a separate document that will be an
  inseparable part of the present Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="27364">The Contracting Parties shall not:

      directly or indirectly impose on commodities, which come within
      the purview of the present Agreement, domestic taxes and charges
      that exceed corresponding taxes or charges imposed on similar
      commodities of domestic manufacture or commodities originating
      from third countries;
    
      apply to the import or export of commodities, which come within
      the purview of the present Agreement, special restrictions and
      requirements, which under similar situations are not applied to
      similar commodities of domestic manufacture or commodities
      originating from third countries;
    
      apply to the warehousing, reloading, storage, movement of
      commodities originating from another Contracting Party, as well as
      payments and remittance of payments other rules than those that
      are applied in similar cases to the commodities originating from
      third countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="27365">1. The Contracting Parties shall undertake not to apply quantitative
  restrictions or equivalent measures to the export and/or import of
  commodities under the present Agreement.

  2. The quantitative restrictions referred to in Item 1 of this Article
  may be set under unilateral procedure within reasonable limits and for
  a clearly defined time only in the following cases:

      acute shortage of a given commodity on the domestic market before
      the stization of the situation on the market;
    
      acute balance of payments deficit before the stization of the
      balance of payments;
    
      import of commodities into the territory of one of the Contracting
      Parties in such large quantities and on such terms that cause or
      threaten to cause damage to domestic producers of similar or
      directly competitive commodities;
    
      in order to take measures provided for in Article 4 of the present
      Agreement.
    
  3. The quantitative restrictions referred to in Item 1 of the Article
  may also be set by mutual consent of the Parties and be included in
  the protocols referred to in Item 1, Article 1 of the present
  Contract.

  4. The Contracting Party that applies quantitative restrictions in
  accordance with Item 2 of this Article shall, prior to the
  introduction of the referred to quantitative restrictions, provide
  necessary information about the reasons of the introduction, forms and
  possible time of application of the referred to restrictions, as well
  as additional information in response to the request of the other
  Contracting Party.

  5. The Contracting Parties shall strive to resolve through
  consultations all the issues that arise from the introduction of the
  quantitative restrictions referred to in Item 2 of this Article.

  6. When selecting the measures in compliance with this Article, the
  Parties shall give priority to those of them that produce the least
  negative impact on the achievement of the purposes of the present
  Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="27366">Each of the Contracting Parties shall not permit the reexport of
  commodities, relative to the export of which the Party from whose
  customs territory these commodities originate applies measures of
  tariff and/or nontariff regulation. The Contracting parties shall
  identify the list of commodities prohibited from reexport, and also
  exchange the lists of commodities to which are applied the measures of
  tariff and nontariff regulation.

  Such commodities may be reexported only by a written consent and on
  the terms set by the authorized agency of the country of origin of the
  said commodities. In case of failure to comply with this provision,
  the Contracting Party whose interests have been affected shall be
  entitled to unilaterally take measures on regulating the export of
  such commodities to the territory of the other Party that permitted
  the unsanctioned reexport, after preliminary notification about the
  intention to introduce such measures and joint consultations. In this
  case the currency earnings from such reexport shall be returned to the
  country of origin of the corresponding commodities.

  For the purposes of this Article, reexport shall mean the removal of
  commodities from the customs territory of one of the Contracting
  Parties by another Contracting Party beyond its customs territory in
  order to export them to a third country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="27367">The Contracting Parties shall on a regular basis exchange principal
  information about customs issues, all available customs statistics
  included. Corresponding authorized agencies of the Contracting Parties
  shall conciliate the procedure for exchanging such information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="27368">1. The Contracting Parties shall strive to approximate the customs
  rates that are used in the trade with third countries, for which
  purpose regular consultations shall be held.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="27369">The Contracting Parties recognize the incompatibility with the
  purposes of the present Agreement of the unfair business practices
  manifested, in particular, in the following:

      agreements between enterprises, decisions made by associations of
      enterprises that aim to hinder or restrict competition or violate
      the terms for it on the territories of the Contracting Parties;
    
      actions by which one or several enterprises use their dominating
      status, restricting competition on the entire and/or a substantial
      part of the territories of the Contracting Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="27370">When effecting measures of tariff and nontariff regulation of
  bilateral economic relations, for the exchange of statistical
  information and for conducting customs procedures, the Contracting
  Parties have agreed to use the uniform nine-digital classification of
  foreign trade commodities (CFTC) based on the Harmonized System of
  Description and Coding of Commodities and the combined
  tariff-statistical classification of the European Union. For their own
  needs the Contracting Parties shall, when necessary, develop the
  commodity classification beyond the nine-digital limit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="27371">The Contracting Parties agree that abidance by the principle of free
  transit is a most important condition for achieving the purposes of
  the present Agreement and an essential element in the process of their
  linkup with the system of international division of labor and
  cooperation.

  In this connection, each Contracting Party shall ensure unhindered
  transit through its territory of commodities originated from the
  customs territory of another Contracting Party and/or third countries
  and intended for the customs territory of the other Contracting Party
  or any third country, and provide to exporters, importers or carriers
  all the available and required facilities and services for transit on
  terms that are not worse than those on which the very same facilities
  and services are provided to their own exporters, importers or
  carriers of any third country.

  The transit tariffs for any type of transport, including tariffs of
  loading and unloading, shall be economically justified and not exceed
  the normal operational expenses, the reasonable profit rates included.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="27372">Nothing in the present Agreement shall hinder any of the Contracting
  Parties to take measures it considers necessary for the protection of
  its vital interests or which are undoubtedly necessary for the
  performance of the international treaties to which it is a party or
  intends to be a party, if these measures concern the following:

      information that affects the interest of national defense;
    
      trade in weapons, ammunition and materiel;
    
      research or production related to the needs of defense;
    
      delivery of material and equipment used in the nuclear industry;
    
      protection of public morals and public order;
    
      protection of industrial or intellectual property;
    
      gold, silver or other precious metals and stones;
    
      protection of the health of people, animals and plants.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="27373">The provisions of the present Agreement shall replace the provisions
  of the agreements concluded earlier between the Contracting Parties
  insofar as the latter are either incompatible with the first or
  identical to them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="27374">The present Agreement does not affect the validity of the agreements
  the Contracting Parties concluded with third countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="27375">Nothing in the present Agreement shall hinder the Contracting Parties
  from maintaining relations with third countries, which does not
  contradict the purposes and terms of the present Agreement, as well as
  with their associations and international organizations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="27376">Disputes between the Contracting Parties as to the interpretation or
  application of provisions of the present Agreement shall be settled
  through negotiations. For achieving agreement, the Parties shall take
  guidance from the provisions of the present Agreement and the
  documents concluded on its basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="27377">For achieving the purposes of the present Agreement and in order to
  work out recommendations for the improvement of trade and economic
  cooperation between the two states, the Contracting Parties have
  agreed to establish a joint Russian-Ukrainian Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="27378">The Protocol on the Exclusion from the Regime of Free Trade shall be
  an inseparable part of the present Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="27379">The present Agreement shall come into force after the exchange of
  notifications about the Contracting Parties’ performance of the
  inter-state procedures, and remain in force until the expiry of twelve
  months from the date when one of the Contracting Parties forwards a
  written notification to the other Contracting Party about the
  intention to terminate the effect of the Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="3251">
      <article article_identifier="27380">Made at the city of on June 24, two valid copies, each in the
  Ukrainian and Russian languages, both texts being of equal force.
On behalf of the Government of
            Leonid KuchmaOn behalf of the Government of the
            Victor Chernomyrdin____________________(signature)___________________(signature)</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
