<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU – Overseas Countries and Territories (OCT)</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>148</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>134</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1970-09-29</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1971-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1970-12-14</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>1971-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">ANT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">ATF</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">NCL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">PYF</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">SPM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">WLF</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AIA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">ANT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">ATF</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">CYM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">FLK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">GRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">IOT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">MSR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="30">MYT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="31">NCL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="32">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="33">PCN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="34">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="35">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="36">PYF</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="37">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="38">SGS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="39">SHN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="40">SPM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="41">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="42">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="43">SWE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="44">TCA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="45">VGB</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="46">WLF</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Caribbean; Europe; Africa; South America; Oceania; North America</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391564401&amp;uri=CELEX:32001D0822</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/ES/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32001D0822&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32001D0822&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391564401&amp;uri=CELEX:32001D0822</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391564401&amp;uri=CELEX:32001D0822</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391564401&amp;uri=CELEX:32001D0822</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1404">
      <article article_identifier="11432">Council Decision

  of 27 November 2001

  on the association of the overseas countries and territories with the
  European Community

  ("Overseas Association Decision")

  (2001/822/EC)

  THE COUNCIL OF THE EUROPEAN UNION,

  Having regard to the Treaty establishing the European Community,
  hereinafter referred to as the Treaty, and in particular Article 187
  thereof,

  Having regard to the proposal from the Commission,

  Whereas:

  (1) Council Decision 91/482/EEC of 25 July 1991 on the association of
  the overseas countries and territories with the European Economic
  Community(1), was applicable until 1 December 2001. Article 240(4)
  thereof states that the Council, acting unanimously on a proposal from
  the Commission, shall establish the provisions to be laid down for the
  subsequent application of the principles set out in Articles 182 to
  186 of the Treaty.

  (2) Declaration No 36 on the overseas countries and territories,
  hereinafter referred to as the "OCTs", annexed to the final
  act of the Conference of the Representatives of the Governments of the
  Member States signed in Amsterdam in 1997, invites the Council, acting
  in accordance with Article 187 of the Treaty, to review the
  association arrangements with the OCTs with a fourfold objective as
  follows:

  - promoting the economic and social development of the OCTs more
  effectively;

  - developing economic relations between the OCTs and the European
  Union;

  - taking greater account of the diversity and specific characteristics
  of the individual OCTs, including aspects relating to freedom of
  establishment;

  - and ensuring that the effectiveness of the financial instrument is
  improved.

  (3) On 11 February 1999 the European Parliament adopted a resolution
  on relations between the OCTs, the ACP States and the outermost
  regions of the European Union(2). Furthermore, on 4 October 2001, it
  adopted a resolution on the proposal from the Commission for a Council
  Decision on the association of the OCTs with the European
  Community(3).

  (4) In its communication of 20 May 1999 entitled "the Status of
  OCTs associated with the EC and options for 'OCT 2000'", the
  Commission examined the features and the development of the OCT-EC
  association since 1957, noted the basic principles and the current
  situation of the association and sketched out alternative policies for
  it for the period beginning 1 March 2000.

  (5) In accordance with Article 10 of Decision 91/482/EEC, the
  competent OCT authorities informed the Commission of the amendments or
  additions they desired in future, notably at a meeting held in the
  context of the partnership on 29 and 30 April 1999, attended by the
  Commission, the four Member States to which the OCTs are linked and
  the 20 OCTs concerned.

  (6) Though not third countries, the OCTs do not form part of the
  single market and must comply with the obligations imposed on third
  countries in respect of trade, notably rules of origin, health and
  plant health standards and safeguard measures.

  (7) As a general rule, when the Council adopts measures under Article
  187 of the Treaty, it must take account both of the principles laid
  down in Part Four of the Treaty and of the other principles of
  Community law. It should also take account of experience acquired in
  the implementation of the trade arrangements of Decision 91/482/EEC.

  (8) These arrangements provide for duty-free access for products
  originating in the OCTs and rules of origin allowing cumulation with
  products originating in the ACP States, which are subject to different
  arrangements, or in the Community. This causes or threatens to cause
  serious disruption to the functioning of certain common market
  organisations under the common agricultural policy, in particular
  those for rice and sugar. Such disruption has on a number of occasions
  led the Commission and the Council to adopt safeguard measures.

  (9) By limiting the scope for use of cumulation of origin, the changes
  made in relation to rice at the mid-term review of the Decision(4)
  have helped maintain access for OCT products to the Community market
  on terms conducive to its balance. This access should be improved in
  respect of the least developed OCTs, but without modifying the overall
  quantity benefiting from cumulation. Given that only two other OCTs
  have ever operated in this sector, the remaining available quantities
  should be allocated to them, in the interest of transparency.

  (10) However, as regards sugar and sugar mixes, the rise in OCT
  exports made from sugar of ACP or Community origin to a heavily
  oversupplied market has resulted in a greater reduction in the quota
  allowed for Community producers and therefore a greater loss of
  guaranteed income for them.

  (11) Moreover, in view of the minimal, low value-added operations that
  currently suffice to obtain the status of a product originating in the
  OCTs in the sugar sector, the contribution of these exports to the
  development of the territories can only be small at best and, without
  a doubt, out of all proportion to the disruption caused to the
  Community sectors concerned.

  (12) For the above reasons, origin rules should therefore be adopted
  which exclude the possibility of ACP/EC-OCT cumulation for sugar when
  only minimal operations are carried out. However, taking into account
  the investments already made in the OCTs on the basis of the rules in
  force since 1991, such exclusion should enter into force in a
  progressive way. Therefore, subject to the adoption of the necessary
  implementing provisions, cumulation should be temporarily allowed to
  continue within progressively decreasing quantitative limits which are
  compatible with the objectives of the Community's common market
  organisation for sugar whilst taking due account of the legitimate
  interests of OCT operators.

  (13) Provision should also be made to ensure that agricultural
  products originating in the Community and which have benefited from an
  export refund cannot be re-imported duty-free into the Community by
  means of the cumulation procedure.

  (14) Furthermore, all the OCT rules of origin should be updated, in
  the interests of the operators and administrations concerned, to take
  account of technical progress and the policy adopted by the Community
  of origin-rule harmonisation. Likewise, the procedure should be
  simplified to enable the necessary technical amendments to the rules
  to be made more easily in future.

  (15) The procedure for the transhipment of goods not originating in
  the OCTs but in free circulation there should be completed and
  clarified, with a view to ensuring a transparent and reliable legal
  framework for operators and administrations. It should also be
  extended to cover certain fishery products of particular importance
  for Greenland and Saint-Pierre-et-Miquelon, subject to the adoption of
  the necessary implementing provisions.

  (16) The general provisions of the Treaty and legislation derived
  thereunder do not automatically apply to the OCTs, barring express
  provisions to the contrary. OCT products imported into the Community
  must nevertheless comply with the Community rules in force.

  (17) Financial assistance to the OCTs should be allocated on the basis
  of uniform, transparent and effective criteria, taking into account
  the needs and performances of the OCTs. Such criteria should include
  in particular the economic and physical dimensions of the OCTs, the
  use made of past allocations, respect for the principles of sound
  financial management, fair fiscal policy, estimated absorption
  capacity, the need for establishing a reserve in order to finance
  non-programmable expenditure and a smooth transition to prevent a
  sudden considerable setback in allocation for New Caledonia, French
  Polynesia and the Netherlands Antilles. In the interests of
  efficiency, simplification and recognition of the management
  capacities of the OCT authorities, the financial resources granted to
  the OCTs should be managed more on the basis of partnership by
  applying procedures based on the rules in force for the structural
  funds.

  (18) For this purpose, the procedures delegate the main responsibility
  for programming and implementing cooperation to the OCTs in
  particular. Cooperation will be conducted predominantly in conformity
  with OCT territorial regulations and will underpin support for the
  monitoring, evaluation and audit of the operations programmed. In
  addition, it is necessary to clarify which Community programmes and
  budget lines are open to the OCTs, as well as the procedures for a
  smooth transition from previous EDFs to the 9th one.

  (19) Global changes, reflected in the continuing process of trade
  liberalisation, broadly implicate the Community, the OCTs' principal
  trading partner, as well as their ACP neighbours and other economic
  partners. In the market access equation, the level of tariffs plays an
  increasingly reduced role while trade in services and trade-related
  areas assume an ever greater importance in the relationship between
  the OCTs and their economic partners. That relationship should
  therefore be fostered, while retaining the broad outline of the
  current trade arrangements, and the conditions for the gradual
  integration of those OCTs who so wish into the regional and global
  economy simplified by helping them to increase their capacity to
  handle all these new areas.

  (20) The measures necessary for the implementation of this Decision
  should be adopted in accordance with Council Decision 1999/468/EC of
  28 June 1999, laying down the procedures for the exercise of
  implementing powers conferred on the Commission(5). However, so far as
  the implementation of the 9th EDF is concerned, the voting and the
  majority should be as laid down in Article 21 of the Internal
  Agreement between the representatives of the Governments of the Member
  States, meeting within the Council, on the financing and
  administration of Community Aid under the Financial Protocol to the
  Partnership Agreement between the African, Caribbean and Pacific
  States and the European Community and its Member States signed in
  Cotonou (Benin) on 23 June 2000 and the allocation of financial
  assistance for the Overseas Countries and Territories to which Part
  Four of the Treaty applies(6), hereinafter the "Internal
  Agreement".

  (21) The OCTs are fragile island environments requiring adequate
  protection, including in respect of waste management. In respect of
  radioactive waste, this is provided under Article 198 of the Euratom
  Treaty and legislation adopted thereunder, except for Greenland, to
  which the Euratom Treaty does not apply. For other waste, it should be
  specified which Community rules are to apply in respect of the OCTs.

  (22) The arrangements for association laid down in this Decision
  should not be applied to Bermuda in accordance with the wishes of the
  Government of Bermuda.

  (23) The Council should produce an innovative response to all the
  above mentioned new factors which is both consistent and tailored to
  the variety of situations. A new status for the association can
  provide such a response,

  HAS DECIDED AS FOLLOWS:

  GENERAL PROVISIONS OF THE ASSOCIATION OF THE OCTs WITH THE COMMUNITY</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1405">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Purpose, Objectives And Principles" article_identifier="11433">1. The association of the OCTs with the Community, hereinafter
  referred to as the "OCT-EC Association", shall have as its
  basis the purpose set out in Article 182 of the Treaty, namely to
  promote the economic and social development of the OCTs and to
  establish close economic relations between them and the Community as a
  whole.

  It shall pursue the objectives laid down in Article 183 of the Treaty
  in accordance with the principles set out in Articles 184 to 188 of
  the Treaty by focusing on the reduction, prevention and, eventually,
  eradication of poverty and on sustainable development and gradual
  integration into the regional and world economies.

  2. The association relates to the OCTs listed in Annex I A.

  3. In accordance with Article 188 of the Treaty, this Decision shall
  apply to Greenland subject to the specific provisions set out in the
  Protocol on the special arrangements for Greenland annexed to the
  Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Basic Elements" article_identifier="11434">1. The OCT-EC association shall be based on the principles of liberty,
  democracy, respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms and the
  rule of law. These principles, on which the Union is founded in
  accordance with Article 6 of the Treaty on European Union, shall be
  common to the Member States and the OCTs linked to them.

  2. There shall be no discrimination based on sex, racial or ethnic
  origin, religion or belief, disability, age or sexual orientation in
  the areas of cooperation referred to in this Decision.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="The Least-Developed Octs" article_identifier="11435">1. The Community shall accord special treatment to the least-developed
  OCTs and to those unable to take advantage of the regional cooperation
  and integration referred to in Article 16.

  2. To respond to such difficulties, development finance cooperation
  shall comprise, inter alia, special treatment when determining the
  volume of financial resources and the conditions attached thereto in
  order to enable the least-developed OCTs to overcome structural and
  other obstacles to their development. It shall pay special attention
  to improving the living conditions of the poorest sections of the
  population in the context of poverty alleviation.

  3. The OCTs considered the least developed for the purposes of this
  Decision are listed in Annex I B. This list shall be amended by
  decision of the Council, acting unanimously on a proposal from the
  Commission, where the economic situation of an OCT undergoes a
  significant and lasting change, necessitating its inclusion in the
  category of least-developed OCTs or where its inclusion in that
  category is no longer warranted.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Actors Of Cooperation In The Octs" chapter_identifier="1406">
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Principles" article_identifier="11436">1. Within the framework of the partnership laid down in Article 7, the
  OCT authorities shall assume primary responsibility for the
  formulation of association and development strategies and their
  implementation through the preparation, together with the Commission
  and the Member State to which the OCT is linked, of Single Programming
  Documents (hereinafter referred to as SPDs) and cooperation
  programmes.

  2. The Community shall recognise that local public and private actors
  play a key role in achieving the objectives laid down in Article 183
  of the Treaty.

  3. In implementing this Decision, the parties shall have as their
  guiding principles transparency, subsidiarity and the need for
  efficiency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="The Different Actors Involved" article_identifier="11437">1. Actors of cooperation in the OCTs shall include:

  - the OCT authorities;

  - the other regional and local authorities within the OCTs;

  - civil society, social, business and trade union associations, public
  service providers and local, national or international
  non-governmental organisations (NGOs).

  The Member States to which the OCTs are linked shall inform the
  Commission within three months of the entry into force of this
  Decision of the national, regional or local authorities referred to in
  the various Articles of the Decision.

  2. The recognition of non-governmental actors shall depend on their
  capacity to meet the needs of the local population, their expertise
  and their having democratic and accountable organisation and
  management.

  3. Non-governmental actors shall be identified by agreement between
  the OCT authorities, the Commission and the Member State to which the
  OCT is linked, taking into account the subject concerned, their
  expertise and field of activity. The process of identification shall
  be conducted in each OCT as part of the process for the preparation of
  cooperation programmes referred to in Article 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Responsibilities Of The Non-Governmental Actors" article_identifier="11438">Non-governmental actors identified pursuant to Article 5(3) may play a
  role in:

  - information and consultation;

  - the preparation and implementation of cooperation programmes;

  - decentralised cooperation in the context of responsibilities
  delegated for the purpose of supporting local development initiatives.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Principles And Procedures Of The Oct-Ec Partnership" chapter_identifier="1407">
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Dialogue And Partnership" article_identifier="11439">1. With the aim of enabling the OCT to take a full part in the
  implementation of the OCT-EC association, with due regard for the way
  that the institutions of the Member States concerned are organised,
  the association shall use a consultation procedure based on the
  provisions referred to below. It shall deal with any issue arising in
  relations between the OCTs and the Community.

  2. A broad-based dialogue should enable the Community, all the OCTs
  and the Member States to which they are linked to consult each other
  on the principles, detailed procedures and results of the association.

  An OCT-EU forum for dialogue, hereinafter referred to as the "OCT
  Forum", shall meet annually to bring together OCT authorities,
  representatives of the Member States and the Commission.

  3. There shall be separate partnerships between the Commission, the
  Member State to which the OCT is linked and each OCT, represented by
  its authorities, to enable the objectives and principles of this
  Decision, in particular those referred to in Articles 4 and 19 to be
  put into practice. This trilateral consultation shall hereinafter be
  referred to as the "partnership".

  Partnership working parties, acting in an advisory capacity, shall be
  set up for each OCT. Their membership shall comprise the
  abovementioned three partners. These working parties may be convened
  at the request of the Commission, of a Member State or of an OCT. At
  the request of one of the partners, several partnership working
  parties may hold joint meetings to consider subjects of common
  interest or the regional aspects of the association.

  4. This consultation shall be conducted in full compliance with the
  respective institutional, legal and financial powers of each of the
  three partners.

  The Commission shall chair the working parties and the OCT Forum and
  provide their secretariat.

  A representative of the European Investment Bank, hereinafter referred
  to as the EIB, shall be present at meetings when matters concerning it
  are on the agenda.

  5. The opinions of the working parties and the OCT Forum shall, where
  appropriate, be the subject of Commission decisions, within the limits
  of its powers, or of proposals from the Commission to the Council with
  a view to implementation of new elements of the OCT-EC association or
  its amendment on the basis of Article 187 of the Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Acp-Eu Joint Parliamentary Assembly" article_identifier="11440">The OCT authorities shall be informed of the agenda, resolutions and
  recommendations of the ACP-EU Joint Parliamentary Assembly.

  Member States and the Commission shall support any request by OCT
  authorities to participate as observers at the plenary sessions of the
  ACP-EU Joint Parliamentary Assembly, subject to the Assembly's own
  rules of procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Management" article_identifier="11441">Day-to-day management of this Decision shall be conducted by the
  Commission and the OCT authorities and, should the need arise, by the
  Member State to which the OCT is linked, in accordance with the
  institutional, legal and financial powers of each of the partners,
  notably as regards development finance cooperation and cooperation in
  the area of trade and services.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART TWO" name="The Areas Of Oct-Ec Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1408">
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Areas Of Cooperation" article_identifier="11442">The Community shall contribute to cooperation in those areas in the
  OCTs listed in this Title in accordance with the priorities
  established in the development strategies for each OCT or, where
  appropriate, in the form of regional measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Productive Sectors" article_identifier="11443">Cooperation shall support sectoral policies and strategies that
  facilitate access to productive activities and resources, in
  particular:

  (a) Agriculture: agricultural policy and institution building,
  diversification, irrigation, seed multiplication, crop protection
  measures, fertiliser production, equipment, agro-processing, livestock
  and cattle breeding, animal husbandry, extension and research;
  marketing; storage and transportation; food security; agricultural
  credit; land settlement and reform, land use and registration policy,
  technology transfer, irrigation and drainage infrastructure, other
  support services.

  (b) Forestry: forestry policy and institution building, including use
  of trees to conserve the environment in erosion and desertification
  control; afforestation; forest management, including the rational
  utilisation and management of timber exports; issues relating to
  tropical rain-forests; research and training.

  (c) Fisheries: fishing policy and institution building, fish stock
  protection and rational management of fish stocks; fish farming and
  artisanal fisheries; fishery transport; cold storage and fish
  marketing and preservation.

  (d) Rural development: rural policy and institution building,
  integrated rural development projects/programmes; assistance and
  projects targeted at people, production and marketing in rural areas;
  rural infrastructure.

  (e) Industry: sectoral policy and institution building; craft
  industries; agro-industries and other manufacturing sectors, transport
  equipment industry; technological research and development; quality
  control; development and expansion of SMEs and micro-enterprises.

  (f) Mining: sectoral policy and institution building, technological
  research and development; small-scale mining, etc.

  (g) Energy: energy policy and institution building; power generation
  (non-renewable and renewable); efficient use of energy resources;
  energy research and training; encouraging private sector involvement
  in power generation and distribution.

  (h) Transport: transport policy and institution building; transport by
  road, rail, air, sea or inland waterway and storage facilities.

  (i) Communication: communication policy and institution building;
  telecommunications and media.

  (j) Water: water policy and institution building; protecting water
  resources, waste management, water supplies in rural and urban areas
  for domestic, industrial or agricultural purposes; storage,
  distribution and management of water resources.

  (k) Banking, finance and business services: financial sector policy
  and institution building, business services; privatisation, equity
  participation and marketing; support to trade, commerce and business
  associations (including export promotion agencies); financial and
  banking institutions.

  (l) Technology development and application, research: policy and
  institution building; concerted action at local, national and/or
  regional level for the promotion of science and technology activities
  and their application to production and promotion of computer literacy
  in the public and private sectors, scientific programmes and equipment
  for research.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Trade Development" article_identifier="11444">1. The Community shall implement measures for the development of trade
  at all stages up to final distribution of the product.

  The object is to ensure that the OCTs derive the maximum benefit from
  the provisions of his Decision and may participate under the most
  favourable conditions in the Community, domestic, sub-regional,
  regional and international markets by diversifying the range and
  increasing the value and the volume of OCT trade in goods and
  services.

  2. In addition to developing trade between the OCTs and the Community,
  particular attention shall be given to operations designed to increase
  the OCTs' self-reliance and improve regional cooperation in trade and
  services.

  3. Within the instruments provided for in this Decision and in
  accordance with the provisions set out in relation thereto, operations
  shall be undertaken at the request of the OCT authorities,
  particularly in the following areas:

  (a) support for the definition of appropriate macroeconomic policies
  necessary for trade development;

  (b) support for the creation or reform of appropriate legal and
  regulatory frameworks as well as for the reform of administrative
  procedures;

  (c) the establishment of coherent trade strategies;

  (d) support for OCTs in developing their internal capacities,
  information systems and awareness of the role and importance of trade
  in economic development;

  (e) support for strengthening the infrastructure related to trade and
  in particular support for the OCTs' efforts to develop and improve
  supportive service infrastructure, including transport and storage
  facilities, in order to ensure their effective participation in the
  distribution of goods and services and in order to enhance the flow of
  exports from the OCTs;

  (f) development of human resources and professional skills in the
  field of trade and services, in particular in the processing,
  marketing, distribution and transport sectors for the Community,
  regional and international markets;

  (g) support to private sector development and, in particular, to SMEs
  for product identification and development, market outlets and
  export-oriented joint ventures;

  (h) support for OCT actions aimed at encouraging and attracting
  private investment and joint venture operations;

  (i) the establishment, adaptation and strengthening of organisations
  in the OCTs dealing with the development of trade and services,
  particular attention being paid to the special needs of organisations
  in the least-developed OCTs;

  (j) support for OCTs aiming to improve the quality of their products,
  adapt them to market requirements and diversify their outlets;

  (k) support for OCT efforts to penetrate third country markets more
  effectively;

  (l) market development measures including increasing contacts and
  exchange of information between economic operators in OCTs, ACP
  States, the Member States and in third countries;

  (m) support for OCTs in the application of modern marketing techniques
  in production-oriented sectors and programmes, in particular in areas
  such as rural development and agriculture;

  (n) the establishment and development of insurance and credit
  institutions in the field of trade development.

  4. Support for OCTs' participation in trade fairs, exhibitions and
  trade missions shall be carried out only where such events form an
  integral part of overall trade and market development programmes.

  5. Participation of the least-developed OCTs in various trade
  activities shall be encouraged by special provisions, inter alia, the
  payment of travel expenses of personnel and costs of transporting
  exhibits, on the occasion of their participation in local, regional
  and third-country fairs, exhibitions or trade missions, including the
  cost of the temporary construction and/or renting of exhibition booths
  and stalls. The least-developed OCTs shall be granted special aid to
  assist in the preparation and/or purchase of promotional materials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Trade In Services" article_identifier="11445">1. The Community agrees to develop and finance infrastructure and
  human resources as regards trade in services in accordance with the
  priorities established under the development strategies for each OCT.

  2. The Community shall contribute to the development and promotion of
  cost-effective and efficient maritime transport services in the OCTs,
  by:

  (a) promoting the efficient shipment of cargo at economically and
  commercially meaningful rates;

  (b) implementing good policies and competition rules;

  (c) facilitating greater OCT participation in international shipping
  services;

  (d) encouraging regional programmes of maritime transport and trade
  development;

  (e) increasing local private sector involvement in shipping
  activities.

  The Community and the OCTs undertake to promote shipping safety,
  security of crews and the prevention of pollution.

  3. The Community shall step up cooperation with the OCTs so as to
  ensure regular improvement and growth in air traffic.

  This shall involve:

  (a) examining all means of reforming and modernising the OCT air
  transport industries;

  (b) promoting their commercial viability and competitiveness;

  (c) encouraging higher levels of private sector investment and
  participation and a greater exchange of knowledge and good business
  practice;

  (d) providing passengers and exporters in all OCTs with access to
  global air transport networks.

  4. Safety must be ensured in the air transport sector and the relevant
  international standards introduced and implemented.

  To that end, the Community shall assist the OCTs in:

  (a) implementing air navigation safety systems, including the
  Communications, Navigation and Surveillance/Air Traffic Management
  (CNS/ATM) system;

  (b) implementing airport security and strengthening the capacity of
  civil aviation authorities to manage all aspects of operational
  security placed under their control;

  (c) developing infrastructures and human resources;

  (d) ensuring that any measures taken in this field are based on advice
  from the relevant international organisations and that they will be
  effective and sustainable in the long term.

  5. Proper attention must be paid to minimising the environmental
  impact of air transport, in particular by means of appropriate
  environmental impact studies.

  6. In many aspects of air transport, regional solutions may offer
  scope for greater cost effectiveness and economies of scale. To that
  end, the Community undertakes to support and encourage actions on a
  regional level where appropriate.

  7. Since telecommunication and active participation in the information
  society are prerequisites for the successful integration of the OCTs
  into the world economy, the Community and the OCTs reconfirm their
  respective commitments under existing multilateral agreements, in
  particular the World Trade Organisation (WTO) Agreement on Basic
  Telecommunications.

  8. The Community shall support the efforts of the OCTs to increase
  their capacity in the field of trade in services. Cooperation shall
  cover, inter alia, the following areas:

  (a) promoting consultations between competent telecommunications
  bodies in the OCTs and the Community with a view to encouraging
  development of a competitive telecommunications environment bringing
  rates closer to costs;

  (b) establishment of a dialogue on different aspects of the
  information society, including regulatory aspects and communications
  policy;

  (c) information exchanges and possible technical assistance on
  regulation, standardisation, conformity testing and certification of
  information and communications technologies and the use of
  frequencies;

  (d) dissemination of new information and communications technologies
  and the development of new facilities, particularly in relation to
  interconnection of networks and interoperability of applications;

  (e) promotion and implementation of joint research in the field of new
  technologies related to the information society;

  (f) design and implementation of programmes and policies to raise the
  awareness of the economic and social benefits deriving from the
  information society.

  9. Cooperation shall, in particular, be directed towards greater
  complementarity and harmonisation of communication systems at local,
  national, regional, inter-regional and international level and their
  adaptation to new technologies.

  10. The Community shall support measures and operations to develop and
  support sustainable tourism. These measures shall be implemented at
  all levels, from the identification of the tourist product to the
  marketing and promotion stage.

  The aim shall be to support the efforts of the authorities of the OCT
  to derive maximum benefit from local, regional and international
  tourism in view of tourism's impact on economic development and to
  stimulate private financial flows from the Community and other sources
  into the development of tourism in the OCTs. Particular attention
  shall be given to the need to integrate tourism into the social,
  cultural and economic life of the people, as well as to respect for
  the environment.

  Specific tourism development measures shall be aimed at the
  definition, adaptation and development of appropriate policies at
  local, regional, sub-regional and international levels. Tourism
  development programmes and projects shall be based on these policies
  on the basis of the following four components:

  (a) human resource and institutional development, inter alia:

  - professional management development in specific skills and
  continuous training at appropriate levels in the private and public
  sectors to ensure adequate planning and development;

  - establishment and strengthening of tourism promotion centres;

  - education and training for specific segments of the population and
  public/private organisations active in the tourism sector, including
  personnel involved in sectors that support tourism;

  - inter-OCT and OCT-ACP cooperation and exchanges in the fields of
  training, technical assistance and the development of institutions.

  (b) the development of products including, inter alia:

  - identification of the tourism product, development of
  non-traditional and new tourism products, adaptation of existing
  products including the preservation and development of cultural
  heritage, ecological and environmental aspects, management, protection
  and conservation of flora and fauna, historical, social and other
  natural assets, development of ancillary services;

  - promotion of private investment in the OCTs' tourist industries,
  including the creation of joint ventures;

  - production of crafts of a cultural nature for the tourist market.

  (c) market development including, inter alia:

  - assistance for the definition and execution of objectives and market
  development plans at local, sub-regional, regional and international
  levels;

  - support for the OCTs' efforts to gain access to services for the
  tourist industry such as central reservation systems and air traffic
  control and security systems;

  - marketing and promotional measures and materials in the framework of
  integrated market development plans and programmes with a view to
  improved market penetration, aimed at the main generators of tourism
  flows in traditional and non-traditional markets as well as specific
  activities such as participation at specialised trade events, such as
  fairs, production of quality literature, films and marketing aids;

  (d) research and information including, inter alia:

  - improving tourism information and collecting, analysing,
  disseminating and utilising statistical data;

  - assessment of the socio-economic impact of tourism on the economies
  of the OCT with particular emphasis on the development of linkages to
  other sectors in the OCT and the surrounding regions, such as food
  production, construction, technology and management.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Trade-Related Areas" article_identifier="11446">1. The Community shall help reinforce, within the development
  strategies of each OCT, the capacity of the OCTs to handle all areas
  related to trade, including where necessary improving and supporting
  the institutional framework.

  2. The Community shall cooperate with the OCTs in the introduction of
  the general principles on protection and promotion of investments.

  3. The Community shall also help to reinforce cooperation with the
  OCTs with a view to formulating and supporting effective competition
  policies with the appropriate competition agencies that progressively
  ensure the efficient enforcement of the competition rules by both
  private and state enterprises. Cooperation in this area shall, in
  particular, include assistance in the drafting of an appropriate legal
  framework and its administrative enforcement with particular reference
  to the least developed OCTs.

  4. The Community shall continue to foster cooperation with the OCTs
  and extend it, in particular, to the following areas:

  (a) the preparation of laws and regulations for the protection and
  enforcement of intellectual property rights, the prevention of the
  abuse of such rights by rightholders and the infringement of such
  rights by competitors, the establishment and reinforcement of local,
  national and regional offices and other agencies including support for
  regional intellectual property organisations involved in enforcement
  and protection, including the training of personnel;

  (b) the conclusion of agreements aimed at protecting trademarks and
  geographical indications for products of particular interest.

  5. The Community shall assist the OCTs in their efforts with regard to
  standardisation and certification aimed at promoting compatible
  systems between the Community and the OCTs. Cooperation shall comprise
  the following in particular:

  (a) measures to promote greater use of international technical
  regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures, including
  sector-specific measures, in accordance with the level of economic
  development of the OCTs;

  (b) cooperation in the area of quality management and assurance in
  selected sectors of importance to the OCTs;

  (c) support for OCT capacity building initiatives in the fields of
  conformity assessment, metrology and standardisation;

  (d) developing links between OCT and European standardisation,
  conformity assessment and certification institutions.

  6. The Community shall help strengthen cooperation with the OCTs with
  regard to human, animal and plant health measures with a view to
  building public and private sector capacity in this area.

  7. Bearing in mind the Rio Principles and with a view to reinforcing
  the mutual supportiveness of trade and environment policies, the
  Community shall enhance cooperation with the OCTs. The aim of
  cooperation shall in particular be to:

  (a) establish coherent local, national, regional and international
  policies;

  (b) reinforce quality controls of goods and services related to the
  environment;

  (c) improve environment-friendly production methods in relevant
  sectors.

  8. The Community shall cooperate with the OCTs in relation to labour
  standards. Cooperation in this area shall mainly consist of:

  (a) exchanges of information on respective labour laws and
  regulations;

  (b) assistance in the formulation of labour legislation and
  strengthening of existing legislation;

  (c) educational and awareness-raising programmes aimed at eliminating
  child labour;

  (d) enforcement of labour legislation and regulations.

  9. The Community shall cooperate with the OCTs in the area of consumer
  policy and consumer health protection by:

  (a) improving institutional and technical capacity in this area;

  (b) establishing rapid-alert systems of mutual information on
  dangerous products;

  (c) exchanging information and experiences on the establishment and
  operation of post-market surveillance of products and product safety;

  (d) improving information provided to consumers on prices,
  characteristics of products and services offered;

  (e) encouraging the development of private consumer associations and
  contacts between consumer-interest representatives;

  (f) improving compatibility of consumer policies and systems;

  (g) informing on the entry into force of legislation and promoting
  cooperation in investigating harmful or unfair business practices;

  (h) implementing exports prohibitions on the trade of goods and
  services the marketing of which has been prohibited in their country
  of production.

  10. The Community shall support the efforts deployed by the OCT public
  and private actors in the field of information technology and
  telecommunications to:

  (a) modernise telecommunications infrastructure, data transmission
  services, remote processing applications and telematics application
  projects (TAP);

  (b) develop and improve the services and the human capacity needed for
  achieving the information society, and integrate those services in the
  best possible way in a regional context;

  (c) improve awareness of economic opportunities and exchanges of
  experience and of know-how;

  (d) provide better information to the users of those resources;

  (e) exploit the potential of this sector in an optimum and sustainable
  manner;

  (f) develop the use of communications and information technology in
  the field of education, including distance learning;

  (g) increase electronic commerce and economic cooperation;

  (h) improve and modernise health networks, through the development of
  links between hospitals, the use of remote diagnosis and the creation
  of joint databases;

  (i) develop multimedia access to cultural and tourist resources;

  (j) improve and increase the use of information and communications
  technology in industry and for innovation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Social Sectors" article_identifier="11447">The Community shall contribute, within the development strategies of
  each OCT, to human and social development measures. Cooperation could
  in particular support programmes in the following sectors:

  (a) Education policy and institution building (buildings and
  materials); language and teacher training; primary education;
  secondary education and vocational training; higher education
  (including sector-specific education activities, e.g. agricultural
  training).

  In education, the focus should be on widening access to and improving
  the quality of basic education by constructing more schools,
  rehabilitating existing classrooms and providing educational
  materials, teacher training, and bursaries for poor students;

  (b) Health sector reform activities, health policy and institution
  building; medical education, training and research, health
  infrastructure; HIV/AIDS.

  In the health sector, projects should help to provide primary and
  preventive care services, particularly family planning and child and
  maternal health services;

  (c) Population policy and family planning; mother and child care,
  including support for projects on the nurturing and development of the
  next generation.

  (d) Increasing the efficiency of policies to prevent the production,
  distribution and trafficking of all kinds of drugs, narcotics and
  psychotropic substances, preventing and reducing drug abuse, taking
  into account work done in this context by international bodies.

  Cooperation shall comprise the following:

  (i) training, education, health promotion and rehabilitation of
  addicts, including projects for the reintegration of addicts into work
  and social environments;

  (ii) measures to encourage alternative economic opportunities, for
  example programmes for the alternative development of areas used for
  the illicit production of narcotic plants, linked to effective
  enforcement measures;

  (iii) technical, financial and administrative assistance relating to
  the monitoring of precursors trade, and the establishment of standards
  equivalent to those adopted by the Community and international
  authorities concerned;

  (iv) technical, financial and administrative assistance relating to
  the prevention, treatment and reduction of drug abuse;

  (v) technical assistance and training, and the establishment of
  standards to prevent money laundering equivalent to those adopted by
  the Community and other international bodies, in particular the
  Financial Action Task Force on Money Laudering;

  (vi) exchange of relevant information for the implementation of points
  (a) to (d).

  (e) Water policy and institution building; water resources protection;
  waste management (water for agriculture or energy will be covered
  under the relevant sector).

  In the water supply and sanitation sector, the aim shall be to provide
  services in under-served areas. Funding that supports increasing
  access to drinking water supply and sanitation services contributes
  directly to human resources development by improving the state of
  health, and thus increasing the productivity, of people who do not
  already have access to these services; the continuing need to extend
  basic services in water, sanitation, and transport to both urban and
  rural populations must be addressed in environmentally sustainable
  ways.

  (f) The Community shall cooperate with the OCTs in the conservation,
  sustainable use and management of their biological diversity taking
  into account the Community Action Plan on biological diversity.

  Cooperation in this area may, in particular, extend to:

  (i) supporting the elaboration, updating and implementation of
  national biodiversity strategies and action plans;

  (ii) facilitating the establishment of local, regional and
  sub-regional mechanisms for the exchange of information and the
  monitoring and assessment of progress in the implementation of the
  Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD)(7);

  (iii) developing and maintaining up-to-date databases on OCT
  biological diversitys;

  (iv) implementing appropriate measures relating to the access to
  genetic resources;

  (v) promoting the conclusion of agreements with the private sector for
  the use of the country's genetic resources, so that local communities
  may effectively benefit from the economic revenue derived from such
  agreements and so that the use of genetic resources does not harm the
  protection and conservation of the biodiversity;

  (vi) assisting the OCTs to participate actively in the policy-making
  process and negotiations under the CBD.

  (g) Housing and integrated urban development projects and programmes.

  In urban development, efforts shall focus on building or
  rehabilitating roads and other basic infrastructure, including
  low-income housing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Regional Cooperation And Integration" article_identifier="11448">Cooperation shall ensure that effective aid is provided in order to
  achieve the objectives and priorities established by the competent OCT
  authorities in the framework of regional and sub-regional cooperation
  and integration:

  1. Regional cooperation shall cover operations agreed on between:

  (a) two or more OCTs;

  (b) one or more OCTs and one or more neighbouring ACP or non-ACP
  States;

  (c) one or more OCTs and one or more ACP States or one or more of the
  most remote regions referred to in Article 299(2) of the Treaty
  (Guadeloupe, Guyana, Martinique, Réunion, the Canary Islands, Azores
  and Madeira);

  (d) two or more regional bodies of which OCTs are members;

  (e) one or more OCTs and regional bodies of which OCTs, ACP States or
  one or more of the most remote regions are members.

  2. The objectives of cooperation in this context shall be to:

  (a) foster the gradual integration of the OCTs into the world economy;

  (b) accelerate economic cooperation and development within the regions
  of the OCT and between them and the regions of the ACP States;

  (c) promote the free movement of persons, goods, services, capital,
  labour and technology;

  (d) accelerate economic diversification and the coordination and
  harmonisation of regional and sub-regional cooperation policies;

  (e) promote and foster inter-OCT and intra-OCT trade as well as trade
  with the most remote regions, ACP States or other third countries.

  3. In the context of regional integration, the aim of cooperation
  shall be to:

  (a) build and enhance the capacity of regional cooperation and
  integration organisations and institutions to promote regional
  cooperation and integration;

  (b) encourage the least developed OCTs to take part in the development
  of regional markets and benefit therefrom;

  (c) implement sectoral reform policies at regional level;

  (d) liberalise trade and payments;

  (e) stimulate cross-border foreign and domestic investment and other
  regional or sub-regional economic integration initiatives;

  (f) take account of the net transitional cost of regional integration
  on budget revenue and balance of payments.

  4. Cooperation shall, in the area of regional cooperation, cover a
  wide variety of functional and thematic fields which specifically
  address common problems and take advantage of economies of scale,
  including:

  (a) infrastructure, particularly transport and communications
  infrastructure and related safety problems, energy;

  (b) the environment, water resource management;

  (c) health, education and training;

  (d) research and scientific and technical cooperation;

  (e) regional disaster preparedness and alleviation initiatives;

  (f) other areas, e.g. arms controls, drugs, organised crime, money
  laundering, fraud and corruption.

  5. Cooperation shall also support inter-regional, inter-OCT and
  inter-ACP cooperation schemes and initiatives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Cultural And Social Cooperation" article_identifier="11449">Cooperation shall contribute to the self-reliant development of the
  OCTs, this being a process centred on people themselves and rooted in
  each people's culture. The human and cultural dimension shall embrace
  all areas and be reflected in all development projects and programmes.
  Cooperation shall back up the policies and measures adopted by the
  competent OCT authorities to enhance their human resources, increase
  their own creative capacities and promote their cultural identities.
  It shall foster participation by the population in the process of
  development.

  Cultural and social cooperation shall be expressed through:

  - the taking into account of the cultural and social dimension;

  - promotion of cultural identities and intercultural dialogue, with
  particular reference to preserving the cultural heritage, the
  production and dissemination of cultural products, cultural events and
  information and communication;

  - operations to enhance human resources, notably covering education
  and training, scientific and technical cooperation, the role of women
  in development, health and combating drug abuse, population and
  demography.

  INSTRUMENTS OF OCT-EC COOPERATION

  DEVELOPMENT FINANCE COOPERATION</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1409">
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Objectives" article_identifier="11450">The objective of development finance cooperation shall be, through the
  provision of adequate financial resources and appropriate technical
  assistance, to:

  (a) support and promote the OCTs' own efforts to achieve sustainable
  social, cultural and economic development on the basis of mutual
  interest and in a spirit of interdependence;

  (b) help raise the standard of living of the peoples of the OCTs;

  (c) promote measures likely to mobilise the capacity for initiative of
  communities, groups, associations and individuals and their
  participation in the design and implementation of development
  programmes;

  (d) contribute to the fullest participation of the population in the
  benefits of development in the interests of alleviating poverty;

  (e) contribute to the development of the capacity of the OCTs to
  innovate, adapt and transform local technologies and to master
  appropriate new technologies;

  (f) support the efforts of the OCTs to achieve economic
  diversification, inter alia by contributing to sustainable
  exploration, conservation, processing and exploitation of their
  natural resources;

  (g) provide support for and promote the optimal development of human
  resources in the OCTs;

  (h) facilitate an increase in the financial flows to the OCTs that
  meet their evolving needs and support the efforts of the OCTs to
  harmonise international cooperation for their development through
  cofinancing of operations with other financing agencies or third
  parties;

  (i) promote direct private investment in the OCTs, support the
  development of a healthy, prosperous and dynamic OCT private sector
  and encourage local, national and foreign private investment flows
  into the productive sectors in the OCTs;

  (j) encourage inter-OCT and OCT-ACP regional cooperation, solidarity
  and integration;

  (k) permit the establishment of more balanced economic and social
  relations and better understanding between the OCTs, ACP States,
  Member States and the rest of the world, with a view to assisting the
  integration of the OCTs into the world economy;

  (l) enable OCTs faced with serious economic and social difficulties of
  an exceptional nature resulting from natural disasters or
  extraordinary circumstances having comparable effects to benefit from
  emergency assistance;

  (m) help the least-developed OCTs to overcome the specific obstacles
  which hamper their development efforts.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Principles" article_identifier="11451">1. Development finance cooperation shall be based on partnership,
  complementarity and subsidiarity and shall:

  (a) be implemented, in accordance with the association and development
  strategies adopted pursuant to Article 4, with due regard to the OCTs
  respective geographical, social and cultural characteristics, as well
  as their specific potential;

  (b) ensure that resource flows are accorded on a predictable and
  regular basis;

  (c) be flexible and tailored to the situation in each OCT.

  2. Member States shall cooperate with the Commission to ensure sound
  financial management in the use of Community funds.

  3. Following a partnership approach, Community activities shall be
  decided in close consultation between the Commission, the OCT
  authorities concerned and the Member State to which it is linked. Such
  partnership shall be conducted in full compliance with the respective
  institutional, legal and financial powers of each of the partners.

  4. Without prejudice to the second subparagraph of Article 25(1),
  Community and Member States contributions shall be complementary.

  5. In accordance with the principle of subsidiarity, the authorities
  of the OCT concerned shall be responsible for implementing operations
  without prejudice to the powers of the Commission designed to ensure
  sound financial management in the use of Community funds.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Single Programming Documents" article_identifier="11452">1. Pursuant to Article 4, the OCT authorities, the Commission and the
  Member State to which the OCT is linked, acting in partnership, shall
  lay down the strategy and the priority aims on which the SPD is to be
  based.

  2. The OCT authorities shall be responsible for:

  (a) establishing their priorities on which the cooperation strategy
  should be based;

  (b) in the framework of sectoral planning, identifying projects and
  programmes and establishing back-up measures to ensure the
  sustainability and viability of the proposed schemes;

  (c) preparing project and programme dossiers;

  (d) preparing, negotiating and concluding contracts;

  (e) implementing and managing projects and programmes;

  (f) maintaining projects and programmes and ensuring their
  sustainability.

  3. The relevant authorities of the OCTs and the Commission shall be
  jointly responsible for:

  (a) adopting the SPD;

  (b) ensuring equality of conditions for participation in invitations
  to tender and contracts;

  (c) monitoring and evaluating the effects and results of projects and
  programmes;

  (d) ensuring the proper, prompt and efficient execution of projects
  and programmes.

  4. The Commission shall be responsible for taking the financing
  decision on the overall allocation corresponding to the SPD, in
  accordance with the procedure referred to in Article 24.

  5. Unless otherwise provided in this Decision, all decisions requiring
  the approval of a party to the association shall be approved, or be
  deemed approved, within six months of notification by the other party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Scope Of Financing" article_identifier="11453">Within the framework of the strategy and priorities established by the
  OCT concerned at local or regional level, financial support may be
  given to operations helping to achieve the objectives set out in this
  Decision.

  The following activities shall fall within its scope:

  (a) sectoral policies and reforms as well as projects that are in
  coherence with them;

  (b) institutional development, capacity building and integration of
  environmental aspects;

  (c) technical cooperation programmes;

  (d) humanitarian aid and emergency relief operations;

  (e) additional support in the event of fluctuations in export earnings
  from exports of goods and services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Eligibility For Financing" article_identifier="11454">1. The following entities or bodies shall be eligible for financial
  support provided under this Decision:

  (a) OCTs;

  (b) regional or inter-State bodies to which one or more OCTs belong
  and which are authorised by their relevant authorities;

  (c) joint bodies set up by the Community and the OCTs to pursue
  certain specific objectives.

  2. Subject to the agreement of the authorities of OCTs concerned, the
  following shall also be eligible for support:

  (a) local, national and/or regional public or semi-public agencies,
  departments or local authorities of the OCTs and in particular their
  financial institutions and development banks;

  (b) companies and firms of the OCTs and of regional groups;

  (c) enterprises of a Member State, so as to enable them, in addition
  to their own contribution, to undertake productive projects in the
  territory of an OCT;

  (d) OCT or Community financial intermediaries promoting and financing
  private investments in the OCTs;

  (e) actors of decentralised cooperation and other non-State actors
  from OCTs and from the Community, to enable them to undertake
  economic, cultural, social and educational projects and programmes in
  the OCTs in the framework of decentralised cooperation, as referred to
  in Article 29.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Programming And Implementation" article_identifier="11455">The Commission shall adopt the implementing provisions for this Part
  of the Decision and for Annexes II A to D within 12 months of its
  entry into force, in accordance with the procedure laid down in
  Article 24 and in cooperation with the OCTs in accordance with Article
  7.

  It shall support the full utilisation by the OCTs of the instruments
  laid down in this Decision, in particular the trade and financial
  provisions, by providing the relevant guidelines and information
  within 12 months of its entry into force.

  The provisions shall include in particular:

  (a) the procedure for preparing the SPD and its essential elements;

  (b) the procedures and criteria for the follow-up, audit, ex-ante,
  mid-term and ex-post evaluation, review and implementation of the SPD,
  including those in relation to the Commission's participation in these
  activities;

  (c) the preparation of periodical or other reports;

  (d) detailed rules for the financial corrections referred to in
  Article 32.

  The financial and accounting procedures shall be laid down in the 9th
  EDF Financial Regulation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="The Edf-Oct Committee" article_identifier="11456">1. The Commission shall, where appropriate, be assisted by the
  Committee created by the Internal Agreement, hereinafter referred to
  in this Article as "the Committee".

  2. When exercising the powers conferred on it by this Decision, the
  Committee shall be known as the "EDF-OCT Committee". The
  internal rules of procedure of the Committee created by the Internal
  Agreement shall apply to the EDF-OCT Committee.

  3. The Committee shall focus its work on the substantive issues of
  development cooperation at OCT and regional level. In the interests of
  coherence, coordination and complementarity, it shall monitor the
  implementation of the SPDs.

  4. The Committee shall give its opinion on:

  (a) draft SPDs and any amendments to them;

  (b) the implementing provisions for this Part of the Decision and for
  Annexes II A to D.

  5. The representative of the Commission shall submit to the Committee
  a draft of the measures to be taken. The Committee shall deliver its
  opinion on the draft within a time limit laid down by the chairman.
  The opinion shall be delivered by the majority laid down in Article
  21(4) of the Internal Agreement. The votes of the representatives of
  the Member States within the Committee shall be weighted in the manner
  set out in paragraph 3 of that Article. The chairman shall not vote.

  6. The Commission shall adopt the measures, which shall apply
  immediately. However, if the measures are not in accordance with the
  opinion of the Committee they shall be communicated by the Commission
  to the Council forthwith. In that event, the Commission may defer
  application of the measures which it has decided on for a period of
  not more than three months from the date of such communication.

  7. The Council, acting by the majority and in accordance with the
  weighting referred to in paragraph 5, may take a different decision
  within the period provided for in paragraph 6.

  8. The Commission shall inform the Committee of the follow-up,
  evaluation and audit of SPDs.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Resources Made Available To The Octs" chapter_identifier="1410">
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Financial Assistance" article_identifier="11457">1. The overall amount of Community financial assistance for the
  purposes of Chapter 1, its allocation, financing terms and
  arrangements and of the use of the assistance for the period from 2000
  to 2007 can be found in Annexes II A to D and in Chapter 3, without
  prejudice to the provisions to be adopted by the Commission as laid
  down in Article 24.

  Financial assistance under this Decision may be used to cover the
  total cost of both the local and foreign expenditure of projects and
  programmes, including financing of recurrent costs.

  2. OCTs are also eligible for financing under the legislation in force
  in favour of the developing countries listed in Annex II E and for the
  Community programmes listed in Annex II F.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Private Sector Investment Support" chapter_identifier="1411">
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Investment Promotion" article_identifier="11458">The authorities of the OCT, Member States and the Community,
  recognising the importance of private investment in the promotion of
  their development cooperation and acknowledging the need to take steps
  to promote such investment, shall:

  (a) implement measures to encourage participation in their development
  efforts by private investors who comply with the objectives and
  priorities of OCT-EC development cooperation and with the appropriate
  laws and regulations;

  (b) accord fair and equitable treatment to such investors;

  (c) take measures and actions which help to create and maintain a
  predictable and secure investment climate as well as enter into
  negotiations on agreements which will improve such a climate;

  (d) promote effective cooperation among OCT economic operators and
  between them and those of the Community in order to increase the flow
  of capital, management skills, technology and other forms of know-how;

  (e) seek to promote a greater flow of private resources between the
  Community and the OCTs by contributing, inter alia, to the removal of
  obstacles which impede OCT operators' access to international capital
  markets, including those of the Community;

  (f) create an environment which encourages the development of
  financial institutions and the mobilisation of resources which are
  essential to capital formation and the growth of entrepreneurship;

  (g) promote the development of enterprises by taking such steps as are
  necessary to improve the business environment and, in particular,
  foster a legal, administrative and incentive framework which is
  conducive to the emergence and development of dynamic private sector
  enterprises including grassroots operations;

  (h) strengthen the capacity of local institutions in the OCTs to
  provide the range of services which can encourage greater local
  participation in industrial and business activity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Investment Support And Financing" article_identifier="11459">Cooperation will provide long-term financing to help promote private
  sector growth and mobilise national and foreign capital to that
  effect. To this end, cooperation shall in particular provide:

  (a) grants to cover technical and financial assistance in support of
  human resource development, institutional capacity building, or other
  forms of institutional aid linked to a specific investment; measures
  designed to make enterprises more competitive and build the capacity
  of private financial and non-financial intermediaries; measures to
  facilitate and promote investment and activities to improve
  competitiveness;

  (b) advisory and consultancy services to help create an
  investment-friendly climate and a stock of information to help guide
  and encourage capital flows;

  (c) grants funded by the Investment Facility referred to in Annex II
  C;

  (d) loans from the EIB's own resources.

  The conditions applicable to the Investment Facility and the
  abovementioned loans are laid down respectively in Annexes II B and C.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Additional Support In The Event Of Fluctuations In Export Earnings" chapter_identifier="1412">
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Additional Support" article_identifier="11460">1. In order to mitigate the adverse effects of any short-term
  fluctuations in export earnings, in particular in the agricultural and
  mining sectors, which might jeopardise the attainment of the
  development objectives of the OCT concerned, a system of additional
  support shall be instituted within the financial allocation referred
  to in Annex II A.

  2. The purpose of support in the event of short-term fluctuations in
  export earnings is to safeguard macroeconomic and sectoral reforms and
  policies that are at risk as a result of a drop in revenue and remedy
  the adverse effects of instability of export earnings in particular
  from agricultural and mining products.

  3. The dependence of the OCT economies on exports, in particular in
  the agricultural and mining sectors, shall be taken into account in
  the allocation of resources referred to in Annex II D. In this
  context, the least developed OCTs shall receive more favourable
  treatment.

  4. The additional resources shall be provided in accordance with the
  specific modalities of the support mechanism as set out in Annex II D.

  5. The Community shall also provide support for market-based insurance
  schemes designed for OCTs seeking to protect themselves against the
  risk of fluctuations in export earnings.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Support For Other Actors Of Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1413">
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Objectives And Financing" article_identifier="11461">1. In order to respond to the development needs of local communities
  and encourage all actors of decentralised cooperation which are in a
  position to contribute to the autonomous development of the OCTs to
  put forward and implement initiatives, OCT-EC cooperation shall
  support such development operations within limits laid down by the
  OCTs concerned and by the Member States to which these OCTs are
  linked, and within the framework of the SPD provisions.

  2. In this context, financial support shall be given to decentralised
  projects and microprojects as follows:

  (a) The cooperation partners eligible for financial support under this
  Chapter shall be decentralised cooperation agents in the Community or
  the OCTs or other developing countries, namely: local authorities,
  non-governmental organisations, local traders' associations and local
  citizens' groups, cooperatives, trade unions, women's and youth
  organisations, teaching and research institutions, churches and any
  non-governmental associations likely to contribute do development.

  This form of cooperation shall make available for the development of
  the OCTs the capabilities, innovative operating methods and resources
  of the actors of decentralised cooperation. Support will take account
  in particular joint actions between Community, OCT and other
  developing countries;

  (b) Local microprojects shall have an economic and social impact on
  the life of the people, meet a demonstrated and observed priority need
  and be undertaken at the initiative and with the active participation
  of the local community which will benefit therefrom.

  3. Projects or programmes under this form of cooperation may be a way
  of achieving the specific objectives of the SPD or the results of
  initiatives by local communities or decentralised actors.

  4. The support provided for under this Chapter shall be additional or,
  if need be, complementary in respect of the provisions in Annex II E.

  5. Contributions to the funding of microprojects and decentralised
  cooperation shall come from grants, in which case the contribution
  shall not normally exceed three-quarters of the total cost of each
  project. The balance shall be financed:

  (a) for microprojects, by the local community concerned, in kind or in
  the form of services or cash and adapted to its capacity to
  contribute;

  (b) for decentralised cooperation, by the actors of decentralised
  cooperation, provided that the financial, technical, material and
  other resources brought in by such actors is not, as a general rule,
  less than 25 % of the estimated cost of the project/programme;

  (c) in exceptional cases where both microprojects and decentralised
  cooperation are concerned, by the authorities of the OCT concerned,
  either in the form of financial contribution or through the use of
  public equipment or the supply of services.

  The procedures applicable to projects and programmes financed in the
  context of microprojects or decentralised cooperation shall be as set
  out in this Decision, notably with regard to the SPD implementing
  provisions.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Support For Humanitarian And Emergency Aid" chapter_identifier="1414">
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Objectives And Means" article_identifier="11462">1. Humanitarian and emergency aid shall be granted to OCTs faced with
  serious economic and social difficulties of an exceptional nature
  resulting from natural disasters or extraordinary circumstances having
  comparable effects. Humanitarian and emergency aid shall be maintained
  as long as necessary to deal with the urgent problems which arise in
  such situations.

  Humanitarian and emergency aid shall be granted solely on the basis of
  the needs and interests of disaster victims.

  2. The aim of humanitarian and emergency aid shall be to:

  (a) save human lives in crisis and post-crisis situations caused by
  natural disasters or extraordinary circumstances having comparable
  effects;

  (b) help finance the transport of aid and efforts to ensure that it is
  accessible to those for whom it is intended, by all logistical means
  available;

  (c) implement short-term rehabilitation and reconstruction measures in
  order to establish conditions as soon as possible for the people
  concerned to be integrated or reintegrated;

  (d) respond to needs arising as a result of people being displaced,
  such as refugees, displaced persons and returnees following natural or
  man-made disasters so as to meet all the requirements of refugees and
  displaced persons wherever they may be for as long as is necessary and
  facilitate their voluntary resettlement;

  (e) help the OCTs to develop or perfect systems of disaster prevention
  and preparedness, including prediction and early-warning systems, with
  a view to reducing the consequences of disasters.

  3. Similarly aid may be granted to OCTs taking in refugees or
  returnees to meet acute needs not covered by emergency assistance.

  4. Aid provided for by this Article shall be financed from the
  Community budget. However, it may exceptionally be financed from the
  allocations laid down in Annex II A, in addition to the funding from
  the budget heading concerned.

  5. Humanitarian and emergency aid operations shall be undertaken at
  the request of the OCT affected, the Commission, the Member State to
  which the OCT is linked, international organisations or local or
  international non-governmental organisations. Such aid shall be
  administered and implemented under procedures that facilitate rapid,
  flexible and effective operations.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Implementation Procedures" chapter_identifier="1415">
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Technical Assistance" article_identifier="11463">1. On the initiative of or on behalf of the Commission, studies or
  technical assistance measures may be financed in order to ensure the
  preparation, monitoring, evaluation and supervision necessary for
  implementing this Decision.

  Such studies or technical assistance measures shall be financed by the
  overall grant allocation.

  2. On the initiative of the OCT, studies or technical assistance
  measures may be financed in relation to the implementation of the
  activities contained in the SPD, subject to the Commission's opinion.

  Such studies or technical assistance measures shall be financed from
  the allocation of the OCT concerned.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Financial Control" article_identifier="11464">1. The OCT concerned shall bear primary responsibility for the
  financial supervision of the operation. This shall be carried out,
  where appropriate, in coordination with the Member State to which the
  OCT is linked in accordance with the applicable national legislation.

  2. The Commission shall be responsible for:

  (a) ensuring that management and control systems exist and function
  properly in the OCT concerned so as to ensure that the Community funds
  are used correctly and effectively;

  (b) in the event of irregularities, sending recommendations or
  requests for corrective measures to remedy those irregularities and
  rectify any management shortcomings found.

  3. The Commission, OCT and, where appropriate, the Member State to
  which it is linked, shall cooperate on the basis of administrative
  arrangements at annual or biannual meeting to coordinate programmes,
  methodologies and the implementation of controls.

  4. With regard to financial corrections:

  (a) the OCT shall be responsible in the first instance for detecting
  and correcting financial irregularities;

  (b) however, in the event of shortcomings by the OCT concerned, the
  Commission shall take action, if the OCT fails to remedy the situation
  and attempts at conciliation are unsuccessful, to reduce or withdraw
  the balance of the overall allocation corresponding to the SPD
  financing decision.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Transition From Previous European Development Funds (Edfs) To The 9Th Edf" chapter_identifier="1416">
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Implementing The Previous Edfs And The Transitional Phase" article_identifier="11465">1. Commitments made in the framework of the 6th, 7th and 8th EDFs
  before the entry into force of this Decision shall continue to be
  executed following the rules applicable to those EDFs.

  Resources from the sixth, seventh and eighth EDFs which were allocated
  to OCTs before the entry into force of this Decision shall remain
  allocated to them. These resources shall continue to be used in
  accordance with the relevant provisions of Decision 91/482/EEC, which
  shall remain applicable for such purposes, until the entry into force
  of the Internal Agreement establishing the 9th EDF.

  Until the Internal Agreement establishing the 9th EDF comes into
  force, the officials responsible for managing and implementing
  European Development Fund resources, namely the EDF Chief Authorising
  Officer, the OCT Local Authorising Officer and the Commission's Head
  of Delegation, shall remain responsible for the management and
  implementation tasks assigned to them by Council Decision 91/482/EC.

  2. Any balances remaining from previous EDFs on the date of entry into
  force of the Internal Agreement establishing the 9th EDF, as well as
  any amounts that shall be decommitted at a later date from ongoing
  projects under these Funds, shall be transferred to the 9th EDF and
  used in accordance with the conditions laid down in this Decision.

  Any resources thus transferred to the 9th EDF that previously had been
  allocated to the indicative programme of an OCT or region shall remain
  allocated to that OCT or to regional cooperation.

  Any other remaining balances not allocated to an indicative programme
  shall be transferred to the non-committed amount of the 9th EDF. The
  overall amount of this Decision, supplemented by the transferred
  balances from previous EDFs, shall cover the period 2000-2007. This
  paragraph shall apply in particular to any remaining balances of the
  overall amounts referred to in Articles 118 and 142 of Decision
  91/482/EEC concerning, respectively, the stabilisation of export
  earnings from agricultural commodities (Stabex) and the special
  financing facility (Sysmin).

  ECONOMIC AND TRADE COOPERATION</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Objective" article_identifier="11466">1. The objective of economic and trade cooperation shall be to promote
  the economic and social development of the OCTs, in particular by
  establishing close economic relations between them and the Community
  as a whole.

  The implementation of such cooperation must be consistent with the
  objectives of the other common policies.

  2. Furthermore, the Community undertakes to support the effective
  integration of the OCTs in the global economy and the development of
  their trade in goods and services to regional and world markets.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Arrangements For Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="1417">
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Free Access For Originating Products" article_identifier="11467">1. Products originating in the OCTs shall be imported into the
  Community free of import duty.

  2. The concept of originating products and the methods of
  administrative cooperation relating thereto are laid down in Annex
  III.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Transhipment Of Non-Originating Products In Free Circulation In The Octs" article_identifier="11468">1. Products not originating in the OCTs but which are in free
  circulation in an OCT and are re-exported as such to the Community
  shall be accepted for import into the Community free of customs duties
  and taxes having equivalent effect providing that they:

  (a) have paid, in the OCT concerned, customs duties or taxes having
  equivalent effect of a level equal to, or higher than, the customs
  duties applicable in the Community on import of these same products
  originating in third countries eligible for the most-favoured-nation
  clause;

  (b) have not been the subject of an exemption from, or a refund of, in
  whole or in part, customs duties or taxes having equivalent effect,
  without prejudice to paragraph 2;

  (c) are accompanied by an export certificate.

  2. Without prejudice to paragraph 1, the Commission may, following a
  duly substantiated request from the authorities of the OCT concerned
  and in the light of the objectives of this Decision, authorise OCT
  public financial aid to those operating the transhipment procedure.

  The request shall in particular indicate the nature and the
  anticipated volume of trade, which would benefit from the aid.

  This aid must take the form of an aid for transport of goods put in
  free circulation, including legitimate running costs supported in
  relationship with the transhipment procedure. This aid shall not
  provoke a serious disturbance or difficulties, which may result in a
  deterioration in an economic sector of the Community or of one or more
  Member States.

  The OCT authorities may make representations to the Commission in
  order to provide further information to substantiate their written
  request.

  If the OCT authorities so request, a partnership working party
  referred to in Article 7(3) shall be convened to resolve any issues
  arising from the administration of the transhipment procedure.

  3. Paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply to:

  (a) the agricultural products listed in Annex I to the Treaty nor to
  products covered by Council Regulation (EEC) No 3448/93 of 6 December
  1993 laying down the trade arrangements applicable to certain goods
  resulting from the processing of agricultural products(8) except, as
  from 1 February 2002 and subject to the adoption by the Commission of
  the necessary implementing arrangements, for fisheries products:

  (A) falling within CN codes 0303 31 10 00, 0304 20 95 10 and 0306 13
  10 transhipped through Greenland within an annual quantity of 10000
  tons, and

  (B) falling within CN codes 0302 21 10, 0303 31 10, 0305 49 10, 0306
  12 10, 0306 12 90, 0306 22 91, 0306 22 99, 0306 13 10, 0306 13 30,
  0306 13 40, 0306 13 50, 0306 13 80, 0306 23 10, 0306 23 31, 0306 23
  39, 0306 23 90 transhipped through Saint-Pierre-et-Miquelon within an
  annual quantity of 2000 tonnes;

  (b) products subject, on import into the Community, to quantitative
  restrictions or limitations or to anti-dumping duties.

  4. The conditions for entry into the Community of products not
  originating in the OCTs but in free circulation in an OCT, and the
  methods of administrative cooperation relating thereto, are laid down
  in Annex IV.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Committee Procedure" article_identifier="11469">1. In matters covered by Article 36, the Commission shall be assisted
  by a Committee.

  2. Articles 3 and 7 of Decision 1999/468/EC shall apply to the
  proceedings of the Committee.

  3. The Committee shall adopt its rules of procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Quantitative Restrictions And Measures Having Equivalent Effect" article_identifier="11470">1. The Community shall not apply to imports of products originating in
  the OCTs any quantitative restrictions or measures having equivalent
  effect.

  2. Paragraph 1 shall not preclude prohibitions or restrictions on
  imports, exports or goods in transit justified on grounds of public
  morality or public policy, the protection of health and life of
  humans, animals and plants, the protection of national treasures
  possessing artistic, historic or archaeological value, the
  conservation of exhaustible natural resources or the protection of
  industrial and commercial property.

  Such prohibitions or restrictions shall in no case constitute a means
  of arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination or a disguised
  restriction of trade generally.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Waste" article_identifier="11471">1. Movements of waste between the Member States and the OCTs shall be
  controlled in accordance with international and Community law. The
  Community shall support the establishment and development of effective
  international cooperation in this area with a view to protecting the
  environment and public health.

  2. The Community shall prohibit all direct or indirect export of waste
  to the OCTs, with the exception of exports of non-hazardous waste
  destined for recovery operations while at the same time the OCT
  authorities shall prohibit the direct or indirect import into their
  country of such waste from the Community or any other country, without
  prejudice to specific international undertakings concerning these
  areas that have been made, or may be made in future, in the competent
  international fora.

  3. As regards the Community, Council Regulation (EEC) No 259/93 of 1
  February 1993 on the supervision and control of shipments of waste
  within, into and out of the European Community(9) shall apply.

  4. As regards those OCTs, which, due to their constitutional status,
  are not Party to the Basle Convention, their relevant authorities
  shall expedite adoption of the necessary internal legislation and
  administrative regulations to implement the provisions of the Basle
  Convention(10).

  5. In addition, the Member States concerned shall promote the adoption
  by the OCTs of the necessary internal legislation and administrative
  regulations to implement:

  (a) Regulation (EEC) No 259/93 as follows:

  (i) Article 13 as regards shipments of waste within the OCTs,

  (ii) Article 18 as regards exports of waste to the ACP States from the
  OCTs;

  (b) Regulation (EC) No 1420/1999(11);

  (c) Commission Regulation (EC) No 1547/1999(12);

  (d) European Parliament and Council Directive 2000/59/EC subject to
  the time limits for transposition laid down in Article 16 thereof(13).

  6. As regards imports into the Community from the OCTs of hazardous
  waste and of non-hazardous waste destined for final disposal, Articles
  1 to 12 and 25 to 39 of Regulation (EEC) No 259/93 and Commission
  Decision 94/774/EC(14), shall apply.

  7. One or more OCTs and the Member State to which they are linked may
  apply national procedures to export of waste from the OCTs to that
  Member State.

  In this case, the Member State concerned notifies to the Commission
  the applicable legislation within six months from the entry into force
  of this Decision or of any future relevant national legislation,
  including any amendments to it.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Measures Adopted By The Octs" article_identifier="11472">1. In view of the present development needs of the OCTs, the
  authorities of the OCTs may retain or introduce, in respect of imports
  of products originating in the Community, such customs duties or
  quantitative restrictions as they consider necessary.

  2. (a) The trade arrangements applied to the Community by the OCTs may
  not give rise to any discrimination between Member States nor be less
  favourable than most-favoured-nation treatment.

  (b) Notwithstanding specific provisions of this Decision, the
  Community shall not discriminate between OCTs in the field of trade.

  (c) The provisions of (a) shall not preclude a country or territory
  from granting certain other OCTs or other developing countries more
  favourable treatment than that accorded to the Community.

  3. The authorities of the OCTs shall communicate to the Commission,
  within a period of three months following the entry into force of this
  Decision, the customs tariffs and lists of quantitative restrictions
  which they apply.

  They shall also communicate to the Commission any subsequent
  amendments to such measures as and when they are adopted.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Surveillance Clause" article_identifier="11473">1. The products originating in the OCTs referred to in Article 35 or
  products not originating in the OCT referred to in Article 36 may be
  subject to special surveillance. The Commission shall decide to which
  products surveillance shall apply in consultation with the OCT
  authorities and the Member State to which the OCT is linked.

  2. Article 308d of Commission Regulation (EEC) No 2454/93 of 2 July
  1993, laying down provisions for the implementation of Council
  Regulation (EEC) No 2913/92 on the Community Customs Code(15), shall
  apply.

  3. The Commission and the competent OCT authorities shall ensure the
  effectiveness of the surveillance measures by introducing the methods
  of administrative cooperation set out in Annexes III and IV.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="11474">1. If, as a result of the application of this Decision, serious
  disturbances occur in a sector of the economy of the Community or one
  or more of its Member States, or their external financial stability is
  jeopardised, or if difficulties arise which may result in a
  deterioration in a sector of the Community's activity or in a region
  of the Community, the Commission may, on its own initiative or at the
  request of one or more Member States and following consultation with
  the Committee referred to in Article 43 take or authorise the Member
  States concerned to take the necessary safeguard measures, in
  accordance with the paragraphs below.

  2. For the purpose of implementing paragraph 1, priority shall be
  given to such measures as would least disturb the functioning of the
  association and the Community. These measures shall not exceed the
  limits of what is strictly necessary to remedy the difficulties that
  have arisen. They cannot exceed the withdrawal of the preferential
  treatment granted by this Decision.

  3. When safeguard measures are taken or modified, particular attention
  shall be paid to the interests of the least-developed OCTs.

  4. This Article is without prejudice to the rights and obligations of
  the Community under WTO rules, including those contained in the WTO
  Agreement on Safeguards(16). Neither shall it preclude application of
  the regulations establishing a common organisation of agricultural
  markets, or Community or national administrative provisions derived
  therefrom, or the specific rules adopted under Article 235 of the
  Treaty for processed agricultural products.

  5. (a) If a Member State asks the Commission for safeguard measures to
  be applied, the Commission shall inform the Council, the Member States
  and the OCT authorities accordingly within three working days from the
  date of receipt of the Member State's request, and shall invite the
  OCT authorities to supply any information which they consider
  important to the situation at hand.

  (b) When the Commission acts on its own initiative, it shall inform
  the OCTs concerned and the Member States at the earliest possible
  stage.

  (c) If the OCT authorities so require and without prejudice to the
  deadlines referred to in this Article, a partnership working party
  referred to in Article 7(3) shall be convened. The outcome of the
  working party shall be transmitted to the consultative committee. In
  this case, the deadline referred to in paragraph 9 of this Article
  shall be extended by ten working days. At the same time it shall
  invite the Member States to a meeting of the committee referred to in
  Article 43.

  Member States and the OCTs shall provide the Commission with any
  information necessary to justify their requests to apply safeguard
  measures or not to do so.

  6. The Commission shall notify the Council, the Member States and the
  OCT authorities immediately of the decision to take the necessary
  safeguard measures. The Decision shall apply with immediate effect.

  7. Any Member State may refer the Commission's decision referred to in
  paragraph 6 to the Council within 10 working days of receiving
  notification of the decision.

  8. Should the Commission fail to adopt a decision within 21 working
  days or if it rejects the request or if the Commission decides not to
  take safeguard measures, any Member State that has brought the matter
  before the Commission may refer it to the Council.

  9. In the cases referred to in paragraphs 7 and 8, the Council, acting
  by a qualified majority, may adopt a different decision within 21
  working days.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Committee Procedure" article_identifier="11475">1. In matters covered by Article 42, the Commission shall be assisted
  by a Committee.

  2. Articles 3 and 7 of Decision 1999/468/EC shall apply to the
  proceedings of the Committee.

  3. The Committee shall adopt its rules of procedure.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Services And Rules Of Establishment" chapter_identifier="1418">
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="General Objective" article_identifier="11476">The long-term aim in this area is a progressive liberalisation of
  trade in services, with due respect for the OCTs' local policy
  objectives, and taking due account of the level of development of the
  OCT and the obligations entered into by the Community, Member States
  or the OCTs in the WTO framework.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="General Principles Of Establishment And The Provision Of Services" article_identifier="11477">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, the following definitions shall
  apply:

  (a) "companies or enterprises": companies or enterprises
  constituted under civil or commercial law, including public or other
  companies, cooperative societies and any other legal person or
  association governed by public or private law, save for those which
  are non-profit-making.

  "Companies or enterprises of Member States" are those formed
  in accordance with the laws of a Member State and whose registered
  office, central administration or principal place of business is in a
  Member State. However, a company or enterprise having only its
  registered office in a Member State must be engaged in an activity
  which has an actual and continuous link with the economy of that
  Member State.

  "OCT companies or enterprises" are those formed in
  accordance with the law applicable in a given OCT and whose registered
  office, central administration or principal place of business is in
  that OCT; however, a company or enterprise having only its registered
  office in a country or territory must be engaged in an activity which
  has an actual and continuous link with the economy of that country or
  territory;

  (b) "inhabitants of an OCT": persons ordinarily resident in
  an OCT who are nationals of a Member State or who enjoy a legal status
  specific to an OCT. This definition is without prejudice to the rights
  conferred by citizenship of the Union within the meaning of the
  Treaty.

  2. As regards the arrangements applicable to establishment and the
  provision of services, in line with Article 183(5) of the Treaty and
  subject to paragraph 3 below:

  (a) the Community shall apply to the OCTs the undertakings entered
  into under the General Agreement on Trade in Services (GATS) under the
  conditions laid down in that Agreement and in accordance with this
  Decision; in application of such undertakings, Member States shall not
  discriminate between inhabitants, companies or enterprises of the
  OCTs;

  (b) the OCT authorities shall afford nationals, companies or
  enterprises of the Member States treatment that is no less favourable
  than that which they extend to nationals, companies or enterprises of
  third countries and shall not discriminate between nationals,
  companies or enterprises of Member States.

  3. The authorities of an OCT may with a view to promoting or
  supporting local employment, adopt regulations to aid their
  inhabitants and local activities.

  In this event, the OCT authorities shall notify the Commission of the
  regulations they adopt so that it may inform the Member States.

  4. With regard to the professions of doctor, dentist, midwife, general
  nurse, pharmacist and veterinary surgeon, the Council, acting
  unanimously on a proposal from the Commission, shall adopt the list of
  professional qualifications specific to OCT inhabitants which are to
  be recognised in the Member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Maritime Transport" article_identifier="11478">The objective of cooperation in this field shall be to ensure
  harmonious development of efficient and reliable shipping services on
  economically satisfactory terms by facilitating the active
  participation of all parties according to the principle of
  unrestricted access to the trade on a commercial basis.

  This provision shall not apply to Greenland.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Trade-Related Areas" chapter_identifier="1419">
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Current Payments And Capital Movements" article_identifier="11479">1. Without prejudice to paragraph 2:

  (a) Member States and the OCT authorities shall impose no restrictions
  on any payments in freely convertible currency on the current account
  of balance of payments between residents of the Community and of the
  OCTs;

  (b) with regard to transactions on the capital account of balance of
  payments, the Member States and the OCT authorities shall impose no
  restrictions on the free movement of capital for direct investments in
  companies formed in accordance with the laws of the host Member State,
  country or territory and to ensure that the assets formed by such
  investment and any profit stemming therefrom can be realised and
  repatriated.

  2. The Community, Member States and OCTs shall be entitled to take the
  measures referred to mutatis mutandis in Articles 57, 58, 59, 60 and
  301 of the Treaty in accordance with the conditions laid down therein.
  Equally, where one or more OCTs or one or more Member States is in
  serious balance of payments difficulties, or under threat thereof, the
  OCT authorities, the Member State or the Community may, in accordance
  with the conditions established under the GATT, GATS and Article VIII
  and XIV of the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary
  Fund, adopt restrictions on current transactions which shall be of
  limited duration and may not go beyond what is necessary to remedy the
  balance of payments situation. When taking such measures, the OCT
  authorities, the Member State or the Community shall inform each other
  without delay and submit to each other as soon as possible a timetable
  for the elimination of the measures concerned.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Competition Policies" article_identifier="11480">1. The introduction and implementation of effective and sound
  competition policies and rules are of crucial importance in order to
  improve and secure an investment friendly climate, a sustainable
  industrialisation process and transparency in the access to markets.

  2. To ensure the elimination of distortions to competition and with
  due consideration to the different levels of development and economic
  needs of each OCT, the Community and the OCTs undertake to implement
  local, national or regional rules and policies including the control
  and, under certain conditions, the prohibition of agreements between
  undertakings, decisions by associations of undertakings and concerted
  practices between undertakings which have as their object or effect
  the prevention, restriction or distortion of competition. The above
  prohibition also relates to the abuse by one or more undertakings of a
  dominant position in the territory of the Community or of the OCTs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Protection Of Intellectual Property Rights" article_identifier="11481">1. An adequate and effective level of protection of intellectual,
  industrial and commercial property rights, including means for
  enforcing such rights, shall be ensured in line with the highest
  international standards with a view to reducing distortions and
  impediments to bilateral trade.

  2. Intellectual property rights cover copyright, including in
  particular the copyright on computer programmes and neighbouring
  rights, utility models, patents including bio-technological
  inventions, industrial designs, geographical indications including
  appellations of origin, trademarks for goods or services, topographies
  of integrated circuits, the legal protection of data bases and the
  protection against unfair competition as referred to in Article 10 bis
  of the Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property and
  protection of undisclosed information on know-how.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Standardisation And Certification" article_identifier="11482">Closer cooperation shall be pursued in the field of standardisation,
  certification and quality assurance to remove unnecessary technical
  barriers and to reduce differences in those areas, so as to facilitate
  trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Trade And The Environment" article_identifier="11483">Development of international trade shall be promoted in such a way as
  to ensure sustainable and sound management of the environment, in
  accordance with the relevant international agreements and undertakings
  and with due regard to the respective levels of development of the
  OCTs. The special needs and requirements of the OCTs shall be taken
  into account in the design and implementation of environmental
  measures.

  Bearing in mind the Rio Principles, cooperation shall aim at ensuring
  the mutual supportiveness of trade and environment policies, in
  particular through the reinforcement of quality controls of goods and
  services related to the environment and the improvement of
  environment-friendly production methods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Trade And Labour Standards" article_identifier="11484">The internationally and nationally recognised core labour standards
  must be respected, in particular the freedom of association and
  protection of the right to organise, application of the right to
  organise and to bargain collectively, the abolition of forced labour,
  the elimination of worst forms of child labour, the minimum age for
  admission to employment and non-discrimination in respect to
  employment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Consumer Policy And Consumer Health Protection" article_identifier="11485">Cooperation shall be pursued in the area of consumer policy and
  consumer health protection, having due regard to the legislation in
  force in OCTs and the Community to avoid barriers to trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Prohibition Of Disguised Protectionist Measures" article_identifier="11486">The provisions of this Chapter shall not be used as a means of
  arbitrary discrimination or a disguised restriction on trade.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Monetary And Tax Matters" chapter_identifier="1420">
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Tax Carve-Out Clause" article_identifier="11487">1. Without prejudice to the provisions of Article 56, the
  most-favoured-nation treatment granted in accordance with the
  provisions of this Decision shall not apply to tax advantages which
  the Member States or OCT authorities are providing or may provide in
  the future on the basis of agreements to avoid double taxation or
  other tax arrangements, or domestic fiscal legislation in force.

  2. Nothing in this Decision may be construed to prevent the adoption
  or enforcement of any measure aimed at preventing the avoidance or
  fraud of taxes pursuant to the tax provisions of agreements to avoid
  double taxation or other tax arrangements, or domestic fiscal
  legislation in force.

  3. Nothing in this Decision shall be construed to prevent the
  respective competent authorities from distinguishing, in the
  application of the relevant provisions of their fiscal legislation,
  between taxpayers who are not in the same situation, in particular
  with regard to their place of residence, or with regard to the place
  where their capital is invested.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Tax And Customs Arrangements For Community-Funded Contracts" article_identifier="11488">1. The OCTs shall apply to Community-funded contracts tax and customs
  arrangements no less favourable than those applied by them to the
  most-favoured States or international development organisations with
  which they have relations. For the purpose of determining the
  most-favoured-nation treatment, account shall not be taken of
  arrangements applied by the relevant authorities of the country or
  territory concerned to other developing countries.

  2. Subject to paragraph 1, the following arrangements shall apply to
  contracts financed by the Community:

  (a) the contract shall not be subject in the beneficiary OCT to stamp
  or registration duties or to fiscal charges having equivalent effect,
  whether such charges already exist or are to be instituted in the
  future; however, such contracts shall be registered in accordance with
  the laws in force in the OCT and a fee corresponding to the service
  rendered may be charged for it;

  (b) profits and/or income arising from the performance of contracts
  shall be taxable according to the internal fiscal arrangements of the
  OCT concerned, provided that the natural or legal persons who realise
  such profit and/or income have a permanent place of business in that
  OCT, or that the performance of the contract takes longer than six
  months;

  (c) enterprises which must import equipment in order to carry out
  works contracts shall, if they so request, benefit from the system of
  temporary admission as laid down by the legislation of the beneficiary
  OCT in respect of that equipment;

  (d) professional equipment necessary for carrying out tasks defined in
  a service contract shall be temporarily admitted into the beneficiary
  OCT in accordance with the legislation of that OCT free of fiscal,
  import and customs duties and of other charges having equivalent
  effect where these duties and charges do not constitute remuneration
  for services rendered;

  (e) imports under supply contracts shall be admitted into the
  beneficiary OCT without customs duties, import duties, taxes or fiscal
  charges having equivalent effect. The contract for supplies
  originating in the country or territory concerned shall be concluded
  on the basis of the ex-works price of the supplies, to which may be
  added such internal fiscal charges as may be applicable to those
  supplies in the country or territory;

  (f) fuels, lubricants and hydrocarbon binders and, in general, all
  materials used in the performance of works contracts shall be deemed
  to have been purchased on the local market and shall be subject to
  fiscal rules applicable under the legislation in force in the
  beneficiary OCT;

  (g) personal and household effects imported for use by natural
  persons, other than those recruited locally, engaged in carrying out
  tasks defined in a service contract and members of their families,
  shall be exempt from customs or import duties, taxes and other fiscal
  charges having equivalent effect, within the limits of the legislation
  in force in the beneficiary OCT.

  3. Any matter not covered by paragraphs 1 and 2 shall remain subject
  to the legislation of the OCT concerned.

  4. The Commission officials, excluding locally hired staff, shall be
  exempt from all taxes levied in the country or territory where they
  are posted.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Vocational Training, Eligibility For Community Programmes And Other Provisions" chapter_identifier="1421">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Vocational Training" article_identifier="11489">Individuals from an OCT with the nationality of a Member State shall
  be eligible to receive vocational training in the Community on the
  same basis as nationals of the Member State in question where they can
  meet the conditions required to be met by those nationals, including
  any condition of residence within the Community or the EEA.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Programmes Open To The Octs" article_identifier="11490">Individuals from an OCT and where applicable the relevant public
  and/or private bodies and institutions in an OCT shall be eligible for
  the Community programmes listed in Annex II F and any programmes
  succeeding them, subject to the rules of the programmes and the
  arrangements applicable to the Member State with which they are
  connected.

  The Commission may modify this list at the request of an OCT or a
  Member State or at its own initiative.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Euro-Info Correspondence Centres (Eicc)" article_identifier="11491">At the request of the OCT authorities and in accordance with the
  procedures specified in Part Three, Title I, a Euro-Info
  Correspondence Centre, hereinafter referred to as "'EICC",
  may be set up in an OCT. Part-financing may be made available to the
  EICC host structure from the grant aid available under the SPD or
  regional cooperation.

  The tasks of the EICCs, the tools and services made available to them,
  the establishment procedures and criteria for selecting the host
  structure are set out in Annex V.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Cde And Cta" article_identifier="11492">At the request of their authorities, the OCT shall be eligible for the
  services of the Centre for the Development of Enterprise (CDE) and of
  the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation (CTA)
  referred to in Article 1 of Annex III to the ACP/EC Partnership
  Agreement.

  Any costs resulting from services provided by the CDE or CTA for the
  benefit of the OCTs shall be financed from the funds provided for in
  Annex II A.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART FOUR" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1422">
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Change Of Status" article_identifier="11493">If an OCT becomes independent:

  (a) the arrangements provided for in this Decision may continue to
  apply provisionally to that country or territory under conditions laid
  down by the Council;

  (b) the Council, acting unanimously on a proposal from the Commission,
  shall decide on any necessary adjustments to this Decision, in
  particular to the amounts specified in Annex II A.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Review" article_identifier="11494">Before 31 December 2007, the Council, acting unanimously on a proposal
  from the Commission, shall establish the provisions to be laid down
  for the subsequent application of the principles set out in Articles
  182 to 186 of the Treaty. In this context, the Council shall in
  particular adopt any necessary measures where an OCT decides in
  accordance with its own constitutional procedures to enter into
  special preferential arrangements between the Community and various
  partners in the region to which it belongs. The Council shall take
  particular account in this respect of international obligations
  entered into by the Community, its Member States or the OCTs,
  including those within the framework of the WTO.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="11495">This Decision shall enter into force on 2 December 2001. It shall be
  applicable until 31 December 2011.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Publication" article_identifier="11496">This Decision shall be published in the Official Journal of the
  European Communities.

  Done at Brussels, 27 November 2001.

  For the Council

  The President

  A. Neyts-Uyttebroeck

  (1) OJ L 263, 19.9.1991, p. 1. Decision as last amended and extended
  by Decision 2001/161/EC (OJ L 58, 28.2.2001, p. 21).

  (2) PE 228.210, 1.12.1998.

  (3) Not yet published C5-0070 - 2001/2033 (COS).

  (4) Council Decision 97/803/EC of 29 November 1997 amending at
  mid-term Decision 91/482/EEC on the association of the overseas
  countries and territories with the European Economic Community (OJ L
  329, 29.11.1997, p. 50).

  (5) OJ L 184, 7.7.1999, p. 23.

  (6) OJ L 317, 15.12.2000, p. 355.

  (7) Council Decision 93/626/ΕEC of 25 October 1993 concerning the
  conclusion of the convention on Biological Diversity (OJ L 309,
  13.12.1993, p. 1).

  (8) OJ L 318, 20.12.1993, p. 18. Regulation as last amended by
  Regulation (EC) No 2580/2000 (OJ L 298, 25.11.2000, p. 5).

  (9) OJ L 30, 6.2.1993, p. 1. Regulation as last amended by Commission
  Decision 1999/816/EC (OJ L 316, 10.12.1999, p. 45).

  (10) Council Decision 93/98/EEC of 1 February 1993 on the conclusion
  on behalf of the Community, of the Convention on the control of
  transboundery movements of hazardous wastes and their disposal (Basle
  Convention) (OJ L 39, 16.2.1993, p. 1).

  (11) Council Regulation (EC) No 1420/1999 of 29 April 1999
  establishing common rules and procedures to apply to shipments to
  certain non-OECD countries of certain types of waste (OJ L 166,
  1.7.1999, p. 6). Regulation as last amended by Commission Regulation
  (EC) No 1800/2001 (OJ L 244, 14.9.2001, p. 19).

  (12) Commission Regulation No 1547/1999/EC of 12 July 1999 determining
  the control procedures under Council Regulation (EEC) No 259/93 to
  apply to shipments of certain types of waste to certain countries to
  which OECD Decision C(92)39 final does not apply (OJ L 185, 17.7.1999,
  p. 1). Regulation as last amended by Regulation (EC) No 1800/2001.

  (13) European Parliament and Council Directive No 2000/59/EC of 27
  November 2000 on port reception facilities for ship-generated waste
  and cargo residues (OJ L 332, 28.12.2000, p. 81).

  (14) Commission Decision 94/774/EC of 24 November 1994 concerning the
  standard consignment note referred to in Council Regulation No
  259/93/EEC on the supervision and control of shipments of waste
  within, into and out of the European Community (OJ L 310, 3.12.94, p.
  70).

  (15) OJ L 253, 11.10.1993, p. 1. Regulation as last amended by
  Regulation (EC) No 993/2001 (OJ L 141, 28.5.2001, p. 1).

  (16) OJ L 336, 23.12.1994, p. 184.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
