<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>ASEAN - Japan</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>176</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>152</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2008-03-26</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2008-12-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2009-11-23</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2026-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BRN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">IDN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KHM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">LAO</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">MMR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">MYS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">PHL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">SGP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">THA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">BRN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">IDN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KHM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">LAO</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">MMR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">MYS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">PHL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">SGP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">THA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/policy/economy/fta/asean/agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/policy/economy/fta/asean/agreement.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1679">
      <article article_identifier="13922">Preamble 

The Governments of Japan, and Brunei Darussalam, theKingdom of Cambodia, the Republic of Indonesia, the LaoPeople’s Democratic Republic, Malaysia, the Union ofMyanmar, the Republic of the Philippines, the Republic ofSingapore, the Kingdom of Thailand and the SocialistRepublic of Viet Nam, Member States of the Association ofSoutheast Asian Nations (hereinafter referred to as“ASEAN”); 

Recalling the Joint Declaration signed in Phnom Penh,Cambodia on 5 November 2002 and the Framework for Comprehensive Economic Partnership between Japan and theAssociation of Southeast Asian Nations signed in Bali,Indonesia on 8 October 2003; 

Desiring to deepen the relationship between Japan andASEAN, which is built on mutual confidence and trust inwide-ranging fields covering not only political andeconomic areas, but also social and cultural areas; 

Inspired by the continuous development of ASEANthrough economic activities among Japan and ASEAN MemberStates, and the significant progress in the relationshipbetween Japan and ASEAN which has spanned thirty years ofeconomic ties that have been expanding over a wide range ofareas; 

Confident that a comprehensive economic partnershipbetween Japan and ASEAN (hereinafter referred to as“AJCEP”) will strengthen their economic ties, create alarger and more efficient market with greater opportunitiesand larger economies of scale, and enhance theirattractiveness to capital and talent, for mutual benefit; 

Recognising that multi-layered and multi-facetedbilateral and regional efforts towards strengtheningeconomic relations among Japan and ASEAN Member States willfacilitate the realisation of such comprehensive economicpartnership; 

Sharing the view that such comprehensive economicpartnership should benefit from, and be complementary to,the economic integration and integrity of ASEAN; 

Recognising further the various stages of economicdevelopment among the ASEAN Member States; 

Confident that this Agreement, covering areas such astrade in goods and services, and investment, would serve asan important building block towards economic integration inEast Asia; 

 Recalling Article XXIV of the General Agreement onTariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General Agreement on Trade in Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B,respectively, to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing theWorld Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, 15 April 1994(hereinafter referred to as “WTO Agreement”); 

Recognising the role of regional trade agreements as acatalyst in accelerating regional and global liberalisationin the framework of the multilateral trading system; 

Reaffirming the rights and obligations of each Partyunder the WTO Agreement and multilateral, regional andbilateral agreements and arrangements; and 

Determined to establish a legal framework for suchcomprehensive economic partnership among the Parties, 

HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1680">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="13923">For the purposes of this Agreement, the term: 


(a) “ASEAN Member States” means Brunei Darussalam,the Kingdom of Cambodia, the Republic ofIndonesia, the Lao People’s Democratic Republic,Malaysia, the Union of Myanmar, the Republic ofthe Philippines, the Republic of Singapore, theKingdom of Thailand and the Socialist Republic ofViet Nam collectively; 


(b) “customs authority” means the competent authoritythat is responsible for the administration andenforcement of customs laws and regulations; 


(c) “days” means calendar days, including weekendsand holidays; 


(d) “GATS” means the General Agreement on Trade inServices in Annex 1B to the WTO Agreement; 


(e) “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement onTariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. For the purposes of this Agreement, references to articles in GATT 1994 include its Notes and Supplementary Provisions; 


(f) “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the HarmonizedCommodity Description and Coding System set outin the Annex to the International Convention on the Harmonized Commodity Description and CodingSystem, and adopted and implemented by theParties in their respective laws; 


(g) “newer ASEAN Member States” means the Kingdom ofCambodia, the Lao People’s Democratic Republic,the Union of Myanmar and the Socialist Republicof Viet Nam; 


(h) “Parties” means Japan and those ASEAN MemberStates for which this Agreement has entered intoforce collectively; and 


(i) “Party” means either of Japan or one (1) of ASEANMember States for which this Agreement hasentered into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Principles" article_identifier="13924">The Parties reaffirm the importance of realising theAJCEP through both this Agreement and other bilateral orregional agreements or arrangements, and are guided by thefollowing principles: 


(a) the AJCEP shall involve Japan and all ASEANMember States and includes a broad range ofsectors focusing on liberalisation, facilitationand economic cooperation; 


(b) the integrity, solidarity and integration ofASEAN shall be maintained in the realisation of the AJCEP; 


(c) special and differential treatment is accorded toASEAN Member States, especially the newer ASEANMember States, in recognition of their differentlevels of economic development; additionalflexibility is accorded to the newer ASEAN MemberStates; 


(d) recognition shall be given to the provisions ofthe ministerial declarations of the World Trade Organization on measures in favour of least-developed countries; 


(e) flexibility should also be given to address thesensitive sectors in Japan and each ASEAN MemberState; and 


(f) technical assistance and capacity building areimportant elements of economic cooperationprovided under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Objectives" article_identifier="13925">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 


(a) progressively liberalise and facilitate trade ingoods and services among the Parties; 


(b) improve investment opportunities and ensureprotection for investments and investmentactivities in the Parties; and 


(c) 	establish a framework for the enhancement of economic cooperation among the Parties with aview to supporting ASEAN economic integration,bridging the development gap among ASEAN MemberStates, and enhancing trade and investment amongthe Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13926">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, make publicly available its laws, regulations,administrative procedures and administrative rulings andjudicial decisions of general application as well asinternational agreements to which the Party is a party,that pertain to or affect the implementation and operationof this Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall make publicly available the names andaddresses of the competent authorities responsible forlaws, regulations, administrative procedures andadministrative rulings, referred to in paragraph 1. 


3. Each Party shall, upon the request by another Party,respond to specific questions from, and provide informationto, the latter, in the English language, with respect tomatters referred to in paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="13927">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party toprovide confidential information, the disclosure of whichwould impede law enforcement of the Party, or otherwise becontrary to the public interest, or which would prejudicelegitimate commercial interests of any particularenterprise, public or private. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed torequire a Party to provide information relating to theaffairs and accounts of customers of financial institutions. 


3. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, maintain the confidentiality of informationprovided as confidential by another Party pursuant to thisAgreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Taxation" article_identifier="13928">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, theprovisions of this Agreement shall not apply to anytaxation measures. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights andobligations of any Party under any tax convention. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and anysuch convention, that convention shall prevail to theextent of the inconsistency. 


3. Articles 4 and 5 shall apply to taxation measures, tothe extent that the provisions of this Agreement areapplicable to such taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="13929">For the purposes of Chapters 2 through 5, Article XXof GATT 1994 is incorporated into and forms part of thisAgreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="13930">Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed: 


(a) to require any Party to furnish any information,the disclosure of which it considers contrary toits essential security interests; or 


(b) to prevent any Party from taking any action whichit considers necessary for the protection of itsessential security interests: 

(i) relating to fissionable materials or thematerials from which they are derived; 

(ii) relating to the traffic in arms, ammunitionand implements of war and to such traffic inother goods and materials as is carried ondirectly or indirectly for the purpose ofsupplying a military establishment; 

(iii) taken so as to protect critical publicinfrastructure, including communications,power and water infrastructures, fromdeliberate attempts intended to disable ordegrade such infrastructure; 

(iv) taken in time of domestic emergency, or waror other emergency in internationalrelations; or 

(c) to prevent any Party from taking any action inpursuance of its obligations under the UnitedNations Charter for the maintenance of international peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Non-Governmental Bodies" article_identifier="13931">In fulfilling its obligations and commitments underthis Agreement, each Party shall endeavour to ensure theirobservance by non-governmental bodies in the exercise ofpowers delegated by central, regional or local governmentsor authorities within the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="13932">1. Each Party reaffirms its rights and obligations vis-àvis another Party under the WTO Agreement and/or otheragreements to which these Parties are parties. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed toderogate from any obligation of a Party vis-à-vis anotherParty under agreements to which these Parties are parties,if such an obligation entitles the latter Party totreatment more favourable than that accorded by thisAgreement. 


3. In the event of any inconsistency between thisAgreement and the WTO Agreement, the WTO Agreement shallprevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 


4. In the event of any inconsistency between thisAgreement and any agreement other than the WTO Agreement towhich more than one (1) Party are parties, these Partiesshall immediately consult with each other with a view tofinding a mutually satisfactory solution, taking intoconsideration general principles of international law. 


5. A Party which is not a party to the WTO Agreementshall abide by the provisions of the said Agreement inaccordance with its accession commitments to the World Trade Organization.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="13933">1. A Joint Committee shall be established under this Agreement. 


2. The functions of the Joint Committee shall be to: 


(a) review the implementation and operation of thisAgreement; 


(b) submit a report to the Parties on theimplementation and operation of this Agreement; 


(c) consider and recommend to the Parties anyamendments to this Agreement; 


(d) supervise and coordinate the work of all Sub-Committees established under this Agreement; 


(e) adopt: 

(i) the Implementing Regulations referred to inRule 11 of Annex 4; and 

(ii) any necessary decisions; and 

(f) carry out other functions as may be agreed by theParties. 

3. The Joint Committee: 


(a) shall be composed of representatives of Japan andASEAN Member States; and 


(b) may establish Sub-Committees and delegate itsresponsibilities thereto. 

4. The Joint Committee shall meet at such venues and times as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Communications" article_identifier="13934">Each Party shall designate a contact point tofacilitate communications among the Parties on, except asotherwise provided for in Article 61, any matter relatingto this Agreement. All official communications in this regard shall be done in the English language.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="1681">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13935">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “customs duties” means any customs or import dutyand a charge of any kind imposed in connectionwith the importation of a good, but does notinclude any: 

(i) charge equivalent to an internal tax imposedconsistently with the provisions ofparagraph 2 of Article III of GATT 1994, inrespect of the like domestic goods or inrespect of goods from which the importedgoods have been manufactured or produced inwhole or in part; 

(ii) anti-dumping or countervailing duty appliedconsistently with the provisions of ArticleVI of GATT 1994, the Agreement onImplementation of Article VI of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994, and theAgreement on Subsidies and CountervailingMeasures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement;or 

(iii) fee or any charge commensurate with the costof services rendered; 

(b) “customs laws” means such laws and regulationsadministered and enforced by the customsauthority of each Party concerning theimportation, exportation, and transit of goods,as they relate to customs duties, charges, andother taxes, or to prohibitions, restrictions,and other similar controls with respect to themovement of controlled items across the boundaryof the customs territory of each Party; 


(c) “customs value of goods” means the value of goodsfor the purposes of levying ad valorem customsduties on imported goods; 


(d) “domestic industry” means the producers as awhole of the like or directly competitive goodsoperating in a Party, or those whose collectiveoutput of the like or directly competitive goodsconstitutes a major proportion of the totaldomestic production of those goods; 


(e) “originating goods” means goods that qualify asoriginating in accordance with the provisions ofChapter 3; 


(f) “serious injury” means a significant overallimpairment in the position of a domesticindustry; and 


(g) “threat of serious injury” means serious injurythat, on the basis of facts and not merely onallegation, conjecture or remote possibility, isclearly imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="13936">The classification of goods in trade between theParties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="National Treatment On Internal Taxation And Regulation" article_identifier="13937">Each Party shall accord national treatment to thegoods of the other Parties in accordance with Article IIIof GATT 1994, which to this end is incorporated into andforms part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Elimination Or Reduction Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="13938">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,each Party shall, in accordance with its Schedule in Annex1, eliminate or reduce its customs duties on originatinggoods of the other Parties. Such elimination or reduction shall be applied to originating goods of all the otherParties on a non-discriminatory basis. 


2. The Parties shall endeavour to take further stepstowards liberalisation of trade in goods throughunilateral, bilateral or regional efforts consistent withGATT 1994. 


3. The Parties reaffirm that, as is provided for inArticle 7, nothing in this Chapter shall be construed toprevent a Party which is a party to the Basel Convention onthe Control of Transboundary Movements of Hazardous Wastesand their Disposal or other relevant internationalagreements from adopting or enforcing any measure inrelation to hazardous wastes or hazardous substances based on its laws and regulations, in accordance with suchinternational agreements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="13939">For the purposes of determining the customs value ofgoods traded between the Parties, the provisions of Part Iof the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A tothe WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “theAgreement on Customs Valuation”) shall apply, mutatis mutandis. 

Note: 	In the case of the Kingdom of Cambodia, theAgreement on Customs Valuation, as implemented inaccordance with the provisions of the Protocol onthe Accession of the Kingdom of Cambodia to theWorld Trade Organization, shall apply, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Non-Tariff Measures" article_identifier="13940">1. Each Party shall not institute or maintain any non-tariff measures including quantitative restrictions on theimportation of any good of the other Parties or on theexportation or sale for export of any good destined foranother Party, except the same measures as those permittedunder the WTO Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall ensure transparency of its non-tariffmeasures permitted under paragraph 1, includingquantitative restrictions. Each Party which is a member of the World Trade Organization shall ensure full compliancewith the obligations under the WTO Agreement with a view tominimising possible distortions to trade to the maximumextent possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Modification Of Concessions" article_identifier="13941">1. The Parties shall not nullify or impair any of theconcessions under this Agreement, except in cases providedfor in this Agreement. 


2. Any Party may negotiate with any interested Party tomodify or withdraw its concession made under thisAgreement. In such negotiations, which may include compensatory adjustment with respect to other goods, theParties concerned shall maintain a general level ofreciprocal and mutually advantageous concessions not lessfavourable to trade than that provided for in thisAgreement prior to such negotiations. In reflecting the results of such negotiations to this Agreement, Article 77shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="13942">1. A Party which is a member of the World TradeOrganization may apply a safeguard measure to anoriginating good of the other Parties in accordance withArticle XIX of GATT 1994 and the Agreement on Safeguards inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as“the Agreement on Safeguards”), or Article 5 of theAgreement on Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement(hereinafter referred to as “Agreement on Agriculture”).Any action taken pursuant to Article XIX of GATT 1994 andthe Agreement on Safeguards, or Article 5 of the Agreementon Agriculture shall not be subject to Chapter 9 of thisAgreement. 


2. Each Party shall be free to apply a safeguard measureprovided for under this Article (hereinafter referred to as“an AJCEP safeguard measure”), to the minimum extentnecessary to prevent or remedy the serious injury to adomestic industry of that Party and to facilitateadjustment, if as an effect of the obligations incurred bythat Party under this Agreement, including tariffconcessions, or if as a result of unforeseen developmentsand of the effects of the obligations incurred by thatParty under this Agreement, an originating good of theother Parties is being imported in such increasedquantities, in absolute terms or relative to domesticproduction, and under such conditions as to cause orthreaten to cause serious injury to the domestic industryof the importing Party that produces like or directlycompetitive goods in the importing Party. 


3. An AJCEP safeguard measure shall not be appliedagainst an originating good of a Party which is an ASEANMember State, as long as its share of imports of the goodconcerned in the importing Party does not exceed three (3)per cent of the total imports from the other Parties,provided that those Parties with less than three (3) percent import share collectively account for not more thannine (9) per cent of total imports of the good concernedfrom the other Parties. 


4. A Party shall not apply an AJCEP safeguard measure toan originating good imported up to the limit of quotaquantities granted under tariff rate quotas applied inaccordance with its Schedule in Annex 1. 


5. A Party applying an AJCEP safeguard measure may: 


(a) suspend the further reduction of any customs dutyon the originating good of the other Partiesprovided for under this Chapter; or 


(b) increase the customs duty on the originating goodof the other Parties to a level not to exceed the lesser of: 
(i) the applied most-favoured-nation rate(hereinafter referred to as “applied MFNrate”) on the good in effect on the day whenthe AJCEP safeguard measure is applied; and 

(ii) the applied MFN rate on the good in effecton the day immediately preceding the date ofentry into force of this Agreement pursuantto paragraph 1 of Article 79. 

6. 	(a) A Party may apply an AJCEP safeguard measure only after an investigation has been carried out bythe competent authorities of that Party inaccordance with the same procedures as thoseprovided for in Article 3 and paragraph 2 ofArticle 4 of the Agreement on Safeguards. 

(b) The investigation referred to in subparagraph (a)shall be completed within one (1) year followingits date of initiation. 

7. The following conditions and limitations shall applywith regard to an AJCEP safeguard measure: 


(a) A Party shall immediately give a written noticeto the other Parties upon: 

(i) initiating an investigation referred to insubparagraph 6(a) relating to seriousinjury, or threat of serious injury, and thereasons for it; 

(ii) making a finding of serious injury or threatof serious injury caused by increasedimports; and 

(iii) taking a decision to apply or extend anAJCEP safeguard measure. 

(b) The Party giving the written notice referred toin subparagraph (a) shall provide the otherParties with all pertinent information, whichshall include: 

(i) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraph (a)(i), the reason for theinitiation of the investigation, a precisedescription of an originating good subjectto the investigation and its heading orsubheading of the Harmonized System, onwhich the Schedules in Annex 1 are based,the period subject to the investigation andthe date of initiation of the investigation;and 

(ii) 	in the written notice referred to in subparagraphs (a)(ii) and (iii), theevidence of serious injury or threat ofserious injury caused by the increasedimports of the originating good, a precisedescription of the originating good subjectto the proposed safeguard measure and itsheading or subheading of the HarmonizedSystem, on which the Schedules in Annex 1are based, a precise description of theAJCEP safeguard measure, the proposed dateof its introduction and its expectedduration. 

(c) A Party proposing to apply or extend an AJCEPsafeguard measure shall provide adequateopportunity for prior consultations with thoseParties which would be affected by the AJCEPsafeguard measure with a view to reviewing theinformation arising from the investigationreferred to in subparagraph (a), exchanging viewson the AJCEP safeguard measure and reaching anagreement on compensation set out in paragraph 8. 


(d) No AJCEP safeguard measure shall be maintainedexcept to the extent and for such time as may benecessary to prevent or remedy serious injury andto facilitate adjustment, provided that such timeshall not exceed a period of three (3) years. An AJCEP safeguard measure may be extended, providedthat the conditions set out in this Article are met. The total duration of the AJCEP safeguardmeasure, including any extensions thereof, shallnot exceed four (4) years. In order to facilitate adjustment in a situation where theexpected duration of an AJCEP safeguard measureis over one (1) year, the Party maintaining theAJCEP safeguard measure shall progressivelyliberalise the AJCEP safeguard measure at regularintervals during the period of application. 


(e) No AJCEP safeguard measure shall be applied againto the import of a particular originating goodwhich has been subject to such an AJCEP safeguardmeasure, for a period of time equal to theduration of the previous safeguard measure or one

(1) year, whichever is longer. 

(f) Upon the termination of an AJCEP safeguardmeasure on a good, the rate of the customs dutyfor that good shall be the rate that, inaccordance with the Schedule of the Partyapplying the AJCEP safeguard measure set out inAnnex 1, would have been in effect had the AJCEPsafeguard measure not been applied. 

8. 	(a) A Party proposing to apply or extend an AJCEP safeguard measure shall provide to the otherParties mutually agreed adequate means of tradecompensation in the form of substantiallyequivalent level of concessions or otherobligations to that existing under this Agreementbetween the Party applying the AJCEP safeguardmeasure and the exporting Parties which would beaffected by such a measure. 


(b) In seeking compensation provided for insubparagraph (a), the Parties shall holdconsultations in the Joint Committee. Anyproceedings arising from such consultations shallbe completed within thirty (30) days from thedate on which the AJCEP safeguard measure wasapplied. 


(c) If no agreement on the compensation is reachedwithin the time frame specified in subparagraph(b), the Parties other than the one applying theAJCEP safeguard measure shall be free to suspendconcessions of customs duties under this Agreement, which is substantially equivalent tothe AJCEP safeguard measure, on originating goodsof the Party applying the AJCEP safeguardmeasure. The Parties may suspend the concessionsonly for the minimum period necessary to achievethe substantially equivalent effects and onlywhile the AJCEP safeguard measure is maintained.The right of suspension provided for in thissubparagraph shall not be exercised for the firsttwo (2) years that an AJCEP safeguard measure isin effect, provided that the AJCEP safeguardmeasure has been applied as a result of anabsolute increase in imports and that such anAJCEP safeguard measure conforms to theprovisions of this Article. 

9. 	(a) A Party applying a safeguard measure in connection with an importation of an originatinggood of another Party in accordance with ArticleXIX of GATT 1994 and the Agreement on Safeguards,or Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture,shall not apply the AJCEP safeguard measure tothat importation. 

(b) The period of application of the AJCEP safeguardmeasure referred to in subparagraph 7(d) shallnot be interrupted by the Party’s non-applicationof the AJCEP safeguard measure in accordance withsubparagraph (a). 

10. 	(a) Within ten (10) years after the entry into force of this Agreement pursuant to paragraph 1 ofArticle 79, the Parties shall review this Articlewith a view to determining whether there is aneed to maintain the AJCEP safeguard mechanism. 

(b) If the Parties do not agree to remove the AJCEPsafeguard mechanism during the review pursuant tosubparagraph (a), the Parties shall thereafterconduct reviews to determine the necessity of theAJCEP safeguard mechanism, in conjunction withthe general review pursuant to Article 75. 

11. 	(a) In critical circumstances, where delay would cause damage which it would be difficult torepair, a Party may apply a provisional AJCEPsafeguard measure, which shall take the form ofthe measure set out in subparagraph 5(a) or 5(b),pursuant to a preliminary determination thatthere is clear evidence that increased imports ofan originating good have caused or arethreatening to cause serious injury to a domesticindustry. 


(b) A Party shall give a written notice to the otherParties prior to applying a provisional AJCEPsafeguard measure. Consultations by the Parties in the Joint Committee on the application of theprovisional AJCEP safeguard measure shall beinitiated immediately after the provisional AJCEPsafeguard measure is applied. 


(c) The duration of a provisional AJCEP safeguardmeasure shall not exceed two hundred (200) days.During that period, the pertinent requirements ofparagraph 6 shall be met. The duration of the provisional AJCEP safeguard measure shall becounted as a part of the period referred to insubparagraph 7(d). 


(d) Paragraph 3 and subparagraph 7(f) shall apply,mutatis mutandis, to the provisional AJCEPsafeguard measure. 


(e) The customs duty imposed as a result of theprovisional AJCEP safeguard measure shall berefunded if the subsequent investigation referredto in subparagraph 6(a) does not determine thatincreased imports of the originating good havecaused or threatened to cause serious injury to adomestic industry. 

12. All official communications and documentations exchanged among the Parties relating to an AJCEP safeguardmeasure shall be in writing and shall be in the Englishlanguage.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Measures To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="13943">Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to preventa Party from taking any measure for balance-of-paymentspurposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in accordance with the conditions established under Article XII of GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Balance-of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement on Tariffs andTrade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Customs Procedures" article_identifier="13944">1. Each Party shall endeavour to apply its customsprocedures in a predictable, consistent and transparentmanner. 


2. Recognising the importance of improving transparencyin the area of customs procedures, each Party, subject toits laws and regulations, and available resources, shallendeavour to provide information relating to specificmatters raised by interested persons of the Partiespertaining to its customs laws. Each Party shall endeavour to supply not only such information but also otherpertinent information which it considers the interestedpersons should be made aware of. 


3. For prompt customs clearance of goods traded among theParties, each Party, recognising the significant role ofcustoms authorities and the importance of customsprocedures in promoting trade facilitation, shall endeavourto: 


(a) simplify its customs procedures; and 


(b) harmonise its customs procedures, to the extentpossible, with relevant international standardsand recommended practices such as those madeunder the auspices of the Customs Co-operationCouncil.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="1682">
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13945">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “exporter” means a natural or juridical personlocated in an exporting Party who exports a goodfrom the exporting Party; 


(b) “factory ships of the Party” or “vessels of theParty” respectively means factory ships orvessels: 

(i) which are registered in the Party; 

(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; 

(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least fifty (50) per cent by nationals of one ormore of the Parties, or by a juridicalperson with its head office in a Party, ofwhich the representatives, chairman of theboard of directors, and the majority of themembers of such board are nationals of one or more of the Parties, and of which atleast fifty (50) per cent of the equityinterest is owned by nationals or juridicalpersons of one or more of the Parties; and 

(iv) of which at least seventy-five (75) per centof the total of the master, officers andcrew are nationals of one or more of the Parties; 

(c) “generally accepted accounting principles” meansthe recognised consensus or substantialauthoritative support in a Party, with respect tothe recording of revenues, expenses, costs,assets and liabilities; the disclosure ofinformation; and the preparation of financialstatements. These standards may encompass broadguidelines of general application as well asdetailed standards, practices and procedures; 


(d) “good” means any merchandise, product, article ormaterial; 


(e) “identical and interchangeable materials” meansmaterials being of the same kind and commercialquality, possessing the same technical andphysical characteristics, and which once they areincorporated into the good cannot bedistinguished from one another for originpurposes by virtue of any markings; 


(f) “importer” means a natural or juridical personwho imports a good into the importing Party; 


(g) “materials” means any matter or substance used orconsumed in the production of a good, physicallyincorporated into a good, or used in theproduction of another good; 


(h) “originating good” or “originating material”means a good or material that qualifies asoriginating in accordance with the provisions ofthis Chapter; 


(i) “packing materials and containers fortransportation and shipment” means the goods usedto protect a good during its transportation andshipment, different from those containers ormaterials used for its retail sale; 


(j) “preferential tariff treatment” means the rate ofcustoms duties applicable to an originating goodof the exporting Party in accordance withparagraph 1 of Article 16; and 


(k) “production” means methods of obtaining a goodincluding growing, mining, harvesting, raising,breeding, extracting, gathering, collecting,capturing, fishing, trapping, hunting,manufacturing, processing or assembling.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="13946">For the purposes of this Agreement, a good shallqualify as an originating good of a Party if it: 


(a) is wholly obtained or produced entirely in theParty as provided for in Article 25; 


(b) satisfies the requirements of Article 26 whenusing non-originating materials; or 


(c) is produced entirely in the Party exclusivelyfrom originating materials of one or more of theParties, 
and meets all other applicable requirements of thisChapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Goods Wholly Obtained Or Produced" article_identifier="13947">For the purposes of paragraph (a) of Article 24, thefollowing shall be considered as wholly obtained orproduced entirely in a Party: 


(a) plant and plant products grown and harvested,picked or gathered in the Party; 

Note: 	For the purposes of this paragraph, theterm “plant” refers to all plant life,including fruit, flowers, vegetables,trees, seaweed, fungi and live plants. 

(b) live animals born and raised in the Party; 

Note: 	For the purposes of paragraphs (b) and(c), the term “animals” covers all animallife, including mammals, birds, fish,crustaceans, molluscs, reptiles, bacteriaand viruses. 

(c) goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 


(d) goods obtained from hunting, trapping, fishing,gathering or capturing conducted in the Party; 


(e) minerals and other naturally occurringsubstances, not included in paragraphs (a)through (d), extracted or taken from soil,waters, seabed or beneath the seabed of theParty; 


(f) goods taken from the waters, seabed or beneaththe seabed outside the territorial waters of the Party, provided that the Party has the rights toexploit such waters, seabed and beneath theseabed in accordance with its laws and regulations and international law; 

Note: 	Nothing in this Agreement shall affect therights and obligations of the Partiesunder international law, including thoseunder the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. 

(g) goods of sea-fishing and other marine productstaken by vessels of the Party from outside theterritorial sea of any Party; 


(h) goods processed and/or made on board factoryships of the Party exclusively from productsreferred to in paragraph (g); 


(i) articles collected in the Party which can nolonger perform their original purpose or berestored or repaired, and are fit only fordisposal, for the recovery of parts or rawmaterials, or for recycling purposes; 


(j) scrap and waste derived from manufacturing orprocessing operations, including mining,agriculture, construction, refining, incinerationand sewage treatment operations, or fromconsumption, in the Party, and fit only fordisposal or for the recovery of raw materials;and 


(k) goods obtained or produced in the Partyexclusively from goods referred to in paragraphs
(a) through (j).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Goods Not Wholly Obtained Or Produced" article_identifier="13948">1. For the purposes of paragraph (b) of Article 24, agood shall qualify as an originating good of a Party if: 


(a) the good has a regional value content(hereinafter referred to as “RVC”), calculatedusing the formula set out in Article 27, of notless than forty (40) per cent, and the finalprocess of production has been performed in theParty; or 


(b) all non-originating materials used in theproduction of the good have undergone in theParty a change in tariff classification(hereinafter referred to as “CTC”) at the 4-digitlevel (i.e. a change in tariff heading) ofHarmonized System. 
Note: 	For the purposes of this subparagraph,“Harmonized System” is that on which theproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2are based. 

Each Party shall permit the exporter of the good todecide whether to use subparagraph (a) or (b) whendetermining whether the good qualifies as an originatinggood of the Party. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, a good subject to productspecific rules shall qualify as an originating good if itsatisfies the applicable product specific rules set out inAnnex 2. Where a product specific rule provides a choiceof rules from a RVC-based rule of origin, a CTC-based ruleof origin, a specific manufacturing or processingoperation, or a combination of any of these, each Partyshall permit the exporter of the good to decide which ruleto use in determining whether the good qualifies as anoriginating good of the Party. 


3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a) and the relevantproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2 which specify acertain RVC, it is required that the RVC of a good,calculated using the formula set out in Article 27, is notless than the percentage specified by the rule for thegood. 


4. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(b) and the relevantproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2, the rulesrequiring that the materials used have undergone CTC, or aspecific manufacturing or processing operation, shall applyonly to non-originating materials. 


5. For the purposes of this Chapter, Annex 3 shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Calculation Of Regional Value Content" article_identifier="13949">1. For the purposes of calculating the RVC of a good, thefollowing formula shall be used: 

                             FOB - VNM RVC = --------------- X 100 % FOB 

2. For the purposes of this Article: 


(a) “FOB” is, except as provided for in paragraph 3,the free-on-board value of a good, inclusive ofthe cost of transport from the producer to theport or site of final shipment abroad; 


(b) “RVC” is the RVC of a good, expressed as apercentage; and 


(c) “VNM” is the value of non-originating materialsused in the production of a good. 

3. FOB referred to in subparagraph 2(a) shall be thevalue: 


(a) adjusted to the first ascertainable price paidfor a good from the buyer to the producer of thegood, if there is free-on-board value of thegood, but it is unknown and cannot beascertained; or 


(b) determined in accordance with Articles 1 through8 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if thereis no free-on-board value of a good. 

4. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the value of non-originating materials used in the production of a good in aParty: 


(a) 	shall be determined in accordance with the Agreement on Customs Valuation and shall includefreight, insurance, and where appropriate,packing and all other costs incurred intransporting the material to the importation portin the Party where the producer of the good islocated; or 


(b) 	if such value is unknown and cannot be ascertained, shall be the first ascertainableprice paid for the material in the Party, but mayexclude all the costs incurred in the Party intransporting the material from the warehouse ofthe supplier of the material to the place wherethe producer is located such as freight,insurance and packing as well as any other knownand ascertainable cost incurred in the Party. 

5. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the VNM of a goodshall not include the value of non-originating materialsused in the production of originating materials of theParty which are used in the production of the good. 


6. For the purposes of subparagraph 3(b) or 4(a), inapplying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to determinethe value of a good or non-originating material, theAgreement on Customs Valuation shall apply, mutatis mutandis, to domestic transactions or to the cases wherethere is no domestic transaction of the good or non-originating material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="13950">1. A good that does not satisfy the requirements ofsubparagraph 1(b) of Article 26 or an applicable CTC-basedrule of origin set out in Annex 2 shall be considered as anoriginating good of a Party if: 


(a) in the case of a good classified under Chapters16, 19, 20, 22, 23, 28 through 49, and 64 through97 of the Harmonized System, the total value ofnon-originating materials used in the productionof the good that have not undergone the requiredCTC does not exceed ten (10) per cent of the FOB; 


(b) in the case of a particular good classified underChapters 18 and 21 of the Harmonized System, thetotal value of non-originating materials used inthe production of the good that have notundergone the required CTC does not exceed ten

(10) per cent or seven (7) per cent of the FOB,as specified in Annex 2; or 

(c) in the case of a good classified under Chapters50 through 63 of the Harmonized System, theweight of all non-originating materials used inthe production of the good that have notundergone the required CTC does not exceed ten
(10) per cent of the total weight of the good, 

provided that it meets all other applicable criteria setout in this Chapter for qualifying as an originating good. 

Note: 	For the purposes of this paragraph, subparagraph2(a) of Article 27 shall apply. 

2. The value of non-originating materials referred to inparagraph 1 shall, however, be included in the value ofnon-originating materials for any applicable RVC-based ruleof origin for the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="13951">Originating materials of a Party used in theproduction of a good in another Party shall be consideredas originating materials of that Party where the working orprocessing of the good has taken place.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="13952">A good shall not be considered to satisfy therequirements of CTC or specific manufacturing or processingoperation merely by reason of: 


(a) operations to ensure the preservation of productsin good condition during transport and storage(such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine) andother similar operations; 


(b) changes of packaging and breaking up and assemblyof packages; 


(c) disassembly; 


(d) placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simplepackaging operations; 


(e) collection of parts and components classified asa good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rulesfor the Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 


(f) mere making-up of sets of articles; or 


(g) any combination of operations referred to insubparagraphs (a) through (f).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Direct Consignment" article_identifier="13953">1. Preferential tariff treatment shall be accorded to an originating good satisfying the requirements of thisChapter and which is consigned directly from the exportingParty to the importing Party. 


2. The following shall be considered as consigneddirectly from the exporting Party to the importing Party: 


(a) a good transported directly from the exportingParty to the importing Party; or 


(b) a good transported through one or more Parties,other than the exporting Party and the importingParty, or through a non-Party, provided that thegood does not undergo operations other thantransit or temporary storage in warehouses,unloading, reloading, and any other operation topreserve it in good condition.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Packing Materials And Containers" article_identifier="13954">1. Packing materials and containers for transportationand shipment of a good shall not be taken into account indetermining the origin of any good. 


2. Packing materials and containers in which a good ispackaged for retail sale, when classified together with thegood, shall not be taken into account in determiningwhether all of the non-originating materials used in theproduction of the good have met the applicable CTC-basedrule of origin for the good. 


3. If a good is subject to a RVC-based rule of origin,the value of the packing materials and containers in whichthe good is packaged for retail sale shall be taken intoaccount as originating or non-originating materials, as thecase may be, in calculating the RVC of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Accessories, Spare Parts, Tools And Instructional Or Other Information Materials" article_identifier="13955">1. If a good is subject to the requirements of CTC orspecific manufacturing or processing operation, the originof accessories, spare parts, tools and instructional orother information materials presented with the good shallnot be taken into account in determining whether the goodqualifies as an originating good, provided that: 


(a) the accessories, spare parts, tools andinstructional or other information materials are not invoiced separately from the good; and 


(b) the quantities and value of the accessories,spare parts, tools and instructional or otherinformation materials are customary for the good. 
2. If a good is subject to a RVC-based rule of origin,the value of the accessories, spare parts, tools andinstructional or other information materials shall be taken into account as the value of the originating or non-originating materials, as the case may be, in calculatingthe RVC of the originating goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="13956">1. Indirect materials shall be treated as originatingmaterials regardless of where they are produced. 


2. For the purposes of this Article, the term “indirectmaterials” means goods used in the production, testing, orinspection of a good but not physically incorporated intothe good, or goods used in the maintenance of buildings orthe operation of equipment associated with the productionof a good, including: 


(a) fuel and energy; 


(b) tools, dies and moulds; 


(c) spare parts and materials used in the maintenanceof equipment and buildings; 


(d) lubricants, greases, compounding materials andother materials used in production or used tooperate equipment and buildings; 


(e) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safetyequipment and supplies; 


(f) equipment, devices and supplies used for testingor inspecting the good; 


(g) catalysts and solvents; and 


(h) any other goods that are not incorporated intothe good but whose use in the production of thegood can reasonably be demonstrated to be a partof that production.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Identical And Interchangeable Materials" article_identifier="13957">The determination of whether identical and interchangeable materials are originating materials shallbe made by the use of generally accepted accountingprinciples of stock control applicable, or those ofinventory management practised, in the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Operational Certification Procedures" article_identifier="13958">The operational certification procedures, as set outin Annex 4, shall apply with respect to proceduresregarding certificate of origin and related matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="13959">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Rules ofOrigin (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

11. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be to: 


(a) review and make appropriate recommendations, asneeded, to the Joint Committee on: 

(i) the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 

(ii) any amendments to Annexes 2 and 3, andAttachment to Annex 4, proposed by anyParty; and 

(iii) the Implementing Regulations referred to inRule 11 of Annex 4; 

(b) consider any other matter as the Parties mayagree related to this Chapter; 


(c) report the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; and 


(d) carry out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representativesof the Governments of the Parties, and may inviterepresentatives of relevant entities other than theGovernments of the Parties with necessary expertiserelevant to the issues to be discussed, upon agreement ofall the Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="1683">
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Scope" article_identifier="13960">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary andphytosanitary (hereinafter referred to as “SPS”) measuresof the Parties as defined in Annex A of the Agreement onthe Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as“SPS Agreement”) that may, directly or indirectly, affecttrade between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="13961">The Parties reaffirm the rights and obligationsrelating to SPS measures under the SPS Agreement amongthose Parties that are parties to the said Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Sub-Committee On Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="13962">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Sanitary andPhytosanitary Measures (hereinafter referred to in thisArticle as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be establishedpursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be to: 


(a) exchange information on such matters asoccurrences of SPS incidents in the Parties and non-Parties, and change or introduction of SPS-related regulations and standards of the Parties,which may, directly or indirectly, affect tradebetween Japan and more than one (1) ASEAN MemberState which are the Parties; 


(b) facilitate cooperation in the area of SPSmeasures, including capacity building, technicalassistance and exchange of experts, subject tothe availability of appropriated funds and theapplicable laws and regulations of each Party; 


(c) undertake science-based consultations to identifyand address specific issues that may arise fromthe application of SPS measures and are shared byJapan and more than one (1) ASEAN Member Statewhich are the Parties; 


(d) review the implementation and operation of thisChapter; and 


(e) report, where appropriate, its findings to theJoint Committee. 

3. The Parties shall coordinate their undertakings withthe activities conducted in the bilateral, regional andmultilateral context, with the objective of avoidingunnecessary duplication and maximising efficiency ofefforts of the Parties in this field. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


5. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of government officials of the Partieswith responsibility for SPS measures; and 


(b) co-chaired by an official of the Government ofJapan and an official of one of the Governmentsof the ASEAN Member States which are the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="13963">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point to answerall reasonable enquiries from another Party regarding SPSmeasures and, if appropriate, provide the latter withrelevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 9" article_identifier="13964">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 9 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Standards, Technical Regulations And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="1684">
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Objectives" article_identifier="13965">The objectives of this Chapter are to promote tradeamong the Parties by: 


(a) ensuring that standards, technical regulationsand conformity assessment procedures do notcreate unnecessary obstacles to trade; 


(b) promoting mutual understanding of the standards,technical regulations and conformity assessmentprocedures in each Party; 


(c) strengthening information exchange andcooperation among the Parties in relation to thepreparation, adoption and application ofstandards, technical regulations and conformityassessment procedures; 


(d) strengthening cooperation among the Parties inthe work of international bodies related to standardisation and conformity assessments; and 


(e) providing a framework to realise these
objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Scope" article_identifier="13966">1. This Chapter shall apply to standards, technicalregulations and conformity assessment procedures as definedin the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1Ato the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “TBTAgreement”). 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to purchasingspecifications prepared by governmental bodies forproduction or consumption requirements of governmentalbodies and sanitary and phytosanitary measures as definedin Annex A of the SPS Agreement. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall limit the right of aParty to prepare, adopt and apply standards and technicalregulations, to the extent necessary, to fulfil alegitimate objective. Such legitimate objectives are, inter alia, national security requirements; the preventionof deceptive practices; protection of human health orsafety, animal or plant life or health, or the environment.In pursuance of this, each Party retains all authority tointerpret its laws, regulations and administrativeprovisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="13967">The Parties reaffirm the rights and obligationsrelating to standards, technical regulations and conformityassessment procedures under the TBT Agreement among thoseParties that are parties to the said Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="13968">1. For the purposes of ensuring that standards, technicalregulations and conformity assessment procedures do notcreate unnecessary obstacles to trade in goods among theParties, the Parties shall, where possible, cooperate inthe field of standards, technical regulations andconformity assessment procedures. 


2. The forms of cooperation pursuant to paragraph 1 mayinclude the following: 


(a) conducting joint studies and holding seminars, inorder to enhance mutual understanding ofstandards, technical regulations and conformityassessment procedures in each Party; 


(b) exchanging information on standards, technicalregulations and conformity assessment procedures; 


(c) developing and implementing joint programmes forbuilding and/or upgrading capacity in the Partiesfor advancement of activities within the scope ofthe TBT Agreement; 


(d) encouraging the bodies responsible for standards,technical regulations and conformity assessmentprocedures in each Party to cooperate on mattersof mutual interest; 


(e) contributing, where appropriate, jointly to theactivities related to standards, technicalregulations and conformity assessment proceduresin international and regional fora; and 


(f) jointly identifying work in the field ofstandards, technical regulations and conformityassessment procedures, where appropriate, toavoid unnecessary obstacle to trade among theParties. 

3. The implementation of this Article shall be subject tothe availability of appropriated funds and the applicablelaws and regulations of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="13969">1. Each Party shall designate an enquiry point whichshall have the responsibility to coordinate theimplementation of this Chapter. 


2. Each Party shall provide the other Parties with thename of its designated enquiry point and the contactdetails of relevant officials in that organisationincluding information on telephone, facsimile and e-mailand other relevant details. 


3. Each Party shall notify the other Parties promptly ofany change of its enquiry point or any amendments to theinformation of the relevant officials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Sub-Committee On Standards, Technical Regulations And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="13970">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Standards,Technical Regulations and Conformity Assessment Procedures(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be to: 


(a) coordinate cooperation pursuant to Article 46; 


(b) identify mutually agreed priority sectors forenhanced cooperation, including giving favourableconsideration to any proposal made by a Party; 


(c) establish work programmes in mutually agreedpriority areas to facilitate the acceptance ofconformity assessment results and equivalence oftechnical regulations; 


(d) monitor the progress of work programmes; 


(e) review the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 


(f) facilitate technical consultations; 


(g) report, where appropriate, its findings to theJoint Committee; and 


(h) carry out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


4. The Parties shall coordinate their undertakings withthe activities conducted in the bilateral, regional andmultilateral context, with the objective of avoidingunnecessary duplication and maximising efficiency ofefforts of the Parties in this field. 


5. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of representatives of the Governments ofthe Parties; and 


(b) co-chaired by an official of the Government ofJapan and an official of one of the Governmentsof the ASEAN Member States, which are theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 9" article_identifier="13971">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 9 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="1685">
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Trade In Services" article_identifier="13972">1. Each Party shall endeavour to, in accordance with itslaws, regulations and policies, take further steps towardsthe expansion of trade in services among or between theParties consistent with GATS. 


2. The Parties shall, with the participation of Japan andall ASEAN Member States, continue to discuss and negotiateprovisions for trade in services with a view to exploringmeasures towards further liberalisation and facilitation of trade in services among Japan and ASEAN Member States andto enhance cooperation in order to improve the efficiencyand competitiveness of services and service suppliers ofJapan and the ASEAN Member States. For this purpose, a Sub-Committee on Trade in Services, which shall be composedof representatives of the Governments of Japan and allASEAN Member States, shall be established in accordancewith Article 11 within one (1) year from the date of entryinto force of this Agreement pursuant to paragraph 1 ofArticle 79. 


3. The results of the negotiations referred to inparagraph 2, if any, shall be incorporated into thisChapter in accordance with Article 77.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="1686">
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Investment" article_identifier="13973">1. Each Party shall endeavour to, in accordance with itslaws, regulations and policies, create and maintainfavourable and transparent conditions in the Party forinvestments of investors of the other Parties. 


2. The Parties shall, with the participation of Japan andall ASEAN Member States, continue to discuss and negotiateprovisions for investment, with a view to improving theefficiency and competitiveness of the investmentenvironment of Japan and ASEAN Member States throughprogressive liberalisation, promotion, facilitation andprotection of investment. For this purpose, a Sub-Committee on Investment, which shall be composed of therepresentatives of the Governments of Japan and all ASEANMember States, shall be established in accordance withArticle 11 within one (1) year from the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article
79. 

3. The results of the negotiations referred to inparagraph 2, if any, shall be incorporated into thisChapter in accordance with Article 77.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Economic Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1687">
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="13974">1. The Parties shall, subject to the availability ofresources as well as their respective applicable laws andregulations, promote cooperation under this Agreement fortheir mutual benefits in order to liberalise and facilitate trade and investment among the Parties and to promote thewell-being of the peoples of the Parties, taking intoaccount the different levels of economic development amongASEAN Member States. 


2. The Parties shall promote regional and sub-regionaldevelopment through economic cooperation activitiesincluding capacity building, technical assistance, andother such activities as may be mutually agreed upon amongthe Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Fields Of Economic Cooperation" article_identifier="13975">The Parties, on the basis of mutual benefit, shallexplore and undertake economic cooperation activities inthe following fields: 


(a) Trade-Related Procedures; 


(b) Business Environment; 


(c) Intellectual Property; 


(d) Energy; 


(e) Information and Communications Technology; 


(f) Human Resource Development; 


(g) Small and Medium Enterprises; 


(h) Tourism and Hospitality; 


(i) Transportation and Logistics; 


(j) Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry; 


(k) Environment; 


(l) Competition Policy; and 


(m) Other fields as may be mutually agreed upon amongthe Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Sub-Committee On Economic Cooperation" article_identifier="13976">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on EconomicCooperation (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established in accordancewith Article 11 on the date of entry into force of thisAgreement pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article 79. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be to: 


(a) modify and formulate relevant Work Programmessetting out areas and forms of each field ofeconomic cooperation; 


(b) make recommendations on existing and new economiccooperation activities under this Chapter inaccordance with the priorities of the Parties; 


(c) review and monitor the implementation andoperation of this Chapter and the application andfulfilment of its basic principles; and 


(d) report the findings and the outcome of itsdiscussions to the Joint Committee. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of representatives of the Governments ofJapan and all ASEAN Member States; and 


(b) co-chaired by an official of the Government ofJapan and an official of one of the Governmentsof ASEAN Member States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Work Programmes For Economic Cooperation" article_identifier="13977">1. Work Programmes setting out areas and forms of eachfield of cooperation activities shall be set forth in Annex

5. 

2. Any modification of existing Work Programmes orformulation of new Work Programmes shall be made inaccordance with paragraph 2 of Article 54 and throughamending Annex 5 pursuant to the procedures set out inArticle 77.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Resources For Economic Cooperation" article_identifier="13978">Taking into account the different levels of economicdevelopment and capacity among the Parties, resources foreconomic cooperation under this Chapter shall be providedin such a manner as may be mutually agreed upon among theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Implementation Of Economic Cooperation Activities" article_identifier="13979">1. Economic cooperation activities shall involve Japanand at least two (2) ASEAN Member States. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, economic cooperationactivities may also involve Japan and one (1) ASEAN MemberState, provided that those activities are regional innature and of benefit to other ASEAN Member States. Such activities shall aim at narrowing the gaps of economicdevelopment among ASEAN Member States or at promoting thewell-being of the people of ASEAN Member States towardsfurther integration of ASEAN. 


3. The Parties shall undertake economic cooperationactivities at mutually agreed time.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 9" article_identifier="13980">The dispute settlement procedures provided for inChapter 9 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Settlement Of Disputes" chapter_identifier="1688">
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13981">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “complaining party” means any Party or Partiesthat request consultations under paragraph 1 ofArticle 62; 


(b) “party to a dispute” means any Party which is acomplaining party or a party complained against; 


(c) “party complained against” means any Party orParties to which the request for consultations ismade under paragraph 1 of Article 62; and 


(d) “third party” means a Party, other than theparties to a dispute, that notifies its interestin writing in accordance with Article 66.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Scope Of Application" article_identifier="13982">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, thisChapter shall apply with respect to the settlement of alldisputes between the Parties concerning the interpretationor application of this Agreement. 


2. This Chapter may apply to measures affecting a Party’sobservance of this Agreement taken by regional or localgovernments or authorities within the Party. When the arbitral tribunal has awarded that a provision of thisAgreement has not been observed in accordance with Article67, the responsible Party shall take such reasonablemeasures as may be available to it to ensure itsobservance. Paragraphs 3 and 4 of Article 71 shall applyin cases where it has not been possible for the Party tosecure such observance. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights ofthe Parties to have recourse to dispute settlementprocedures available under any other internationalagreement to which all of the parties to a dispute areparties. 


4. Notwithstanding paragraph 3, once dispute settlementproceedings have been initiated under this Chapter or underany other international agreement to which all of theparties to a dispute are parties with respect to aparticular dispute, the forum selected by the complainingparty shall be used to the exclusion of any other fora forthat particular dispute. However, this shall not apply if substantially separate and distinct rights or obligationsunder different international agreements are in dispute. 


5. For the purposes of paragraphs 3 and 4, thecomplaining party shall be deemed to have selected a forumwhen it has requested the establishment of, or referred adispute to, an arbitral tribunal or a dispute settlementpanel, in accordance with this Chapter or any otherinternational agreement to which the parties to a disputeare parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="13983">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, a Party maydesignate a contact point responsible for communications onall matters referred to in this Chapter. The submission of any request, notice or other document under this Chapter tothe contact point so designated shall be deemed to havebeen made to that Party. 


2. Where a Party chooses not to designate a contact pointpursuant to paragraph 1, the submission of any request,notice or other document under this Chapter shall be madeto the contact point which the Party designates inaccordance with Article 12. 


3. Any Party receiving any request, notice or otherdocument under this Chapter shall acknowledge receipt inwriting.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Consultations" article_identifier="13984">1. A Party or Parties may make a request in writing forconsultations to other Party or Parties concerning anymatter on the interpretation or application of thisAgreement where the complaining party considers that anybenefit accruing to it under this Agreement is beingnullified or impaired as a result of the failure of theparty complained against to carry out its obligations underthis Agreement, or as a result of the application by theparty complained against of measures which are in conflictwith its obligations under this Agreement. 


2. Any request for consultations shall be submitted inwriting, containing the identification of the specificmeasures at issue and indication of the factual and legalbasis (including the provisions of this Agreement allegedto have been breached and any other relevant provisions) ofthe complaint. The complaining party shall at the same time notify the rest of the Parties thereof. 


3. Upon receipt of the request referred to in paragraph1, the party complained against shall promptly acknowledgereceipt of such request to the complaining party and therest of the Parties at the same time. 


4. If a request for consultations is made, the partycomplained against shall reply to the request within ten
(10) days after the date of receipt of the request andshall enter into consultations in good faith within aperiod of not more than thirty (30) days after the date ofreceipt of the request, with a view to reaching a mutuallysatisfactory solution. 


5. The parties to a dispute shall make every effort toreach a mutually satisfactory resolution of any matterthrough consultations under this Article. To this end, the parties to the dispute shall provide each other withsufficient information to enable a full examination of the dispute. 


6. Consultations shall be confidential between the parties to the dispute and are without prejudice to therights of any Party in any further proceedings under thisChapter or in other proceedings. The parties to the dispute shall inform the rest of the Parties of the outcomeof the consultations. 


7. In cases of urgency, including those which concernperishable goods, the parties to the dispute shall enterinto consultations within a period of no more than ten (10)days after the date of receipt of the request by the partycomplained against. 


8. In cases of urgency, including those which concernperishable goods, the parties to the dispute shall makeevery effort to accelerate the consultations to thegreatest extent possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Good Offices, Conciliation And Mediation" article_identifier="13985">1. Good offices, conciliation and mediation areprocedures that are undertaken voluntarily if the partiesto the dispute so agree. 


2. Good offices, conciliation or mediation may berequested at any time by any party to a dispute. They may begin at any time by agreement of the parties to thedispute and be terminated at any time upon the request ofany party to the dispute. 


3. If the parties to the dispute agree, good offices,conciliation or mediation may continue while theproceedings of the arbitral tribunal provided for in thisChapter are in progress. 


4. Proceedings involving good offices, conciliation ormediation, and, in particular, positions taken by theparties to the dispute during these proceedings, shall bekept confidential and without prejudice to the rights ofany Party in any proceedings under this Chapter or in otherproceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13986">1. The complaining party may request in writing, to theparty complained against, the establishment of an arbitraltribunal: 


(a) if the party complained against does not respondwithin ten (10) days, or does not enter into suchconsultations within thirty (30) days after thedate of receipt of the request for suchconsultations; or 


(b) if the parties to the dispute fail to resolve thedispute through such consultations within sixty


(60) days after the date of receipt of therequest for such consultations, or within twenty


(20) days after such date in cases of urgencyincluding those which concern perishable goods. 

2. A copy of the request referred to in paragraph 1 shallalso be communicated to the rest of the Parties. 


3. Where more than one (1) complaining party request theestablishment of an arbitral tribunal related to the same matter, a single arbitral tribunal may, whenever feasible,be established by the parties to the dispute to examine thematter, taking into account the rights of each party to thedispute. 


4. Where a single arbitral tribunal is establishedpursuant to paragraph 3, the arbitral tribunal shallorganise its examination and present its findings to allthe parties to the dispute in such a manner that the rightswhich the parties to the dispute would have enjoyed hadseparate arbitral tribunals examined the same matter are inno way impaired. If any of the parties to the dispute so requests, the arbitral tribunal may make separate awards onthe dispute concerned as long as the timeframe for makingthe awards so permits. The written submissions by a party to the dispute shall be made available to the other partiesto the dispute, and each party to the dispute shall havethe right to be present when any other party to the disputepresents its views to the arbitral tribunal. 


5. Where more than one (1) arbitral tribunal areestablished to examine the dispute related to the samematter, to the greatest extent possible, the same personsshall be appointed by the parties to the disputes to serveon each of the separate arbitral tribunals. 


6. Any request for the establishment of an arbitraltribunal shall indicate whether consultations under Article 62 have been held, identify the factual basis for thecomplaint including the specific measures at issue andprovide the legal basis of the complaint including theprovisions of this Agreement alleged to have been breachedand any other relevant provisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Composition Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13987">1. An arbitral tribunal shall consist of three (3)arbitrators. 


2. The complaining party and the party complained againstshall, within thirty (30) days after the date of receipt ofthe request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,each appoint one (1) arbitrator who may be a national ofany party to the dispute and propose up to three (3)candidates to serve as the third arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. The third arbitrator shall not be a national of any party to the dispute, norhave his or her usual place of residence in any party tothe dispute, nor be employed by any party to the dispute,nor have dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 


3. The complaining party and the party complained againstshall agree on and appoint the third arbitrator withinforty-five (45) days after the date of receipt of therequest for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,taking into account the candidates proposed pursuant toparagraph 2. If either the complaining party or the party complained against has not appointed an arbitrator pursuantto paragraph 2, or if the parties to the dispute fail toagree on and appoint the third arbitrator pursuant to thisparagraph, the Director-General of the World TradeOrganization shall immediately be requested to make thenecessary appointments. In the event that the Director-General is a national of any party to the dispute, theDeputy Director-General or the officer next in senioritywho is not a national of any party to the dispute shall berequested to make the necessary appointments. Appointments made pursuant to this paragraph other than that of thethird arbitrator shall be deemed to have been made by thecomplaining party or the party complained against which hasfailed to make such an appointment. 


4. The date of establishment of an arbitral tribunal shall be the date on which the third arbitrator is appointed pursuant to paragraph 3. 


5. If an arbitrator appointed under this Article resignsor becomes unable to act, a succeeding arbitrator shall beappointed in the same manner as prescribed for theappointment of the original arbitrator and the succeedingarbitrator shall have all the powers and duties of theoriginal arbitrator. The work of the arbitral tribunal shall be suspended until the succeeding arbitrator isappointed. 


6. Any person appointed as an arbitrator shall haveexpertise or experience in law, international trade, othermatters covered by this Agreement or the resolution ofdisputes arising under international trade agreements. An arbitrator shall be chosen strictly on the basis ofobjectivity, reliability, sound judgment and independenceand shall conduct himself or herself on the same basis throughout the course of the arbitral tribunal proceedings.If a party to the dispute believes that an arbitrator isnot adhering to the basis stated above, the parties to thedispute shall consult and if they agree, the arbitratorshall be removed and a new arbitrator shall be appointed inaccordance with this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Third Parties" article_identifier="13988">1. Any Party having a substantial interest in a disputebefore an arbitral tribunal and having notified itsinterest in writing to the parties to the dispute and therest of the Parties shall have an opportunity to makewritten submissions to the arbitral tribunal. These submissions shall also be given to the parties to thedispute and may be reflected in the award of the arbitraltribunal. 


2. A third party shall receive the submissions of theparties to the dispute to the first meeting of the arbitraltribunal. 


3. If a third party considers that a measure that isalready the subject of any arbitral tribunal proceedingsnullifies or impairs benefits accruing to it under thisAgreement, such third party may have recourse to normaldispute settlement procedures under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13989">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article

64: 


(a) should make an objective assessment of the matterbefore it, including an examination of the factsof the case and the applicability of andconformity with the Agreement; 


(b) should consult with the parties to the dispute asappropriate and provide them with adequateopportunities for the development of a mutuallysatisfactory resolution; 


(c) 	shall make its award in accordance with this Agreement and applicable rules of internationallaw; 


(d) shall set out, in its award, its findings of lawand fact, together with the reasons therefor; 


(e) may, apart from giving its findings, include inits award suggested implementation options forthe parties to the dispute to consider inconjunction with Article 71; and 


(f) cannot, in its award, add to or diminish therights and obligations of any Party provided inthis Agreement. 

2. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Parties, suchrelevant information as it considers necessary andappropriate. The Parties shall respond promptly and fully to any request by the arbitral tribunal for suchinformation. 


3. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from anyrelevant source and may consult experts to obtain theiropinion on certain aspects of the matter. With respect to factual issues concerning a scientific or other technicalmatter raised by any party to the dispute, the arbitraltribunal may request advisory reports in writing fromexperts. The arbitral tribunal may, at the request of any party to the dispute or on its own initiative, select, inconsultation with the parties to the dispute, no fewer thantwo (2) scientific or technical experts who shall assistthe arbitral tribunal throughout its proceedings, but whoshall not have the right to vote in respect of any decisionto be made by the arbitral tribunal, including its award.Any information and technical advice so obtained shall bemade available to the parties to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13990">1. The rules and procedures as set out in this Articleshall apply to the proceedings of an arbitral tribunal. 


2. The parties to the dispute, in consultation with thearbitral tribunal, may agree to adopt additional rules andprocedures not inconsistent with the provisions of thisArticle. 
Terms of Reference for Arbitral Tribunals 

3. An arbitral tribunal shall have the following terms ofreference: 

"To examine, in the light of (the relevant provisionsin this Agreement to be cited by the parties to thedispute), the matter referred to in the request forthe establishment of an arbitral tribunal pursuant toArticle 64, and to issue awards including findings,determinations and suggested implementation options,if any, as provided for in Article 67.” 

Written Submissions and Other Documents 


4. Each party to the dispute shall deliver to the otherparties to the dispute a copy of its written submissions tothe arbitral tribunal. 


5. In respect of any request, notice or other documentsrelated to the arbitral tribunal proceedings that is notcovered by paragraph 4, each party to the dispute maydeliver a copy of the documents to the other parties to thedispute by facsimile, e-mail or other means of electronictransmission. 


6. Any party to the dispute may at any time correct minorerrors of a clerical nature in any request, notice, writtensubmission or other documents related to the arbitral tribunal proceedings by delivering a new document clearlyindicating the changes. 
Timetable 

7. After consulting the parties to the dispute, thearbitral tribunal shall as soon as practicable and wheneverpossible within seven (7) days after the establishment ofthe arbitral tribunal, fix the timetable for the arbitraltribunal process. The timetable fixed for the arbitral tribunal shall include precise deadlines for writtensubmissions by the parties to the dispute. Modifications to such timetable may be made by the agreement of theparties to the dispute in consultation with the arbitraltribunal. 

Operation of Arbitral Tribunals 


8. An arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. The parties to the dispute shall be present at the meetingsonly when invited by the arbitral tribunal to appear beforeit. 


9. All third parties which have notified their interestin the dispute shall be invited in writing to present theirviews during a session of the first meeting of the arbitral tribunal proceedings set aside for that purpose.All such third parties may be present during the entiretyof this session. 


10. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 


11. Notwithstanding paragraph 10, any party to the disputemay make public statements of its positions and its viewsregarding the dispute, but shall treat as confidential,information and written submissions made by the otherparties to the dispute to the arbitral tribunal which theother parties to the dispute have designated asconfidential. Where a party to the dispute submits aconfidential version of its written submissions to the arbitral tribunal, it shall also, upon request of anotherparty to the dispute, provide a non-confidential summary ofthe information or written submissions which may bedisclosed publicly. 


12. The venue for the arbitral tribunal proceedings shallbe decided by mutual agreement between the complainingparty and the party complained against. If there is no agreement, the venue shall alternate among the capitals ofthe parties to the dispute with the first meeting of thearbitral tribunal proceedings to be held in one (1) of thecapitals of the party complained against. 


13. The parties to the dispute shall be given theopportunity to attend any of the presentations, statementsor rebuttals in the proceedings. Any information provided and written submissions made to the arbitral tribunal by aparty to the dispute, including any comments on thedescriptive part of the draft award and responses toquestions put by the arbitral tribunal, shall be madeavailable to the other parties to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Draft Award And Award" article_identifier="13991">1. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted without the presence of the parties to the dispute and inthe light of the information provided and the statementsmade in the proceedings. Opinions expressed in the award of the arbitral tribunal by its individual arbitrator shallbe anonymous. 


2. The arbitral tribunal shall, within ninety (90) daysafter the date of its establishment, issue to the partiesto the dispute its draft award including both thedescriptive part and its findings and conclusions for thepurposes of enabling the parties to the dispute to reviewprecise aspects of the draft award. 


3. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot issue its draft award within the ninety (90) day periodreferred to in paragraph 2, it shall inform the parties tothe dispute in writing of the reasons for the delaytogether with the estimate of the period within which itwill issue its draft award. 


4. The parties to the dispute may submit comments inwriting to the arbitral tribunal on the draft award withinfifteen (15) days after the date of issuance of the draftaward. 


5. Where written comments by the parties to the disputeas provided for in paragraph 4 are received, the arbitraltribunal, on its own initiative or at the request of aparty to the dispute, may reconsider its award and make anyfurther examination that it considers appropriate. 


6. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award to the parties to the dispute within thirty (30) days after theissuance of the draft award. 


7. The arbitral tribunal shall make its decisions,including its award, by consensus, failing which it maymake its decisions by majority vote. 


8. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute. 


9. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be circulated to the Parties within ten (10) days after its issuance tothe parties to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Suspension And Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="13992">1. Where the parties to the dispute agree, the arbitraltribunal may suspend its work at any time for a period notexceeding twelve (12) months from the date of the jointnotification of such agreement to the chair of the arbitraltribunal by the parties to the dispute. Upon the request of any party to the dispute, the arbitral tribunalproceedings shall be resumed after such suspension. If the work of the arbitral tribunal has been suspended for morethan twelve (12) months, the authority of the arbitraltribunal shall lapse unless the parties to the disputeagree otherwise. 


2. The parties to the dispute may agree to terminate theproceedings of an arbitral tribunal at any time before theissuance of the award by jointly so notifying the chair ofthe arbitral tribunal. 


3. Before the arbitral tribunal issues its draft award,it may, at any stage of the proceedings, propose to theparties to the dispute that the dispute be settledamicably.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="13993">1. The party complained against shall promptly complywith the award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant toArticle 69. 


2. The party complained against shall, within twenty (20)days after the date of issuance of the award, notify thecomplaining party of the period of time in which toimplement the award. If the complaining party considers the period of time notified to be unacceptable, it mayrefer the matter to an arbitral tribunal which then determines the reasonable implementation period. The arbitral tribunal shall inform the parties to the disputeof its determination within thirty (30) days after the dateof the referral of the matter to it. 


3. If the party complained against considers itimpracticable to comply with the award within theimplementation period as determined pursuant to paragraph2, the party complained against shall, no later than theexpiry of that implementation period, enter intoconsultations with the complaining party, with a view todeveloping mutually satisfactory compensation. If no satisfactory compensation has been agreed within twenty
(20) days after the date of expiry of that implementationperiod, the complaining party may request an arbitraltribunal to determine the appropriate level of anysuspension of the application to the party complainedagainst of concessions or other obligations under thisAgreement. 


4. If the complaining party considers that the partycomplained against has failed to comply with the awardwithin the implementation period as determined pursuant toparagraph 2, the complaining party may refer the matter toan arbitral tribunal to confirm the failure and to determine the appropriate level of any suspension of theapplication to the party complained against of concessionsor other obligations under this Agreement. 


5. The arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall, wherever possible, have as its arbitrators, thearbitrators of the original arbitral tribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators of such arbitraltribunal shall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 2 and 3of Article 65. 


6. Unless the parties to the dispute agree to a differentperiod, the arbitral tribunal established under paragraphs3 and 4 shall issue its award within sixty (60) days afterthe date when the matter is referred to it. 


7. The award of the arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall be binding on all the parties to thedispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Compensation And The Suspension Of Concessions" article_identifier="13994">1. Compensation and the suspension of concessions orother obligations under this Agreement are temporarymeasures available in the event that the award is not implemented within a reasonable period of time. However, neither compensation nor the suspension of concessions orother obligations under this Agreement is preferred to fullimplementation of the award to bring a measure intoconformity with this Agreement. Compensation, if granted, shall be consistent with this Agreement. 


2. The application of concessions or other obligationsunder this Agreement shall not be suspended before thecommencement and during the course of the proceedings underparagraphs 3 and 4 of Article 71. 


3. The suspension of the application of concessions orother obligations under paragraphs 3 and 4 of Article 71may only be implemented after the complaining partynotifies the party complained against and the rest of theParties that the complaining party intends to suspend theapplication to the party complained against of concessionsor other obligations under this Agreement. The party complained against and the rest of the Parties shall beinformed of the commencement of the suspension and whichconcessions or other obligations under this Agreement wouldbe suspended. 


4. In considering what concessions or other obligationsunder this Agreement to be suspended under paragraphs 3 and4 of Article 71, such suspension shall: 


(a) be temporary, and be discontinued when theparties to the dispute reach a mutuallysatisfactory resolution or where compliance withthe award is effected; 


(b) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification or impairment that is attributable to the failureto comply with the award; and 


(c) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors as those in which the arbitral tribunal has found the nullification or impairment, unless it is notpracticable or effective to suspend theapplication of concessions or obligations in suchsector or sectors, in which case, the complainingparty may suspend concessions or benefits inother sectors under this Agreement. 

5. If the party complained against considers that thesuspension of concessions or other obligations under thisAgreement by the complaining party is inconsistent with theprovisions of paragraph 4, the matter shall be referred toan arbitral tribunal. For the purposes of the arbitraltribunal established under this Article, paragraph 5 ofArticle 71 shall apply, mutatis mutandis. 


6. Unless the parties to the dispute agree to a differentperiod, the arbitral tribunal established under thisArticle shall issue its award within sixty (60) days afterthe date when the matter is referred to it. Such award shall be binding on all the parties to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Expenses" article_identifier="13995">1. The complaining party and the party complained againstshall respectively bear the costs of the arbitrators whichthey appointed, and their own expenses and legal costs. 


2. Unless the parties to the dispute otherwise agree, thecosts of the chair of the arbitral tribunal and other expenses associated with the conduct of the proceedings ofthe arbitral tribunal shall be borne in equal parts by theparties to a dispute. 


3. The arbitral tribunal shall keep a record and render afinal account of all general expenses incurred inconnection with the proceedings, including those paid totheir assistants, designated note takers or otherindividuals that it retains.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1689">
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Table Of Contents, Headings And Subheadings" article_identifier="13996">The table of contents, headings and subheadings areinserted for convenience of reference only and shall notaffect the interpretation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Review" article_identifier="13997">The Parties shall undertake a general review of theimplementation and operation of this Agreement in the fifthcalendar year following the calendar year in which thisAgreement enters into force pursuant to paragraph 1 ofArticle 79, and every five (5) years thereafter, unlessotherwise agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="13998">The Annexes including attachment and Notes to thisAgreement shall form an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Amendments" article_identifier="13999">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement among theParties. 


2. The Government of each Party shall notify theGovernments of the other Parties in writing that its legalprocedures necessary for entry into force of the amendmenthave been completed. Such amendment shall enter into force on the first day of the second month following the date bywhich such notifications have been made by the Governmentsof Japan and at least one (1) ASEAN Member State, which isa Party, in relation to those Parties whose Governmentshave made such notifications by that date. 


3. Where an ASEAN Member State, which is a Party, makesthe notification referred to in paragraph 2 after the dateby which the notifications have been made by theGovernments of Japan and at least one (1) ASEAN MemberState, which is a Party, as referred to in paragraph 2, theamendment referred to in paragraph 1 shall enter into forcein relation to that ASEAN Member State on the first day ofthe second month following the date on which it makes thenotification. 


4. Notwithstanding paragraphs 2 and 3, the number ofASEAN Member States referred to in paragraph 2 which isnecessary for entry into force of the amendment may beincreased by agreement among the Parties. 


5. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, amendments relating onlyto: 


(a) Annex 1 (provided that the amendments are made inaccordance with the amendment of the Harmonized System, and include no change on tariff ratesapplied to the originating goods of the otherParties in accordance with Annex 1); 


(b) Annex 2; 


(c) Attachment to Annex 4; or 


(d) Annex 5, 
may be made by diplomatic notes exchanged among theGovernments of the Parties. Such amendments shall enter into force in relation to all the Parties on the date specified in such diplomatic notes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Depositary" article_identifier="14000">For the ASEAN Member States, this Agreement includingits amendments shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of ASEAN, who shall promptly furnish a certifiedcopy thereof, to each ASEAN Member State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="14001">1. The Government of each signatory State shall notifythe Governments of other signatory States in writing thatits legal procedures necessary for entry into force of thisAgreement have been completed. This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the second month followingthe date by which such notifications have been made by theGovernments of Japan and at least one (1) ASEAN MemberState, in relation to those signatory States that have madesuch notifications by that date. 


2. In relation to an ASEAN Member State making thenotification referred to in paragraph 1 after the date bywhich the notifications have been made by the Governmentsof Japan and at least one (1) ASEAN Member State asreferred to in paragraph 1, this Agreement shall enter intoforce on the first day of the second month following thedate on which that ASEAN Member State makes the notification. That ASEAN Member State shall be bound bythe existing terms and conditions of this Agreement,including any amendments that may have entered into forcepursuant to Article 77 by the time of such notification.For the purposes of Annex 1, the staging of tariffelimination or reduction of that ASEAN Member State shall also commence from the date of entry into force of thisAgreement pursuant to paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Withdrawal And Termination" article_identifier="14002">1. Any Party may withdraw from this Agreement by givingone (1) year’s advance notice in writing to the otherParties. 


2. This Agreement shall terminate either when all ASEANMember States which are Parties withdraw in accordance with paragraph 1 or when Japan does so.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1690">
      <article article_identifier="14003">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being dulyauthorised by their respective Governments, have signedthis Agreement. 

DONE in duplicate in the English language and SIGNEDat Tokyo on the  day of  in the year 2008, at Bandar Seri Begawan on the  day of  in the year 2008, at Phnom Penh on the  day of  in the year 2008, at Jakarta on the  day of  in the year 2008, at Vientiane on the  day of         in the year 2008, at Kuala Lumpur on the  day of      in the year 2008, at Nay Pyi Taw on the  day of      in the year 2008, at Manila on the  day of         in the year 2008, at Singapore on the  day of         in the year 2008, at Bangkok on the  day of         in the year 2008, and at Hanoi on the  day of         in the year 2008. 

For the Government of For the Government of Japan: Brunei Darussalam: 

For the Government of the Kingdom of Cambodia: 

For the Government of the Republic of Indonesia: 

For the Government of the Lao People’s DemocraticRepublic: For the Government of Malaysia: 

For the Government of the Union of Myanmar: 

For the Government of the Republic ofthe Philippines: 

For the Government of the Republic of Singapore: 

For the Government of the Kingdom of Thailand: 

For the Government of the Socialist Republic ofViet Nam:</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
