<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Eurasian Economic Union (EAEU) - Viet Nam</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>973</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>447</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2015-05-29</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2016-10-05</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2017-05-04</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">ARM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KGZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">ARM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BLR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">KAZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">KGZ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS); East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/973/TOA/English/FTA text.docx</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/973/AnnexAndRelatedDocs/English/Files.zip</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="4590">
      <article article_identifier="39678">Free Trade
  Agreement between the Eurasian Economic Union and its Member States,
  of the one part, and
  the Socialist
  Republic of Viet Nam, of the other part
  PREAMBLE
The Republic of Armenia, the Republic of
  Belarus, the Republic of Kazakhstan, the Kyrgyz Republic, the Russian
  Federation (hereinafter referred to as “the Member States of the
  Eurasian Economic Union”), and the Eurasian Economic Union, of the one
  part, and the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam (hereinafter referred to
  as “Viet Nam”), of the other part:RECOGNISING the importance of
  enhancing their longstanding and strong friendship and the traditional
  multi-faceted cooperation between the Parties;
DESIRING to create favourable
  conditions for the development and diversification of trade between
  them and for the promotion of commercial and economic cooperation in
  areas of common interest on the basis of equality, mutual benefit,
  non-discrimination and international law;
REAFFIRMING their respective rights
  and obligations under the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World
  Trade Organization and other existing international agreements to
  which the Parties are party;
RECOGNISING the need to uphold the principles and practices which promote free and unhindered trade in a stable, transparent and
non-discriminatory manner;CONVINCED that this Agreement will
  enhance the competitiveness of the economies of the Parties in global
  markets and create conditions encouraging economic, trade and
  investment relations between them;
BEING CONSCIOUS of the importance
  of trade facilitation in promoting efficient and transparent
  procedures to reduce costs and ensure predictability;
EMPHASISING the complementarities
  of the economies of the Parties and the significant potential to
  advance economic relations by further developing the framework for
  trade and investment;
ACKNOWLEDGING the important role
  and contribution of investments in enhancing trade and cooperation
  between the Parties and the need to further promote and facilitate
  cooperation and greater business opportunities provided by this
  Agreement;
REAFFIRMING the importance of
  ongoing economic cooperation initiatives between the Parties, and
  agreeing to further develop the existing economic partnership in areas
  where the Parties have mutual interests;
DESIRING to eliminate barriers to
  trade and investment between the Parties, lower business costs and
  enhance economic efficiency; and
CONVINCED that joint efforts
  between the Parties towards an advanced free trade agreement will
  develop an enhanced framework for the promotion and development of
  economic and trade relations between the Member States of the Eurasian
  Economic Union and Viet Nam in their common interest and for their
  mutual benefit;
HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="4591">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.1" name="General Provisions And Definitions" article_identifier="39679">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise specified:
  “central customs authority”
        means the highest authorised customs authority of each of the
        Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union or Viet Nam
        exercising, in accordance with the respective domestic laws and
        regulations, the functions of implementing the relevant
        government policies, regulations, control and supervision in the
        customs sphere;
      “customs authorities” means
        the customs authority or customs authorities of the Member
        States of the Eurasian Economic Union or Viet Nam;
      “customs duty” means any duty
        or charge of any kind imposed on or in connection with the
        importation of a good, but does not include any:
      
            
              charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed consistently
              with Article III.2 of GATT 1994;
            
        
            
              fee or other charge in connection with the importation
              commensurate with the cost of services rendered; and
            
        
            
              duty imposed consistently with Chapter 3 (Trade Remedies)
              of this Agreement;
            
        “days” means calendar days
        including weekends and holidays;
      “declarant” means a person
        who declares goods for customs purposes or on whose behalf the
        goods are declared;
      “Eurasian Economic
        Commission” means the permanent regulatory body of
        the Eurasian Economic Union in accordance with the Treaty on the
        Eurasian Economic Union of 29 May 2014 (hereinafter referred to
        as “the Treaty on the EAEU”);
      “GATS” means the General
        Agreement on Trade in Services, in Annex 1B to the WTO
        Agreement;
      “GATT 1994” means the General
        Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 and its interpretative
        notes, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement;
      “good” means any merchandise,
        product, article or material;
      “Harmonized System” or
        “HS” means the Harmonized
        Commodity Description and Coding System established by the
        International Convention on the Harmonized Commodity Description
        and Coding System, done on 14 June 1983 as adopted and
        implemented by the Parties in their respective laws and
        regulations;
      “laws and regulations”
        includes any law or any other legal normative act;
      “measure” means any measure
        by a Party, whether in the form of a law, regulation, rule,
        procedure, decision, administrative action, practice or any
        other form;
      “originating” means
        qualifying under the rules of origin set out in Chapter 4 (Rules
        of Origin) of this Agreement;
      “Parties” means the Member
        States of the Eurasian Economic Union and the Eurasian Economic
        Union acting jointly or individually within their respective
        areas of competence as derived from the Treaty on the EAEU, of
        the one part, and Viet Nam, of the other part;
      “person” means a natural
        person or a juridical person;
      “SCM Agreement” means the
        Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures, in Annex 1A
        to the WTO Agreement;
      “SPS Agreement” means the
        Agreement on the Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary
        Measures, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement;
      “TBT Agreement” means the
        Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade, in Annex 1A to the WTO
        Agreement;
      “TRIPS Agreement” means the
        Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property
        Rights, in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement;
      “WTO” means the World Trade
        Organization established in accordance with the WTO Agreement;
        and
      “WTO Agreement” means the
        Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization,
        done on 15 April 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.2" name="Establishment Of Free Trade Area" article_identifier="39680">The Parties hereby establish a Free Trade Area consistent with
    Article XXIV of GATT 1994 and Article V of GATS.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.3" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39681">The objectives of this Agreement are:
  
        to liberalise and facilitate trade in goods between the Parties
        through, inter alia, reduction of tariff
        and non-tariff barriers and simplification of customs
        formalities;
      
        to liberalise and facilitate trade in services between the
        Parties;
      
        to facilitate, promote and enhance investment opportunities
        between the Parties through further development of favourable
        investment environments;
      
        to support economic and trade cooperation between the Parties;
      
        to protect adequately and effectively intellectual property and
        promote cooperation in the field thereof; and
      
        to establish a framework to enhance closer cooperation in the
        fields agreed in this Agreement and facilitate communications
        between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.4" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="39682">The Parties hereby establish a Joint Committee comprising
    representatives of each Party, which shall be co-chaired by two
    representatives – one from the Eurasian Economic Union or from a
    Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union and the other from Viet
    Nam. The Parties shall be represented by senior officials delegated
    by them for this purpose.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.5" name="Functions Of The Joint Committee" article_identifier="39683">The Joint Committee shall have the following functions:
      
        considering any matter related to the implementation and
        operation of this Agreement;
      
        supervising the work of all committees and other bodies
        established under this Agreement;
      
        considering ways to further enhance trade relations between the
        Parties;
      
        considering and recommending to the Parties any amendment to
        this Agreement; and
      
        taking other actions on any matter covered by this Agreement as
        the Parties may agree.
      
        In the fulfilment of its functions, the Joint Committee may
        establish subsidiary bodies, including ad
        hoc bodies, and assign them with tasks on specific
        matters. The Joint Committee may, if necessary, decide to seek
        advice of third persons or groups.
      
        Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the Joint Committee shall
        convene:
      
        in regular session every year, with such sessions to be held
        alternately in the territories of the Parties; and
      
        in special session within 30 days of the request of a Party,
        with such sessions to be held in the territory of the other
        Party or at such location as the Parties may agree.
      
        The Joint Committee shall meet within 30 days of a Party giving
        an advance notice in accordance with Article 15.3 of this
        Agreement in order to discuss the implications of that action
        for the Parties and for any arrangement made under this
        Agreement.
      
        All decisions of the Joint Committee, committees and other
        bodies established under this Agreement shall be taken by
        consensus of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.6" name="Priority Investment Projects" article_identifier="39684">Priority investment projects shall be approved by the respective
        Governments of the Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union
        on the one side and the Government of Viet Nam on the other
        side.
      
        Notwithstanding other provisions of this Agreement and as a
        result of consultations of the Parties aimed at support of
        priority investment projects, the Parties shall be entitled to
        provide additional preferences. Such decisions shall be made by
        the relevant authorities of the respective Parties within their
        competence.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.7" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="39685">Each Party shall designate a contact point or contact points to
        facilitate communications between the Parties on any matter
        covered by this Agreement and shall notify the Joint Committee
        of its contact point or contact points.
      
        Upon request of a Party, the other Party’s contact point or
        contact points shall identify the office or official responsible
        for the matter and assist, as necessary, in facilitating
        communications with the requesting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.8" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="39686">Each Party shall, in accordance with its respective laws and
        regulations, maintain the confidentiality of information
        provided in confidence by the other Party pursuant to this
        Agreement.
      
        Nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party to provide
        confidential information, the disclosure of which would impede
        law enforcement, or otherwise be contrary to the public
        interest, or which would prejudice legitimate commercial
        interests of particular enterprises, public or private.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.9" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="39687">Article XX of GATT 1994 and Article XIV of GATS are incorporated
        into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis
        mutandis.
      
        Article XXI of GATT 1994 and Article XIV
        bis of GATS are incorporated into and form
        part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.
      
        The Joint Committee shall be informed to the fullest extent
        possible of measures taken under paragraph 2 of this Article and
        of their termination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.10" name="Dual Use Goods And Services" article_identifier="39688">The Parties recognise the sovereign right of the Member States of
    the Eurasian Economic Union and Viet Nam to regulate trade in dual
    use goods and services subject to their respective export control
    laws and regulations as well as international obligations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.11" name="Measures To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="39689">Article XII of GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the
Balance-of-Payments Provisions of GATT 1994 are incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.12" name="Relation To Other International Agreements" article_identifier="39690">This Agreement shall apply without prejudice to the rights and
        obligations of the Parties arising from bilateral and
        multilateral agreements to which the Parties are party,
        including the WTO Agreement and the Parties’ respective WTO
        obligations and commitments.
      
        Without prejudice to Article 4.7 of this Agreement, the
        provisions of this Agreement shall neither apply between the
        Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union or between the
        Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union and the Eurasian
        Economic Union, nor shall they grant Viet Nam the rights and
        privileges that the Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union
        grant exclusively to each other.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.13" name="Transparency" article_identifier="39691">Each Party shall ensure, in accordance with its respective laws
        and regulations, that its laws and regulations of general
        application as well as its respective international agreements,
        with respect to any matter covered by this Agreement, are
        promptly published or otherwise made publicly available,
        including wherever possible in electronic form.
      
        To the extent possible, in accordance with its respective laws
        and regulations, each Party shall:
      
        publish in advance such laws and regulations referred to in
        paragraph 1 of this Article that it proposes to adopt; and
      
        provide interested persons and the other Party with a reasonable
        opportunity to comment on such laws and regulations referred to
        in paragraph 1 of this Article that it proposes to adopt.
      
        Upon request of a Party, the other Party shall promptly respond
        to specific questions and provide information on the laws and
        regulations referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="4592">
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.1" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39692">With respect to customs duties and charges of any kind imposed
        on or in connection with importation or exportation or imposed
        on the international transfer of payments for imports or
        exports, and with respect to the method of levying such duties
        and charges, and with respect to all rules and formalities in
        connection with importation and exportation, and with respect to
        all matters referred to in paragraphs 2 and 4 of Article III of
        GATT 1994, any advantage, favour, privilege or immunity granted
        by a Party to any good originating in or destined for the
        territory of any third country shall be accorded immediately and
        unconditionally to the like good of the other Party or like good
        destined for the territory of such Party.
      Nothing in paragraph 1 of this Article obliges a Party to provide the other Party with an advantage, favour, privilege or immunity on a
most-favoured-nation basis which the former Party provides to any other third country fulfilling any of the following criteria:
        to adjacent countries for the purposes of facilitating frontier
        traffic;
      
        to the participants of a customs union, free trade area or
        regional economic organisation, or any other regional trade
        agreements as defined in Article XXIV of GATT 1994; or
      
        to developing and least developed countries in accordance with
        GATT 1994, Generalized System of Preferences under United
        Nations Conference on Trade and Development or the respective
        laws and regulations of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.2" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="39693">Article III of GATT 1994 and the interpretative notes to this
    Article are incorporated into and form part of this Agreement,
    mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.3" name="Reduction And/Or Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="39694">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, each Party
          shall progressively reduce and/or eliminate customs duties on
          originating goods of the other Party in accordance with its
          schedule of tariff commitments in Annex 1 to this Agreement
          and shall not increase any customs duty or adopt any new
          customs duty resulting in the customs duty rate for
          originating goods of the other Party exceeding the level
          specified in its schedule of tariff commitments in Annex 1 to
          this Agreement.
        
    
        
          A Party may, at any time, unilaterally accelerate the
          reduction and/or elimination of customs duties on originating
          goods of the other Party set out in its schedule of tariff
          commitments in Annex 1 to this Agreement. This shall not
          preclude either Party from raising a customs duty to the level
          established in its schedule of tariff commitments in Annex 1
          to this Agreement for the respective year following a
          unilateral reduction. A Party considering such raise,
          reduction and/or elimination of a customs duty shall inform
          the other Party as early as practicable before the new rate of
          customs duty takes effect.
        
    
The Parties may consider accelerating the reduction and/or elimination of customs duties set out in their schedules of tariff commitments in Annex 1 to this Agreement by amending this Agreement in accordance with
Article 15.5 of this Agreement.
    
If the rate of customs duty on an originating good of a Party applied in accordance with Annex 1 to this Agreement is higher than the
most-favoured-nation applied rate of customs duty on the same good, such good shall be eligible for the latter one.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.4" name="Changes To Hs Code And Description" article_identifier="39695">Each Party shall ensure that any change to its HS code and
          description shall be carried out without impairing tariff
          concessions undertaken in accordance with Annex 1 to this
          Agreement.
        
    
        
          Such change to the Eurasian Economic Union HS code and
          description and Viet Nam HS code and description shall be
          carried out by the Eurasian Economic Commission and Viet Nam,
          respectively. The Parties shall make any change to their HS
          code and description publicly available in a timely manner and
          inform each other every three months.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.5" name="Fees, Charges And Formalities Connected With Importation And Exportation" article_identifier="39696">Article VIII of GATT 1994 and the interpretative notes to this
          Article are incorporated into and form part of this Agreement,
          mutatis mutandis.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall ensure that its competent authorities make
          available through their official websites information about
          fees and charges it imposes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.6" name="Administration Of Trade Regulations" article_identifier="39697">Each Party shall administer in a uniform, impartial and reasonable
    manner all its laws, regulations, judicial decisions and
    administrative rulings of general application pertaining to trade in
    goods between the Parties in accordance with Article X of GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.7" name="Subsidies" article_identifier="39698">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of subsidies for goods not covered by the Agreement on Agriculture, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, shall be governed by the provisions of Article XVI of
GATT 1994, the SCM Agreement and their respective WTO obligations and commitments.
    
        
          The Parties share the objective of multilateral elimination of
          export subsidies for agricultural goods.
        
    
        
          The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of export
          subsidies on any agricultural good destined for the territory
          of the other Party shall be governed by their respective WTO
          obligations and commitments.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall ensure transparency in the area of subsidies
          covered by this Article. Upon request of a Party, the other
          Party within a reasonable period of time shall give notice on
          a specific subsidy, as defined in the SCM Agreement, that it
          grants or maintains. Such notice shall contain the information
          set out in Article 25.3 of the SCM Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.8" name="Import Licensing" article_identifier="39699">Each Party shall ensure that its import licensing procedures,
          as defined in Articles 1 through 3 of the Agreement on Import
          Licensing Procedures, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement
          (hereinafter referred to as “the Agreement on Import Licensing
          Procedures”), are implemented in a transparent and predictable
          manner, and applied in accordance with the Agreement on Import
          Licensing Procedures.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall publish its rules and information concerning
          licensing procedures in a manner consistent with Article 1.4
          of the Agreement on Import Licensing Procedures. A Party which
          introduces licensing procedures or changes in these procedures
          shall notify the other Party of such licensing procedures or
          changes in these procedures within 60 days of publication.
          Such notification shall contain information set out in
          Articles 5.2 and 5.3 of the Agreement on Import Licensing
          Procedures. The information shall be provided through a
          contact point of each Party designated for this purpose.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.9" name="Quantitative Restrictions" article_identifier="39700">Neither Party may adopt or maintain any quantitative
          restriction, including prohibition or restriction on the
          importation of any good of the other Party or on the
          exportation of any good destined for the territory of the
          other Party, except in accordance with its WTO obligations and
          commitments, and to this end Articles XI and XIII of GATT 1994
          and the interpretative notes to these Articles are
          incorporated into and form part of this Agreement,
          mutatis mutandis.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall ensure the transparency of any quantitative
          restriction permitted in accordance with paragraph 1 of this
          Article and shall ensure that any such measure is not
          prepared, adopted or applied with a view to, or with the
          effect of, creating unnecessary obstacles to trade between the
          Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.10" name="Trigger Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="39701">The Eurasian Economic Union may apply a trigger safeguard
          measure to originating goods of Viet Nam listed in Annex 2 to
          this Agreement and imported into the territories of the Member
          States of the Eurasian Economic Union if the volume of imports
          during any calendar year exceeds the relevant trigger level
          for that year specified in Annex 2 to this Agreement.
        
    
        
          A trigger safeguard measure shall be applied in the form of a
          customs duty equal to the most-favoured-nation rate of customs
          duty applied with respect to the goods concerned on the date
          when the trigger safeguard measure comes into effect.
        
    
        
          A trigger safeguard measure shall be applied for a period of
          time not exceeding six months.
        
    
        
          Notwithstanding paragraph 3 of this Article, if on the date of
          the application of the trigger safeguard measure the volume of
          imports concerned exceeds 150 percent of the relevant trigger
          level, the period of application of such measure may be
          extended by another three months.
        
    
        
          The Eurasian Economic Commission shall publish the data on the
          volume of imports concerned in a readily accessible manner for
          Viet Nam. Upon finding that the conditions referred to in
          paragraph 1 of this Article are met, the Eurasian Economic
          Commission shall immediately give notice thereof in writing.
          The Eurasian Economic Commission shall also give notice in
          writing at least 20 days before taking decision on the
          application of a trigger safeguard measure, as well as three
          days after taking such decision, provided that such decision
          comes into effect not earlier than 30 days from the date the
          decision is taken, without prejudice to the right of the
          Eurasian Economic Union to apply such measure. If the Eurasian
          Economic Union decides not to apply the trigger safeguard
          measure it shall promptly notify Viet Nam of its decision in
          writing.
        
    
        
          Upon request of a Party, the other Party shall promptly enter
          into consultations and/or provide the requested information
          with the aim of clarifying the conditions of imposition and
          application of a trigger safeguard measure under paragraphs 1
          through 4 of this Article.
        
    
        
          Every three years from the date of entry into force of this
          Agreement, the Parties shall review the operation of this
          Article and, if necessary, jointly decide to amend this
          Article as well as Annex 2 to this Agreement in accordance
          with Article 15.5 of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.11" name="State Trading Enterprises" article_identifier="39702">Each Party shall ensure that its state trading enterprises operate
    in consistence with Article XVII of GATT 1994 and its WTO
    obligations and commitments.
  Article
    2.12Committee on Trade in Goods 
        
          The Parties hereby establish the Committee on Trade in Goods
          (hereinafter referred to as “the Goods Committee”), comprising
          representatives of each Party.
        
    
        
          The Goods Committee shall meet upon request of either Party to
          consider any matter arising under this Chapter and under
          Chapters 3 (Trade Remedies), 4 (Rules of Origin), 5 (Customs
          Administration and Trade Facilitation), 6 (Technical Barriers
          to Trade) and 7 (Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures).
        
    
        
          The Goods Committee shall have the following functions:
        
    
        
          reviewing and monitoring the implementation and operation of
          the Chapters referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article;
        
    
        
          reviewing and making appropriate recommendations, as needed,
          to the Joint Committee on any amendment to the provisions of
          this Chapter and to the schedules of tariff commitments in
          Annex 1 to this Agreement in order to promote and facilitate
          improved market access;
        
    
        
          identifying and recommending measures to resolve any problem
          that may arise;
        
    
        
          reporting the findings on any other issue arising from the
          implementation of this Chapter to the Joint Committee.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Trade Remedies" chapter_identifier="4593">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.1" name="Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="39703">The Parties shall apply countervailing measures in accordance with the provisions of Articles VI and XVI of GATT 1994 and
the SCM Agreement.
    
        
          For the purposes of conducting countervailing investigations
          and applying countervailing measures by Viet Nam, the Member
          States of the Eurasian Economic Union shall be considered
          individually and not as the Eurasian Economic Union as a
          whole, unless there are subsidies within the meaning of
          Article XVI of GATT 1994 and the SCM Agreement available at
          the level of the Eurasian Economic Union for all Member States
          of the Eurasian Economic Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.2" name="Anti-Dumping Measures" article_identifier="39704">The Parties shall apply anti-dumping measures in accordance
          with the provisions of Article VI of GATT 1994 and the
          Agreement on Implementation of Article VI of the General
          Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994, in Annex 1A to the WTO
          Agreement.
        
    
        For the purposes of conducting anti-dumping investigations and
        applying anti-dumping measures by Viet Nam, the Member States of
        the Eurasian Economic Union shall be considered individually and
        not as the Eurasian Economic Union as a whole, unless both
        Parties agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.3" name="Global Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="39705">The Parties shall apply global safeguard measures in accordance with
    the provisions of Article XIX of GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
    Safeguards, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.4" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="39706">Where, as a result of the reduction or elimination of a customs
        duty under this Agreement, any originating good of a Party is
        being imported into the territory of the other Party in such
        increased quantities, in absolute terms or relative to domestic
        production, and under such conditions as to constitute a
        substantial cause of serious injury or threat thereof to the
        domestic industry producing like or directly competitive goods
        in the territory of the importing Party, the importing Party may
        apply a bilateral safeguard measure during the transition period
        for that good to the extent necessary to remedy or prevent the
        serious injury or threat thereof, subject to the provisions of
        this Article.
      
        A bilateral safeguard measure shall only be applied upon
        demonstrating clear evidence that increased imports constitute a
        substantial cause of or are threatening to cause serious injury.
      
        The Party intending to apply a bilateral safeguard measure under
        this Article shall promptly, and in any case before applying a
        measure, notify the other Party and the Joint Committee. The
        notification shall contain all pertinent information, which
        shall include evidence of serious injury or threat thereof
        caused by increased imports, a precise description of the good
        concerned and the proposed measure, as well as the proposed date
        of introduction, expected duration and timetable for the
        progressive removal of the measure if relevant.
      
        The Party that may be affected by the measure shall be offered
        compensation in the form of substantially equivalent trade
        liberalisation in relation to the imports from such Party. The
        Party shall, within 30 days from the date of notification
        referred to in paragraph 3 of this Article, examine the
        information provided in order to facilitate a mutually
        acceptable resolution of the matter. In the absence of such
        resolution, the importing Party may apply a bilateral safeguard
        measure to resolve the problem, and, in the absence of mutually
        agreed compensation, the Party against whose good the bilateral
        safeguard measure is applied may take compensatory action. The
        bilateral safeguard measure and the compensatory action shall be
        promptly notified to the other Party. The compensatory action
        shall normally consist of suspension of concessions having
        substantially equivalent trade effects and/or concessions
        substantially equivalent to the value of the additional duties
        expected to result from the bilateral safeguard measure.
        Compensatory action shall be taken only for the minimum period
        necessary to achieve the substantially equivalent trade effects
        and in any event, only while the bilateral safeguard measure
        under paragraph 5 of this Article is being applied.
      
        If the conditions set out in paragraph 1 of this Article are
        met, the importing Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure
        in the form of:
      
        suspension of further reduction of any applicable rate of
        customs duty provided for in this Agreement for the good
        concerned; or
      
        increase of the applicable rate of customs duty for the good
        concerned to a necessary level not exceeding the base rate
        indicated in Annex 1 to this Agreement.
      
        The Parties may apply a bilateral safeguard measure for the
        following periods of time:
      
in the case of a good for which the customs duty reaches the final reduction rate within three years from the date of entry into force of this Agreement, a Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure for a period of time not exceeding two years. A Party shall not apply a bilateral safeguard measure again on the same good during the
one-year period after the expiration of the previous bilateral safeguard measure. Any bilateral safeguard measure shall not be applied more than twice to the same good.
    
        
          in the case of a good for which the customs duty reaches the
          final reduction rate after three years from the date of entry
          into force of this Agreement, a Party may apply a bilateral
          safeguard measure for a period of time not exceeding two
          years. The period of application of a bilateral safeguard
          measure may be extended by up to one year if there is evidence
          that it is necessary to remedy or prevent serious injury or
          threat thereof and that the industry is adjusting. A Party
          shall not apply a bilateral safeguard measure again on the
          same good for the period of time equal to that during which
          such measure had been previously applied. Any bilateral
          safeguard measure shall not be applied more than twice to the
          same good.
        
    
        Upon the termination of the bilateral safeguard measure, the
        rate of customs duty shall be the rate, which would have been in
        effect on the date of termination of the measure.
      
        Neither Party may apply, with respect to the same good, at the
        same time:
      
        a bilateral safeguard measure; and
      
        a measure under Article XIX of GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
        Safeguards, in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement.
      
        Domestic industry referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article
        means the producers as a whole of the like or directly
        competitive goods operating within the territory of a Party or
        those producers whose collective production of the like or
        directly competitive goods constitutes a major proportion but
        not less than 25 percent of the total domestic production of
        such good.
      
        Transition period referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article in
        relation to particular goods subject to a bilateral safeguard
        measure, means:
      
        the period of time from the date of entry into force of this
        Agreement until seven years from the date of completion of the
        customs duty elimination or reduction in the case of a good for
        which the customs duty reaches the final reduction rate within
        three years from the date of entry into force of this Agreement;
      
        the period of time from the date of entry into force of this
        Agreement until five years from the date of completion of the
        customs duty elimination or reduction in the case of a good for
        which the customs duty reaches the final reduction rate after
        three years, but only up to five years from the date of entry
        into force of this Agreement; and
      
        the period of time from the date of entry into force of this
        Agreement until three years from the date of completion of the
        customs duty elimination or reduction in the case of a good for
        which the customs duty reaches the final reduction rate after
        five years from the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.5" name="Notifications" article_identifier="39707">All official communications and documentation exchanged between
        the Parties with respect to matters covered by this Chapter
        shall take place between the relevant authorities having the
        legal power to initiate and conduct investigations under this
        Chapter (hereinafter referred to as “the investigating
        authorities”). In case Viet Nam intends to apply a measure under
        this Chapter, the other Party may designate a different
        responsible authority and shall notify Viet Nam of its
        designation.
      
        The Parties shall exchange information on the names and contacts
        of the investigating authorities within 30 days from the date of
        entry into force of this Agreement. The Parties shall promptly
        notify each other of any change to the investigating
        authorities.
      
        The Party intending to apply a global safeguard measure shall
        immediately provide to the other Party a written notification of
        all pertinent information on the initiation of an investigation,
        the provisional findings and the final findings of the
        investigation.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="4594">
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="39708">The rules of origin provided for in this Chapter shall be applied
    only for the purposes of granting preferential tariff treatment in
    accordance with this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39709">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  
        “aquaculture” means farming
          of aquatic organisms including fish, molluscs, crustaceans,
          other aquatic invertebrates and aquatic plants, from feedstock
          such as eggs, fry, fingerlings and larvae, by intervention in
          the rearing or growth processes to enhance production such as
          regular stocking, feeding, or protection from predators;
        
    
        “authorised body” means the
          competent authority designated by a Party to issue a
          Certificate of Origin under this Agreement;
        
    
        “CIF value” means the value
          of the goods imported and includes the cost of freight and
          insurance up to the port or place of entry into the country of
          importation;
        
    
        “consignment” means goods
          that are sent simultaneously covered by one or more transport
          documents to the consignee from the exporter, as well as goods
          that are sent over a single post-invoice or transferred as a
          luggage of the person crossing the border;
        
    
        “exporter” means a person
          registered in the territory of a Party where the goods are
          exported from by such person;
        
    
        “FOB value” means the
          free-on-board value of the goods, inclusive of the cost of
          transport to the port or site of final shipment abroad;
        
    
        “importer” means a person
          registered in the territory of a Party where the goods are
          imported into by such person;
        
    
        “material” means any matter
          or substance including ingredient, raw material, component or
          part used or consumed in the production of goods or physically
          incorporated into goods or subjected to a process in the
          production of other goods;
        
    
        “non-originating goods” or
          “non-originating materials”
          means goods or materials that do not fulfil the origin
          criteria of this Chapter;
        
    
        “originating goods” or
          “originating materials”
          means goods or materials that fulfil the origin criteria of
          this Chapter;
        
    
        “producer” means a person
          who carries out production in the territory of a Party;
        
    
        “production” means methods
          of obtaining goods including growing, mining, harvesting,
          raising, breeding, extracting, gathering, capturing, fishing,
          hunting, manufacturing, processing or assembling such goods;
          and
        
    
        “verification authority”
          means the competent governmental authority designated by a
          Party to conduct verification procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.3" name="Origin Criteria" article_identifier="39710">For the purposes of this Chapter, goods shall be considered as
    originating in a Party if they are:
  
        wholly obtained or produced in such Party as provided for in
        Article 4.4 of this Agreement; or
      
        produced entirely in one or both Parties, exclusively from
        originating materials from one or both Parties; or
      
        produced in a Party using non-originating materials and satisfy
        the requirements of product specific rules specified in Annex 3
        to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.4" name="Wholly Obtained Or Produced Goods" article_identifier="39711">For the purposes of Article 4.3 of this Agreement, the following
    goods shall be considered as wholly obtained or produced in a Party:
  
        plants and plant goods, including fruit, berries, flowers,
        vegetables, trees, seaweed, fungi and live plants, grown,
        harvested, or gathered in the territory of a Party;
      
        live animals born and raised in the territory of a Party;
      
        goods obtained from live animals in the territory of a Party;
      
        goods obtained from gathering, hunting, capturing, fishing,
        growing, raising and aquaculture in the territory of a Party;
      
        minerals and other naturally occurring substances extracted or
        taken from the air, soil, waters or seabed and subsoil in the
        territory of a Party;
      
        goods of sea fishing and other marine goods taken from the high
        seas, in accordance with international law, by a vessel
        registered or recorded in a Party and flying its flag;
      
        goods manufactured exclusively from goods referred to in
        subparagraph f) of this Article, on board a factory ship
        registered or recorded in a Party and flying its flag;
      
        waste and scrap resulting from production and consumption
        conducted in the territory of a Party provided that such goods
        are fit only for the recovery of raw materials;
      
        used goods collected in the territory of a Party provided that
        such goods are fit only for the recovery of raw materials;
      
        goods produced in outer space on board a spacecraft provided
        that the same spacecraft is registered in a Party; and
      
        goods produced or obtained in the territory of a Party solely
        from goods referred to in subparagraphs a) through j) of this
        Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.5" name="Value Added Content" article_identifier="39712">For the purposes of this Chapter and product specific rules
    specified in Annex 3 to this Agreement, the formula for calculating
    value added content (hereinafter referred to as “VAC”) shall be:
  
    where the value of non-originating materials shall be:
  
        CIF value of the materials at the time of importation to a
        Party; or
      
        the earliest ascertained price paid or payable for
        non-originating materials in the territory of the Party where
        the working or processing takes place.
      When, in the territory of a Party, the producer of the goods acquires
non-originating materials within such Party, the value of such materials shall not include freight, insurance, packing costs and any other costs incidental to the transport of those materials from the location of the supplier to the location of production.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.6" name="Insufficient Working Or Processing" article_identifier="39713">The following operations undertaken exclusively by themselves
          or in combination with each other are considered to be
          insufficient to meet the requirements of Article 4.3 of this
          Agreement:
        
    
        
          preserving operations to ensure that a product retains its
          condition during transportation and storage;
        
    
        
          freezing or thawing;
        
    
        
          packaging and re-packaging;
        
    
        
          washing, cleaning, removing dust, oxide, oil, paint or other
          coverings;
        
    
        
          ironing or pressing of textiles;
        
    
        
          colouring, polishing, varnishing, oiling;
        
    
        
          husking, partial or total bleaching, polishing and glazing of
          cereals and rice;
        
    
        
          operations to colour sugar or form sugar lumps;
        
    
        
          peeling and removal of stones and shells from fruits, nuts and
          vegetables;
        
    
        
          simple sharpening, grinding;
        
    
        
          cutting;
        
    
        
          sifting, screening, sorting, classifying;
        
    
        
          placing in bottles, cans, flasks, bags, cases, boxes, fixing
          on surface and all other simple packaging operations;
        
    
        
          affixing or printing marks, labels, logos and other like
          distinguishing signs on products or their packaging;
        
    
        
          simple mixing of products (components) which does not lead to
          a sufficient difference of product from the original
          components;
        
    
        
          simple assembly of a product or disassembly of products into
          parts; and
        
    
        
          slaughter of animals, sorting of meat.
        
    
        For the purposes of paragraph 1 of this Article, “simple”
        describes activities which do not require special skills or
        machines, apparatus or equipment especially designed for
        carrying out such activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.7" name="Accumulation Of Origin" article_identifier="39714">Without prejudice to Article 4.3 of this Agreement, the goods or
    materials originating in a Party, which are used as material in the
    manufacture of a product in the other Party, shall be considered as
    originating in such Party where the last operations other than those
    referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 4.6 of this Agreement have
    been carried out. The origin of such material shall be confirmed by
    a Certificate of Origin (Form EAV) issued by an authorised body.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.8" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="39715">Goods that do not undergo a change in tariff classification
          pursuant to Annex 3 to this Agreement are nonetheless
          considered originating if:
        
    
        the value of all non-originating materials that are used in the
        production of the goods and do not undergo the required change
        in tariff classification, does not exceed 10 percent of the FOB
        value of such goods; and
      
        the goods meet all other applicable requirements of this
        Chapter.
      
        
          The value of materials referred to in subparagraph a) of
          paragraph 1 of this Article shall be included in the value of
          non-originating materials for any applicable VAC requirement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.9" name="Direct Consignment" article_identifier="39716">Preferential tariff treatment in accordance with this Chapter
          shall be granted to originating goods provided that such goods
          are transported directly from the territory of the exporting
          Party to the territory of the importing Party.
        
    
        
          Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article, originating goods
          may be transported through the territory of one or more third
          countries, provided that:
        
    
        transit through the territory of a third country is justified
        for geographical reasons or related exclusively to transport
        requirements;
      
        the goods have not entered into trade or consumption there; and
      
        the goods have not undergone any operation there other than
        unloading, reloading, storing or any necessary operation
        designed to preserve their condition.
      
        
          A declarant shall submit appropriate documentary evidence to
          the customs authorities of the importing Party confirming that
          the conditions set out in paragraph 2 of this Article have
          been fulfilled. Such evidence shall be provided to the customs
          authorities of the importing Party by submission of:
        
    
        the transport documents covering the passage from the territory
        of a Party to the territory of the other Party containing:
      
            an exact description of the goods;
          
            
              the dates of unloading and reloading of the goods (if the
              transport documents do not contain the dates of unloading
              and reloading of the goods, other supporting document
              containing such information shall be submitted in addition
              to transport documents); and
            
        
            
              where applicable:
            
          
                
                  the names of the ships or other means of transport
                  used;
                
            
                
                  the containers’ numbers;
                
            
                
                  the conditions under which the goods remained in the
                  country of transit in proper condition;
                
            
                
                  the marks of the customs authorities of the country of
                  transit; and
                
            
        the commercial invoice in respect of the goods.
      
        
          A declarant may submit other supporting documents to prove
          that the requirements of paragraph 2 of this Article are
          fulfilled.
        
    
        If the transport documents cannot be provided, a document issued
        by the customs authorities of the country of transit containing
        all the information referred to in subparagraph a) of paragraph
        3 of this Article shall be submitted.
      
        If a declarant fails to provide the customs authorities of the
        importing Party with documentary evidence of direct consignment,
        preferential tariff treatment shall not be granted.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.10" name="Direct Purchase" article_identifier="39717">The importing Party shall grant preferential tariff treatment
        for originating goods in cases where the invoice is issued by a
        person registered in a third country, provided that such goods
        meet the requirements of this Chapter.
      
        Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article the importing Party
        shall not grant preferential tariff treatment in cases where the
        invoice is issued by a person registered in a third country
        included in the list of offshore countries to be established in
        a joint protocol. The respective competent authorities of the
        Parties shall be entitled to adopt such protocol by mutual
        consent and shall make it publicly available.
      
        Without prejudice to paragraph 2 of this Article before the
        joint protocol referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article is
        adopted, the list of offshore countries or territories specified
        in Annex 4 to this Agreement shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.11" name="Packaging Materials For Retail Sale" article_identifier="39718">Packaging materials and containers in which goods are packaged
        for retail sale, if classified with the goods, shall be
        disregarded in determining whether all the non-originating
        materials used in the production of those goods have undergone
        the applicable change in tariff classification set out in Annex
        3 to this Agreement.
      
        Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article in determining
        whether the goods fulfil the VAC requirement, the value of the
        packaging used for retail sale will be counted as originating or
        non-originating materials, as the case may be, in calculating
        the VAC of the goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.12" name="Packing Materials For Shipment" article_identifier="39719">Packing materials and containers in which goods are packed
    exclusively for transport shall not be taken into account for the
    purposes of establishing whether the goods are originating.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.13" name="Accessories, Spare Parts, Tools And Instructional Or Other Information Materials" article_identifier="39720">In determining whether the goods fulfil the change in tariff
        classification requirements specified in Annex 3 to this
        Agreement, accessories, spare parts, tools and instructional or
        other information materials, which are part of the normal
        equipment and included in its FOB price, or which are not
        separately invoiced, shall be considered as part of the goods in
        question and shall not be taken into account in determining
        whether the goods qualify as originating.
      
        Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article in determining
        whether the goods fulfil the VAC requirement, the value of
        accessories, spare parts, tools and instructional or other
        information materials shall be taken into account as originating
        materials or non-originating materials, as the case may be, in
        calculating VAC of the goods.
      
        This Article shall apply only where:
      
        
          accessories, spare parts, tools and instructional or other
          information materials presented with the goods are not
          invoiced separately from such goods; and
        
    
        the quantities and value of accessories, spare parts, tools and
        instructional or other information materials presented with the
        goods are customary for such goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.14" name="Sets" article_identifier="39721">Sets, as defined in Rule 3 of the General Rules of the
    interpretation of the Harmonized System, shall be regarded as
    originating when all component products are originating.
    Nevertheless, when a set is composed of originating and
    non-originating products, the set as a whole shall be regarded as
    originating, provided that the value of the non-originating products
    does not exceed 15 percent of the FOB value of the set.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.15" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="39722">In order to determine the origin of goods, the origin of the
    following indirect materials which might be used in the production
    of such goods and not be incorporated into such goods shall not be
    taken into account:
  
        
          fuel and energy;
        
    
        
          tools, dies and moulds;
        
    
        
          spare parts and materials used in the maintenance of equipment
          and buildings;
        
    
        
          lubricants, greases, compounding materials and other materials
          used in the production or used to operate equipment and
          buildings;
        
    
        
          gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safety equipment;
        
    
        
          equipment, devices used for testing or inspecting the goods;
        
    
        
          catalyst and solvent; and
        
    
        
          any other goods that are not incorporated into such goods but
          the use of which in the production of such goods can be
          demonstrated to be a part of that production.
        
    SECTION II.
    DOCUMENTARY PROOF OF ORIGIN</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.16" name="Claim For Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="39723">For the purposes of obtaining preferential tariff treatment, the
        declarant shall submit a Certificate of Origin to the customs
        authorities of the importing Party in accordance with the
        requirements of this Section.
      
        The Certificate of Origin submitted to the customs authorities
        of the importing Party shall be an original, valid and in
        conformity with the format as set out in Annex 5 to this
        Agreement and shall be duly completed in accordance with the
        requirements set out in Annex 5 to this Agreement.
      
        The authorised body of the exporting Party shall ensure that
        Certificates of Origin are duly completed in accordance with the
        requirements set out in Annex 5 to this Agreement.
      
        The Certificate of Origin shall be valid for a period of 12
        months from the date of issuance and must be submitted to the
        customs authorities of the importing Party within that period
        but not later than the moment of the submission of the import
        customs declaration, except in circumstances stipulated in
        paragraph 2 of Article 4.20 of this Agreement.
      
        Where the central customs authorities and the authorised bodies
        of the Parties have developed and implemented the Electronic
        Origin Certification and Verification System (hereinafter
        referred to as “EOCVS”) referred to in Article 4.29 of this
        Agreement, the customs authorities of the importing Party in
        accordance with its respective domestic laws and regulations may
        not require the submission of the original Certificate of Origin
        if the customs declaration is submitted by electronic means. In
        this case, the date and number of such Certificate of Origin
        shall be specified in the customs declaration. Where the customs
        authorities of the importing Party have a reasonable doubt as to
        the origin of the goods for which preferential tariff treatment
        is claimed and/or there is a discrepancy with the information
        containing in the EOCVS, the customs authorities of the
        importing Party may require the submission of the original
        Certificate of Origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.17" name="Circumstances When Certificate Of Origin Is Not Required" article_identifier="39724">A Certificate of Origin is not required in order to obtain preferential tariff treatment for commercial or non-commercial importation of originating goods where the customs value does not exceed the amount of
200 US dollars or the equivalent amount in the importing Party’s currency or such higher amount as such importing Party may establish, provided that the importation does not form part of one or more consignments that may reasonably be considered to have been undertaken or arranged for the purposes of avoiding the submission of the Certificate of Origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.18" name="Issuance Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="39725">The producer or exporter of the goods or its authorised
        representative shall apply to an authorised body of the
        exporting Party for a Certificate of Origin in writing or by
        electronic means if applicable.
      
        The Certificate of Origin shall be issued by the authorised body
        of the exporting Party to the producer or exporter of the goods
        or its authorised representative prior to or at the time of
        exportation whenever the goods to be exported can be considered
        originating in a Party within the meaning of this Chapter.
      
        The Certificate of Origin shall cover the goods under one
        consignment.
      
        Each Certificate of Origin shall bear a unique reference number
        separately given by the authorised body.
      
        If all goods covered by the Certificate of Origin cannot be
        listed on one page, additional sheets, as set out in Annex 5 to
        this Agreement, shall be used.
      
        The Certificate of Origin shall be done in hard copy and shall
        comprise one original and two copies.
      
        One copy shall be retained by the authorised body of the
        exporting Party. The other copy shall be retained by the
        exporter.
      
        Without prejudice to paragraph 4 of Article 4.16 of this
        Agreement, in exceptional cases, where a Certificate of Origin
        has not been issued prior to or at the time of exportation it
        may be issued retroactively and shall be marked “ISSUED
        RETROACTIVELY”.
      
        The submitted original Certificate of Origin shall be retained
        by the customs authorities of the importing Party except in
        circumstances stipulated in its respective domestic laws and
        regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.19" name="Minor Discrepancies" article_identifier="39726">Where the origin of the goods is not in doubt, the discovery of
        minor discrepancies between the information in the Certificate
        of Origin and in the documents submitted to the customs
        authorities of the importing Party shall not, of themselves,
        invalidate the Certificate of Origin, if such information in
        fact corresponds to the goods submitted.
      For multiple goods declared under the same Certificate of Origin,
a problem encountered with one of the goods listed shall not affect or delay the granting of preferential tariff treatment for the remaining goods covered by the Certificate of Origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.20" name="Specific Cases Of Issuance Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="39727">In the event of theft, loss or destruction of a Certificate of
        Origin, the producer or exporter of the goods or its authorised
        representative may apply to the authorised body of the exporting
        Party for a certified duplicate of the original Certificate of
        Origin, specifying the reasons for such application. The
        duplicate shall be made on the basis of the previously issued
        Certificate of Origin and supporting documents. A certified
        duplicate shall bear the words “DUPLICATE OF THE CERTIFICATE OF
        ORIGIN NUMBER_DATE_”. The certified duplicate of a Certificate
        of Origin shall be valid no longer than 12 months from the date
        of issuance of the original Certificate of Origin.
      
        Due to accidental errors or omissions made in the original
        Certificate of Origin, the authorised body shall issue the
        Certificate of Origin in substitution for the original
        Certificate of Origin. In this instance, the Certificate of
        Origin shall bear the words: “ISSUED IN SUBSTITUTION FOR THE
        CERTIFICATE OF ORIGIN NUMBER___DATE___”. Such Certificate of
        Origin shall be valid no longer than 12 months from the date of
        issuance of the original Certificate of Origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.21" name="Alterations In Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="39728">Neither erasures nor superimpositions shall be allowed on the
    Certificate of Origin. Any alteration shall be made by striking out
    the erroneous data and printing any additional information required.
    Such alteration shall be approved by a person authorised to sign the
    Certificate of Origin and certified by an official seal of the
    appropriate authorised body.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.22" name="Record-Keeping Requirements" article_identifier="39729">The producer and/or exporter of the goods shall keep all records
        and copies of the documents submitted for the issuance of a
        Certificate of Origin for the period of no less than three years
        from the date of issuance of the Certificate of Origin.
      
        An importer who has been granted preferential tariff treatment
        must keep the copy of the Certificate of Origin, based on the
        date when the preferential tariff treatment was granted, for the
        period of no less than three years.
      
        The application for a Certificate of Origin and all documents
        related to such application shall be retained by the authorised
        body for the period of no less than three years from the date of
        issuance of the Certificate of Origin.
    TREATMENT</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.23" name="Granting Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="39730">Preferential tariff treatment under this Agreement shall be
        applied to originating goods that satisfy the requirements of
        this Chapter.
      
        Customs authorities of the importing Party shall grant
        preferential tariff treatment to originating goods of the
        exporting Party provided that:
      
        the goods satisfy the origin criteria referred to in Article 4.3
        of this Agreement;
      
        the declarant demonstrates compliance with the requirements of
        this Chapter;
      
        a valid and duly completed original Certificate of Origin has
        been submitted in accordance with the requirements of Section II
        (Documentary Proof of Origin) of this Chapter to the customs
        authorities of the importing Party. An original Certificate of
        Origin may not be required to be submitted if the Parties have
        implemented the EOCVS as stipulated in paragraph 5 of Article
        4.16 of this Agreement.
      
        Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of this Article, where the customs
        authorities of the importing Party have a reasonable doubt as to
        the origin of the goods for which preferential tariff treatment
        is claimed and/or to the authenticity of the submitted
        Certificate of Origin, such customs authorities may suspend or
        deny the application of preferential tariff treatment to such
        goods. However, the goods can be released in accordance with the
        requirements of such Party’s respective domestic laws and
        regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.24" name="Denial Of Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="39731">Where the goods do not meet the requirements of this Chapter or
        where the importer or exporter of the goods fails to comply with
        the requirements of this Chapter, the customs authorities of the
        importing Party may deny preferential tariff treatment and
        recover unpaid customs duties in accordance with the respective
        domestic laws and regulations.
      
        The customs authorities of the importing Party may deny
        preferential tariff treatment if:
      
        the goods do not meet the requirements of this Chapter to be
        considered as originating in the exporting Party; and/or
      
        other requirements of this Chapter are not met, including:
      
        the requirements of Article 4.9 of this Agreement;
      
        the requirements of Article 4.10 of this Agreement;
      
        the submitted Certificate of Origin has not been duly completed
        as specified in Annex 5 to this Agreement;
      
        the verification procedures undertaken under Articles 4.30 and
        4.31 of this Agreement are unable to establish the origin of the
        goods or indicate the inconsistency of the origin criteria;
      
        the verification authority of the exporting Party has confirmed
        that the Certificate of Origin had not been issued (i.e. forged)
        or had been annulled (withdrawn);
      
        the customs authorities of the importing Party receive no reply
        within a maximum of six months after the date of a verification
        request made to the verification authority of the exporting
        Party, or if the response to the request does not contain
        sufficient information to conclude whether the goods originate
        in a Party; or
      
        the customs authorities of the importing Party within 60 days
        from the date of dispatch of the notification, stipulated in
        paragraph 2 of Article 4.31 of this Agreement, do not receive a
        written consent from the verification authority, pursuant to
        paragraph 5 of Article 4.31 of this Agreement, for conducting a
        verification visit or receive a refusal to conduct such
        verification visit.
      
        Where the importing Party determines through verification
        procedures that an exporter or producer of the goods has engaged
        in providing false and/or incomplete information for the
        purposes of obtaining Certificates of Origin, customs
        authorities of the importing Party may deny preferential tariff
        treatment to identical goods covered by the Certificates of
        Origin issued to that exporter or producer in accordance with
        its respective domestic laws and regulations.
      
        In cases as set out in subparagraph b) of paragraph 2 of this
        Article and paragraph 1 of Article 4.25 of this Agreement
        customs authorities of the importing Party are not required to
        make a verification request, as provided for in Article 4.30 of
        this Agreement, to the authorised body for the purposes of
        making decisions on denial of preferential tariff treatment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.25" name="Temporary Suspension Of Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="39732">Where a Party has found:
      
            systematic fraud regarding claims of preferential tariff
            treatment under this Agreement in respect of the goods
            exported or produced by a person of the other Party; or
          
            that the other Party systematically and unjustifiably
            refuses to fulfil obligations under Articles 4.30 and/or
            4.31 of this Agreement,
          
    such Party may in exceptional circumstances temporarily suspend
    preferential tariff treatment under this Agreement.
  
        Temporary suspension of preferential tariff treatment referred
        to in paragraph 1 of this Article may be applied to the goods
        concerned:
      
        of a person where the importing Party has concluded that such
        person of the exporting Party has committed systematic fraud
        regarding claims of preferential tariff treatment under this
        Agreement;
      
        of the person who is subject to verification request or
        verification visit request referred to in subparagraph b) of
        paragraph 1 of this Article.
      
        Where the importing Party has concluded that the already
        suspended preferential tariff treatment in accordance with
        subparagraph a) of paragraph 2 of this Article had not resulted
        in cessation of systematic fraud regarding claims of
        preferential tariff treatment under this Agreement, it may
        temporarily suspend preferential tariff treatment with regard to
        identical goods classified in the same tariff lines at 8-10
        digit level of the respective domestic nomenclatures of the
        Parties.
      
        For the purposes of this Article:
      
            a finding of systematic fraud can be made where a Party has
            concluded that a person of the other Party has
            systematically provided false or incorrect information in
            order to obtain preferential tariff treatment under this
            Agreement as a result of an investigation based on
            objective, compelling and verifiable information;
          
            systematic and unjustifiable refusal to fulfil obligations
            under Articles 4.30 and/or 4.31 of this Agreement means a
            systematic refusal to verify the originating status of the
            goods concerned and/or to carry out verification visits as
            requested by a Party or absence of response to verification
            and verification visit requests;
          
            identical goods means the goods which are the same in all
            respects including physical characteristics, quality and
            reputation.
          
        A Party that has made a finding pursuant to paragraph 1 or 3 of
        this Article, shall:
      
            notify the other Party and provide the information and
            evidence upon which the finding was based;
          
            engage in consultations with the other Party with a view to
            achieving a mutually acceptable solution.
          If the Parties have not achieved a mutually acceptable solution within
30 days of the engagement into consultations pursuant to subparagraph b) of paragraph 5 of this Article, the Party that has made the finding shall refer the issue to the Joint Committee.
        If the Joint Committee has not resolved the issue within 60 days
        of the referral of such issue to the Joint Committee, the Party
        which has made the finding may temporarily suspend preferential
        tariff treatment under this Agreement pursuant to paragraphs 2
        and 3 of this Article. The Party that has made a decision on
        temporary suspension shall immediately notify the other Party
        and the Joint Committee. Temporary suspension shall not apply to
        the goods which have already been exported on the day that the
        temporary suspension comes into effect. The day of such
        exportation shall be the date of a transport document issued by
        a carrier.
      
        Temporary suspension of preferential tariff treatment under this
        Article may be applied until the exporting Party provides
        convincing evidence of the ability to comply with the
        requirements of this Chapter and ensure the fulfilment of all
        the requirements of this Chapter by producers or exporters of
        the goods but shall not exceed a period of four months, which
        may be renewed for no longer than three months.
      
        Any suspension under this Article and any renewed suspension
        shall be subject to periodic consultations of the Parties with a
        view to resolving the issue.
    COOPERATION</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.26" name="Administrative Cooperation Language" article_identifier="39733">Any notification or communication under this Section shall be
    conducted between the Parties through the relevant authorities in
    the English language.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.27" name="Authorised Body And Verification Authority" article_identifier="39734">Each Government of the Parties shall designate or maintain an
    authorised body and a verification authority.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.28" name="Notifications" article_identifier="39735">Prior to the issuance of any Certificate of Origin under this
        Agreement by the authorised body, each Party shall provide the
        other Party, through the Eurasian Economic Commission and the
        Ministry of Industry and Trade of Viet Nam, respectively, with
        the names and addresses of each authorised body and verification
        authority, together with the original and legible specimen
        impressions of their stamps, sample of the Certificate of Origin
        to be used and data on the security features of the Certificate
        of Origin.
      
        Viet Nam shall provide the Eurasian Economic Commission with the
        original information referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article
        in sextuplicate. The Eurasian Economic Commission may request
        Viet Nam to provide additional sets of such information.
      
        The Eurasian Economic Commission and Viet Nam shall publish on
        the internet the information on the names and addresses of the
        authorised body and verification authority of each Party.
      
        Any change to the information stipulated in this Article shall
        be notified by the Eurasian Economic Commission and the Ministry
        of Industry and Trade of Viet Nam in advance and in the same
        manner.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.29" name="Development And Implementation Of Electronic Origin Certification And Verification System" article_identifier="39736">The Parties shall endeavour to implement an EOCVS no later than
        two years from the date of entry into force of this Agreement.
      
        The purpose of the EOCVS is the creation of a web-database that
        records the details of all Certificates of Origin issued by an
        authorised body and that is accessible to the customs
        authorities of the other Party to check the validity and content
        of any issued Certificate of Origin.
      
        The Parties shall establish a working group that shall endeavour
        to develop and implement an EOCVS.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.30" name="Verification Of Origin" article_identifier="39737">Where the customs authorities of the importing Party have a
        reasonable doubt about the authenticity of a Certificate of
        Origin and/or the compliance of the goods, covered by the
        Certificate of Origin, with the origin criteria, pursuant to
        Article 4.3 of this Agreement, and in the case of a random
        check, they may send a request to the verification authority or
        authorised body of the exporting Party to confirm the
        authenticity of the Certificate of Origin and/or the compliance
        of the goods with the origin criteria and/or to provide, if
        requested, documentary evidence from the producer and/or
        exporter of the goods.
      
        All verification requests shall be accompanied by sufficient
        information to identify the concerned goods. A request to the
        verification authority of the exporting Party shall be
        accompanied by a copy of the Certificate of Origin and shall
        specify the circumstances and reasons for the request.
      
        The recipient of a request under paragraph 1 of this Article
        shall respond to the requesting customs authorities of the
        importing Party within six months after the date of such
        verification request.
      
        In response to a request under paragraph 1 of this Article
        verification authority of the exporting Party shall clearly
        indicate whether the Certificate of Origin is authentic and/or
        whether the goods can be considered as originating in such Party
        including by providing requested documentary evidence received
        from the producer and/or exporter of the goods. Before the
        response to the verification request, paragraph 3 of Article
        4.23 of this Agreement may be applied. The customs duties paid
        shall be refunded if the received results of the verification
        process confirm and clearly indicate that the goods qualify as
        originating and all other requirements of this Chapter are met.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.31" name="Verification Visit" article_identifier="39738">If the customs authorities of the importing Party are not
        satisfied with the outcome of the verification referred to in
        Article 4.30 of this Agreement, they may, under exceptional
        circumstances, request verification visits to the exporting
        Party to review the records referred to in Article 4.22 of this
        Agreement and/or observe the facilities used in the production
        of the goods.
      
        Prior to conducting a verification visit pursuant to paragraph 1
        of this Article the customs authorities of the importing Party
        shall deliver a written notification of their intention to
        conduct the verification visit to the verification authority of
        the Party in the territory of which the verification visit is to
        occur.
      
        The written notification referred to in paragraph 2 of this
        Article shall be as comprehensive as possible and shall include,
        inter alia:
      
        the name of the customs authorities of the Party issuing the
        notification;
      
        the names of the producer and/or exporter of the goods whose
        premises are to be visited;
      
        the proposed date of the verification visit;
      
        the coverage of the proposed verification visit, including
        reference to the goods subject to the verification and to the
        doubts regarding their origin; and
      
        the names and designation of the officials performing the
        verification visit.
      
        Verification authority shall send the verification request to
        the producer and/or exporter of the goods whose premises are to
        be visited and transfer its written consent to the requesting
        Party within 60 days from the date of dispatch of the
        notification pursuant to paragraph 2 of this Article.
      
        Where a written consent from the verification authority is not
        obtained within 60 days from the date of dispatch of the
        notification pursuant to paragraph 2 of this Article or the
        notifying Party receives a refusal to conduct such a
        verification visit, the notifying Party shall deny preferential
        tariff treatment to the goods referred to in the Certificate(s)
        of Origin that would have been subject to the verification
        visit.
      
        Any verification visit shall be launched within 60 days from the
        date of the receipt of written consent and finished within a
        reasonable period of time.
      
        The authority conducting the verification visit shall, within a
        maximum period of 90 days from the first day the verification
        visit was conducted, provide the producer and/or exporter of the
        goods, whose goods and premises are subject to such
        verification, and the verification authority of the exporting
        Party with a written determination of the outcomes of the
        verification visit.
      
        The verification visit including the actual visit and
        determination of whether the concerned goods are originating or
        not shall be carried out and its results sent to the authorised
        body within a maximum of 210 days. Before the results of the
        verification visit are available paragraph 3 of Article 4.23 of
        this Agreement may be applied.
      
        Any suspended or denied preferential tariff treatment shall be
        reinstated upon the written determination that the goods qualify
        as originating and the certain origin criteria under this
        Agreement are fulfilled.
      
        Verification team must be formed by the central customs
        authority of the importing Party in accordance with the
        respective domestic laws and regulations.
      
        The verification authority or the authorised body of the
        exporting Party shall assist in the verification visit conducted
        by the customs authorities of the importing Party.
      
        The producer and/or exporter of the goods who has given consent
        for verification visit, shall assist in its implementation,
        provide access to the premises, financial (accounting) and
        production documents related to the subject of the verification
        visit and shall provide any additional information and/or
        documents, if so requested.
      
        If there are obstacles by the authorities or entities of the
        inspected Party during the verification visit, which result in
        the absence of possibility to conduct the verification visit,
        the importing Party has the right to deny preferential tariff
        treatment to the concerned goods.
      
        All costs relating to the conducting of the verification visit
        shall be borne by the importing Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.32" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="39739">All information provided pursuant to this Chapter shall be treated
    by the Parties as confidential in accordance with their respective
    domestic laws and regulations. It shall not be disclosed without the
    permission of the person or authority of the Party providing it.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.33" name="Penalties Or Other Measures Against Fraudulent Acts" article_identifier="39740">Each Party shall provide for criminal or administrative penalties
    for violations of its respective laws and regulations related to
    this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.34" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="39741">For the purposes of effective implementation and operation of
        this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a Sub-Committee on
        Rules of Origin (hereinafter referred to as “the ROO
        Sub-Committee”).
      
        The ROO Sub-Committee shall have the following functions:
      
        reviewing and making appropriate recommendations to the Joint
        Committee and the Goods Committee on:
      
        transposition of Annex 3 to this Agreement that is in the
        nomenclature of the revised HS following periodic amendments of
        the HS. Such transposition shall be carried out without
        impairing the existing commitments and shall be completed in a
        timely manner;
      
        implementation and operation of this Chapter, including
        proposals for establishing implementing arrangements;
      
        failure to fulfil the obligations by the Parties, as determined
        in this Section;
      
        technical amendments to this Chapter;
      
        amendments to Annex 3 to this Agreement;
      
        disputes arising between the Parties during the implementation
        of this Chapter; and
      
        any amendment to the provisions of this Chapter and to Annexes
        3, 4 and 5 to this Agreement;
      
        considering any other matter proposed by a Party relating to
        this Chapter;
      
        reporting the findings of the ROO Sub-Committee to the Goods
        Committee; and
      
        performing other functions as may be delegated by the Joint
        Committee pursuant to Article 1.5 of this Agreement.
      
        The ROO Sub-Committee shall be composed of the representatives
        of the Parties and may invite representatives of other entities
        of the Parties with necessary expertise relevant to the issues
        to be discussed upon mutual agreement of the Parties.
      
        The ROO Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as may
        be agreed by the Parties but not less than once a year.
      
        A provisional agenda for each meeting shall be forwarded to the
        Parties, as a general rule, no later than one month before the
        meeting.
    PROVISIONS</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.35" name="Goods In Transportation Or Storage" article_identifier="39742">Originating goods which have been in transportation from the
    exporting Party to the importing Party, or which have been in
    temporary storage in a bonded area in the importing Party for a
    period not exceeding one year before the entry into force of this
    Agreement, shall be granted preferential tariff treatment if they
    are imported into the importing Party on or after the date of entry
    into force of this Agreement, subject to the submission of a
    Certificate of Origin issued retroactively to the customs
    authorities of the importing Party and subject to the respective
    domestic laws and regulations or administrative practices of the
    importing Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Customs Administration And Trade Facilitation" chapter_identifier="4595">
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="39743">This Chapter shall apply to customs administration measures and
    performance of customs operations required for the release of goods
    traded between the Parties, in order to promote:
  
        transparency of customs procedures and customs formalities;
      
        trade facilitation and harmonisation of customs operations; and
      
        customs cooperation including exchange of information between
        the central customs authorities of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39744">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  
        “customs administration”
          means organisational and management activities of the customs
          authorities of a Party as well as activities carried out
          within the regulatory framework while implementing the
          objectives in the customs area;
        
    
        “customs laws and
          regulations” means any norm and regulation enforced
          by the customs authorities of a Party including laws, rulings,
          decrees, writs, rules and others;
        
    
        “express consignments”
          means goods delivered through high-speed transportation
          systems by any type of transport, using an electronic
          information management system and tracking the movement in
          order to deliver the goods to the recipient in accordance with
          an individual invoice for the minimum possible or a fixed
          period of time, except for goods sent by international post;
        
    
        “inward processing” means
          the customs procedure under which foreign goods can be brought
          into the customs territory of a Party conditionally relieved
          from payment of customs duties and taxes on the basis that
          such goods are intended for processing or repair and
          subsequent exportation from the customs territory of such
          Party within a specified period of time;
        
    
        “outward processing” means
          the customs procedure under which goods, which are in free
          circulation in the customs territory of a Party, may be
          temporarily exported for processing abroad and then
          re-imported with total exemption from customs duties and
          taxes; and
        
    
        “temporary admission” means
          the customs procedure under which foreign goods can be brought
          into the customs territory of a Party conditionally relieved
          totally or partially from payment of customs duties and taxes
          on the basis that such goods shall be re-exported within a
          specified period of time in accordance with the customs laws
          and regulations of such Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.3" name="Facilitation Of Customs Administration Measures" article_identifier="39745">Each Party shall ensure that the customs administration measures
        applied by its customs authorities are predictable, consistent
        and transparent.
      
        Customs administration measures of each Party shall, where
        possible and to the extent permitted by its customs laws and
        regulations, be based on the standards and recommended practices
        of the World Customs Organization.
      
        The central customs authorities of each Party shall endeavour to
        review their customs administration measures with a view to
        simplifying such measures in order to facilitate trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.4" name="Release Of Goods" article_identifier="39746">Each Party shall adopt or maintain the performance of customs
        procedures and operations for the efficient release of goods in
        order to facilitate trade between the Parties. This shall not
        require a Party to release goods where its requirements for the
        release of such goods have not been met.
      
        Pursuant to paragraph 1 of this Article, each Party shall:
      
        provide for the release of goods within a period of time no
        longer than 48 hours from the registration of a customs
        declaration except in the circumstances stipulated in the
        customs laws and regulations of the Parties; and
      
        endeavour to adopt or maintain electronic submission and
        processing of customs information in advance of arrival of the
        goods to expedite the release of goods upon arrival.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.5" name="Risk Management" article_identifier="39747">Customs authorities of the Parties shall apply a risk management
    system by means of a systematic assessment of risks to focus
    inspections on high-risk goods and simplify the application of
    customs operations on low-risk goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.6" name="Customs Cooperation" article_identifier="39748">With a view to facilitating the effective operation of this
          Agreement, central customs authorities of the Parties shall
          encourage cooperation with each other on key customs issues
          that affect goods traded between the Parties.
        
    
        
          Where a central customs authority of a Party in accordance
          with such Party’s respective laws and regulations has a
          reasonable suspicion of an unlawful activity, such central
          customs authority may request the central customs authority of
          the other Party to provide specific confidential information
          normally collected in connection with the exportation and/or
          importation of goods.
        
    
        
          A Party’s request under paragraph 2 of this Article shall be
          in writing, specifying the purpose for which the information
          is sought and shall be accompanied by sufficient information
          to identify the concerned goods.
        
    
        
          The requested Party under paragraph 2 of this Article shall
          provide a written response containing the requested
          information.
        
    
        
          The central customs authority of the requested Party shall
          endeavour to provide any other information to the central
          customs authority of the requesting Party that would assist
          such central customs authority in determining whether imports
          from or exports to the requesting Party are in compliance with
          such Party’s respective laws and regulations.
        
    
        
          The central customs authorities of the Parties shall endeavour
          to establish and maintain channels of communication for
          customs cooperation, including establishing contact points
          that will facilitate the rapid and secure exchange of
          information, and improve coordination on customs issues.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.7" name="Information Exchange" article_identifier="39749">In order to facilitate the performance of customs operations, to
        expedite the release of goods and to prevent violations of
        customs laws and regulations, the central customs authorities of
        the Parties shall create and implement electronic information
        exchange on a regular basis between them (hereinafter referred
        to as “electronic information exchange”) within five years from
        the date of entry into force of this Agreement.
      
        On behalf of the Eurasian Economic Union, the Eurasian Economic
        Commission shall coordinate the creation and facilitate the
        operation of the electronic information exchange.
      
        For the purposes of this Article, “information” means relevant
        and authentic data from customs declarations and transport
        documents.
      
        Within one year from the date of entry into force of this
        Agreement, the central customs authorities of the Member States
        of the Eurasian Economic Union with the assistance of the
        Eurasian Economic Commission and the central customs authority
        of Viet Nam shall enter into consultations in order to develop
        electronic information exchange in accordance with paragraph 6
        of this Article.
      
        All requirements and specifications for the operation of
        electronic information exchange as well as specific contents of
        information to be exchanged shall be set out in separate
        protocols between the central customs authorities of the
        Parties. Such information shall be sufficient for identification
        of transported goods and performance of efficient customs
        control.
      
        The implementation of electronic information exchange shall be
        divided into the following stages:
      
        not later than two years from the date of entry into force of
        this Agreement the authorities involved shall establish trial
        electronic information exchange between individual customs
        authorities of the Parties which are responsible for the customs
        clearance of particular goods traded between the Parties. Such
        individual customs authorities and such particular goods shall
        be determined by the central customs authorities of the Parties
        in a protocol stipulated in paragraph 5 of this Article;
      
        not later than three years from the date of entry into force of
        this Agreement electronic information exchange shall cover goods
        for which the trade flow between the Parties will have increased
        more than 20 percent from the date of entry into force of this
        Agreement; and
      
        not later than five years from the date of entry into force of
        this Agreement central customs authorities of the Parties shall
        provide the application of electronic information exchange,
        covering all goods traded between the Parties, for all customs
        authorities concerned.
      
        Any information exchanged in accordance with the provisions of
        this Article shall be treated as confidential and shall be used
        for customs purposes only.
      
        The operation of electronic information exchange shall not
        hinder the application or establishment of any information
        exchange based on international obligations of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.8" name="Publication" article_identifier="39750">The competent authorities of each Party shall publish, on the
        internet or through any other appropriate media, the customs
        laws and regulations of such Party.
      
        The competent authorities of each Party shall designate or
        maintain one or more enquiry points to process enquiries from
        interested persons concerning customs issues, and shall publish
        on the internet information concerning such enquiry points.
      
        The competent authorities of a Party shall inform the competent
        authorities of the other Party of the contact information of the
        designated enquiry points.
      
        To the extent possible, each Party shall publish in advance its
        laws and regulations of general application governing customs
        issues that it proposes to adopt and shall provide interested
        persons with an opportunity to comment before adopting such laws
        and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.9" name="Advance Rulings" article_identifier="39751">Customs authorities of the Parties shall provide any applicant
        registered in the importing Party in writing with advance
        rulings in respect of tariff classification, origin of goods and
        any additional matter which a Party considers appropriate. The
        Parties shall endeavour to adopt or maintain the issuance of
        advance rulings in respect of the application of the method to
        be used for determining the customs value.
      
        Each Party shall adopt or maintain procedures for advance
        rulings, which shall:
      
        provide that the applicant may apply for an advance ruling
        before the importation of goods;
      
        require that the applicant for an advance ruling provide a
        detailed description of the goods and all relevant information
        needed to process an advance ruling;
      
        provide that its customs authority may, within 30 days from the
        date of application, request that the applicant provide
        additional information within a specified period of time;
      
        provide that any advance ruling be based on the facts and
        circumstances presented by the applicant and any other relevant
        information available to its customs authority; and
      
        provide that an advance ruling be issued to the applicant
        expeditiously, or in any case within 90 days from the date of
        the application or 60 days from the date of receipt of all
        necessary additional information.
      
        A customs authority of a Party may reject requests for an
        advance ruling where the additional information requested by it
        in accordance with subparagraph c) of paragraph 2 of this
        Article is not provided within the specified period of time.
      
        An advance ruling is valid for at least three years from the
        date of issuance, or such other period of time exceeding the
        specified period as required by the customs laws and regulations
        of the Parties.
      
        A customs authority of a Party may modify or revoke an advance
        ruling:
      
        upon a determination that the advance ruling was based on false
        or inaccurate information;
      
        if there is a change in the customs laws and regulations
        consistent with this Agreement; or
      
        if there is a change in material facts or circumstances on which
        the advance ruling is based.
      
        Subject to confidentiality requirements, the customs authorities
        of the Parties shall publish advance rulings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.10" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="39752">The customs value of goods traded between the Parties shall be
    determined in accordance with the customs laws and regulations of
    the importing Party based on the provisions of Article VII of GATT
    1994 and the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of the
    General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994, in Annex 1A to the WTO
    Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.11" name="Tariff Classification" article_identifier="39753">The Parties shall apply nomenclatures of goods based on the current
    edition of the Harmonized System to goods traded between them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.12" name="Transit Of Goods" article_identifier="39754">The Parties may mutually recognise identification tools and
    documents applied by the Parties required for the control of goods
    and vessels as well as other means of transport in transit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.13" name="Express Consignments" article_identifier="39755">Customs authorities of the Parties shall provide expedited
        customs clearance for express consignments while maintaining
        appropriate customs control.
      
        Express consignments shall be placed under the customs procedure
        in an expedited manner in accordance with the customs laws and
        regulations of the respective Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.14" name="Temporary Admission Of Goods" article_identifier="39756">In accordance with international standards, customs authorities of
    the Parties shall endeavour to facilitate the performance of customs
    operations for the customs procedure of temporary admission of
    goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.15" name="Inward Processing And Outward Processing" article_identifier="39757">In accordance with international standards, customs authorities of
    the Parties shall endeavour to facilitate the performance of customs
    operations for temporary importation and exportation of goods for
    inward processing or outward processing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.16" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="39758">All information provided in accordance with this Chapter, excluding
    statistics, shall be treated by the Parties as confidential in
    accordance with the respective laws and regulations of the Parties.
    It shall not be disclosed by the authorities of the Parties without
    the permission of the person or authority of the Party providing
    such information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.17" name="Customs Agents (Representatives)" article_identifier="39759">The customs laws and regulations of each Party shall enable
    declarants to submit their customs declarations without requiring
    mandatory recourse to the services of customs agents
    (representatives).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.18" name="Automation" article_identifier="39760">The customs authorities of the Parties shall ensure that customs
        operations may be performed with the use of information systems
        and information technologies, including those based on
        electronic means of communication.
      
        The central customs authorities of the Parties shall provide
        declarants with an opportunity to declare goods in electronic
        form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.19" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="39761">Each Party shall ensure the possibility of administrative review of
    customs decisions affecting rights of interested persons and
    judicial appeal against such decisions in accordance with the laws
    and regulations of the respective Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.20" name="Penalties" article_identifier="39762">Each Party shall adopt or maintain measures that allow for the
    imposition of administrative penalties for violations of its customs
    laws and regulations during importation and exportation, including
    provisions on tariff classification, customs valuation,
    determination of country of origin and obtaining preferential tariff
    treatment under this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Technical Barriers To Trade" chapter_identifier="4596">
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39763">The objectives of this Chapter are to facilitate trade in goods
    between the Parties by:
  
        
          promoting cooperation on the preparation, adoption and
          application of standards, technical regulations and conformity
          assessment procedures in order to eliminate unnecessary
          technical barriers to trade, reduce, where possible,
          unnecessary costs to exporters;
        
    
        
          promoting mutual understanding of each Party’s standards,
          technical regulations and conformity assessment procedures;
        
    
        
          strengthening information exchange between the Parties in
          relation to the preparation, adoption and application of
          standards, technical regulations and conformity assessment
          procedures;
        
    
        
          strengthening cooperation between the Parties in the work of
          international bodies related to standardisation and conformity
          assessment;
        
    
        
          providing a framework to realise these objectives; and
        
    
        
          promoting cooperation on issues relating to technical barriers
          to trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.2" name="Scope" article_identifier="39764">This Chapter shall apply to all standards, technical
          regulations and conformity assessment procedures of the
          Parties that may directly or indirectly affect the trade in
          goods between the Parties except:
        
    
        purchasing specifications prepared by governmental bodies for
        production or consumption requirements of governmental bodies;
        and
      
        sanitary or phytosanitary measures as defined in Chapter 7
        (Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures) of this Agreement.
      
        
          In accordance with this Chapter and the TBT Agreement each
          Party has the right to prepare, adopt and apply standards,
          technical regulations and conformity assessment procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.3" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39765">For the purposes of this Chapter, the definitions set out in Annex 1
    to the TBT Agreement shall apply, mutatis
    mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.4" name="Incorporation Of The Tbt Agreement" article_identifier="39766">Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, the TBT Agreement
    shall apply between the Parties and is incorporated into and form
    part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.5" name="Transparency" article_identifier="39767">The Parties acknowledge the importance of transparency with
          regard to the preparation, adoption and application of
          standards, technical regulations and conformity assessment
          procedures.
        
    
        
          Each Party should provide the period for comments of at least
          60 days following the publication of a notice of the kind
          envisaged in Articles 2.9 and/or 5.6 of the TBT Agreement,
          except for situations where urgent problems of safety, health,
          environmental protection or national security arise or
          threaten to arise for the Parties.
        
    
        
          Each Party should allow at least 180 days from the adoption of
          a technical regulation and/or conformity assessment procedure
          and their/its entry into force, except for situations where
          urgent problems of safety, health, environmental protection or
          national security arise or threaten to arise for the Parties.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall, to the fullest extent possible, endeavour
          to exchange information in the English language.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.6" name="Marking And Labelling" article_identifier="39768">The Parties note that in accordance with paragraph 1 of Annex 1 to
    the TBT Agreement, a technical regulation may include or deal
    exclusively with marking or labelling requirements, and agree that
    where such technical regulation contains mandatory marking or
    labelling requirements, they will act in accordance with the
    principles of Article 2.2 of the TBT Agreement that technical
    regulations should not be prepared, adopted and applied with a view
    to, or with the effect of, creating unnecessary obstacles to
    international trade, and should not be more trade restrictive than
    necessary to fulfil a legitimate objective.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.7" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39769">Where the day to day application of standards, technical
        regulations and conformity assessment procedures is affecting
        trade between the Parties, a Party may request consultations
        aimed at resolving the matter. A request for consultations shall
        be directed to the other Party’s contact point established in
        accordance with Article 6.9 of this Agreement.
      
        Each Party shall make every effort to give prompt and positive
        consideration to any request from the other Party for
        consultations on issues relating to the implementation of this
        Chapter.
      
        Where a matter covered under this Chapter cannot be clarified or
        resolved as a result of consultations, the Parties may establish
        an ad hoc working group with a view to
        identifying a workable and practical solution that would
        facilitate trade. The working group shall comprise
        representatives of the Parties.
      
        Where a Party declines a request from the other Party to
        establish a working group, it shall, upon request, explain the
        reasons for its decision.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.8" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="39770">For the purposes of ensuring that standards, technical
        regulations and conformity assessment procedures do not create
        unnecessary obstacles to trade in goods between the Parties, the
        Parties shall, where possible, cooperate in the field of
        standards, technical regulations and conformity assessment
        procedures.
      
        The cooperation pursuant to paragraph 1 of this Article may
        include the following:
      
        holding joint seminars in order to enhance mutual understanding
        of standards, technical regulations and conformity assessment
        procedures in each Party;
      
        exchanging officials of the Parties for training purposes;
      
        exchanging information on standards, technical regulations and
        conformity assessment procedures;
      
        strengthening cooperation in international fora, including
        international bodies related to standardisation and conformity
        assessment and the WTO Committee on Technical Barriers to Trade,
        in areas of mutual interest;
      
        encouraging the bodies responsible for standards, technical
        regulations and conformity assessment procedures in each Party
        to cooperate on matters of mutual interest;
      
        providing scientific and technical cooperation in order to
        improve the quality of technical regulations; and
      
        making efficient use of regulatory resources.
      
        The implementation of paragraph 2 of this Article shall be
        subject to the availability of appropriated funds and the
        respective laws and regulations of each Party.
      
        Cooperation on issues relating to technical barriers to trade
        may be undertaken, inter alia, through
        dialogue in appropriate channels, joint projects and technical
        assistance.
      
        The Parties may conduct joint projects, technical assistance and
        cooperation on standards, technical regulations and conformity
        assessment procedures in selected areas, as mutually agreed.
      
        The Parties undertake to exchange views on matters of market
        surveillance and enforcement activities in the field thereof
        relating to technical barriers to trade.
      
        Upon request, a Party shall give appropriate consideration to
        proposals that the other Party makes for cooperation under this
        Chapter.
      
        In order to promote cooperation in the framework of this
        Chapter, the Parties may conclude ad hoc
        arrangements on the matters covered therein.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.9" name="Competent Authorities And Contact Points" article_identifier="39771">The Parties shall designate competent authorities and contact
        points and exchange information containing the names of the
        designated competent authorities and contact points, contact
        details of relevant officials in such competent authorities and
        contact points, including telephone and facsimile numbers, email
        addresses and other relevant details.
      
        The Parties shall promptly notify each other of any change to
        their competent authorities and contact points or amendment to
        the information of the relevant officials.
      
        The contact points’ functions shall include the following:
      
        facilitating the exchange of information between the Parties on
        standards, technical regulations and conformity assessment
        procedures in response to all reasonable requests for such
        information from a Party; and
      
        referring the enquiries from a Party to the appropriate
        regulatory authorities.
      
        The competent authorities’ functions shall include:
      
        monitoring the implementation of this Chapter;
      
        facilitating cooperation activities, as appropriate, in
        accordance with Article 6.8 of this Agreement;
      
        promptly addressing any issue that a Party raises related to the
        preparation, adoption, application or enforcement of standards,
        technical regulations and conformity assessment procedures;
      
        facilitating consultations on any matter arising under this
        Chapter upon request of a Party;
      
        taking any other action that the Parties consider will assist
        them in implementing this Chapter; and
      
        carrying out other functions as may be delegated by the Joint
        Committee.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="4597">
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39772">The objectives of this Chapter are to facilitate trade in goods
    between the Parties by:
  
        
          seeking to resolve issues relating to sanitary and
          phytosanitary measures while protecting human, animal or plant
          life or health in the territories of the Parties;
        
    
        
          strengthening cooperation between the Parties and among their
          competent authorities including in the development and
          application of sanitary and phytosanitary measures as defined
          in the SPS Agreement; and
        
    
        
          facilitating information exchange in the field of sanitary and
          phytosanitary measures and enhancing the knowledge and
          understanding of each Party’s regulatory system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.2" name="Scope" article_identifier="39773">This Chapter shall apply to sanitary and phytosanitary measures of
    the Parties that may, directly or indirectly, affect trade between
    the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.3" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39774">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  
        
          the definitions set out in Annex A to the SPS Agreement shall
          apply, mutatis mutandis; and
        
    
        
          the relevant definitions developed by the international
          organisations: the Codex Alimentarius Commission, the World
          Organization for Animal Health (hereinafter referred to as
          “OIE”) and international and regional organisations operating
          within the framework of the International Plant Protection
          Convention (hereinafter referred to as “IPPC”) shall apply in
          the implementation of this Chapter, mutatis
          mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.4" name="Incorporation Of The Sps Agreement" article_identifier="39775">Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, the SPS Agreement
    shall apply between the Parties and is incorporated into and form
    part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.5" name="Equivalence" article_identifier="39776">The Parties recognise that equivalence is an important means
          to facilitate trade.
        
    
        
          The Parties may recognise equivalence of a measure, a group of
          measures or a system to the extent feasible and appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.6" name="Adaptation To Regional Conditions" article_identifier="39777">The Parties recognise the concept of adaptation to regional
          conditions, including pest- or disease-free areas and areas of
          low pest or disease prevalence, as an important means to
          facilitate trade.
        
    
        
          When determining such areas, the Parties shall consider
          factors such as information of the Parties confirming the
          status of pest- or disease-free areas and areas of low pest or
          disease prevalence, the results of an audit, inspection
          monitoring, information provided by OIE and IPPC and other
          factors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.7" name="Audit And Inspections" article_identifier="39778">Each Party may carry out an audit and/or inspection in order
          to ensure the safety of the products (goods).
        
    
        
          The Parties agree to enhance further their cooperation in the
          field of audits and inspections.
        
    
        
          In undertaking audits and/or inspections, each Party shall
          take into account relevant international standards, guidelines
          and recommendations.
        
    
        
          The auditing or inspecting Party shall provide the audited or
          inspected Party the opportunities to comment on the findings
          of the audits and/or inspections.
        
    
        
          Costs incurred by the auditing or inspecting Party shall be
          borne by the auditing or inspecting Party, unless both Parties
          agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.8" name="Documents Confirming Safety" article_identifier="39779">Where a document is required to confirm safety of the products
          (goods) traded between the Parties, the exporting Party shall
          ensure compliance with the requirements of the importing
          Party. The importing Party shall ensure the requirements of
          the documents for confirming safety of the products (goods)
          traded between the Parties are applied only to the extent
          necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall take into account relevant international
          standards, guidelines and recommendations, when developing the
          documents for confirming safety of the products (goods), as
          appropriate.
        
    
        
          The Parties may agree to develop bilateral documents for
          confirming safety of specific product (good) or groups of
          products (goods) traded between the Parties.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall promote the use of electronic technologies
          in the documents for confirming safety of the products (goods)
          in order to facilitate trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.9" name="Emergency Measures" article_identifier="39780">Where a Party adopts emergency measures necessary to protect
          human, animal or plant life or health, such Party shall as
          soon as possible notify such measures to the other Party. The
          Party that adopted the emergency measures shall take into
          consideration relevant information provided by the other
          Party.
        
    
        
          Upon request of either Party, consultations of the relevant
          competent authorities regarding the emergency measures shall
          be held as soon as possible unless otherwise agreed by the
          Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.10" name="Contact Points And Information Exchange" article_identifier="39781">The Parties shall notify each other of the contact points for
          the provision of information in accordance with this Chapter
          and of their designated competent authorities responsible for
          matters covered by this Chapter and the areas of
          responsibility of such competent authorities.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall inform each other of any change to their
          contact points or any significant change in the structure or
          competence of their competent authorities.
        
    
        
          The Parties, through their contact points, shall provide each
          other in a timely manner with a written notification of:
        
    
        any significant food safety issue or change in animal or plant
        health, disease or pest status in their territories; and
      
        any change to the legal frameworks or other sanitary or
        phytosanitary measures.
      
        
          The Parties, through their contact points, shall inform each
          other of systematic or significant cases of non-compliance of
          sanitary and phytosanitary measures and exchange relevant
          documents which confirm this non-compliance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.11" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="39782">The Parties agree to cooperate in order to facilitate the
          implementation of this Chapter.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall explore opportunities for further
          cooperation, collaboration and information exchange on
          sanitary and phytosanitary matters of mutual interest
          consistent with the provisions of this Chapter. Such
          opportunities may include trade facilitation initiatives and
          technical assistance.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall aim to work together in international fora,
          including international organisations, and in areas of mutual
          interest.
        
    
        
          In order to promote cooperation within the framework of this
          Chapter, the Parties may conclude ad hoc
          arrangements on sanitary and phytosanitary measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.12" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39783">Where a Party considers that a sanitary or phytosanitary
          measure is affecting its trade with the other Party, it may,
          through the relevant contact points, request consultations
          with the aim of resolving the matter.
        
    
        
          A Party shall consider to hold consultations under the context
          of this Chapter, upon request of the other Party, with the aim
          of resolving matters arising under this Chapter.
        
    
        
          In case either Party considers that the matter cannot be
          resolved through consultations in accordance with this
          Article, such Party shall have the right to seek resolution
          through the dispute settlement mechanism provided for in
          Chapter 14 (Dispute Settlement) of this Agreement.
    TRADE IN SERVICES, INVESTMENT AND MOVEMENT OF NATURAL PERSONS</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION I" name="Horizontal Provisions" chapter_identifier="4598">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39784">The objectives of this Chapter are to encourage efficiency,
    competition and economic growth of the Parties to this Chapter by
    facilitating the expansion of trade in services, establishment,
    investment and movement of natural persons of the Parties to this
    Chapter on the basis of a transparent and stable legal framework,
    while recognising the right of the Parties to this Chapter to
    regulate in order to meet national policy objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.2" name="Scope" article_identifier="39785">This Chapter shall apply only between the Russian Federation and
Viet Nam, hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as the “Parties to this Chapter”.
    
        
          This Chapter shall apply to measures by the Parties to this
          Chapter affecting trade in services, establishment,
          investments and movement of natural persons.
        
    
        
          In respect of air transport services, this Chapter shall not
          apply to measures affecting air traffic rights, however
          granted, or measures affecting services directly related to
          the exercise of air traffic rights, except the measures
          affecting aircraft repair and maintenance services, the
          selling and marketing of air transport services, computer
          reservation system services as provided for in paragraph 6 of
          the Annex on Air Transport Services of GATS. The definitions
          of paragraph 6 of the Annex on Air Transport Services of GATS
          are incorporated into and form part of this Chapter.
        
    
        
          This Chapter shall not apply to:
        
    
        government procurement, which is subject to Chapter 10 of this
        Agreement;
      
        measures affecting natural persons seeking access to the
        employment market of a Party to this Chapter; or
      
        measures regarding citizenship, residence or employment on a
        permanent basis.
      
        
          This Chapter shall not prevent a Party to this Chapter from
          applying measures to regulate the entry of natural persons of
          the other Party to this Chapter into or their temporary stay
          in its territory, including those necessary to protect the
          integrity of, and to ensure the orderly movement of natural
          persons across its borders, provided that such measures are
          not applied in such a manner as to nullify or impair the
          benefits accruing to the other Party to this Chapter under the
          terms of a specific commitment. The sole fact of requiring a
          visa for natural persons of a Party to this Chapter and not
          for those of any other third country shall not be regarded as
          nullifying or impairing benefits under the commitments made in
          this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.3" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39786">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  “trade in services” means the
        supply of a service:
      
        from the territory of a Party to this Chapter into the territory
        of the other Party to this Chapter;
      
        in the territory of a Party to this Chapter to the service
        consumer of the other Party to this Chapter;
      “supply of a service”
        includes production, distribution, marketing, sale and delivery
        of a service;
      “services” includes any
        service in any sector except services supplied neither on a
        commercial basis nor in competition with one or more service
        suppliers;
      “service supplier” means any
        person that supplies a service;
      “service consumer” means any
        person that receives or uses a service;
      “person” means either a
        natural person or a juridical person;
      “natural person of a Party to this
        Chapter” means a natural person who, under the
        applicable laws and regulations of that Party to this Chapter,
        is a national of such Party to this Chapter;
      “juridical person” means any
        legal entity duly constituted or otherwise organised under
        applicable laws and regulations;
      
    
      A juridical person is:
    “owned” by persons of a Party to this Chapter if more than
50 percent of the equity interest in it is beneficially owned by persons of such Party to this Chapter;
      “controlled” by persons of a Party to this Chapter if such persons
      have the power to name a majority of its directors or otherwise to
      legally direct its actions.
    
  “juridical person of a Party to this
        Chapter” means a juridical person which is
        constituted or otherwise organised under the laws and
        regulations of such Party;
      “economic integration
        agreements” means international agreements complying
        with the requirements of Articles V and/or
        Vbis of GATS;
      “measure” means any measure
        by a Party to this Chapter, whether in form of a law,
        regulation, rule, procedure, decision, administrative action or
        any other form;
      “measure by a Party to this
        Chapter” means measures taken by:
      
        central, regional or local governments and authorities of that
        Party to this Chapter; and
      
        non-governmental bodies in the exercise of powers delegated by
        central, regional or local governments or authorities of that
        Party to this Chapter.
      “measures by Parties to this Chapter
        affecting trade in services” include measures in
        respect of:
      
        the purchase, payment or use of a service;
      
        the access to and use of, in connection with the supply of a
        service, services which are required by the Parties to this
        Chapter to be offered to the public generally.
      “measures by Parties to this Chapter
        affecting establishment, commercial presence and
        activities” include measures in respect of
        establishment, commercial presence of juridical persons of a
        Party to this Chapter in the territory of the other Party to
        this Chapter or activities thereof;
      “establishment” means:
      
        the establishment (or constitution) and/or acquisition of a
        juridical person (participation in the capital of an existing
        juridical person) of any legal form and ownership provided for
        in laws and regulations of a Party to this Chapter within the
        territory of which this person is being established, constituted
        or acquired;
      
        the acquisition of control over a juridical person of a Party to
        this Chapter by legally determining, directly or indirectly, the
        decisions taken by such juridical person, including through
        voting shares (stocks), participation in managing bodies of such
        juridical person (including in board of directors, supervisory
        board, et cetera);
      
        the creation of a branch; or
      
        the creation of a representative office,
      
    
      for the purposes of supplying a service and/or performing an
      economic activity in sectors other than services.
    
  “commercial presence” means
        juridical persons established, constituted, acquired or
        controlled and/or branches or a representative office created
        for the purpose of supplying a service and/or performing an
        economic activity in sectors other than services. For the
        purposes of this Section commercial presence established,
        constituted, acquired, controlled or created is hereinafter
        referred to as “commercial presence set up”;
      “activities” means activities
        of industrial, commercial or professional character of the
        juridical persons, branches, representative offices, referred to
        in subparagraph o) of this Article, except for those carried out
        neither on a commercial basis nor in competition with one or
        more persons engaged in the same type of activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.4" name="Other International Agreements" article_identifier="39787">In case an international agreement to which both Parties to this
    Chapter are party, including the WTO Agreement, provides for more
    favourable treatment in respect of matters covered by this Chapter
    for their persons (service suppliers) and/or their commercial
    presences, services or investments, such more favourable treatment
    shall not be affected by this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.5" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="39788">Article VI of GATS shall apply between the Parties to this
          Chapter, mutatis mutandis.
        
    
        
          Without prejudice to the right of a Party to this Chapter to
          establish and apply licensing procedures and requirements,
          regarding the services sectors in respect of which such Party
          has undertaken specific commitments in accordance with Section
          II (Trade in Services) of this Chapter, as well as regarding
          the establishment and activities covered by Section III
          (Establishment, Commercial Presence and Activities) of this
          Chapter such Party shall ensure that:
        
    
        its licensing procedures are not in themselves a restriction on
        the establishment, activities or supply of a service, and that
        its licensing requirements directly related to eligibility to
        supply a service were not in themselves an unjustified barrier
        to the supply of the service;
      
        its competent authorities make a decision on granting/denial of
        a licence without undue delay and no later than the period
        specified in relevant laws and regulations of such Party;
      
        any fees charged in connection with the filing and review of an
        application for a licence would not in themselves be a
        restriction on the supply of the service, establishment or
        activities;
      
        once any period for review of an application for a licence
        established in the laws and regulations of such Party lapsed,
        and upon the request of an applicant, such Party’s competent
        authority informs the applicant of the status of its application
        and whether it was considered complete. If the authority
        requires additional information from the applicant, it shall
        notify the applicant without undue delay and specify the
        additional information required to complete the application.
        Applicants shall have the opportunity to provide the additional
        information requested and to make technical corrections in the
        application. An application shall not be considered complete
        until all information and documents specified in the respective
        laws and regulations of that Party are received;
      
        upon the written request of an unsuccessful applicant, the
        competent authority that has denied an application will inform
        the applicant in writing of the reasons for the denial of the
        application. However, this provision shall not be construed to
        require a regulatory authority to disclose information, where
        that disclosure would impede law enforcement or otherwise be
        contrary to the public interest or essential security interests;
      
        where an application is denied, an applicant shall have the
        right to submit a new application that attempts to address any
        prior problems for licensing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.6" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="39789">The Parties to this Chapter shall designate their contact points to
    facilitate communications between the Parties to this Chapter on the
    issues covered by this Chapter and shall exchange information on the
    details of such contact points. The Parties to this Chapter shall
    notify each other promptly of any amendments to the details of their
    contact points.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.7" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="39790">A Party to this Chapter may deny benefits of this Section to a
    person of the other Party to this Chapter, if the former Party
    establishes that this person is a juridical person that has no
    substantive business operations in the territory of the other Party
    to this Chapter and is owned or controlled by persons of either:
  
        any third country; or
      
        the former Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.8" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="39791">Notwithstanding the provisions of Articles 8.18 and 8.37 of
          this Agreement each Party to this Chapter may adopt and
          maintain restrictions on trade in services, establishment and
          investments in respect of which commitments were undertaken by
          such Party in accordance with this Chapter, including on
          payments or transfers for transactions related to such
          commitments referred to in Articles 8.18 and 8.37 of this
          Agreement in the event of serious balance of payments and
          external financial difficulties and threat thereof and subject
          to the condition that such restrictions:
        
    
        shall be applied on a most-favoured-nation basis;
      
        shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the
        International Monetary Fund;
      
        shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial, economic and
        financial interests of the other Party to this Chapter;
      
        shall not exceed those necessary to deal with circumstances
        described in this paragraph;
      
        shall be temporary and be phased out progressively as the
        situation specified in this paragraph improve.
      
        
          The Party to this Chapter introducing a restriction under
          paragraph 1 of this Article shall promptly notify the other
          Party to this Chapter of such measure.
        
    
        
          In determining the incidence of such restrictions, the Parties
          to this Chapter may give priority to the supply of services
          which are more essential to their economic or development
          programmes. However, such restrictions shall not be adopted or
          maintained for the purpose of protecting a particular service
          sector.
        
    
        
          Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and
          obligations of a Party to this Chapter which is a member of
          the International Monetary Fund under the Articles of
          Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, including the
          use of exchange actions which are in conformity with the
          Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund,
          provided that such Party to this Chapter shall not impose
          restrictions inconsistently with the conditions provided for
          in paragraph 1 of this Article.
        
    
        
          This Article shall not be subject to the dispute settlement
          procedures stipulated by the Article 8.38 of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.9" name="Accession" article_identifier="39792">Notwithstanding Article 15.2 of the Agreement, any Member
          State of the Eurasian Economic Union may accede to this
          Chapter on terms and conditions as agreed between such Member
          State of the Eurasian Economic Union and Viet Nam in respect
          of Schedules of Specific Commitments and Lists of
          reservations.
        
    
        
          In case of accession of a Member State of the Eurasian
          Economic Union to this Chapter the provisions of this Chapter
          shall neither apply between the Parties to this Chapter that
          are Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union nor shall
          they grant to Viet Nam any rights and privileges that Member
          States of the Eurasian Economic Union grant exclusively to
          each other.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.10" name="Amendments" article_identifier="39793">Notwithstanding Article 15.5 of the Agreement, this Chapter
          may be amended by mutual written consent of the Parties to
          this Chapter.
        
    
        
          The amendments to this Chapter resulting from accession of a
          Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union shall be
          introduced by mutual written consent of the Parties to this
    
          acceding to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.11" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39794">The Parties to this Chapter shall consult at the request of
          either of them, on the matter concerning the interpretation or
          application of this Chapter.
        
    
The consultations referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article may be conducted by the Joint Committee established in accordance with
Article 1.4 of this Agreement.
    
        
          For the purposes of this Chapter the Joint Committee shall be
          co-chaired by the representatives of the Parties to this
          Chapter and any of the decisions of Joint Committee on the
          matters covered by this Chapter shall be taken by consensus
          only by the Parties to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.12" name="Settlement Of Disputes Between The Parties To This Chapter" article_identifier="39795">The provisions of Chapter 14 (Dispute Settlement) of this
          Agreement shall apply with respect to the settlement of
          disputes between the Parties to this Chapter regarding the
          interpretation or application of this Chapter with the
          modifications set out in paragraph 2 of this Article.
        
    
        
          For the purposes of this Chapter:
        
    
        the term “a disputing Party” referred to in Chapter 14 of this
        Agreement means “a Party to this Chapter”;
      the request for consultations referred to in paragraph 2 of
Article 14.6 of this Agreement shall be submitted in writing to the responding Party through its contact points designated in accordance with Article 8.6 of this Agreement;
        the request for the establishment of an Arbitral Panel referred
        to in paragraph 3 of Article 14.7 of this Agreement shall be
        submitted in writing to the responding Party through its contact
        points designated in accordance with Article 8.6 of this
        Agreement; and
      
        the suspension of benefits referred to in Article 14.15 of this
        Agreement may be performed only in respect of the benefits
        provided for in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.13" name="Lists Of Commitments" article_identifier="39796">The “Schedule of Specific Commitments under Section II (Trade in
    Services)”, “List of Reservations under Section III (Establishment,
    Commercial Presence and Activities)”, the “Schedule of Specific
    Commitments under Section IV (Movement of Natural Persons)” and
    “List of MFN Exemptions in accordance with Articles 8.15 and 8.22 of
    the Agreement” shall be signed in the form of Protocol No. 1 between
    the Russian Federation and the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam to the
    Free Trade Agreement between the Eurasian Economic Union and its
    Member States, of the one part, and the Socialist Republic of Viet
    Nam, of the other part (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as
    “Protocol No. 1”) on the date of signature of this Agreement. The
    Protocol No.1 shall constitute an integral part of this Agreement
    and shall be binding only in respect of the Russian Federation and
    Viet Nam.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION II" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="4599">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.14" name="Scope" article_identifier="39797">This Section shall apply to any measure of the Parties to this
          Chapter affecting trade in services.
        
    
        
          This Section shall not apply to provision of subsidies or
          other forms of State or municipal support to service suppliers
          or their services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.15" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39798">With respect to any measure covered by this Section, each
          Party to this Chapter shall accord immediately and
          unconditionally to services and service suppliers of the other
          Party to this Chapter treatment no less favourable than that
          it accords to like services and service suppliers of any third
          country.
        
    
        
          A Party to this Chapter may maintain a measure inconsistent
          with paragraph 1 of this Article provided that such a measure
          is set out in its individual national List in Annex 1 to
          Protocol No. 1.
        
    
        
          The provisions of this Section shall not be construed to
          prevent a Party to this Chapter from conferring or according
          advantages to adjacent countries in order to facilitate trade
          in services limited to contiguous frontier zones of services
          that are both locally produced and consumed.
        
    
        
          Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to oblige a Party
          to this Chapter to provide to services or service suppliers of
          the other Party to this Chapter benefits or privileges that
          the former Party is providing or will provide in future:
        
    
        in accordance with the economic integration agreements of the
        former Party; or
      
        on the basis of the agreements on avoidance of double taxation
        or other arrangements on taxation issues.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.16" name="Market Access" article_identifier="39799">With respect to market access through the modes of supply defined in Article 8.3 of this Agreement, each Party to this Chapter shall accord to services and service suppliers of the other Party to this Chapter treatment no less favourable than that provided for under the terms, limitations and conditions agreed and specified in its Schedule in Annex 2 to
Protocol No. 1.
 If a Party to this Chapter undertakes a market-access commitment in
relation to the supply of a service from the territory of a Party to
this Chapter into the territory of the other Party to this Chapter and
if the cross-border movement of capital is an essential part of the
service itself, that Party is thereby committed to allow such movement
of capital.

    
        
          In sectors where market access commitments are undertaken, the
          measures which a Party to this Chapter shall not maintain or
          adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision or on the
          basis of its entire territory, unless otherwise specified in
          its Schedule in Annex 2 to Protocol No. 1, are defined as:
        
    
        limitations on the number of service suppliers whether in the
        form of numerical quotas, monopolies, exclusive service
        suppliers or the requirements of an economic needs test;
      
        limitations on the total value of service transactions or assets
        in the form of numerical quotas or the requirement of an
        economic needs test; or
      
        limitations on the total number of service operations or on the
        total quantity of service output expressed in terms of
        designated numerical units in the form of quotas or the
        requirement of an economic needs test.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.17" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="39800">In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule in Annex 2 to
          Protocol No. 1, and subject to any condition and qualification
          set out therein, each Party to this Chapter shall accord to
          services and service suppliers of the other Party to this
          Chapter, in respect of all measures affecting supply of
          services, treatment no less favourable than that it accords to
          its own like services and service suppliers.
               Specific commitments assumed under this Article shall not
              be construed to require any Party to this Chapter to
              compensate for any inherent competitive disadvantages
              which result from the foreign character of the relevant
              services or service suppliers.
            
    
        
          A Party to this Chapter may meet the requirement of paragraph
          1 of this Article by according to services and service
          suppliers of the other Party to this Chapter, either formally
          identical treatment or formally different treatment to that it
          accords to its own like services and service suppliers.
        
    
        
          Formally identical or formally different treatment shall be
          considered to be less favourable if it modifies the conditions
          of competition in favour of services or service suppliers of a
          Party to this Chapter compared to like services or service
          suppliers of the other Party to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.18" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="39801">Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article 8.8 of
          this Agreement a Party to this Chapter shall not apply
          restrictions on international transfers and payments for
          current transactions relating to its specific commitments
          under this Section.
        
    
        
          Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and
          obligations of the Parties to this Chapter as members of the
          International Monetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of
          the International Monetary Fund, including the use of exchange
          actions which are in conformity with the Articles of Agreement
          of the International Monetary Fund, provided that a Party to
          this Chapter shall not impose restrictions on any capital
          transactions inconsistently with its specific commitments
          under this Section regarding such transactions, except under
          Article 8.8 of this Agreement or at the request of the
          International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.19" name="Recognition" article_identifier="39802">Article VII of GATS shall apply between the Parties to this Chapter,
    mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION III" name="Establishment, Commercial Presence And Activities" chapter_identifier="4600">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.20" name="Scope" article_identifier="39803">This Section shall apply to any measure by the Parties to this
          Chapter affecting establishment, commercial presence and
          activities.
        
    
        
          This Section shall apply to commercial presence set up by a
          person of a Party to this Chapter within the territory of the
          other Party to this Chapter at the date or after the date of
          entry into force of this Agreement.
        
    
        
          This Section shall not apply to provision of subsidies or
          other forms of State or municipal support to persons and their
          commercial presence in connection with establishment and/or
          activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.21" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="39804">With respect to establishment and subject to the reservations
          set out in its individual national List provided for in Annex
          3 to Protocol No. 1, each Party to this Chapter shall grant,
          within its territory, to the persons of the other Party to
          this Chapter treatment no less favourable than that it accords
          in like circumstances to its own persons.
        
    
        
          With respect to activities and subject to the reservations set
          out in its individual national List provided for in Annex 3 to
          Protocol No. 1, each Party to this Chapter shall grant to the
          commercial presence set up by a person of other Party to this
          Chapter within the territory of the former Party treatment not
          less favourable than the treatment granted in like
          circumstances to the commercial presences of its own persons
          set up within its territory.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.22" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39805">With respect to establishment and subject to the reservations
          set out in its individual national List provided for in Annex
          1 to Protocol No. 1, each Party to this Chapter shall grant to
          the persons of the other Party to this Chapter treatment no
          less favourable than that it accords in like circumstances to
          persons of any third country.
        
    
        
          With respect to activities and subject to the reservations set
          out in its individual national List provided for in Annex 1 to
          Protocol No. 1, each Party to this Chapter shall grant to the
          commercial presence set up by a person of the other Party to
          this Chapter within the territory of the former Party
          treatment not less favourable than the treatment granted in
          like circumstances to the commercial presences of persons of
          any third country.
        
    
        
          For greater certainty, this Article shall not apply to
          international dispute settlement procedures or mechanisms such
          as those set out in Article 8.38 of this Agreement.
        
    
        
          Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to oblige a Party
          to this Chapter to provide to the persons of the other Party
          to this Chapter or their commercial presences benefits or
          privileges that the former Party is providing or will provide
          in future:
        
    
        in accordance with economic integration agreements of the former
        Party; or
      
        on the basis of the agreements on avoidance of double taxation
        or other arrangements on taxation issues.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.23" name="Market Access" article_identifier="39806">With respect to establishment and/or activities neither Party to
    this Chapter shall maintain or apply to persons of the other Party
    to this Chapter and/or to commercial presences of such persons set
    up within the territory of the former Party, respectively,
    limitations in respect of:
  
        form of the commercial presence, including legal form of the
        entity;
      
        total number of commercial presences set up;
      
        maximum percentage limit on shareholding by the persons of the
        other Party to this Chapter in the capital of a juridical person
        of the former Party or on degree of control over such juridical
        person; or
      
        transactions/operations performed by the commercial presence set
        up by the person of the other Party to this Chapter in the
        course of their activities in the form of quota or the
        requirement of economic needs test
      
    except for the limitations provided for in the individual national
    List of the former Party set out in Annex 3 to Protocol No. 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.24" name="Performance Requirements" article_identifier="39807">Subject to the reservations set out in its individual national
          List provided for in Annex 3 to Protocol No. 1 neither Party
          to this Chapter shall in connection with establishment and/or
          activities impose or enforce in respect of commercial
          presences of persons of the other Party to this Chapter set up
          within the territory of the former Party, respectively, any
          requirement:
        
    
        to export a given level or percentage of goods or services;
      
        to purchase, use or accord a preference to goods produced in its
        territory;
      
        to relate in any way the volume or value of imports to the
        volume or value of exports or to the amount of foreign exchange
        inflows associated with such establishment and/or activities;
      
        to restrict sales of goods or services in its territory that
        such commercial presences produces or supplies by relating such
        sales in any way to the volume or value of its exports or
        foreign exchange earnings;
      
        to transfer a particular technology, a production process, or
        other proprietary information to persons in the territory of the
        former Party; or
      
        to supply exclusively from the territory of the former Party the
        goods that it produces or the services that it supplies to a
        specific regional market or to the world market.
      
        
          Neither Party to this Chapter shall condition the receipt or
          continued receipt of an advantage in connection with
          establishment and/or activities of commercial presences of
          persons of the other Party to this Chapter set up within the
          territory of the former Party on compliance with any of the
          following requirements:
        
    
        to purchase, use or accord a preference to goods produced in the
        territory of the former Party;
      
        to relate in any way the volume or value of imports to the
        volume or value of exports or to the amount of foreign exchange
        inflows associated with such establishment and/or activities; or
      
        to restrict sales of goods or services in its territory that
        such commercial presences produces or supplies by relating such
        sales in any way to the volume or value of its exports or
        foreign exchange earnings.
      
        
          Nothing in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be construed to
          prevent a Party to this Chapter from conditioning the receipt
          or continued receipt of an advantage, in connection with
          establishment and/or activities of the persons of the other
          Party to this Chapter and/or to commercial presences of that
          persons set up within the territory of the former Party on
          compliance with a requirement to locate production, supply a
          service, train or employ workers, construct or expand
          particular facilities or carry out research and development,
          in the territory of the former Party.
        
    
        
          For greater certainty, nothing in paragraph 1 of this Article
          shall be construed to prevent a Party to this Chapter from
          imposing or enforcing any requirement, in connection with
          commercial presences of persons of the other Party to this
          Chapter, to employ or train workers in its territory provided
          that such employment or training does not require the transfer
          of a particular technology, production process, or other
          proprietary knowledge to a person in its territory.
        
    
        
          Subparagraph e) of paragraph 1 of this Article shall not
          apply:
        
    when a Party to this Chapter authorizes use of an intellectual property right in accordance with Article 31 of
the TRIPS Agreement, or to measures requiring the disclosure of proprietary information that fall within the scope of, and are consistent with, Article 39 of the TRIPS Agreement; or
        when the requirement is imposed or enforced by a court or
        relevant authority in accordance with the competition laws and
        regulations of the Party to this Chapter imposing or enforcing
        the requirement.
      
Subparagraphs a) and b) of paragraph 1 of this Article, and
subparagraph a) of paragraph 2 of this Article shall not apply to qualification requirements for goods or services with respect to export promotion and foreign aid programmes.
    
        
          This Article is without prejudice to the rules of origin
          applied by the Parties to this Chapter that are subject to
          Chapter 4 (Rules of Origin) of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.25" name="Senior Management Boards Of Director" article_identifier="39808">With respect to establishment and/or activities and subject to limitations provided for in its individual national List set out in Annex 3 to
Protocol No. 1 and subject to conditions and limitations set out in the
Section IV (Movement of Natural Persons) of this Chapter, a Party to this Chapter shall not require that a juridical person of that Party appoint to senior management positions natural persons of any particular nationality.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION IV" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="4601">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.26" name="Scope" article_identifier="39809">This Section shall apply to measures affecting temporary entry and stay of natural persons of a Party to this Chapter into the territory of the other Party to this Chapter with respect to the categories of such natural persons that are set out in that other Party’s Schedule in Annex 4 to
Protocol No. 1. Such categories of natural persons may include:
    
        business visitors;
      
        intra-corporate transferees;
      
        installers or servicers;
      
        investors; or
      
        contractual services supplier.
      
    
      This Section shall not apply to provision of subsidies or other
      forms of State or municipal support to service suppliers or their
      services covered by this Section.
    
  
        
          This Section shall not apply to measures affecting natural
          persons of a Party to this Chapter seeking access to the
          employment market of the other Party to this Chapter, nor
          shall it apply to measures regarding citizenship, nationality,
          residence or employment on a permanent basis.
        
    
        
          For greater certainty, nothing in this Agreement shall be
          construed as a commitment of a Party to this Chapter in
          respect of any requirement or procedure related to granting
          visas to the natural persons of the other Party to this
          Chapter.
        
    
        
          For the purposes of this Section, “temporary entry or stay”
          means entry or stay by a natural person of a Party to this
          Chapter, without the intent to reside permanently within the
          territory of the other Party to this Chapter.
        
    
        
          Neither Party to this Chapter may impose or maintain any
          numerical restriction or requirement of economic needs test
          relating to temporary entry or stay of natural persons
          referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article except as provided
          for in its Schedule in Annex 4 to Protocol No. 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.27" name="Recognition" article_identifier="39810">Article VII of GATS shall apply between the Parties to this Chapter,
    mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="SECTION V" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="4602">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.28" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39811">For the purposes of this Section:
  “investment” means any type
        of asset invested by the investor of a Party to this Chapter in
        the territory of the other Party to this Chapter in accordance
        with the latter Party's laws and regulations, that has the
        characteristics of an investment, including such characteristics
        as the commitment to capital or other resources, the expectation
        of profit and assumption of risk, in particular, though not
        exclusively:
      
        movable and immovable property as well as any property rights
        such as mortgages or pledges;
      
        shares, stocks and any other form of participation in capital of
        a juridical person;
      
        bonds and debentures;
      
        claims to money or claims under contracts having an economic
        value
            For greater certainty, investment does not mean claims to
            money that arise solely from:
          
            
              a) commercial contracts for sale of goods or services; or
            
              b) the extension of credit in connection with such
              commercial contracts.
            
        , relating to investments;
      
        intellectual property rights;
      
        goodwill;
      
        rights conferred by law or under contract to conduct business
        activity and having financial value, including, but not limited
        to construction, production, revenue-sharing contracts and
        concessions related in particular to exploration, development,
        extraction and exploitation of natural resources.
      
    
      Any change of the form in which assets are invested or reinvested
      shall not affect their character as investments. Such change shall
      be made in accordance with laws and regulations of the Party to
      this Chapter in which territory the investments were made.
    
  “investor of a Party to this
        Chapter” means any natural or juridical person of a
        Party to this Chapter in accordance with its laws and
        regulations that has made investments in the territory of the
        other Party to this Chapter;
      “returns” means the amounts
        derived from an investment including but not limited to profit,
        dividends, interest, capital gains, royalties and other fees;
        and
      “freely usable currency”
        means a freely usable currency as determined by the
        International Monetary Fund in accordance with Articles of
        Agreement of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.29" name="Scope" article_identifier="39812">This Section shall apply to all investments made by investors of a Party to this Chapter in the territory of the other Party to this Chapter after
19 June 1981, in existence as of the date of entry into force of this Agreement, but it shall not apply to any act or fact that took place or any situation or dispute that arose or ceased to exist before entry into force of this Agreement.
    
Investments of investors of a Party to this Chapter made in the territory of the other Party to this Chapter in the form of establishment and commercial presence, as defined and governed by
Section III (Establishment, Commercial Presence and Activities) of this Chapter shall not be covered by Articles 8.30, 8.31, 8.32 and 8.33 of this Agreement.
    
        
          This Section shall not apply to provision of subsidies or
          other forms of State or municipal support to investors and its
          investments, except for those subsidies and other forms of
          State or municipal support to investors and its investments
          under Article 8.34 of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.30" name="Promotion And Admission Of Investments" article_identifier="39813">Each Party to this Chapter shall encourage and create favourable
    conditions to investors of the other Party to make investments in
    its territory and admit the investments of investors of the other
    Party to this Chapter in accordance with the laws and regulations of
    the former Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.31" name="Fair And Equitable Treatment And Full Protection And Security" article_identifier="39814">Each Party to this Chapter shall accord to investments of
          investors of the other Party to this Chapter fair and
          equitable treatment and full protection and security.
        
    
        
          “Fair and equitable treatment” referred to in paragraph 1 of
          this Article requires, in particular, each Party to this
          Chapter not to deny justice in any judicial or administrative
          proceedings.
        
    
        
          “Full protection and security” referred to in paragraph 1 of
          this Article requires each Party to this Chapter to take such
          measures as may be reasonably necessary to ensure the
          protection and security of investments of an investor of the
          other Party to this Chapter.
        
    
        
          With respect to investments of an investor of the other Party
          to this Chapter in the territory of the former Party, “fair
          and equitable treatment” and “full protection and security”
          referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article do not require
          treatment more favourable than that accorded to the former
          Party’s own investors and/or investors of any third country in
          accordance with its laws and regulations.
        
    
        
          A determination that there has been a breach of another
          provision of this Agreement or of a separate international
          agreement does not establish that there has been a breach of
          this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.32" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="39815">Each Party to this Chapter shall accord to investors of the
          other Party to this Chapter and investments of an investor of
          the other Party to this Chapter treatment no less favourable
          than that it accords, in like circumstances, to its own
          investors and their investments in its territory.
        
    
        
          Each Party to this Chapter shall reserve the right in
          accordance with its laws and regulations to apply and
          introduce exemptions from national treatment, referred to in
          paragraph 1 of this Article, to foreign investors and their
          investments including reinvestements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.33" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39816">Each Party to this Chapter shall accord to investors of the
          other Party to this Chapter and investments of an investor of
          the other Party to this Chapter treatment no less favourable
          than that it accords, in like circumstances, to investors of
          any third country and their investments in its territory.
        
    
        
          For greater certainty, this Article shall not apply to
          international dispute settlement procedures or mechanisms such
          as those set out in Article 8.38 of this Agreement.
        
    
        
          Nothing in this Section shall be construed as to oblige a
          Party to this Chapter to provide to investors of the other
          Party to this Chapter or their investments benefits or
          privileges that the former Party is providing or will provide
          in future:
        
    
        in accordance with the economic integration agreements of the
        former Party; or
      
        on the basis of the agreements on avoidance of double taxation
        or other arrangements on taxation issues.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.34" name="Compensation For Losses" article_identifier="39817">Each Party to this Chapter shall accord to investors of the other
    Party to this Chapter and to investments of investors of the other
    Party to this Chapter with respect to measures it adopts or
    maintains relating to losses suffered by investments of such
    investors in its territory owing to war or other armed conflict,
    revolt, insurrection, revolution, riot, civil strife or civil
    disturbance, treatment no less favourable than that it accords, in
    like circumstances, to:
  
        its own investors and their investments; or
      
        investors of any third country and their investments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.35" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="39818">Neither Party to this Chapter shall nationalise, expropriate
          or subject to measures equivalent in effect to nationalisation
          or expropriation an investment of the investor of the other
          Party to this Chapter (hereinafter referred to as
          “expropriation”), except:
        
    
        for a public purpose;
      
        in accordance with the procedure established by the laws and
        regulations of the former Party;
      
        in a non-discriminatory manner; and
      
        on payment of prompt, adequate and effective compensation in
        accordance with paragraph 3 of this Article.
      
        
          The determination of whether a measure or series of such
          measures of either Party to this Chapter have an effect
          equivalent to nationalisation or expropriation shall require a
          case-by-case, fact-based inquiry to consider, inter alia:
        
    
        the economic impact of the measure or series of measures,
        although the sole fact that a measure or series of measures of
        either Party to this Chapter has an adverse effect on the
        economic value of investments does not establish that an
        expropriation has occurred;
      
        the character of the measure or series of measures of either
        Party to this Chapter.
      
        
          The compensation referred to in subparagraph d) of paragraph 1
          of this Article shall:
        
    
        be paid without undue delay;
      
        be equivalent to the fair market value of the expropriated
        investment calculated on date when the actual or impending
        expropriation has become publicly announced whichever is
        earlier; and
      
        be paid in a freely usable currency or, if agreed by the
        investor, in the currency of the expropriating Party to this
        Chapter and be freely transferable subject to the provisions of
        Article 8.37 of this Agreement. From the date of expropriation
        until the date of payment the amount of compensation shall be
        subject to accrued interest at a commercial rate established on
        a market basis.
      
This Article shall not apply to the issuance of compulsory licences granted in relation to intellectual property rights in accordance with
the TRIPS Agreement.
    
        
          Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 through 4 of this Article,
          expropriation relating to land within the territory of either
          Party to this Chapter shall be carried out in accordance with
          the laws and regulations of that Party for a purpose
          established in accordance with such laws and regulations, and
          upon payment of compensation, which shall be assessed with due
          consideration to market value and paid without undue delay, in
          accordance with the laws and regulations of that Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.36" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="39819">If a Party to this Chapter or its designated agency made a
          payment to an investor of that Party under a guarantee, a
          contract of insurance or other form of indemnity against
          non-commercial risks it has granted in respect of an
          investment, the other Party to this Chapter shall recognise
          the subrogation or transfer of any right or claim of the
          investor in respect of such investment to the former Party or
          its designated agency. The subrogated or transferred right or
          claim shall not be greater than the original right or claim of
          the investor. For greater certainty, such right or claim shall
          be exercised in accordance with the laws and regulations of
          the latter Party, but without prejudice to Articles 8.21,
          8.22, 8.23, 8.24 and 8.25 of this Agreement.
        
    
        
          Where a Party to this Chapter or its designated agency has
          made a payment to an investor of that Party and has taken over
          rights and claims of the investor, that investor shall not,
          unless authorised to act on behalf of that Party or its
          designated agency making the payment, pursue those rights and
          claims against the other Party to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.37" name="Transfer Of Payments" article_identifier="39820">Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article 8.8 of
          this Agreement each Party to this Chapter shall guarantee to
          investors of the other Party to this Chapter, upon fulfilment
          by them of all tax and other obligations in accordance with
          the laws and regulations of the former Party, a free transfer
          abroad of payments related to their investments, and in
          particular:
        
    
        returns;
      
        funds in repayment of loans and credits recognised by each Party
        to this Chapter as investments, as well as accrued interest;
      
        proceeds from sale or full or partial liquidation of
        investments;
      
        compensation, stipulated in the Articles 8.34 and 8.35 of this
        Agreement;
      
        wages and other remunerations received by investors and natural
        persons of the other Party to this Chapter authorised to work in
        connection with investments in the territory of the former
        Party.
      
        
          Transfer of payments shall be made without undue delay in a
          freely usable currency at the rate of exchange applicable on
          the date of the transfer pursuant to the exchange laws and
          regulations of the Party to this Chapter in which territory
          the investments were made.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.38" name="Settlement Of Disputes Between A Party To This Chapter And Investor Of The Other Party To This Chapter" article_identifier="39821">Disputes between a Party to this Chapter and an investor of
          the other Party to this Chapter arising from an alleged breach
          of an obligation of the former Party under this Chapter in
          connection with an investment made by the investor in the
          territory of the former Party shall be settled to the extent
          possible amicably by means of negotiations. Such negotiations
          may include the use of non-binding, third-party procedures,
          such as good offices, conciliation and mediation.
        
    
        
          The written request submitted by the investor for negotiations
          referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article shall include:
        
    
        the name and address of the investor who is a party to a
        dispute;
      
        for each claim the specific provisions under this Chapter
        alleged to have been breached;
      
        the legal and factual basis for each claim;
      
        the relief sought and approximate amount of damages claimed.
      
        
          If a dispute cannot be settled amicably by means of
          negotiations during a period of six months starting from the
          date of receipt by the Party who is a party to the dispute of
          the written request of the investor of the other Party to this
          Chapter, it shall be submitted at the choice of the investor
          for consideration to:
        
    
        a competent court of the Party to this Chapter in which
        territory the investments were made, or
      
        an ad hoc arbitration court in accordance
        with the Arbitration Rules of the United Nations Commission on
        International Trade Law; or
      
        arbitration by the International Centre for Settlement of
        Investment Disputes (hereinafter referred to as “ICSID”),
        created pursuant to the Convention on the Settlement of
        Investment Disputes between States and Nationals of Other
        States, opened for signature at Washington on 18 March 1965
        (ICSID Convention), provided that both the Party who is a party
        to the dispute and the Party of the investor are party to the
        ICSID Convention; or
      
        arbitration under the ICSID Additional Facility Rules, provided
        that either the Party who is a party to the dispute or the Party
        of the investor is a party to the ICSID Convention; or
      
        if the parties to a dispute so agree, to any other arbitration
        institution or under any other arbitration rules.
      
        
          The choice of the institution referred to in paragraph 3 of
          this Article shall be final.
        
    
        
          An arbitration award shall be final and binding upon both
          parties to the dispute. Each Party to this Chapter undertakes
          to enforce this award in accordance with its laws and
          regulations.
        
    
        
          No claim can be submitted to arbitration under this Section if
          more than three years have elapsed from the date on which the
          investor who is a party to a dispute first acquired or
          reasonably should have first acquired, knowledge of the breach
          alleged under paragraph 1 of this Article.
        
    
        
          A natural person possessing the nationality of a Party to this
          Chapter on the date the investments were made may not pursue a
          claim against that Party under this Article.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8BIS" name="State Owned, State Controlled Enterprises And Enterprises With Special Or Exclusive Privileges" chapter_identifier="4603">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8BIS.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="39822">This Chapter shall apply only between the Russian Federation and
    Viet Nam.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8BIS.2" name="State-Owned, State-Controlled Enterprises And Enterprises With Special Or Exclusive Privileges" article_identifier="39823">The Russian Federation and Viet Nam shall ensure that their state-owned or state-controlled enterprises and enterprises with special or exclusive privileges shall operate in a manner consistent with their respective WTO commitments in the Protocols on accession to the WTO of
the Russian Federation and Viet Nam, respectively.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="4604">
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39824">The Parties confirm their commitment to reducing impediments to
    trade and investment by promoting deeper economic integration
    through the creation of intellectual property and effective and
    adequate utilisation, protection and enforcement of intellectual
    property rights, taking into account the differences in their
    respective laws and regulations and in levels of economic
    development and capacity and the need to maintain an appropriate
    balance between the rights of intellectual property owners and the
    legitimate interests of users in subject matter protected by
    intellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39825">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  “intellectual property” means
        copyright and related rights, trademarks, geographical
        indications (including appellations of origin of goods),
        inventions (including utility solutions), utility models,
        industrial designs, layout designs (topographies) of integrated
        circuits, plant varieties and undisclosed information;
      “geographical indication”
        means an indication which identifies a good as originating in
        the territory of a Party or a region or locality in that
        territory, where a given quality, reputation or other
        characteristic of the good is essentially attributable to its
        geographical origin, as defined in Article 22 of the TRIPS
        Agreement;
      “appellation of origin of
        goods” means a geographical denomination that
        constitutes or contains contemporary or historical, official or
        unofficial, full or abbreviated name of a country, region or
        locality or other geographical area, which became known through
        its use in the country of origin in relation to the goods, the
        quality and characteristics of which are exclusively or
        essentially determined by the geographical environment,
        including natural and human factors;
      “counterfeit trademark goods”
        means goods, including packaging, bearing without authorisation
        a trademark which is identical to the trademark validly
        registered in respect of such goods, or which cannot be
        distinguished in its essential aspects from such a trademark,
        and which thereby infringes the rights of the owner of the
        trademark in question under the laws and regulations of the
        country of importation. The definition of counterfeit trademark
        goods above shall apply, mutatis mutandis,
        to counterfeit geographical indication and appellation of origin
        goods; and
      “pirated copyright goods”
        means goods which are copies made without the consent of the
        right holder or person duly authorised by the right holder in
        the country of production and which are made directly or
        indirectly from an article where the making of that copy would
        have constituted an infringement of a copyright or a related
        right under the laws and regulations of the country of
        importation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.3" name="International Agreements" article_identifier="39826">The Parties which are party to the TRIPS Agreement reaffirm their obligations set out therein. The Parties which are not party to
the TRIPS Agreement shall follow the principles of
the TRIPS Agreement. The Parties reaffirm their obligations set out in the international agreements on intellectual property to which they are party, in particular:
    the Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property of
20 March 1883 (hereinafter referred to as “the Paris Convention”);
        the Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic
        Works of 9 September 1886;
      the International Convention for the Protection of Performers, Producers of Phonograms and Broadcasting Organisations of
26 October 1961 (the Rome Convention);the Convention for the Protection of Producers of Phonograms Against Unauthorized Duplication of Their Phonograms of
29 October 1971;the Madrid Agreement Concerning the International Registration of Marks of 14 April 1891 and the Protocol Relating to the Madrid Agreement Concerning the International Registration of Marks of
27 June 1989; and
        the Patent Cooperation Treaty of 19 June 1970.
      
        
          The Parties which are not party to one or more of the
          international agreements listed below shall endeavour to join:
        
    the WIPO Performances and Phonograms Treaty of
20 December 1996;
        the WIPO Copyright Treaty of 20 December 1996;
      
        the Act of International Convention for the Protection of New
        Varieties of Plants of 19 March 1991; and
      
        the Singapore Treaty on the Law of Trademarks of 27 March 2006.
      
        
          The Parties shall endeavour to apply the provisions of the
          following international agreements:
        
    
        the Strasbourg Agreement Concerning the International Patent
        Classification of 24 March 1971;
      
        the Nice Agreement Concerning the International Classification
        of Goods and Services for the Purposes of the Registration of
        Marks of 15 June 1957; and
      
        the Locarno Agreement Establishing an International
        Classification for Industrial Designs of 8 October 1968.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.4" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="39827">Each Party shall accord to the nationals of the other Party treatment no less favourable than that it accords to its own nationals with regard to the protection of intellectual property set out in Articles 3 and 5 of
the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.5" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="39828">Each Party shall accord to the nationals of the other Party
    treatment no less favourable than that it accords to the nationals
    of any other country with regard to the protection of intellectual
    property set out in Articles 4 and 5 of the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.6" name="Copyright And Related Rights" article_identifier="39829">Without prejudice to the obligations set out in international
          agreements to which the Parties are party, each Party shall,
          in accordance with its respective laws and regulations,
          guarantee and provide effective protection of the interests of
          authors, performers, producers of phonograms and broadcasting
          organisations for their works, performances, phonograms and
          broadcasts, respectively.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall aim to ensure that its respective laws and
          regulations guarantee the effective protection and provide
          enforcement of copyright and related rights in the digital
          environment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.7" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="39830">Each Party shall provide adequate and effective protection of
    trademarks for goods and services in accordance with its respective
    laws and regulations, the international agreements to which it is
    party and the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 15 through 21.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.8" name="Geographical Indications/Appellations Of Origin Of Goods" article_identifier="39831">Each Party shall ensure in its territory adequate and effective
        legal protection of geographical indications and/or appellations
        of origin of goods in accordance with its respective laws and
        regulations, the international agreements to which it is a party
        and the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 22 through 24.
      The provisions of appellations of origin of goods in this Chapter shall apply to a denomination which allows to identify a good as originating in the territory of a particular geographical area and although it does not contain the name of the area, which became known as a result of using this denomination in respect of the goods, the quality and characteristics of which meet the requirements provided for in subparagraph c) of
Article 9.2 of this Agreement.
        The Parties recognise that each Party may protect geographical
        indications via a sui generis system of
        protection of appellations of origin of goods in accordance with
        its respective laws and regulations. A Party that provides such
        system of protection shall not be obliged to provide a separate
        system of protection for geographical indications. The Parties
        shall provide other legal means in their respective laws and
        regulations to protect geographical indications other than
        appellations of origin of goods, such as those of collective
        marks and/or certification marks. The definition of appellation
        of origin of goods in subparagraph c) of Article 9.2 of this
        Agreement and paragraph 2 of this Article shall only apply to a
        Party which provides a sui generis system
        of protection of appellations of origin of goods at the time of
        entry into force of this Agreement.
      
        In respect of geographical indications and/or appellations of
        origin of goods, the Parties shall provide the legal means for
        an interested person of the other Party to prevent:
      
        
          the use of any means in the designation or presentation of a
          good that indicates or suggests that the good in question
          originates in a geographical area other than the true place of
          origin in a manner which misleads the public as to the
          geographical origin;
        
    
        
          any use which constitutes an act of unfair competition within
          the meaning of Article 10bis of the Paris
          Convention.
        
    
        Nothing in this Chapter shall require a Party to apply its
        provisions in respect of geographical indications and/or
        appellations of origin of goods of the other Party to goods or
        services for which the relevant indication is identical with the
        term customary in common language as the common name for such
        goods or services in the territory of such Party.
      
        In order to protect the interests of their producers, the
        Parties shall exchange lists of geographical indications and/or
        appellations of origin of goods registered by them in respect of
        goods produced in their territories. The Parties may also agree
        to exchange the lists of geographical indications protected by
        other legal means. The relevant procedures for such exchange
        shall be determined by the competent authorities of the Parties
        by means provided for in Article 9.17 of this Agreement. The
        Parties may agree to enter into negotiations on mutual
        protection of geographical indications and/or appellations of
        origin of goods subject to their respective laws and regulations
        and policy, availability of resources and willingness of each
        Party.
      
        Each Party shall, ex officio if its laws
        and regulations so permit or at the request of an interested
        person of the other Party, refuse or invalidate the registration
        of a trademark which contains or consists of a geographical
        indication and/or appellation of origin of goods with respect to
        goods not originating in the territory indicated, if use of the
        indication in the trademark for such goods in the former Party
        is of such a nature as to mislead the public as to the true
        place of origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.9" name="Inventions And Utility Models" article_identifier="39832">Each Party shall provide adequate and effective protection of
        inventions in accordance with its respective laws and
        regulations, the international agreements to which it is party
        and the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 27 through 34.
      
        Utility models shall be protected in accordance with the
        respective laws and regulations of the Parties and the Paris
        Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.10" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="39833">Each Party shall provide adequate and effective protection of
    industrial designs in accordance with its respective laws and
    regulations, the international agreements to which it is party and
    the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 25 and 26.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.11" name="Layout Designs (Topographies) Of Integrated Circuits" article_identifier="39834">Each Party shall provide adequate and effective protection of layout
    designs (topographies) of integrated circuits in accordance with its
    respective laws and regulations, the international agreements to
    which it is party and the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 35
    through 38.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.12" name="New Varieties Of Plants" article_identifier="39835">Each Party recognises the importance of providing in its respective
    laws and regulations a system of protection of new varieties of
    plants and shall endeavour to provide for the protection of all
    plant genera and species in accordance with the Act of International
    Convention for the Protection of New Varieties of Plants of 19 March
    1991 and the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.13" name="Undisclosed Information" article_identifier="39836">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective protection of
    undisclosed information in its respective laws and regulations in
    accordance with the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Article 39.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.14" name="Protection Against Unfair Competition" article_identifier="39837">Each Party shall ensure effective protection against unfair
    competition in accordance with its respective laws and regulations
    and Article 10bis of the Paris Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.15" name="Enforcement Of Intellectual Property Rights" article_identifier="39838">The Parties shall ensure in their respective laws and regulations
    provisions for enforcement of intellectual property rights at the
    same level as provided for in the TRIPS Agreement, in particular
    Articles 41 through 50.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.16" name="Border Measures" article_identifier="39839">Each Party shall ensure effective enforcement of border
          measures in accordance with Articles 51 through 57, 59 and 60
          of the TRIPS Agreement and that the complementary measures,
          procedures and remedies, covered by its respective laws and
          regulations related to customs procedures, are available to
          permit effective action against counterfeit trademark goods,
          counterfeit geographical indication and appellation of origin
          goods, pirated copyright goods.
        
    
        
          Each Party shall, unless otherwise provided for in this
          Agreement, adopt procedures to enable a right holder, who has
          valid grounds for suspecting that importation or exportation
          is carried out with counterfeit trademark goods, counterfeit
          geographical indication and appellation of origin goods,
          pirated copyright goods, to lodge an application to customs
          authorities claiming to apply measures of intellectual
          property rights protection provided that importation or
          exportation in question infringes an intellectual property
          right under the laws and regulations of the country where the
          goods are found.
        
    
        
          Without prejudice to the protection of confidential
          information, customs authorities shall have the authority to
          provide the right holder with sufficient opportunity to have
          any good detained by the customs authorities inspected in
          order to substantiate the right holder’s claims. The customs
          authorities shall also have the authority to give the importer
          an equivalent opportunity to have any such good inspected.
          Customs authorities shall provide the right holder with the
          information on the names and addresses of the consignor, the
          importer and the consignee and of the quantity of the goods in
          question. Customs authorities shall provide at least the owner
          of the detained goods with the information on the name and
          address of the right holder.
        
    
        
          The Parties are encouraged to exclude from the application of
          the above provisions small quantities of goods of a
          non-commercial nature contained in travellers’ personal
          luggage.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.17" name="Competent Authorities, Contact Points And Information Exchange" article_identifier="39840">The Parties shall notify each other of the competent authorities
        responsible for carrying out the procedures provided for in this
        Chapter, and the contact points designated by each Party to
        facilitate communications between the Parties on any matter
        relating to this Chapter.
      
        The Parties shall promptly inform each other of any change in
        the contact points or any significant change in the structure or
        competence of their competent authorities.
      
        The Parties through their contact points shall provide each
        other with a timely written notification of any significant
        issue or any change in the legal framework of intellectual
        property and, if necessary, request consultations to resolve any
        concern about the issue.
      
        With a view to strengthening their cooperation links, the
        Parties agree to communicate in writing and/or promptly hold
        expert meetings, upon request of either Party and taking into
        account the financial capacity of the Parties, on matters
        related to the international agreements referred to in this
        Chapter or to future international agreements in the field of
        intellectual property, to membership in international
        organisations, such as the World Trade Organization and the
        World Intellectual Property Organization, as well as to
        relations of the Parties with third countries on matters
        concerning intellectual property and to other issues relating to
        the implementation of this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="4605">
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.1" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="39841">The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation in the field
        of government procurement in accordance with their respective
        laws and regulations and given the available resources.
      
        The Parties shall cooperate for the purposes of improving
        transparency, promoting fair competition and the use of
        electronic technologies in the field of government procurement.
      
        The Parties shall inform each other as soon as possible of any
        significant modification of their respective laws and
        regulations and/or government procurement procedures.
      
        The cooperation activities shall include the exchange of, where
        appropriate, non-confidential information, consultations, as
        provided for in Article 10.3 of this Agreement, and technical
        assistance.
      
        The Parties shall endeavour to cooperate in the following:
      
        
          facilitating participation of suppliers in government
          procurement, in particular, with respect to small and medium
          enterprises;
        
    
        
          exchanging experience and information, such as regulatory
          frameworks, best practices and statistics;
        
    
        
          developing and expanding the use of electronic means in
          government procurement systems;
        
    
        
          capacity building for government officials in best government
          procurement practices;
        
    
        
          institutional strengthening for the fulfilment of the
          provisions of this Chapter; and
        
    
        
          enhancing the ability to provide multilingual access to
          procurement opportunities.
        
    
        The Parties shall develop further cooperation based on mutual
        experience in the field of government procurement, including
        electronic forms of procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.2" name="Information On The Procurement System" article_identifier="39842">For the purposes of transparency, the Parties shall make
        publicly available their respective laws and regulations
        relating to government procurement.
      
        The Parties shall exchange the lists of media resources in which
        the Parties publish relevant information on government
        procurement.
      
        The Parties shall endeavour to establish and maintain electronic
        means for publishing their respective laws and regulations and
        information on government procurement, given the available
        resources.
      
        Each Party may expand the content of the government procurement
        information and the scope of the services provided through
        electronic means.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.3" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39843">In the event of any disagreement relating to the application of
        the provisions of this Chapter, the Parties shall make every
        effort to reach a mutually satisfactory resolution through
        consultations.
      
        Each Party shall accord sympathetic consideration to and shall
        afford adequate opportunity for consultations regarding the
        implementation of this Chapter.
      
        A request for such consultations shall be submitted to the other
        Party’s contact point established under Article 10.5 of this
        Agreement. Unless the Parties agree otherwise, they shall hold
        consultations within 60 days from the date of receipt of the
        request.
      
        Consultations may be conducted in person or via email,
        teleconference, videoconference, or any other means, as agreed
        by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.4" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14 (Dispute Settlement)" article_identifier="39844">Any matter arising under this Chapter shall not be subject to the
    dispute settlement mechanism provided for in Chapter 14 (Dispute
    Settlement) of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.5" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="39845">Each Party shall designate a contact point to monitor the
        implementation of this Chapter. The contact points shall work
        collaboratively to facilitate the implementation of this
        Chapter.
      
        The Parties shall provide each other with the names and contact
        details of their contact points.
      
        The Parties shall promptly notify each other of any change to
        their contact points.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.6" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="39846">The Parties may enter into negotiations with a view to liberalising
    their respective government procurement markets and discussing
    potential market access issues, if necessary.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="4606">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.1" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="39847">The Parties recognise the importance of free and undistorted
          competition in their trade relations and respect the
          differences in their capacity in the area of competition
          policy.
        
    
Each Party shall, in accordance with its respective laws and regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate by proscribing
anti-competitive business conduct, in order to promote the efficient functioning of its respective market and consumer welfare.
    
        
          The measures each Party adopts or maintains to proscribe
          anti-competitive business conduct shall be taken in conformity
          with the principles of transparency, non-discrimination and
          fairness.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.2" name="Anti-Competitive Practices" article_identifier="39848">The Parties shall take all necessary measures in accordance with their respective laws and regulations in order to prevent and restrict
anti-competitive practices that affect trade between the Parties. Particular attention shall be given to the following practices which are incompatible with the proper operation of this Agreement:
        
          all agreements between enterprises, decisions by associations
          of enterprises and concerted practices between enterprises
          which have as their object or effect the prevention,
          restriction or distortion of competition;
        
    
        
          abuse by one or more enterprises of a dominant position; and
        
    
        
          unfair competition.
        
    
        The issues concerning state monopolies and enterprises entrusted
        with special or exclusive rights shall not be subject of this
        Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.3" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="39849">The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation activities
        relating to competition law enforcement and competition policy.
        Cooperation shall be conducted in accordance with the respective
        laws and regulations and based on the availability of the
        necessary resources. Cooperation shall include exchange of
        non-confidential information, consultations, cooperation in
        enforcement activities, as provided for in paragraph 2 of this
        Article, and technical assistance, including:
      
        
          exchange of experience regarding the promotion and enforcement
          of competition law and policy;
        
    
        
          joint seminars on competition law and law enforcement
          activities of the Parties; and
        
    
        
          any other form of cooperation as agreed by the Parties.
        
    
        Cooperation in law enforcement is carried out as follows:
      
        
          if a Party considers that its interests are affected in the
          territory of the other Party in the sense of Article 11.2 of
          this Agreement, it may request that the other Party initiates
          appropriate enforcement activities. Such request shall take
          place if possible at an early stage of the anti-competitive
          practice under Article 11.2 of this Agreement and should be of
          sufficient detail;
        
    
        
          the requested Party shall carefully consider the possibility
          for initiating enforcement activities or expanding ongoing
          enforcement activities in accordance with the requirements of
          its respective laws and regulations and inform the requesting
          Party of the results of such consideration as soon as
          practically possible;
        
    
        
          if enforcement activities are initiated or expanded, the
          requested Party shall inform the requesting Party of their
          outcome and, to the extent possible, of significant interim
          developments; and
        
    
        
          nothing in this Chapter shall limit the discretion of the
          requested Party to decide whether to undertake enforcement
          activities with respect to the anti-competitive practices
          identified in the request, or precludes the requesting Party
          from withdrawing its request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.4" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39850">To foster understanding between the Parties, or to address
        specific matters that arise under this Chapter, each Party
        shall, upon request of the other Party, enter into
        consultations. Such consultations shall be without prejudice to
        the rights of each Party to enforce their respective laws and
        regulations. In the request for consultations, the requesting
        Party shall indicate how the matter affects trade between the
        Parties. The Party receiving such request shall promptly hold
        consultations in order to achieve mutually satisfactory results
        in consistence with the provisions of this Chapter.
      
        During the consultations in accordance with this Article, the
        requested Party shall provide full and sympathetic consideration
        to the matter that is the subject of consultations within a
        reasonable period of time. Both Parties shall aspire to reach
        consensus on the issue of concern through constructive
        dialogues.
      
        If a Party considers that its interests are still affected after
        consultations in accordance with this Article, it may request
        consultations in the Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.5" name="Use Of Information" article_identifier="39851">Where a Party provides information to the other Party for the
        purposes of implementing this Chapter, such information shall be
        used by the latter Party only for such purposes and shall not be
        disclosed or transferred to any other organisation and/or
        individual without the consent of the Party providing the
        information.
      
        Notwithstanding any other provision of this Chapter, neither
        Party is required to communicate information to the other Party
        if such communication is prohibited by their respective laws and
        regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.6" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14 (Dispute Settlement)" article_identifier="39852">Any matter arising under this Chapter shall not be subject to the
    dispute settlement mechanism provided for in Chapter 14 (Dispute
    Settlement) of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.7" name="Contact Points" article_identifier="39853">Each Party shall designate a contact point to monitor the
          implementation of this Chapter. The contact points shall work
          collaboratively to facilitate the implementation of the
          provisions of this Chapter.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall exchange information containing the names of
          the designated competent authorities that shall act as their
          contact points and the contact details of relevant officials
          in such organisations, including telephone and facsimile
          numbers, email addresses and other relevant details.
        
    
        
          The Parties shall promptly notify each other of any change to
          their contact points or relevant contact details.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Sustainable Development" chapter_identifier="4607">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39854">The Parties agree to implement this Chapter in a manner
        consistent with labour and environmental protection, and
        sustainable use of their resources. In this regard the Parties
        shall:
      
        strengthen cooperation on environmental and labour issues; and
      
        promote sustainable development.
      
        The Parties recognise that economic development, social
        development and environmental protection are interdependent and
        mutually supportive components of sustainable development.
      
        The Parties shall endeavour to promote their trade relations for
        the purposes of sustainable development to the extent possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.2" name="Scope" article_identifier="39855">This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or maintained by the
    Parties affecting trade-related aspects of environmental and labour
    issues.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.3" name="General Principles" article_identifier="39856">The Parties recognise the importance of and the need to enhance
        the capacity to address trade-related aspects of environmental
        and labour issues, taking into consideration the levels of
        development of the Parties.
      
        The Parties recognise the need to strengthen cooperation with
        the aim of resolving environmental and labour issues of
        bilateral, regional and global concerns.
      
        The Parties recognise the sovereign right of each Party to
        establish its own levels of national environmental and labour
        protection and environmental and labour development policies and
        priorities, and to adopt or modify accordingly its relevant
        environmental and labour laws and regulations and policies.
      
        The Parties may recognise the significance of taking into
        account scientific, technical and other information as well as
        relevant and commonly recognised international standards when
        preparing and implementing measures aimed at protecting the
        environment and labour that affect trade between the Parties.
      
        The provisions of this Chapter shall be without prejudice to the
        Parties’ obligations in accordance with other Chapters of this
        Agreement, including Chapter 8 (Trade in Services, Investment
        and Movement of Natural Persons).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.4" name="Upholding Levels Of Protection" article_identifier="39857">The Parties recognise the importance of mutually supportive
        trade, environment and labour policies and practices as well as
        the efforts to improve environmental and labour protection and
        enhance trade between the Parties.
      
        Each Party shall endeavour to ensure that its environmental and
        labour laws and regulations, policies and practices are not used
        for the purposes of trade protectionism.
      
        Neither Party shall seek to encourage or gain trade or
        investment advantage by weakening or failing through a sustained
        or recurring course of action or inaction to enforce or
        administer its environmental and labour laws and regulations,
        policies and practices in a manner affecting trade between the
        Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.5" name="Environmental And Labour Cooperation" article_identifier="39858">The Parties recognise the importance of strengthening their
        capacity to protect the environment and labour conditions and
        promoting sustainable development in their trade and investment
        relations in accordance with their respective laws and
        regulations.
      
        The Parties shall endeavour to expand their cooperation in
        bilateral, regional, and multilateral fora on environmental and
        labour issues, recognising that such cooperation will help them
        achieve their shared environmental and labour goals and
        objectives, including the development and improvement of
        environmental and labour protection, practices, and
        technologies.
      
        Cooperation activities under this Chapter may take the following
        forms:
      
        exchange of knowledge and experiences;
      
        exchange of experts and researchers;
      
        organisation of joint workshops;
      
        promotion of cooperative activities between relevant ministries,
        research institutes and private enterprises; and
      
        development and implementation of joint research, projects and
        other relevant activities in areas of mutual interest.
      
        The Parties recognise the following fields of cooperation as
        particularly significant:
      
        resolving trade-related environmental problems;
      
        environmental policy development and institutional building;
      
        training and education on environment and climate change issues
        and environmental protection;
      
        exchange of experience and information in the development and
        enforcement of labour and employment-related laws and
        regulations and policies;
      
        technical assistance and joint/cooperation projects on human
        resources development and social security policy aimed at
        creating decent work conditions or on the protection of the
        environment;
      
        other mutually agreed areas in accordance with relevant laws and
        regulations of the Parties;
      
        exchange of information, technology and experience in areas of
        environmental standards and models, training and education;
      
        environmental education and training aimed at raising public
        awareness; and
      
        technical assistance and joint regional research programmes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.6" name="Environmental And Labour Consultations" article_identifier="39859">Either Party may request consultations regarding any matter
        arising under this Chapter through a written request submitted
        to the contact point designated by the other Party in accordance
        with Article 1.7 of this Agreement. The request shall contain
        information that is specific and sufficient to enable the Party
        receiving such request to respond. Unless the Parties agree
        otherwise, consultations shall commence within the period of 30
        days after a Party receives the request for consultations.
      
        The purpose of the consultations is to seek a mutually agreed
        solution to the matter. The Parties shall make every effort to
        arrive at a mutually satisfactory outcome, including by
        considering appropriate cooperation activities to resolve the
        matter. The Parties may agree to seek advice or assistance from
        domestic experts they deem appropriate.
      
        If a Party considers that the matter needs further discussion
        such Party may bring the matter to the Joint Committee in order
        to reach an appropriate resolution of the matter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.7" name="International Labour Standards And Agreements" article_identifier="39860">The Parties recall the obligations deriving from membership of
        the International Labour Organization (ILO) and the ILO
        Declaration on Fundamental Principles and Rights at Work and its
        Follow-up adopted by the International Labour Conference at its
        86th Session in 1998.
      
        The Parties reaffirm their commitment under the Ministerial
        Declaration of the UN Economic and Social Council on Full
        Employment and Decent Work of 2006 to recognise full and
        productive employment and decent work for all as a key element
        of sustainable development for all countries and as a priority
        objective of international cooperation and to promote the
        development of international trade in a way that is conducive to
        full and productive employment and decent work for all.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.8" name="Review Of Sustainability Impacts" article_identifier="39861">The Parties shall periodically review at the meetings of the Joint
    Committee the progress achieved in pursuing the objectives set out
    in this Chapter and may consider relevant international
    developments, as appropriate, to identify areas where further action
    could promote these objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.9" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14 (Dispute Settlement)" article_identifier="39862">Any matter arising under this Chapter shall not be subject to the
    dispute settlement mechanism provided for in Chapter 14 (Dispute
    Settlement) of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Electronic Technologies In Trade" chapter_identifier="4608">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.1" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="39863">The Parties recognise that electronic commerce may increase
        trade opportunities and contribute to economic growth, and
        underscore the importance of promoting the use of electronic
        technologies in trade in order to minimise the costs and
        facilitate trade, as well as the importance of cooperation
        between the Parties on the issues of electronic commerce under
        this Chapter.
      
        This Chapter shall apply to measures taken by a Party relating
        to:
      
            
              the use of electronic documents in trade between the
              Parties by means of digital signatures and a trusted third
              party; and
            
        
            
              electronic commerce as defined in paragraph b) of Article
              13.2 of this Agreement.
            
        
        For the purposes of paragraph 2 of this Article such measures
        shall include the measures taken by:
      
            
              central, regional or local governments and authorities;
              and
            
        
            
              non-governmental bodies in the exercise of powers
              delegated by central, regional or local governments or
              authorities.
            
        
        In fulfilling its obligations and commitments under this
        Chapter, each Party shall take such reasonable measures as may
        be available to it to ensure the observance of such obligations
        and commitments by regional and local governments and
        authorities and non-governmental bodies within its territory.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39864">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  
        “digital certificate” means
          an electronic document issued by an authorised organisation,
          containing information confirming that the particular digital
          signature belongs to a certain person;
        
    
        “electronic commerce” means
          trade with the use of electronic technologies;
        
    
        “electronic document” means
          a document where information is presented in an electronic
          form which can be certified by means of a digital signature;
        
    
        “digital signature” means
          information in electronic form obtained by using public-key
          cryptography, which is the transformation of information by
          using a private signature key that is verified by a public
          signature key, and attached or connected to the other
          information in electronic form (information being signed),
          confirming its integrity and authenticity and assuring
          inability to deny authorship;
        
    
        “electronic technologies”
          means a combination of software and hardware that provides
          interaction between the persons of the Parties using an
          electronic document;
        
    
        “electronic authentication”
          means the process of establishing confidence in user
          identities electronically presented to an information system;
          and
        
    
        “trusted third party” means
          an organisation vested with the rights in accordance with the
          domestic laws and regulations of each Party to verify a
          digital signature in a digitally signed electronic document at
          a fixed time with regard to author and/or recipient of
          electronic document.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.3" name="Electronic Authentication" article_identifier="39865">The Parties shall endeavour to work towards mutual recognition of
    digital signatures in the exchange of electronic documents by means
    of a trusted third party service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.4" name="Use Of Electronic Documents" article_identifier="39866">The Parties shall endeavour:
      
            not to adopt or maintain domestic laws and regulations
            containing the requirement to confirm the authenticity of
            the transactions made in electronic form by presenting
            documents in paper form; and
          
            to ensure that the documents related to trade transactions
            are presented to the competent authorities of the Parties in
            the form of an electronic document that is digitally signed.
          
        The Parties shall endeavour to ensure that in cases where any
        document is required for the importation of a product, a
        participant of trade transaction could receive such document
        confirming that the product is imported in accordance with the
        requirements of the importing country in electronic form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.5" name="Private Data Protection" article_identifier="39867">The Parties shall endeavour to adopt and maintain in force measures
    aimed at the protection of private data of electronic commerce
    users.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.6" name="Cooperation On Electronic Technologies In Trade" article_identifier="39868">The Parties shall exchange information and experience with
        regard to laws and regulations and programmes in the field of
        electronic technologies in trade, in particular with regard to
        private data protection and improvement of consumer confidence.
      
        The Parties recognise the necessity of participation in
        bilateral, regional and multilateral fora on establishing legal
        frameworks regulating electronic commerce.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.7" name="Electronic Commerce Development" article_identifier="39869">Recognising the global nature of electronic commerce and the
    importance of facilitating the use and development of electronic
    commerce, the Parties shall:
  
        endeavour to develop the legal frameworks for electronic
        commerce using relevant international standards on data
        collection and in conformity with international practices
        including, where possible, decisions on electronic commerce
        taken within the framework of the WTO;
      
        encourage the private sector to adopt self-regulation, including
        through codes of conduct, model contracts, guidelines and
        enforcement mechanisms that foster electronic commerce;
      
        promote the adoption of transparent and appropriate measures to
        protect consumers from fraudulent and deceptive commercial
        practices when they engage in electronic commerce; and
      
        promote the cooperation between their respective national
        consumer protection agencies on issues related to cross-border
        electronic commerce in order to enhance consumer welfare.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.8" name="Implementing Arrangements" article_identifier="39870">Competent authorities of the Parties may conclude implementing
        arrangements on any matter within the scope of this Chapter. In
        particular, the implementing arrangements shall set out
        understandings reached in accordance with Articles 13.3, 13.4
        and 13.5 of this Agreement.
      
        The Parties through the relevant competent authorities shall
        take all necessary actions to apply the implementing
        arrangements within a jointly determined reasonable period of
        time.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="4609">
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="39871">The objective of this Chapter is to provide an effective and
    transparent process for the settlement of disputes arising under
    this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="39872">For the purposes of this Chapter:
  “Arbitral Panel” means an
        Arbitral Panel established pursuant to Article 14.7 of this
        Agreement; and
      “disputing Parties” means the
        complaining Party and the responding Party. The Member States of
        the Eurasian Economic Union and the Eurasian Economic Union may
        act jointly or individually as a disputing Party. In the latter
        case if a measure is taken by a Member State of the Eurasian
        Economic Union, such Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union
        shall be a disputing Party, and if a measure is taken by the
        Eurasian Economic Union, it shall be a disputing Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.3" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="39873">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, this Chapter
        shall apply with respect to the settlement of disputes between
        the Parties regarding the interpretation and/or application of
        this Agreement wherever a Party considers that the other Party
        has failed to carry out its obligations under this Agreement.
      
        Disputes regarding the same matter between the same disputing
        Parties arising under both this Agreement and the WTO Agreement
        may be settled in either forum at the discretion of the
        complaining Party. The forum thus selected shall be used to the
        exclusion of the other.
      
        For the purposes of this Agreement, the procedural provisions of
        the relevant incorporated articles of the WTO Agreement relating
        to dispute settlement in case of non-compliance or possible
        violation shall not be applied to any Member State of the
        Eurasian Economic Union which is not a Member of the WTO.
      
        For the purposes of paragraph 2 of this Article, dispute
        settlement procedures under the WTO Agreement are deemed to be
        initiated by a disputing Party’s request for the establishment
        of a panel under Article 6 of the WTO Understanding on Rules and
        Procedures Governing the Settlement of Disputes, whereas dispute
        settlement procedures under this Agreement are deemed to be
        initiated upon a request for arbitration pursuant to paragraph 1
        of Article 14.7 of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.4" name="Information Exchange And Amicus Curiae" article_identifier="39874">The distribution among the Member States of the Eurasian
        Economic Union and the Eurasian Economic Union of any procedural
        document relating to any dispute arising under this Agreement
        shall not be viewed as a violation of the provisions on
        confidentiality under this Agreement and/or WTO Agreement. 
      
        Any Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union and the Eurasian
        Economic Union having substantial interest in a matter in
        dispute may have an opportunity to be heard and to make written
        submissions to the Arbitral Panel as amicus
        curiae.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.5" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="39875">The disputing Parties may at any time agree to good offices,
        conciliation or mediation. Procedures for good offices,
        conciliation or mediation may begin at any time and be
        terminated at any time upon the request by either disputing
        Party.
      
        If the disputing Parties so agree, good offices, conciliation or
        mediation may continue while the proceedings of the Arbitral
        Panel provided for in this Chapter are in progress.
      
        Proceedings involving good offices, conciliation and mediation,
        and in particular positions taken by the disputing Parties
        during those proceedings, shall be confidential and without
        prejudice to the rights of either disputing Party in any further
        proceeding.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.6" name="Consultations" article_identifier="39876">The Parties shall make every attempt through consultations to
        reach a mutually satisfactory solution of any matter raised in
        accordance with this Chapter.
      
        A request for consultations shall be submitted in writing to the
        responding Party through its contact point or contact points
        designated in accordance with Article 1.7 of this Agreement as
        well as to the Joint Committee and shall give the reasons for
        the request, including identification of any measure or other
        matter at issue and an indication of the legal basis for the
        complaint.
      
        When the complaining Party submits a request for consultations
        pursuant to paragraph 2 of this Article, the responding Party
        shall:
      
        reply to the request in writing within 10 days from the date of
        its receipt; and
      
        enter into consultations in good faith within 30 days, or 10
        days in cases of urgency, including those concerning perishable
        goods, from the date of the receipt of the request with a view
        to reaching a prompt and mutually satisfactory resolution of the
        matter.
      
        Periods of time specified in paragraph 3 of this Article may be
        changed by agreement of the disputing Parties.
      
        The consultations shall be confidential, and without prejudice
        to the rights of either disputing Party in any further
        proceeding.
      
        A disputing Party may request the other disputing Party to make
        available for the consultations experts from its governmental
        agencies or other regulatory bodies who have expertise in the
        matter under consultations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.7" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Panel" article_identifier="39877">The complaining Party that made a request for consultations under
Article 14.6 of this Agreement may request in writing the establishment of an Arbitral Panel:
        if the responding Party does not comply with the periods of time
        in accordance with paragraph 3 or 4 of Article 14.6 of this
        Agreement;
      
        if the disputing Parties fail to resolve the dispute through
        such consultations within 60 days, or within 20 days in cases of
        urgency, including those concerning perishable goods, from the
        date of receipt of the request for such consultations; or
      
        if the disputing Parties jointly consider that consultations
        have failed to settle the dispute during the period of time
        specified in subparagraph b) of this paragraph.
      
        In cases of urgency, including those concerning perishable
        goods, the disputing Parties shall make every effort to
        accelerate the proceedings to the greatest extent possible.
      
        The request for the establishment of an Arbitral Panel shall be
        made in writing to the responding Party through its contact
        points designated in accordance with Article 1.7 of this
        Agreement as well as to the Joint Committee. It shall indicate
        whether consultations were held, identify the specific measures
        at issue and provide a brief summary of the legal basis of the
        complaint sufficient to present the problem clearly.
      
        The requirements and procedures specified in this Article may be
        changed by mutual agreement of the disputing Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.8" name="Appointment Of Arbitrators" article_identifier="39878">The Arbitral Panel shall consist of three members.
      
        Within 30 days of receipt of the request to establish an
        Arbitral Panel by the responding Party, each disputing Party
        shall appoint an arbitrator. Within 15 days of the appointment
        of the second arbitrator, the appointed arbitrators shall choose
        by mutual agreement the chair of the Arbitral Panel who shall
        not fall under any of the following disqualifying criteria:
      
        being a national of a Member State of the Eurasian Economic
        Union or Viet Nam; or
      
        having usual place of residence in the territory of a Member
        State of the Eurasian Economic Union or Viet Nam.
      If the necessary appointments have not been made within the periods of time specified in paragraph 2 of this Article, either disputing Party may, unless otherwise agreed by the disputing Parties, invite
the Secretary-General of the Permanent Court of Arbitration (hereinafter referred to as “PCA”) to be the appointing authority. In case
the Secretary-General of the PCA is a national of a Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union or Viet Nam or is incapable to realise this appointing function, the Deputy Secretary-General of the PCA or the officer next in seniority who is not a national of a Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union or Viet Nam and who is capable to realise this appointing function shall be requested to make the necessary appointments.
        All arbitrators shall:
      
        have expertise and/or experience in law, international trade,
        other matters covered by this Agreement, or the resolution of
        disputes arising under international trade agreements;
      
        be chosen strictly on the basis of objectivity, impartiality,
        reliability and sound judgment;
      
        be independent of, and not be affiliated with or take
        instructions from a Party; and
      
        disclose to the disputing Parties any direct or indirect
        conflicts of interest in respect of the matter at hand.
      
        Individuals may not serve as arbitrators for a dispute if they
        have dealt with the dispute previously in any capacity,
        including in accordance with Article 14.5 of this Agreement.
      
        If an arbitrator appointed under this Article resigns or becomes
        unable to act, a successor arbitrator shall be appointed within
        15 days in accordance with the procedure as prescribed for the
        appointment of the original arbitrator and the successor shall
        have all the powers and duties of the original arbitrator. Any
        period of time applicable to the proceeding shall be suspended
        beginning on the date the arbitrator resigns or becomes unable
        to act and ending on the date a replacement is selected.
      
        The date of establishment of the Arbitral Panel shall be the
        date on which the chair of the Arbitral Panel is appointed.
      
        The requirements and procedures specified in this Article may be
        changed by mutual agreement of the disputing Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.9" name="Functions Of Arbitral Panel" article_identifier="39879">The functions of an Arbitral Panel are to make an objective
        assessment of the dispute before it, including an objective
        assessment of the facts of the case and the applicability of and
        conformity with this Agreement, and to make such findings and
        rulings necessary for the resolution of the dispute referred to
        it as it deems appropriate as well as to determine at the
        request of a disputing Party the conformity of any implementing
        measures and/or relevant suspension of benefits with its final
        report.
      
        The findings and rulings of an Arbitral Panel cannot add to or
        diminish the rights and obligations of the Parties provided for
        in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.10" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Panel" article_identifier="39880">The Arbitral Panel proceedings shall be conducted in accordance
        with the provisions of this Chapter.
      
        Subject to paragraph 1 of this Article, the Arbitral Panel shall
        regulate its own procedures in relation to the rights of the
        disputing Parties to be heard and its deliberations in
        consultation with the disputing Parties. The disputing Parties
        in consultation with the Arbitral Panel may agree to adopt
        additional rules and procedures not inconsistent with the
        provisions of this Article.
      
        After consulting the disputing Parties, the Arbitral Panel shall
        as soon as practicable and whenever possible within 10 days
        after its establishment, fix the timetable for the Arbitral
        Panel process. The timetable shall include precise deadlines for
        written submissions by the disputing Parties. Modifications to
        such timetable may be made by mutual agreement of the disputing
        Parties in consultation with the Arbitral Panel.
      
        Upon request of a disputing Party or on its own initiative, the
        Arbitral Panel may, at its discretion, seek information and/or
        technical advice from any individual or body which it deems
        appropriate. However, before the Arbitral Panel seeks such
        information and/or advice, it shall inform the disputing
        Parties. Any information and/or technical advice so obtained
        shall be submitted to the disputing Parties for comment. Where
        the Arbitral Panel takes the information and/or technical advice
        into account in the preparation of its report, it shall also
        take into account any comment by the disputing Parties on the
        information and/or technical advice.
      
        The Arbitral Panel shall make its procedural decisions, findings
        and rulings by consensus, provided that where the Arbitral Panel
        is unable to reach consensus such procedural decisions, findings
        and rulings may be made by majority vote. The Arbitral Panel
        shall not disclose which arbitrators are associated with
        majority or minority opinions.
      
        The Arbitral Panel shall meet in closed session. The disputing
        Parties shall be present at the meetings only when invited by
        the Arbitral Panel to appear before it.
      
        The hearings of the Arbitral Panel shall be closed to the
        public, unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise.
      
        The disputing Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend
        any of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the
        proceedings. Any information provided or written submission made
        by a disputing Party to the Arbitral Panel, including any
        comment on the descriptive part of the initial report and
        response to the questions put by the Arbitral Panel, shall be
        made available to the other disputing Party.
      
        The deliberations of the Arbitral Panel and the documents
        submitted to it shall be kept confidential.
      
        Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude a disputing Party from
        disclosing statements of its own positions to the public. A
        disputing Party shall treat as confidential information
        submitted by the other disputing Party to the Arbitral Panel
        which that other disputing Party has designated as confidential.
        A disputing Party shall also, upon request of a Party, provide a
        non-confidential summary of the information contained in its
        written submissions that could be disclosed to the public.
      
        The venue for hearings shall be decided by mutual agreement of
        the disputing Parties. If there is no agreement, the venue shall
        alternate between the capitals of the disputing Parties with the
        first hearing to be held in the capital of the responding Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.11" name="Terms Of Reference Of Arbitral Panel" article_identifier="39881">Unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise within 20 days from the
    date of receipt of the request for the establishment of the Arbitral
    Panel, the terms of reference shall be:
  
    “To examine, in the light of the relevant provisions of this
    Agreement, the matter referred to in the request for the
    establishment of an Arbitral Panel pursuant to Article 14.7 of this
    Agreement and to make findings and rulings of law and fact together
    with the reasons therefore for the resolution of the dispute.”.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.12" name="Termination Or Suspension Of Proceedings" article_identifier="39882">The Arbitral Panel shall be terminated upon the joint request of
        the disputing Parties. In such event, the disputing Parties
        shall jointly notify the chair of the Arbitral Panel and the
        Joint Committee.
      
        The Arbitral Panel shall, upon the joint request of the
        disputing Parties, suspend its work at any time for a period not
        exceeding 12 consecutive months from the date of receipt of such
        joint request. In such event, the disputing Parties shall
        jointly notify the chair of the Arbitral Panel. Within this
        period, either disputing Party may authorise the Arbitral Panel
        to resume its work by notifying the chair of the Arbitral Panel
        and the other disputing Party. In that event, all relevant
        periods of time set out in this Chapter shall be extended by the
        amount of time that the work was suspended for. If the work of
        the Arbitral Panel has been suspended for more than 12
        consecutive months, the Arbitral Panel shall be terminated. The
        authority for establishment of a new Arbitral Panel by the
        original disputing Parties on the same matter referred to in the
        request for the establishment of the original Arbitral Panel
        shall lapse unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.13" name="Reports Of Arbitral Panel" article_identifier="39883">The reports of the Arbitral Panel shall be drafted without the
        presence of the disputing Parties and shall be based on the
        relevant provisions of this Agreement, the submissions and
        arguments of the disputing Parties and any information and/or
        technical advice provided to it in accordance with paragraph 4
        of Article 14.10 of this Agreement.
      
        The Arbitral Panel shall issue its initial report within 90
        days, or 60 days in cases of urgency, including those concerning
        perishable goods, from the date of establishment of the Arbitral
        Panel. The initial report shall contain, inter
        alia, both the descriptive sections and the Arbitral
        Panel’s findings and conclusions.
      In exceptional circumstances, if the Arbitral Panel considers it cannot issue its initial report within the periods of time specified in paragraph 2 of this Article, it shall inform the disputing Parties in writing of the reasons for the delay together with an estimate of the period within which it will issue its initial report. Any delay shall not exceed a further period of
30 days unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise.
        A disputing Party may submit written comments on the initial
        report to the Arbitral Panel within 15 days of receiving the
        initial report unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise.
      
        After considering any written comment by the disputing Parties
        and making any further examination it considers necessary, the
        Arbitral Panel shall present to the disputing Parties its final
        report within 30 days of issuance of the initial report, unless
        the disputing Parties agree otherwise.
      
        If in its final report, the Arbitral Panel finds that a
        disputing Party’s measure does not conform with this Agreement,
        it shall include in its findings and rulings a requirement to
        remove the non-conformity.
      
        The disputing Parties shall release the final report of the
        Arbitral Panel as a public document within 15 days from the date
        of its issuance, subject to the protection of confidential
        information, unless any disputing Party objects. In this case
        the final report shall still be released for all Parties to the
        Agreement.
      
        The final report of the Arbitral Panel shall be final and
        binding for the disputing Parties with regard to a particular
        dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.14" name="Implementation" article_identifier="39884">The disputing Parties shall immediately comply with the rulings
        of the Arbitral Panel. Where it is not practicable to comply
        immediately, the disputing Parties shall comply with the rulings
        within a reasonable period of time. The reasonable period of
        time shall be mutually determined by the disputing Parties.
        Where the disputing Parties fail to agree on the reasonable
        period of time within 45 days of the issuance of the Arbitral
        Panel’s final report, either disputing Party may refer the
        matter to the original Arbitral Panel, which shall determine the
        reasonable period of time after consulting with the disputing
        Parties.
      
        Where there is disagreement between the disputing Parties as to
        whether a disputing Party has eliminated the non-conformity as
        determined in the report of the Arbitral Panel within the
        reasonable period of time as determined pursuant to this
        Article, the other disputing Party may refer the matter to the
        original Arbitral Panel.
      
        The Arbitral Panel shall issue its report within 60 days from
        the date on which the matter referred to in paragraph 1 or 2 of
        this Article was submitted for its consideration. The report
        shall contain the determination of the Arbitral Panel and the
        reasons for its determination. When the Arbitral Panel considers
        that it cannot issue its report within this period of time, it
        shall inform the disputing Parties in writing of the reasons for
        the delay together with an estimate of the period within which
        it will issue its report. Any delay shall not exceed a further
        period of 30 days unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise.
      
        The disputing Parties may at all times continue to seek mutually
        satisfactory resolution on the implementation of the final
        report of the Arbitral Panel.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.15" name="Compensation And Suspension Of Benefits" article_identifier="39885">If a disputing Party does not comply with the rulings of the
        Arbitral Panel within the reasonable period of time determined
        in accordance with Article 14.14 of this Agreement, or notifies
        the other disputing Party that it does not intend to do so,
        and/or if the original Arbitral Panel determines that a
        disputing Party did not comply with the rulings of the Arbitral
        Panel in accordance with Article 14.14 of this Agreement, such
        disputing Party shall, if so requested by the other disputing
        Party, enter into consultations with a view to agreeing on a
        mutually acceptable compensation. If no such agreement has been
        reached within 20 days from the receipt of the request, the
        other disputing Party shall be entitled to suspend the
        application of benefits granted under this Agreement in respect
        of the responding Party but only equivalent to those affected by
        the measure that the Arbitral Panel has found not to be in
        conformity with this Agreement.
      
        In considering what benefits to suspend, a disputing Party
        should first seek to suspend benefits in the same sector or
        sectors as that affected by the measure that the Arbitral Panel
        has found not to be in conformity with this Agreement. If such
        disputing Party considers that it is not practicable or
        effective to suspend benefits in the same sector or sectors it
        may suspend benefits in other sectors.
      
        A disputing Party shall notify the other disputing Party of the
        benefits which it intends to suspend, the grounds for such
        suspension and when suspension will commence at least 30 days
        before the date on which the suspension is due to take effect.
        Within 15 days from the receipt of such notification, the other
        disputing Party may request the original Arbitral Panel to rule
        on whether the benefits which a disputing Party intends to
        suspend are equivalent to those affected by the measure found
        not to be in conformity with this Agreement, and whether the
        proposed suspension is in accordance with paragraphs 1 and 2 of
        this Article. The rulings of the Arbitral Panel shall be given
        within 45 days from the receipt of such request and shall be
        final and binding to the disputing Parties. Benefits shall not
        be suspended until the Arbitral Panel has issued its rulings.
      
        Compensation and/or suspension of benefits shall be temporary
        and shall not be preferred to full elimination of the
        non-conformity as determined in the final report of the Arbitral
        Panel. Compensation and/or suspension shall only be applied by a
        disputing Party until the measure found not to be in conformity
        with this Agreement has been withdrawn or amended so as to bring
        it into conformity with this Agreement, or until the disputing
        Parties have resolved the dispute otherwise.
      
        Upon request of a disputing Party, the original Arbitral Panel
        shall rule on the conformity with the final report of any
        implementing measure adopted after the suspension of benefits
        and, in light of such rulings, whether the suspension of
        benefits should be terminated or modified. The rulings of the
        Arbitral Panel shall be made within 30 days from the date of the
        receipt of such request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.16" name="Expenses" article_identifier="39886">Unless the disputing Parties agree otherwise:
      
        each disputing Party shall bear the costs of its appointed
        arbitrator, its own expenses and legal costs; and
      
        the costs of the chair of the Arbitral Panel and other expenses
        associated with the conduct of its proceedings shall be borne in
        equal parts by the disputing Parties.
      
        Upon request of a disputing Party, the Arbitral Panel may decide
        on the expenses referred to in subparagraph b) of paragraph 1 of
        this Article taking into account the particular circumstances of
        the case.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.17" name="Language" article_identifier="39887">All proceedings and documents pursuant to this Chapter shall be
        conducted in the English language.
      
        Any document submitted for use in the proceedings pursuant to
        this Chapter shall be in the English language. If any original
        document is not in the English language, the disputing Party
        submitting it shall provide an English language translation of
        such document.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="4610">
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.1" name="Annexes" article_identifier="39888">The Annexes to this Agreement constitute an integral part of this
    Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.2" name="Accession" article_identifier="39889">A new Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union shall accede
        to this Agreement if the Parties mutually agree on such
        accession. Such accession shall be done through an additional
        protocol to this Agreement.
      
        The Eurasian Economic Commission shall promptly notify Viet Nam
        of any third country receiving the status of the candidate for
        membership in the Eurasian Economic Union and of any accession
        to the Eurasian Economic Union.
      
        Without prejudice to the accession of the candidate Member State
        to the Eurasian Economic Union, the provisions included in
        Chapter 8 (Trade in Services, Investment and Movement of Natural
        Persons) of this Agreement may be negotiated by the candidate
        Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union on the one side and
        Viet Nam on the other side.
      The candidate Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union and Viet Nam shall endeavour to complete the negotiations envisaged in
paragraph 3 of this Article prior to the candidate Member State becoming a Member State of the Eurasian Economic Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.3" name="Withdrawal And Termination" article_identifier="39890">Each Party may withdraw from this Agreement by giving a
        six-month advance notice in writing to the other Party.
      
        This Agreement shall terminate for any Member State of the
        Eurasian Economic Union which withdraws from the Treaty on the
        EAEU on the same date as the withdrawal takes effect. Viet Nam
        shall be notified in writing by the Eurasian Economic Union of
        such withdrawal six months in advance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.4" name="Evolutionary Clause" article_identifier="39891">The Parties undertake to review this Agreement in the light of
        further developments in international economic relations,
        inter alia, within the framework of the
        WTO, and to examine in this context and in the light of any
        relevant factor the possibility of further developing and
        deepening their cooperation under this Agreement and to extend
        it to areas not covered therein. The Joint Committee may, where
        appropriate, make recommendations to the Parties, particularly
        with a view to opening up negotiations.
      
        The Parties shall undertake a general review of this Agreement
        with a view to furthering its objectives in three years after
        the date this Agreement enters into force, and every five years
        thereafter, unless the Parties agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.5" name="Amendments" article_identifier="39892">This Agreement may be amended by the Parties by mutual written
        consent.
      Amendments shall enter into force according to the provisions of
Article 15.6 of this Agreement. All amendments shall constitute an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.6" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="39893">This Agreement shall enter into force 60 days from the date of
        receipt of the last written notification certifying that the
        Member States of the Eurasian Economic Union and Viet Nam have
        completed their respective internal legal procedures subject to
        paragraph 2 of this Article. Exchange of such notifications
        shall be made between the Eurasian Economic Commission and Viet
        Nam.
      Lack of written notification certifying that the Kyrgyz Republic has completed its respective internal legal procedures referred to in
paragraph 1 of this Article shall not prevent this Agreement from entry into force between the Eurasian Economic Union, the Republic of Armenia, the Republic of Belarus, the Republic of Kazakhstan and the Russian Federation, of the one part, and Viet Nam, of the other part. This Agreement shall enter into force for the Kyrgyz Republic after 60 days from the date of receipt by Viet Nam of the written notification that the Kyrgyz Republic has completed internal legal procedures necessary for entry into force of this Agreement and not earlier than the entry into force of the Treaty on the Accession of the Kyrgyz Republic to the Treaty on the EAEU of 23 December 2014.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="4611">
      <article article_identifier="39894">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorised thereto,
    have signed this Agreement.
  
    Done at Burabay, this 29th day of May
    2015, in two originals in the English language, both texts being
    equally authentic.
  For the Republic of
            ArmeniaFor the Socialist Republic of Viet
            NamFor the Republic of
            BelarusFor the Republic of
            KazakhstanForthe Kyrgyz RepublicForthe Russian FederationForthe Eurasian Economic
            Union</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
