<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>India - Japan</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>173</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>150</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2011-02-16</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2011-08-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2011-09-14</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2026-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">IND</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">IND</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>West Asia; East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/india/epa201102/pdfs/ijcepa_ba_e.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/india/epa201102/index.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1641">
      <article article_identifier="13497">Preamble 


Japan and the Republic of India (hereinafter referred
to as “India”), 


RECOGNISING that a dynamic and rapidly changing global
environment brought about by globalisation and
technological progress presents various economic and
strategic challenges and opportunities to the Parties; 


CONSCIOUS of their longstanding friendship and strong
economic and political ties that have developed through
many years of fruitful and mutually beneficial cooperation
between the Parties; 


BELIEVING that such bilateral relationship will be
enhanced by forging mutually beneficial economic
partnership through liberalisation and facilitation of
trade and investment, and cooperation; 


REAFFIRMING that the economic partnership will provide
a useful framework for enhanced cooperation and serve the
common interests of the Parties in various fields as agreed
in this Agreement and lead to the improvement of economic
efficiency and the development of trade, investment, and
human resources; 


RECOGNISING that the economic partnership will create
larger and new market, enhance the attractiveness and
vibrancy of their markets, and contribute to improving
efficiency and competitiveness of their manufacturing and
service industries; 


FURTHER RECOGNISING that the economic development,
social development and environmental protection are
interdependent and mutually reinforcing components of
sustainable development and that the economic partnership
can play an important role in promoting sustainable
development; 


RECALLING Article XXIV of the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General 
Agreement on Trade in Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B,
respectively, to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the
World Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15,
1994; 


REAFFIRMING their rights to pursue their economic and
development goals and their rights to realise their
national policy objectives; 


CONVINCED that this Agreement would open a new era for
the relationship between the Parties; 


RESOLVED to promote trade and investment through the
establishment of clear and mutually advantageous rules as
well as regulatory cooperation; 


SHARING the belief that the economic partnership would
contribute to expanding trade and investment not only
between the Parties but also in the region; and 


DETERMINED to establish a legal framework for an
economic partnership between the Parties; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1642">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="13498">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 



(a) liberalise and facilitate trade in goods and
services between the Parties; 



(b) increase investment opportunities and strengthen
protection for investments and investment
activities in the Parties; 



(c) ensure protection of intellectual property and
promote cooperation in the field thereof; 



(d) promote cooperation for the effective enforcement
of competition laws in each Party; 



(e) improve business environment in each Party; 



(f) 	establish a framework to enhance closer 
cooperation in the fields agreed in this
Agreement; and 



(g) create effective procedures for the
implementation and application of this Agreement
and for the resolution of disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Geographical Scope Of Application" article_identifier="13499">Unless otherwise specified, this Agreement shall apply
to “the Area” of each Party, which consists of the
territory of the Party, including its territorial sea,
airspace above such territory; and all the area beyond its
territorial sea, including the sea-bed and subsoil thereof,
over which the Party has sovereign rights or jurisdiction
in accordance with its laws and regulations and
international law, including the United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea, done at Montego Bay, December 10,
1982. 


Note: Nothing in this Article shall affect the rights and 
obligations of the Parties under international law,
including those under the United Nations Convention
on the Law of the Sea, done at Montego Bay, December
10, 1982.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="13500">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise
specified: 



(a) the term “customs authority” means the authority
that, according to the legislation of each Party
or non-Parties, is responsible for the
administration and enforcement of customs laws 
and regulations. In the case of Japan, the 
Ministry of Finance, and in the case of India,
the Central Board of Excise and Customs in the 
Department of Revenue, Ministry of Finance; 



(b) the term “days” means calendar days, including
weekends and holidays; 



(c) the term “enterprise” means any legal person or
any other entity duly formed, constituted or 
organised under applicable law, whether for
profit or otherwise, and whether privately-owned
or controlled or governmentally-owned or
controlled, including any corporation, trust,
partnership, joint venture, sole proprietorship,
association, organisation or company; 



(d) an enterprise is: 


(i) “owned” by an investor if more than 50
percent of the equity interests in it is
beneficially owned by the investor; and 


(ii) “controlled” by an investor if the investor
has the power to name a majority of its
directors or otherwise to legally direct its
actions; 


(e) the term “enterprise of a Party” means an
enterprise formed, constituted or organised under 
the law of a Party and carrying out substantial
business activities in the Area of the Party; 



(f) the term “GATS” means the General Agreement on
Trade in Services in Annex 1B to the WTO 
Agreement; 



(g) the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement
on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement. For the purposes of this Agreement, 
references to articles in the GATT 1994 include 
the interpretative notes; 



(h) the term “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the
Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding
System defined in paragraph (a) of Article 1 of
the International Convention on the Harmonized 
Commodity Description and Coding System, and
adopted and implemented by the Parties in their
respective laws; 



(i) the term “investments” means every kind of asset
owned or controlled by an investor, including: 

(i) an enterprise and a branch of an enterprise; 


(ii) shares, stocks or other forms of equity
participation in an enterprise, including
rights derived therefrom; 


(iii) bonds, debentures, loans and other forms of
debt, including rights derived therefrom; 



(iv) rights under contracts, including turnkey,
construction, management, production or
revenue-sharing contracts; 


(v) rights to claim money and claim any
performance under contract having a
financial value; 


(vi) intellectual property; 

Note: Intellectual property means that set 
out in paragraph 2 of Article 102. 


(vii) goodwill; 


(viii) rights conferred pursuant to laws and
regulations or contracts such as
concessions, licences, authorisations and
permits; and 


(ix) any other movable or immovable property
(including land), whether tangible or
intangible, and any related property rights,
such as leases, mortgages, liens and
pledges; 


Note 1: Investments also include amounts yielded 
by investments, in particular, profit,
interest, capital gains, dividends,
royalties and fees. A change in the form 
in which assets are invested does not 
affect their character as investments. 


Note 2: Where an asset lacks the characteristics 
of an investment, that asset is not an
investment regardless of the form it may
take. The characteristics of an 
investment include the commitment of 
capital, the expectation of gain or
profit through the commitment of the
capital, or the assumption of risk. 



(j) 	the term “investment activities” means 
establishment, acquisition, expansion,
management, conduct, operation, maintenance, use,
enjoyment and sale or other disposition of
investments; 



(k) the term “investor of a Party” means a natural
person or an enterprise of a Party, that seeks to
make, is making, or has made, investments; 



(l) the term “juridical person” means any legal
entity duly constituted or otherwise organised
under applicable law, whether for profit or
otherwise, and whether privately-owned or
governmentally-owned, including any corporation,
trust, partnership, joint venture, sole
proprietorship, association or cooperative; 


Note: A cooperative is a legal entity constituted 
under the relevant applicable laws in
India. 


(m) a juridical person is: 


(i) “owned” by persons of a Party if more than
50 percent of the equity interest in it is
beneficially owned by such persons; 


(ii) “controlled” by persons of a Party if such
persons have the power to name a majority of
its directors or otherwise to legally direct
its actions; and 


(iii) “affiliated” with another person when it
controls, or is controlled by, that other
person; or when it and the other person are
both controlled by the same person; 


(n) the term “juridical person of the other Party”
means a juridical person which is either: 


(i) constituted or otherwise organised under the
law of the other Party and engaged in
substantive business operations in the Area
of the other Party; or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service
through commercial presence, owned or
controlled by: 



(A) natural persons of the other Party; or 



(B) juridical persons of the other Party
identified under subparagraph (i); 


(o) the term “natural person of the other Party”
means a natural person who under the law of the
other Party: 


(i) in respect of India, is a citizen of India;
and 


(ii) in respect of Japan, is a national of Japan; 


(p) the term “originating good” means a good which
qualifies as an originating good under the
provisions of Chapter 3; 



(q) the term “Parties” means Japan and India and the
term “Party” means either Japan or India; 



(r) the term “person” means a natural person or an
enterprise/juridical person; 



(s) the term “service” includes any service in any
sector except a service supplied in the exercise
of governmental authority; 



(t) the term “service supplier” means any person that
supplies a service; and 


Note: Where the service is not supplied directly 
by a juridical person but through other
forms of commercial presence such as a
branch or a representative office, the
service supplier (i.e. the juridical
person) shall, nonetheless, through such
presence be accorded the treatment provided
for service suppliers under Chapter 6.
Such treatment shall be extended to the 
presence through which the service is
supplied and need not be extended to any
other parts of the supplier located outside
the Area of a Party where the service is
supplied. 


(u) the term “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh
Agreement Establishing the World Trade
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13501">1. Each Party shall publish, or otherwise make publicly
available, its laws, regulations, administrative
procedures, and administrative rulings and judicial
decisions of general application, with respect to any
matter covered by this Agreement. 



2. Each Party shall make available to the public the 
names and addresses of the competent authorities
responsible for laws, regulations, administrative
procedures and administrative rulings, referred to in
paragraph 1. 



3. Each Party shall, upon the request by the other Party,
within a reasonable period of time, respond to specific
questions from and provide information to the other Party
with respect to matters referred to in paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="13502">1. Where administrative decisions which pertain to or
affect the implementation and operation of this Agreement
are taken by the competent authorities of a Party, the
competent authorities shall, in accordance with the laws
and regulations of the Party: 



(a) inform the applicant of the decision within a
reasonable period of time after the submission of
the application considered complete under the
laws and regulations of the Party, taking into
account the established standard period of time
referred to in paragraph 2; and 



(b) provide, within a reasonable period of time,
information concerning the status of the
application, at the request of the applicant. 

2. The competent authorities of a Party shall, in
accordance with the laws and regulations of the Party: 



(a) endeavour to establish standard periods of time
between the receipt of applications by the
competent authorities and the administrative
decisions taken in response to the submitted
applications; and 



(b) make publicly available such periods of time, if
established. 

3. The competent authorities of a Party shall, in
accordance with the laws and regulations of the Party,
prior to taking any final decision which imposes
obligations on or restricts rights of a person, provide
that person with: 



(a) a reasonable notice, including a description of
the nature of the measure, specific provisions
upon which such measure would be based, and the
facts which may be a cause of taking such
measure; and 



(b) a reasonable opportunity to present facts and
arguments in support of a position of such
person, 

provided that time, the nature of the measure, and the
public interest permit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="13503">1. Each Party shall maintain judicial tribunals or
procedures for the purpose of the prompt review and, where
warranted, correction of actions taken by its Government
relating to matters covered by this Agreement. Such 
tribunals or procedures shall be impartial and independent
of the authorities entrusted with the administrative 
enforcement of such actions. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that the parties in any such
tribunals or procedures are provided with the right to: 



(a) a reasonable opportunity to support or defend
their respective positions; and 



(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions 
of record. 


3. Each Party shall ensure, subject to appeal or further
review as provided in its laws and regulations, that such
decision is implemented by the relevant authorities with
respect to the action at issue which is taken by its
Government.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Measures Against Corruption" article_identifier="13504">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take appropriate measures to prevent and
combat corruption of its public officials regarding matters
covered by this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Environmental Protection" article_identifier="13505">1. Each Party, acknowledging the importance of
environmental protection and sustainable development and
recognising the right of each Party to establish its own
domestic environmental policies and priorities, shall
ensure that its laws and regulations provide for adequate 
levels of environmental protection and shall strive to 
continue to improve those laws and regulations. 



2. Each Party shall take appropriate governmental action
such as monitoring compliance with, and investigating
suspected violations of, its environmental laws and
regulations. 



3. Each Party shall endeavour to: 



(a) take necessary measures to enhance public
awareness of environmental policy and related
matters by way of, such as, promoting education
in the field thereof; and 



(b) encourage trade and dissemination of
environmentally sound goods and services. 


4. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
under any international agreements concerning the
environment, to which both Parties are parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="13506">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, maintain the confidentiality of information
provided in confidence by the other Party pursuant to this
Agreement. 



2. Information provided in confidence pursuant to this
Agreement shall be used only for the purposes specified by
the Party providing the information. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the confidential
information provided pursuant to this Agreement may be
transmitted to a third party subject to prior consent of
the Party providing the information. 



4. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement,
nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party to provide
confidential information, the disclosure of which would
impede the enforcement of its laws and regulations, or
otherwise be contrary to the public interest, or which
would prejudice the legitimate commercial interests of
particular enterprises, public or private.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Taxation" article_identifier="13507">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, the
provisions of this Agreement shall not apply to any
taxation measures. 



2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and
obligations of either Party under any tax convention. In 
the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and
any such convention, that convention shall prevail to the
extent of the inconsistency. 



3. Articles 4, 6 and 9 shall apply to taxation measures, 
to the extent that the provisions of this Agreement are
applicable to such taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="13508">1. For the purposes of this Agreement except Chapters 6
and 9, Articles XX and XXI of the GATT 1994 are
incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis 
mutandis. 



2. For the purposes of Chapters 6 and 8, Articles XIV and
XIV bis of the GATS are incorporated into and form part of
this Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 



3. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to
prevent a Party from taking any action which it considers
necessary for the protection of its essential security
interests to protect critical public infrastructure,
including communications, power and water infrastructure,
from deliberate attempts to disable or degrade such
infrastructure. 


Note: Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed so 
as to derogate from the rights and obligations
of the Parties under the WTO Agreement. 


4. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to
require a Party to accord the benefits of this Agreement to
the other Party, or to the goods or service suppliers of
the other Party or investors that are enterprises of the
other Party, where the Party adopts or maintains measures
in any legislation or regulations which it considers
necessary for the protection of its essential security
interests with respect to a non-Party, or goods or service
suppliers of a non-Party or investors that are enterprises
of a non-Party, that would be violated or circumvented if
the benefits of this Agreement were accorded to such goods
or service suppliers or such enterprises of the other Party
or to their investments. 



5. For the purposes of Chapters 6 and 8, a Party may deny
the benefits of this Agreement to an investor of the other
Party that is an enterprise of the other Party and to its
investments, or to a service supplier of the other Party
that is a juridical person of the other Party in the
situation where the enterprise or the juridical person is
owned or controlled by an investor or persons of a non-
Party, and the denying Party: 



(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with the
non-Party; or 



(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to the
non-Party that prohibit transactions with the
enterprise or that would be violated or
circumvented if the benefit of this Agreement
were accorded to the service supplier or the
enterprise or to its investments. 


6. For the purposes of Chapter 6, subject to prior
notification to and consultation with the other Party, a
Party may also deny the benefits of the Chapter to a
service supplier of the other Party, where the denying
Party establishes that: 



(a) the service supplier is a juridical person that
is owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party
and has no substantial business activities in the 
Area of the other Party; 



(b) the service is supplied from or in the Area of a
non-Party; 



(c) in the case of the supply of a maritime transport
service, the service is supplied: 


(i) by a vessel registered under the laws of a
non-Party; and 


(ii) by a person which operates and/or uses the
vessel in whole or in part but which is of a
non-Party; or 


(d) the service supplier is not: 

(i) in respect of a natural person, a natural
person of the other Party as defined under
this Agreement; or 


(ii) in respect of a juridical person, a
juridical person of the other Party as
defined under this Agreement. 


7. For the purposes of Chapter 8, subject to prior
notification to and consultation with the other Party, a
Party may also deny the benefits of the Chapter to an
investor of the other Party that is an enterprise of the
other Party and to its investments, where the denying Party
establishes that: 



(a) the enterprise has no substantial business
activities in the Area of the other Party; and 



(b) the enterprise is owned or controlled by an
investor of a non-Party or of the denying Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="13509">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
under the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which
both Parties are parties. 



2. In the event of any inconsistency between this
Agreement and the WTO Agreement or any other agreements, to
which both Parties are parties, the Parties shall
immediately consult with each other with a view to finding
a mutually satisfactory solution, taking into consideration
general principles of international law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="13510">The Governments of the Parties shall, where necessary,
conclude a separate agreement setting forth the details and
procedures for the implementation of this Agreement
(hereinafter referred to in this Agreement as “the
Implementing Agreement”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="13511">1. A Joint Committee shall be established under this 
Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Agreement; 



(b) considering and recommending to the Parties any
amendments to this Agreement; 



(c) supervising and coordinating the work of all Sub-
Committees established under this Agreement; 



(d) adopting: 


(i) the Implementing Procedures referred to in
Section 11 of Annex 3; and 


(ii) any necessary decisions; and 


(e) carrying out other functions as the Parties may
agree. 


3. The Joint Committee: 



(a) shall be composed of representatives of the
Governments of the Parties; and 



(b) may establish, and delegate its responsibilities
to, Sub-Committees. 


4. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules and 
procedures. 



5. The Joint Committee shall meet: 



(a) once a year at the request of either Party or at
such times as may be agreed by the Parties; and 



(b) at such venues as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Communications" article_identifier="13512">1. Each Party shall designate a contact point to
facilitate communications between the Parties on any matter
relating to this Agreement. 



2. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, any
formal communication and notification between the Parties 
under this Agreement shall be made through the contact
points referred to in paragraph 1.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="1643">
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13513">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “bilateral safeguard measure” means a
bilateral safeguard measure provided for in
paragraph 2 of Article 23; 



(b) the term “customs duty” means any customs duty,
import duty or a charge of any kind imposed in
connection with the importation of a good, but
does not include any: 

(i) charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed
consistently with the provisions of
paragraph 2 of Article II and paragraph 2 of
Article III of the GATT 1994; 


(ii) anti-dumping or countervailing duty applied
pursuant to a Party’s law and applied
consistently with the provisions of Article
VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on
Implementation of Article VI of the General
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex
1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter
referred to as “the Agreement on Anti-
Dumping”), and the Agreement on Subsidies
and Countervailing Measures in Annex 1A to
the WTO Agreement; or 


(iii) fees or other charges that shall be limited
in amount to the approximate cost of
services rendered; 


Note 1: Customs duty for India refers to basic 
customs duty as specified in the First
Schedule to the Customs Tariff Act, 1975
of India. 


Note 2: Nothing in this subparagraph, including 
its notes, shall be construed so as to
derogate from any rights and obligations
of each Party under the GATT 1994. 



(c) the term “domestic industry” means the producers
as a whole of the like or directly competitive
goods operating in a Party, or those whose
collective output of the like or directly
competitive goods constitutes a major proportion
of the total domestic production of those goods; 



(d) the term “provisional bilateral safeguard
measure” means a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure provided for in subparagraph 8(a) of
Article 23; 



(e) the term “serious injury” means a significant
overall impairment in the position of a domestic
industry; and 



(f) the term “threat of serious injury” means serious
injury that, on the basis of facts and not merely
on allegation, conjecture or remote possibility,
is clearly imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="13514">The classification of goods in trade between the
Parties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13515">Each Party shall accord national treatment to the
goods of the other Party in accordance with Article III of
the GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="13516">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,
each Party shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties on
originating goods of the other Party designated for such
purposes in its Schedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the
terms and conditions set out in such Schedule. 



2. In cases where its most-favoured-nation applied rate
of customs duty on a particular good is lower than the rate
of customs duty to be applied in accordance with paragraph
1 on the originating good which is classified under the
same tariff line as that particular good, each Party shall
apply the lower rate with respect to that originating good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="13517">For the purpose of determining the customs value of
imported goods from a Party into the other Party,
provisions of Part I of the Agreement on Implementation of
Article VII of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade
1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred
to as “the Agreement on Customs Valuation”), shall apply
mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Export Subsidies And Domestic Support" article_identifier="13518">Neither Party shall introduce or maintain any export
subsidies or domestic support, which are inconsistent with
its obligations under the WTO Agreement, on any
agricultural good which is listed in Annex 1 to the
Agreement on Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to as “the Agreement on
Agriculture”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="13519">1. Each Party shall not introduce or maintain any
prohibition or restriction other than customs duties on the
importation of any good of the other Party or on the
exportation or sale for export of any good destined to the
other Party, which is inconsistent with its obligations
under the relevant provisions of the WTO Agreement. 



2. In the event that a Party introduces a prohibition or
restriction otherwise justified under the relevant
provisions of the WTO Agreement with respect to the
exportation of a good to the other Party, the former Party
shall, upon the request of the other Party, provide to the
other Party, as soon as possible after the prohibition or
restriction is introduced, relevant information, which
shall include a description of the good involved and the
introduced prohibition or restriction, the actual date of
introduction of such prohibition or restriction, unless the
sharing of such information is considered by the former
Party as prejudicial to public interest.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="13520">1. Notwithstanding any provisions of this Chapter but
subject to the provisions of this Article, each Party may
apply a bilateral safeguard measure, to the extent
necessary to prevent or remedy the serious injury to a
domestic industry of that Party and to facilitate
adjustment, if an originating good of the other Party, as a
result of the elimination or reduction of a customs duty in
accordance with Article 19, is being imported into the
former Party in such increased quantities, in absolute
terms or relative to domestic production, and under such
conditions that the imports of that originating good
constitute a substantial cause of serious injury, or threat
thereof, to the domestic industry of the former Party. 



2. A Party may, as a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) suspend the further reduction of any rate of
customs duty on the originating good provided for
in this Chapter; or 



(b) increase the rate of customs duty on the
originating good to a level not to exceed the
lesser of: 

(i) the most-favoured-nation applied rate of
customs duty in effect on the day when the
bilateral safeguard measure is taken; and 


(ii) the most-favoured-nation applied rate of
customs duty in effect on the day
immediately preceding the date of entry into
force of this Agreement. 


3. 	(a) A Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure 
only after an investigation has been carried out
by the competent authorities of that Party in
accordance with the same procedures as those
provided for in Article 3 and subparagraph 2(c)
of Article 4 of the Agreement on Safeguards in
Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter
referred to as “the Agreement on Safeguards”). 



(b) The investigation referred to in subparagraph (a)
shall in all cases be completed as early as
possible and in no case later than one year from
the date of initiation. 



(c) In the investigation referred to in subparagraph


(a) to determine whether increased imports of an
originating good have caused or are threatening
to cause serious injury to a domestic industry
under the terms of this Article, the competent
authorities of the Party who carry out the
investigation shall evaluate all relevant factors
of an objective and quantifiable nature having a
bearing on the situation of that domestic
industry, in particular, the rate and amount of
the increase in imports of the originating good
in absolute and relative terms, the share of the
domestic market taken by the increased imports of
the originating good, and the changes in the
level of sales, production, productivity,
capacity utilisation, profits and losses, and
employment. 


(d) The determination that increased imports of an
originating good have caused or are threatening
to cause serious injury to a domestic industry
shall not be made unless the investigation
referred to in subparagraph (a) demonstrates, on
the basis of objective evidence, the existence of
the causal link between increased imports of the
originating good and serious injury or threat
thereof. When factors other than the increased 
imports of the originating good are causing
injury to the domestic industry at the same time,
such injury shall not be attributed to the
increased imports of the originating good. 


4. The following conditions and limitations shall apply
with regard to a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) A Party shall immediately deliver a written
notice to the other Party upon: 


(i) initiating an investigation referred to in
subparagraph 3(a) relating to serious
injury, or threat thereof, and the reasons
for it; and 


(ii) taking a decision to apply or extend a
bilateral safeguard measure. 


(b) The Party making the written notice referred to
in subparagraph (a) shall provide the other Party
with all pertinent information, which shall
include: 


(i) 	in the written notice referred to in 
subparagraph (a)(i), the reason for the
initiation of the investigation, a precise
description of the originating good subject
to the investigation and its subheading of
the Harmonized System, the period subject to
the investigation and the date of initiation
of the investigation; and 


(ii) 	in the written notice referred to in 
subparagraph (a)(ii), evidence of serious
injury or threat thereof caused by the
increased imports of the originating good, a
precise description of the originating good
subject to the proposed bilateral safeguard
measure and its subheading of the Harmonized
System, a precise description of the
bilateral safeguard measure, and the
proposed date of the introduction and
expected duration of the bilateral safeguard
measure. 


(c) A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral
safeguard measure shall provide adequate
opportunity for prior consultations with the
other Party with a view to reviewing the
information arising from the investigation
referred to in subparagraph 3(a), exchanging
views on the bilateral safeguard measure and
reaching an agreement on compensation set out in
paragraph 5. 



(d) No bilateral safeguard measure shall be
maintained except to the extent and for such time
as may be necessary to prevent or remedy serious
injury and to facilitate adjustment, provided
that such time shall not exceed a period of three
years. However, in highly exceptional 
circumstances, a bilateral safeguard measure may
be extended, provided that the total duration of
the bilateral safeguard measure, including such
extensions, shall not exceed five years. In 
order to facilitate adjustment in a situation
where the expected duration of a bilateral
safeguard measure is over one year, the Party
maintaining the bilateral safeguard measure shall
progressively liberalise the bilateral safeguard
measure at regular intervals during the period of
application. 



(e) No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied
again to the import of a particular originating
good which has been subject to such a bilateral
safeguard measure, for a period of time equal to
that during which such measure had been
previously applied, provided that the period of
non-application is at least one year. 



(f) Upon the termination of a bilateral safeguard
measure, the rate of customs duty for an
originating good subject to the measure shall be
the rate which would have been in effect but for 
the bilateral safeguard measure. 


5. 	(a) A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral 
safeguard measure shall provide to the other
Party mutually agreed adequate means of trade
compensation in the form of concessions whose
value is substantially equivalent to that of the
additional customs duties expected to result from
the bilateral safeguard measure. 



(b) If the Parties are unable to agree on the
compensation within 30 days after the
commencement of the consultations pursuant to
subparagraph 4(c), the Party against whose
originating good the bilateral safeguard measure
is applied shall be free to suspend the
application of concessions under this Agreement,
which are substantially equivalent to the
bilateral safeguard measure. The Party 
exercising the right of suspension may suspend
the application of concessions only for the
minimum period necessary to achieve the
substantially equivalent effects and only while
the bilateral safeguard measure is maintained. 



(c) (i) The right to claim the trade compensation 
which is agreed on by the Parties under
subparagraph (a) and the right of suspension
provided for in subparagraph (b) shall not
be exercised for the first two years that a
bilateral safeguard measure is in effect,
provided that the bilateral safeguard
measure has been taken as a result of an 
absolute increase in imports and that such
bilateral safeguard measure conforms to the
provisions of this Article. 

(ii) The two years period mentioned in
subparagraph (i) may be extended by one
year, provided that the Party applying the
bilateral safeguard measure provides to the
other Party, evidence that the bilateral
safeguard measure continues to be necessary
to prevent or remedy serious injury caused
by an absolute increase in imports and that
the industry concerned is adjusting. 


6. Nothing in this Chapter shall prevent a Party from
applying safeguard measures to an originating good of the
other Party in accordance with: 



(a) Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
Safeguards; or 



(b) Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture. 


7. Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial and
reasonable administration of its laws and regulations
relating to bilateral safeguard measures. 



8. 	(a) In critical circumstances, where delay would 
cause damage which it would be difficult to
repair, a Party may take a provisional bilateral
safeguard measure, which shall take the form of
the measure set out in subparagraph 2(a) or (b),
pursuant to a preliminary determination that
there is clear evidence that increased imports of
an originating good of the other Party have
caused or are threatening to cause serious injury
to a domestic industry. 



(b) A Party shall deliver a written notice to the
other Party prior to applying a provisional
bilateral safeguard measure. Consultations 
between the Parties on the application of the
provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall be
initiated immediately after the provisional
bilateral safeguard measure is taken. 



(c) The duration of a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure shall not exceed 200 days. During that 
period, the pertinent requirements of paragraph 3
shall be met. The duration of the provisional
bilateral safeguard measure shall be counted as a
part of the period referred to in subparagraph
4(d). 



(d) Subparagraph 4(f) and paragraph 7 shall be
applied mutatis mutandis to a provisional
bilateral safeguard measure. The customs duty 
imposed as a result of the provisional bilateral
safeguard measure shall be refunded if the
subsequent investigation referred to in
subparagraph 3(a) does not determine that
increased imports of an originating good of the
other Party have caused or threatened to cause
serious injury to a domestic industry. 


9. A written notice referred to in subparagraphs 4(a) and
8(b) and any other communication between the Parties shall
be done in the English language. 



10. The Parties shall review the provisions of this
Article, after 10 years of the date of entry into force of
this Agreement, or earlier as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Anti-Dumping Investigation" article_identifier="13521">When the authority of a Party competent for initiating
investigation under Article 5 of the Agreement on Anti-
Dumping received a written application by or on behalf of
its domestic industry for the initiation of the
investigation in respect of a good from the other Party,
the former Party shall, at least 10 working days in advance
of the initiation of such investigation, notify the other
Party, and provide it with the full text, of such
application. The other Party may inform the exporters, 
foreign producers and relevant trade associations known to
the other Party of that notification and of the information
included in that application. Due regard shall be paid to 
the requirement for the protection of confidential
information, as provided for in paragraph 5 of Article 6 of
the Agreement on Anti-Dumping.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="13522">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent
a Party from taking any measure for balance-of-payments
purposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in 
accordance with the conditions established under Article 
XII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Balance-
of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude the use by a
Party of exchange controls or exchange restrictions in
accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the
International Monetary Fund.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="1644">
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13523">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “exporter” means a natural or juridical
person located in an exporting Party who exports
a good from the exporting Party; 



(b) the term “factory ships of the Party” or “vessels
of the Party” respectively means factory ships or
vessels: 


(i) which are registered in the Party; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; 


(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 50 
percent by nationals of the Parties, or by a
juridical person with its head office in
either Party, of which the representatives,
chairman of the board of directors, and the
majority of the members of such board are
nationals of the Parties, and of which at
least 50 percent of the equity interest is
owned by nationals or juridical persons of
the Parties; 


(iv) of which at least 50 percent of the total of
the master and officers are nationals of the 
Parties; and 


(v) of which at least 25 percent of the crew are
nationals of the Parties; 


(c) the term “fungible originating goods of a Party”
or “fungible originating materials of a Party”
respectively means originating goods or materials
of a Party that are interchangeable for
commercial purposes, whose properties are
essentially identical; 



(d) the term “Generally Accepted Accounting
Principles” means the recognised consensus or
substantial authoritative support within a Party
at a particular time as to which economic
resources and obligations should be recorded as
assets and liabilities, which changes in assets
and liabilities should be recorded, how the
assets and liabilities and changes in them should
be measured, what information should be disclosed
and how it should be disclosed, and which
financial statements should be prepared. These 
standards may be broad guidelines of general
application as well as detailed practices and
procedures; 



(e) the term “good” means any merchandise, product,
article or material; 



(f) the term “importer” means a natural or juridical
person who imports a good into the importing
Party; 



(g) the term “indirect materials” means goods used in
the production, testing or inspection of another
good but not physically incorporated into the
good, or goods used in the maintenance of
buildings or the operation of equipment
associated with the production of another good,
including: 


(i) fuel and energy; 


(ii) tools, dies and moulds; 


(iii) spare parts and goods used in the
maintenance of equipment and buildings; 



(iv) lubricants, greases, compounding materials
and other goods used in production or used
to operate equipment and buildings; 


(v) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safety
equipment and supplies; 


(vi) equipment, devices and supplies used for
testing or inspection; 

(vii) catalysts and solvents; and 


(viii) any other goods that are not incorporated
into another good but whose use in the
production of the good can reasonably be
demonstrated to be a part of that
production; 


(h) the term “materials” means any matter or
substance consumed in the production of a good,
physically incorporated into a good, or used in
the production of another good; 



(i) the term “non-originating material” means any
materials whose country of origin is other than
the Parties (imported non-originating) and any
material whose origin cannot be determined
(undetermined origin) under this Chapter; 



(j) the term “originating material” means any
material that qualifies as originating under this
Chapter; and 



(k) the term “production” means a method of obtaining
goods including manufacturing, assembling,
processing, raising, growing, breeding, mining,
extracting, harvesting, fishing, trapping,
gathering, collecting, hunting and capturing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="13524">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, a
good shall qualify as an originating good of a Party where: 



(a) the good is wholly obtained or produced entirely
in the Party, as provided for in Article 28; or 



(b) the good is not wholly obtained or produced in
the Party, provided that the good satisfies the
requirements of Article 29.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Wholly Obtained Or Produced Goods" article_identifier="13525">For the purposes of subparagraph (a) of Article 27,
the following goods shall be considered as being wholly
obtained or produced in a Party: 



(a) live animals born and raised in the Party; 



(b) animals obtained by hunting, trapping, fishing,
gathering or capturing in the Party; 



(c) goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 



(d) plants and plant products harvested, picked or
gathered in the Party; 


Note: For the purposes of this subparagraph, the 
term “plant” refers to all plant life,
including fruit, flowers, vegetables,
trees, seaweed, fungi and live plants. 


(e) minerals and other naturally occurring
substances, not included in subparagraphs (a)
through (d), extracted or taken in the Party; 



(f) goods of sea-fishing and other goods taken by
vessels of the Party from the sea outside the
territorial seas of the Parties; 



(g) goods produced on board factory ships of the
Party, outside the territorial seas of the
Parties from the goods referred to in
subparagraph (f); 



(h) goods taken from the sea-bed or subsoil beneath
the sea-bed outside the territorial sea of the 
Party, provided that the Party has rights to
exploit such sea-bed or subsoil in accordance
with the provisions of the United Nations
Convention on the Law of the Sea, done at Montego
Bay, December 10, 1982; 



(i) articles collected in the Party which can no
longer perform their original purpose in the
Party nor are capable of being restored or
repaired and which are fit only for disposal or
for the recovery of parts or raw materials; 



(j) scrap and waste derived from manufacturing or
processing operations or from consumption in the
Party and fit only for disposal or for the
recovery of raw materials; 



(k) parts or raw materials recovered in the Party
from articles which can no longer perform their
original purpose nor are capable of being
restored or repaired; and 



(l) goods obtained or produced in the Party
exclusively from the goods referred to in
subparagraphs (a) through (k).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Goods Produced Using Non-Originating Materials" article_identifier="13526">1. For the purposes of subparagraph (b) of Article 27, a
good shall qualify as an originating good of a Party if: 



(a) the good has a qualifying value content,
calculated using the formula set out in Article
30, of not less than 35 percent; and 



(b) all non-originating materials used in the
production of the good have undergone in the
Party a change in tariff classification at the
six-digit level (i.e. a change in tariff
subheading) of the Harmonized System. 

Note: For the purposes of this subparagraph, 
“Harmonized System” is that on which the
product specific rules set out in Annex 2
are based. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, a good subject to product
specific rules shall qualify as an originating good of a
Party if it satisfies the applicable product specific rules
set out in Annex 2. 



3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(b) and the relevant
product specific rules set out in Annex 2, the rule
requiring that the materials used have undergone a change
in tariff classification or a specific manufacturing or
processing operation, shall apply only to non-originating
materials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Calculation Of Qualifying Value Content" article_identifier="13527">1. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value
content of a good, one or the other of the following
formulas shall be applied: 


(a) 


F.O.B. – V.N.M. 
Q.V.C. = 

F.O.B. 

x 100 
Where: 




Q.V.C. is the qualifying value content of a
good, expressed as a percentage; 


F.O.B. is, except as provided for in
paragraph 2, the free-on-board value of a good
payable by the buyer of the good to the seller of
the good, regardless of the mode of shipment, not
including any internal excise taxes reduced,
exempted, or repaid when the good is exported;
and 


V.N.M. is the value of non-originating
materials used in the production of a good; 


(b) 


V.O.M. + Direct Labour Cost 


+ Direct Overhead Cost + Profit 


Q.V.C. = x 100 


F.O.B. 


Where: 


V.O.M. is the value of originating material
used in the production of the good. 


Note: For the purpose of calculating the qualifying 
value content of a good, the Generally Accepted
Accounting Principles in the exporting Party
shall be applied. 


2. F.O.B. referred to in paragraph 1 shall be the value: 



(a) adjusted to the first ascertainable price paid
for a good from the buyer to the producer of the
good, if there is free-on-board value of the
good, but it is unknown and cannot be
ascertained; or 



(b) determined in accordance with Articles 1 through
8 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if there
is no free-on-board value of a good. 

3. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the value of a
material used in a production of a good in a Party: 



(a) shall be the CIF value; or 



(b) shall be the first ascertainable price paid for
the material in the Party, but may exclude all
the costs incurred in the Party in transporting
the material from the warehouse of the supplier
of the material to the place where the producer
is located such as freight, insurance and packing
as well as any other known and ascertainable cost
incurred in the Party. 

Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, the term 
“CIF value” means the customs value of the 
imported good in accordance with the Agreement
on Customs Valuation and includes freight and
insurance where appropriate, packing and all
other costs incurred in transporting the
material to the importation port in the Party
where the producer of the good is located. 


4. For the purposes of subparagraph 2(b) or 3(a), in
applying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to determine
the value of a good or non-originating material, the
Agreement on Customs Valuation shall apply mutatis mutandis 
to domestic transactions or to the cases where there is no 
domestic transaction of the good or non-originating
material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="13528">For the purposes of determining whether a good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, an originating
good of the other Party which is used as a material in the
production of the good in the former Party may be
considered as an originating material of the former Party,
provided that such good has undergone its last production
process in the former Party which goes beyond the
operations provided for in Article 33.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="13529">Non-originating materials used in the production of a
good that do not satisfy an applicable rule for the good
shall be disregarded, provided that the totality of such
materials does not exceed specific percentages in value or
weight of the good. Such percentages shall be: 



(a) in the case of a good classified under Chapters
15 through 24 (except 1604.20, 1605.20, 1605.90,
2101.11, 2101.20, 2106.10, 2106.90, 2207.10 and
2207.20), 2501.00, 2906.11, 2918.14, 2918.15,
2940.00, 3505.10, 3505.20, 3809.10 and 3824.60 of
the Harmonized System, 7 percent in value of the
good; 



(b) in the case of a good classified under Chapters
28 through 49 (except 2905.44, 2906.11, 2918.14,
2918.15, 2940.00, 3502.11, 3502.19, 3505.10,
3505.20, 3809.10, 3824.60, 4601.29, 4601.94 and
4602.19) and 64 through 97 of the Harmonized
System, 10 percent in value of the good; and 



(c) in the case of a good classified under Chapters
50 through 63 (except 5001.00, 5003.00, heading
51.02, 51.03, 52.01 through 52.03, 53.01 and
53.02) of the Harmonized System, 7 percent in
weight of the good. 

Note 1: For the purposes of this Article, the term “value 


of the good” means the free-on-board value of the


good referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 30 or


the value set out in paragraph 2 of that Article. 


Note 2: For the purposes of this Article, “Harmonized 
System” is that on which the product specific rules
set out in Annex 2 are based. 


Note 3: This Article shall not be applied in calculating 
the qualifying value content set out in Article 30.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="13530">A good shall not be considered to be an originating
good of the exporting Party merely by reason of having
undergone the following: 



(a) operations to ensure the preservation of products
in good condition during transport and storage
(such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine,
removal of damaged parts) and other similar
operations; 



(b) changes of packaging and breaking up and assembly
of packages; 



(c) disassembly; 



(d) placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simple
packaging operations; 



(e) collection of parts and components classified as
a good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules
for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 



(f) simple operations consisting of removal of dust,
sifting or screening, sorting, classifying,
matching (including the making-up of sets of
articles), washing, painting; 



(g) simple cutting, slicing and repacking or placing
in bottles, flasks, bags or boxes, fixing on
cards or boards, and all other simple packing
operations; 



(h) affixing or printing marks, labels and other like
distinguishing signs on products or their
packaging; 



(i) simple mixing of products whether or not of
different kinds; 



(j) simple assembly of parts of goods to constitute a
complete product; 



(k) slaughter of animals; 



(l) 	mere dilution with water or another substance 
that does not materially alter the
characteristics of the goods; or 



(m) any combination of operations referred to in
subparagraphs (a) through (l). 

Note: For the purposes of this Article, an operation is 
described as “simple” if neither special skills nor
machines, apparatus or equipment especially produced
or installed for carrying it out are needed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Consignment Criteria" article_identifier="13531">1. An originating good of the other Party shall be deemed
to meet the consignment criteria when it is: 



(a) transported directly from the other Party; or 



(b) transported through one or more non-Parties for
the purpose of transit or temporary storage in
warehouses in such non-Parties, provided that it
does not undergo operations other than unloading,
reloading and any other operation to preserve it
in good condition. 

2. If an originating good of the other Party does not
meet the consignment criteria referred to in paragraph 1,
the good shall not be considered as an originating good of
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Unassembled Or Disassembled Goods" article_identifier="13532">Where a good satisfies the requirements of the
relevant provisions of Articles 27 through 33 and is
imported into a Party from the other Party in an
unassembled or disassembled form but is classified as an 
assembled good pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules
for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System, such a
good shall be considered as an originating good of the
other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="13533">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, where fungible
originating materials of the Party and fungible non-
originating materials that are mixed in an inventory are
used in the production of the good, the origin of the
materials may be determined pursuant to an inventory
management method under the Generally Accepted Accounting
Principles in the Party. 



2. Where fungible originating goods of a Party and
fungible non-originating goods are mixed in an inventory
and, prior to exportation do not undergo any production
process or any operation in the Party where they were mixed
other than unloading, reloading or any other operation to
preserve them in good condition, the origin of the good may
be determined pursuant to an inventory management method
under the Generally Accepted Accounting Principles in the
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="13534">Indirect materials shall be, without regard to where
they are produced, considered to be originating materials
of a Party where the good is produced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Accessories, Spare Parts, Tools And Instructional Or Other Information Materials" article_identifier="13535">1. In determining whether all the non-originating
materials used in the production of a good undergo the
applicable change in tariff classification or a specific
manufacturing or processing operation, accessories, spare
parts, tools and instructional or other information
materials delivered with the good that form part of the
good's standard accessories, spare parts, tools and
instructional or other information materials, shall be
disregarded, provided that: 



(a) the accessories, spare parts, tools and
instructional or other information materials are 
not invoiced separately from the good, without
regard to whether they are separately described
in the invoice; and 



(b) the quantities and value of the accessories,
spare parts, tools and instructional or other
information materials are customary for the good. 

2. If a good is subject to a qualifying value content
requirement, the value of the accessories, spare parts,
tools and instructional or other information materials 
shall be taken into account as the value of originating or
non-originating materials, as the case may be, in
calculating the qualifying value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Packing And Packaging Materials And Containers" article_identifier="13536">1. Packing materials and containers for shipment that are
used to protect a good during transportation shall not be
taken into account in determining whether the good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party. 



2. With respect to packaging materials and containers
that are used for retail sale of a good: 


(a) such packaging materials and containers shall be
disregarded in determining whether the good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, if
they are classified with the good pursuant to
Rule 5 of the General Rules for the 
Interpretation of the Harmonized System; and 



(b) if the good is subject to a qualifying value
content requirement, the value of such packaging
materials and containers shall be taken into 
account as the value of originating materials of
a Party where the good is produced or non-
originating materials, as the case may be, in
calculating the qualifying value content of the
good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Operational Certification Procedures" article_identifier="13537">The operational certification procedures set out in
Annex 3 shall apply with respect to procedures regarding
certificate of origin and related matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="13538">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Rules of
Origin (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the
Sub-Committee”) shall be established on the date of entry
into force of this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,
as necessary, to the Joint Committee on: 


(i) the implementation and operation of this
Chapter; 


(ii) any amendments to Annex 2 proposed by either
Party; and 


(iii) the Implementing Procedures referred to in
Section 11 of Annex 3; 


(b) considering any other matter, including
development of an electronic system for
facilitating the issuance and verification of
certificate of origin, as the Parties may agree
related to this Chapter; 



(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 14.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="1645">
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="13539">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures
required for the clearance of goods traded between the
Parties. 



2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties in
accordance with the laws and regulations of each Party and
within the available resources of their respective customs
authorities. 



3. The objectives of this Chapter are to establish a
framework to ensure transparency, consistency, fair and
proper application of customs laws and prompt clearance of
goods and to promote cooperation on customs matters,
including the exchange of information, with a view to
facilitating legitimate trade in goods between the Parties,
preventing, investigating and repressing violation or
attempted violation of customs laws, and meeting the needs
of Governments of the Parties for the protection of society
and revenue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Definition" article_identifier="13540">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “customs
laws” means the statutory and regulatory provisions
relating to the importation, exportation, movement or
storage of goods, the administration and enforcement of
which are specifically entrusted to the customs authority
of each Party, and any regulations made by the customs
authority of each Party under its statutory power.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13541">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant information
of general application pertaining to its customs laws is
readily available to any interested person. 



2. When information that has been made available must be 
revised due to changes in its customs laws, each Party
shall make the revised information readily available
sufficiently in advance of the entry into force of the
changes to enable interested persons to take account of
them, unless advance notice is precluded. 



3. At the request of any interested person of the
Parties, each Party shall provide, as quickly and
accurately as possible, information relating to the
specific customs matters raised by the interested person
and pertaining to its customs laws. Each Party shall 
supply not only the information specifically requested but
also any other pertinent information which it considers the
interested person should be made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="13542">1. Both Parties shall apply their respective customs
procedures in a predictable, consistent, transparent and
fair manner. 



2. For prompt customs clearance of goods traded between
the Parties, each Party shall: 



(a) 	make use of information and communications 
technology; 



(b) simplify its customs procedures; 



(c) harmonise its customs procedures, to the extent
possible, with relevant international standards
and recommended practices such as those made
under the auspices of the Customs Co-operation
Council; and 



(d) promote cooperation, wherever appropriate,
between its customs authority and: 

(i) other national authorities of the Party; and 


(ii) the trading communities of the Party. 


3. Each Party shall provide affected parties with easily
accessible processes of administrative and judicial review
in relation to the action concerning the customs matters
taken by the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Temporary Admission And Goods In Transit" article_identifier="13543">1. Each Party shall continue to facilitate the procedures
for the temporary admission of goods traded between the
Parties in accordance with the terms and conditions 
provided for in the Customs Convention on the A.T.A. Carnet
for the Temporary Admission of Goods (hereinafter referred
to as “the A.T.A. Convention”). 



2. Each Party shall continue to facilitate customs
clearance of goods in transit from or to the other Party in
accordance with paragraph 3 of Article V of the GATT 1994. 



3. The Parties shall endeavour to promote, through
seminars and courses, the use of A.T.A. carnets pursuant to
the A.T.A. Convention for the temporary admission of goods
and the facilitation of customs clearance of goods in
transit in the Parties or non-Parties. 



4. For the purposes of this Article, the term “temporary
admission” means customs procedures under which certain
goods may be brought into a customs territory
conditionally, relieved totally or partially from the
payment of customs duties. Such goods shall be imported 
for a specific purpose, and shall be intended for re-
exportation within a specified period and without having
undergone any change except normal depreciation due to the
use made of them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Advance Rulings" article_identifier="13544">Where a written application is made in accordance with
relevant laws or procedures adopted or maintained by the
importing Party and the importing Party has no reasonable
grounds to deny the issuance, the importing Party shall
endeavour to, prior to the importation of the good, issue a
written advance ruling concerning the tariff
classification, the customs valuation and the origin of the
good, as well as the qualification of the good as an
originating good of the exporting Party under the
provisions of Chapter 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Cooperation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="13545">1. The Parties shall cooperate and exchange information
with each other on customs matters, including specific
cases, such as: 



(a) customs procedures; 



(b) customs valuation within the meaning of the
Agreement on Customs Valuation; 



(c) enforcement against the trafficking of prohibited
goods and the importation of goods suspected of
infringing intellectual property rights; 



(d) prevention, investigation and repression of
violation or attempted violation of customs laws;
and 



(e) trade statistics data relating to customs
clearance of goods and conveyances related to
goods, exported from a Party to the other Party. 


2. Such cooperation and exchange of information shall be
implemented as provided for in the Implementing Agreement. 



3. Paragraph 4 of Article 9 shall not apply to the
exchange of information under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Sub-Committee On Customs Procedures" article_identifier="13546">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Customs
Procedures (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the
Sub-Committee”) shall be established on the date of entry
into force of this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing the implementation and operation of
this Chapter; 



(b) identifying areas, relating to this Chapter, to
be improved for facilitating trade between the
Parties; 



(c) reporting its findings to the Joint Committee; 



(d) for the purposes set out in paragraph 1,
reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,
as necessary, to the Joint Committee on the
provisions of the Implementing Procedures
referred to in Section 11 of Annex 3 concerning
documents required by the customs authority under
paragraph 4 of Section 2 of Annex 3; and 



(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 14. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Parties. 



4. The composition of the Sub-Committee shall be
specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures, And Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="1646">
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Scope" article_identifier="13547">This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures as defined
in the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A
to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “the TBT
Agreement”) and sanitary and phytosanitary (hereinafter
referred to as “SPS”) measures under the Agreement on the
Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures in Annex
1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “the
SPS Agreement”), that may, directly or indirectly, affect
trade in goods between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="13548">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
relating to technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures under the TBT Agreement, and their
rights and obligations relating to SPS measures under the
SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="13549">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which is
able to answer all reasonable enquiries from the other
Party regarding technical regulations, standards and
conformity assessment procedures, and SPS measures and, if
appropriate, to provide their relevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures, And Sps Measures" article_identifier="13550">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Technical
Regulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment
Procedures, and SPS Measures (hereinafter referred to in
this Chapter as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established
on the date of entry into force of this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) exchanging information on technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures,
and SPS measures, and where necessary,
coordinating the exchange of information on
generic medicine provided for in Article 54; 



(b) undertaking consultations on issues related to
technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures; 



(c) undertaking science-based consultations to
identify and address specific issues that may
arise from the application of SPS measures; 



(d) consulting cooperative efforts between the
Parties in international fora in relation to 
technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures, and SPS measures; 



(e) holding discussions on the participation of each
Party in the existing frameworks for mutual
recognition in technical regulations, standards
and conformity assessment procedures under
international agreements; 



(f) discussing Mutual Recognition Arrangements
(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as
“MRAs”) pursuant to Article 55 and other
technical cooperation in relation to technical
regulations, standards and conformity assessment
procedures, and SPS measures; 



(g) reviewing the implementation and operation of
this Chapter; 



(h) reporting, where appropriate, its findings to the
Joint Committee; and 



(i) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 14. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed upon by the Parties, unless otherwise
provided for in this Chapter. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. 



5. The Parties shall determine in advance the agenda for
the individual meeting of the Sub-Committee, with a view to
ensuring appropriate participation of relevant experts.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Cooperation On Generic Medicine" article_identifier="13551">1. The Parties shall exchange information on their
respective regulatory measures concerning generic medicine,
with a view to promoting cooperation between the Parties in
the field of pharmaceuticals and building mutual confidence
in the regulatory measures of each Party. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, the term “generic
medicine” means drugs approved by the competent authority
of a Party under the laws and regulations of the Party as
equivalent, in terms of active ingredients, dosages, usages
and indications, to the drugs approved preceding the former
drugs. 



3. Applications by a person of a Party for registration
and other approvals required for release of a generic
medicine in the market of the other Party shall be
considered by the relevant authorities of the other Party.
Such applications shall be accorded, in the relevant
procedure, treatment no less favourable than that accorded
to like applications by its own person, where they fulfil
all the requirements under the laws and regulations of the
other Party. Such procedure shall be completed within a 
reasonable period of time from the date of such
application.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="13552">1. The Parties shall, through the Sub-Committee, discuss
the feasibility of MRAs in such sectors as electrical
products, telecommunications terminal equipment and radio
equipment and other sectors as may be mutually agreed by
the Parties. In elaborating MRAs, the Parties shall
confirm the economic benefits of such arrangements and,
where necessary, the equivalence of the technical
regulations of both Parties. 



2. The Sub-Committee shall meet within three months from 
the date of entry into force of this Agreement, in order to
discuss the feasibility of MRAs in sectors referred to in
paragraph 1, and shall endeavour to arrive at a conclusion
about such feasibility within six months. The Parties 
shall endeavour to reach a conclusion of MRAs under 
paragraph 1 within a reasonable period of time, normally
not exceeding three years, from the date of such conclusion
about the feasibility.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="13553">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in

otherwise agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="1647">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Scope" article_identifier="13554">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Party
affecting trade in services. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) in respect of air transport services, measures
affecting traffic rights, however granted; or to
measures affecting services directly related to
the exercise of traffic rights, other than
measures affecting: 


(i) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 


(ii) the selling and marketing of air transport
services; and 


(iii) computer reservation system services; 


(b) cabotage in maritime transport services; and 



(c) measures affecting natural persons seeking access
to the employment market of a Party, or measures
regarding nationality or citizenship, or
residence or employment on a permanent basis. 


3. Articles 59 and 60 shall not apply to any measure by a
Party with respect to government procurement. 



4. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applying
measures to regulate the entry of natural persons of the
other Party into, or their temporary stay in the former 
Party, including those measures necessary to protect the
integrity of, and to ensure the orderly movement of natural
persons across, its borders, provided that such measures
are not applied in such a manner as to nullify or impair
the benefits accruing to the other Party under the terms of
a specific commitment. 


Note: The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural 
persons of a certain nationality or citizenship
and not for those of others shall not be 
regarded as nullifying or impairing benefits
under a specific commitment. 


5. Annex 4 provides supplementary provisions to this
Chapter on financial services, including scope and
definitions. 



6. Annex 5 provides supplementary provisions to this

definitions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13555">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “aircraft repair and maintenance
services” means such activities when undertaken 
on an aircraft or a part thereof while it is
withdrawn from service and does not include so-
called line maintenance; 



(b) the term “commercial presence” means any type of
business or professional establishment, including
through: 

(i) the constitution, acquisition or maintenance
of a juridical person; or 


(ii) 	the creation or maintenance of a branch or a 
representative office, 


within the Area of a Party for the purposes of 


supplying a service; 



(c) the term “computer reservation system services”
means services provided by computerised systems
that contain information about air carriers’ 
schedules, availability, fares and fare rules,
through which reservations can be made or tickets
may be issued; 



(d) the term “measure” means any measure, whether in
the form of a law, regulation, rule, procedure,
decision, administrative action or any other
form; 


Note: The term “measure” shall include taxation 
measures to the extent covered by the GATS. 


(e) the term “measure by a Party” means any measure
taken by: 


(i) the central, regional or local governments
or authorities of a Party; and 


(ii) non-governmental bodies in the exercise of
powers delegated by the central, regional or
local governments or authorities of a Party; 


(f) the term “measures by a Party affecting trade in
services” includes measures by a Party in respect
of: 


(i) the purchase, payment or use of a service; 


(ii) the access to and use of, in connection with
the supply of a service, services which are
required by the Party to be offered to the
public generally; and 


(iii) the presence, including commercial presence,
of persons of the other Party for the supply
of a service in the Area of the former 
Party; 


(g) the term “monopoly supplier of a service” means
any person, public or private, which in the
relevant market of the Area of a Party is 
authorised or established formally or in effect
by that Party as the sole supplier of that
service; 



(h) the term “selling and marketing of air transport
services” means opportunities for the air carrier
concerned to sell and market freely its air
transport services including all aspects of
marketing such as market research, advertising
and distribution. These activities do not 
include the pricing of air transport services nor
the applicable conditions; 



(i) the term “service consumer” means any person that
receives or uses a service; 



(j) the term “service of the other Party” means a
service which is supplied: 


(i) 	from or in the Area of the other Party, or 
in the case of maritime transport service,
by a vessel registered under the law of the
other Party, or by a person of the other
Party which supplies such service through
the operation of a vessel or its use in
whole or in part; or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service
through commercial presence or through the
presence of natural persons, by a service
supplier of the other Party; 


(k) the term “service supplied in the exercise of
governmental authority” means any service which
is supplied neither on a commercial basis nor in
competition with one or more service suppliers; 



(l) the term “supply of a service” includes the
production, distribution, marketing, sale and
delivery of a service; 



(m) the term “trade in services” means the supply of
a service: 


(i) 	from the Area of a Party into the Area of 
the other Party (“cross-border supply”); 


(ii) in the Area of a Party to the service
consumer of the other Party (“consumption
abroad”); 


(iii) by a service supplier of a Party, through
commercial presence in the Area of the other
Party (“commercial presence”); and 


(iv) by a service supplier of a Party, through
presence of natural persons of that Party in
the Area of the other Party (“presence of
natural persons”); and 


(n) the term “traffic rights” means the rights for
scheduled and non-scheduled services to operate
and/or to carry passengers, cargo and mail for
remuneration or hire from, to, within, or over a
Party, including points to be served, routes to
be operated, types of traffic to be carried,
capacity to be provided, tariffs to be charged
and their conditions, and criteria for
designation of airlines, including such criteria
as number, ownership and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Market Access" article_identifier="13556">1. With respect to market access through the modes of
supply defined in subparagraph (m) of Article 58, each
Party shall accord services and service suppliers of the
other Party treatment no less favourable than that provided
for under the terms, limitations and conditions agreed and
specified in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex


6. 


Note: If a Party undertakes a market-access commitment 
in relation to the supply of a service through
the mode of supply referred to in subparagraph
(m)(i) of Article 58 and if the cross-border
movement of capital is an essential part of the
service itself, that Party is thereby committed
to allow such movement of capital. If a Party 
undertakes a market-access commitment in 
relation to the supply of a service through the
mode of supply referred to in subparagraph
(m)(iii) of Article 58, it is thereby committed
to allow related transfers of capital into its
Area. 


2. In sectors where market-access commitments are 
undertaken, the measures which a Party shall not maintain
or adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision or
on the basis of its entire Area, unless otherwise specified
in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6, are
defined as: 



(a) limitations on the number of service suppliers
whether in the form of numerical quotas,
monopolies, exclusive service suppliers or the
requirements of an economic needs test; 



(b) 	limitations on the total value of service 
transactions or assets in the form of numerical 
quotas or the requirement of an economic needs
test; 



(c) 	limitations on the total number of service 
operations or on the total quantity of service
output expressed in terms of designated numerical
units in the form of quotas or the requirement of
an economic needs test; 


Note: This subparagraph does not cover measures 
of a Party which limit inputs for the
supply of services. 


(d) 	limitations on the total number of natural 
persons that may be employed in a particular
service sector or that a service supplier may
employ and who are necessary for, and directly
related to, the supply of a specific service in
the form of numerical quotas or the requirement
of an economic needs test; 



(e) measures which restrict or require specific types
of legal entity or joint venture through which a
service supplier may supply a service; and 



(f) limitations on the participation of foreign
capital in terms of maximum percentage limit on
foreign shareholding or the total value of
individual or aggregate foreign investment. 

3. Each Party shall endeavour to reduce the requirements
for a service supplier of the other Party to establish or
maintain a representative office or any form of enterprise
or to be resident in its Area, as a condition for the
cross-border supply of a service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13557">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of Specific
Commitments in Annex 6, and subject to any conditions and
qualifications set out therein, each Party shall accord to
services and service suppliers of the other Party, in
respect of all measures affecting the supply of services,
treatment no less favourable than that it accords to its 
own like services and service suppliers. 


Note: Specific commitments assumed under this Article 
shall not be construed to require either Party
to compensate for any inherent competitive
disadvantages which result from the foreign
character of the relevant services or service 
suppliers. 


2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 by
according to services and service suppliers of the other
Party, either formally identical treatment or formally
different treatment to that it accords to its own like 
services and service suppliers. 



3. Formally identical or formally different treatment
shall be considered to be less favourable if it modifies 
the conditions of competition in favour of services or
service suppliers of a Party compared to like services or
service suppliers of the other Party. 



4. A Party shall not invoke the preceding paragraphs
under Chapter 14 with respect to a measure of the other
Party that falls within the scope of an international
agreement between them relating to the avoidance of double
taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Additional Commitments" article_identifier="13558">The Parties may negotiate commitments with respect to
measures affecting trade in services not subject to
scheduling under Articles 59 and 60, including those
regarding qualifications, standards or licensing matters.
Such commitments shall be inscribed in a Party’s Schedule
of Specific Commitments in Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Schedule Of Specific Commitments" article_identifier="13559">1. With respect to sectors or sub-sectors where specific
commitments are undertaken by each Party, its Schedule of
Specific Commitments in Annex 6 shall specify: 



(a) 	terms, limitations and conditions on market 
access; 



(b) conditions and qualifications on national
treatment; 



(c) undertakings relating to additional commitments;
and 



(d) where appropriate, the time-frame for
implementation of such commitments. 

2. Measures inconsistent with both Articles 59 and 60 
shall be inscribed in the column relating to Article 59.
This inscription will be considered to provide a condition
or qualification to Article 60 as well.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="13560">If, after this Agreement enters into force, a Party
enters into any agreement on trade in services with a non-
Party, it shall consider a request by the other Party for
the incorporation in this Agreement of treatment no less
favourable than that provided under the former agreement.
Any such incorporation should maintain the overall balance
of commitments undertaken by each Party under this
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="13561">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of Specific
Commitments in Annex 6, each Party shall ensure that all
measures of general application affecting trade in services
are administered in a reasonable, objective and impartial
manner. 



2. Each Party shall maintain or institute as soon as
practicable judicial, arbitral or administrative tribunals
or procedures which provide, at the request of an affected
service supplier of the other Party, for the prompt review
of, and where justified, appropriate remedies for,
administrative decisions affecting trade in services.
Where such procedures are not independent of the agency
entrusted with the administrative decision concerned, the
Party shall ensure that the procedures in fact provide for
an objective and impartial review. 



3. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall not be construed
to require a Party to institute such tribunals or
procedures where this would be inconsistent with its
constitutional structure or the nature of its legal system. 



4. Where authorisation is required for the supply of a
service on which a specific commitment has been made, the
competent authorities of a Party shall, within a reasonable
period of time after the submission of an application
considered complete under domestic laws and regulations,
inform the applicant of the decision concerning the
application. At the request of the applicant, the 
competent authorities of the Party shall provide, without
undue delay, information concerning the status of the
application. 



5. The Parties shall jointly discuss disciplines on
domestic regulation including measures relating to
qualification requirements and procedures, technical
standards and licensing requirements developed pursuant to
paragraph 4 of Article VI of the GATS, with a view to
incorporating such disciplines into this Chapter and
thereby ensuring that such domestic regulation does not
constitute unnecessary barriers to trade in services. The 
Parties note that such disciplines aim to ensure that such
requirements are inter alia: 



(a) based on objective and transparent criteria, such
as competence and the ability to supply the
service; 



(b) not more burdensome than necessary to ensure the
quality of the service; and 



(c) in the case of licensing procedures, not in
themselves a restriction on the supply of the
service. 


6. Pending the incorporation of disciplines developed
under the GATS as referred to in paragraph 5, in the
sectors inscribed in its Schedule of Specific Commitments
in Annex 6 and subject to any terms, limitations,
conditions or qualifications set out therein, each Party
shall not apply licensing and qualification requirements
and technical standards that nullify or impair its specific
commitments in a manner which: 



(a) does not comply with the criteria outlined in
subparagraph (a), (b) or (c) of paragraph 5; and 



(b) could not reasonably have been expected of that
Party at the time the specific commitments in
those sectors were made. 


7. In determining whether a Party is in conformity with
the obligation under paragraph 6, account shall be taken of
international standards of relevant international 
organisations applied by that Party. 


Note: The term “relevant international organisations” 
refers to international bodies whose membership
is open to the relevant bodies of the Parties. 


8. In sectors where specific commitments regarding
professional services are undertaken, each Party shall
provide for adequate procedures to verify the competence of
professionals of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Recognition" article_identifier="13562">1. For the purposes of the fulfilment, in whole or in
part, of its standards or criteria for the authorisation,
licensing or certification of service suppliers, a Party
may recognise the education or experience obtained,
requirements met, or licences or certifications granted in
the other Party. 



2. The Parties shall enter into negotiations regarding
the possibility of recognition of the education or
experience obtained, requirements met, or licences or
certifications granted on specific services sectors with a
view to reaching a conclusion within three years after the
entry into force of this Agreement. 



3. Upon request being made in writing by a Party to the
other Party, the Parties shall encourage that their
respective professional bodies in any regulated service
sector negotiate and conclude, within 12 months, any
arrangement for mutual recognition of education or
experience obtained, requirements met, or licences or
certifications granted in that service sector, with a view
to the achievement of early outcomes. Any delay or failure 
by these professional bodies to reach and conclude
agreement on the details of such arrangements shall not be
regarded as a breach of a Party’s obligations under this
paragraph and shall not be subject to Chapter 14. Progress 
in this regard shall be periodically reviewed by the
Parties in the Joint Committee established under Article 

14. 


4. Where a Party recognises, by agreement or arrangement,
the education or experience obtained, requirements met or
licences or certifications granted in any non-Party, the
Party shall afford the other Party, upon request, adequate
opportunity to negotiate its accession to such an agreement
or arrangement or to negotiate comparable ones with it.
Where a Party accords recognition autonomously, it shall
afford the other Party adequate opportunity to demonstrate
that the education or experience obtained, requirements met
or licences or certifications granted in the other Party
should also be recognised.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13563">1. The competent authorities referred to in paragraph 2
of Article 4 shall, upon request by the other Party or
service suppliers of the other Party, promptly respond to
specific questions from, and provide information to, the
other Party or the service suppliers with respect to
matters referred to in Article 4, including requirements
and procedures for licensing and qualification, through
enquiry points. The enquiry points shall be notified to 
the other Party by diplomatic note on the date of entry
into force of this Agreement. 



2. Each Party shall endeavour to prepare, forward to the
other Party and make public a list providing all existing
measures, within the scope of this Chapter, at the central
governmental level, and prefectural governmental level in
the case of Japan and governmental level of states and
Union territories in the case of India, which are
inconsistent with Articles 59 and/or 60, whether or not
these measures are included in its Schedule of Specific
Commitments in Annex 6. The list shall include the 
following elements and shall be reviewed annually and
revised as necessary: 



(a) sector and sub-sector or matter; 



(b) type of inconsistency (i.e. Market Access and/or
National Treatment); 



(c) legal source or authority of the measure; and 



(d) succinct description of the measure. 

Note: The list under this paragraph will be made 
solely for the purposes of transparency, and
shall not be construed to affect any rights and
obligations of a Party under this Chapter. The 
Parties understand that the list as required in
this paragraph shall be prepared if possible
within five years after the entry into force of
this Agreement. 


3. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in

paragraphs 1 and 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="13564">1. Each Party shall ensure that any monopoly supplier of
a service in its Area does not, in the supply of the 
monopoly service in the relevant market, act in a manner
inconsistent with the Party’s commitments under this
Chapter. 



2. Where a Party’s monopoly supplier of a service
competes, either directly or through an affiliated company,
in the supply of a service outside the scope of its
monopoly rights and which is subject to that Party’s
specific commitments, the Party shall ensure that such a
supplier does not abuse its monopoly position to act in the
Area of the Party in a manner inconsistent with such
commitments. 



3. If a Party has a reason to believe that a monopoly
supplier of a service of the other Party is acting in a
manner inconsistent with paragraph 1 or 2, the Party may
request the other Party establishing, maintaining or
authorising such supplier to provide specific information
concerning the relevant operations. 



4. The provisions of this Article shall also apply to
cases of exclusive service suppliers, where a Party,
formally or in effect: 



(a) 	authorises or establishes a small number of 
service suppliers; and 



(b) substantially prevents competition among those
suppliers in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="13565">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article
69, a Party shall not apply restrictions on international
transfers and payments for current transactions relating to
its specific commitments. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and
obligations of the Parties as members of the International
Monetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of the
International Monetary Fund, including the use of exchange
actions which are in conformity with the Articles of
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, provided that
a Party shall not impose restrictions on any capital
transactions inconsistently with its specific commitments
under this Chapter regarding such transactions, except
under Article 69, or at the request of the International
Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="13566">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and
external financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party
may adopt or maintain restrictions on trade in services on
which it has undertaken specific commitments, including on
payments or transfers for transactions relating to such
commitments. It is recognised that particular pressure on
the balance of payments of a Party in the process of
economic development may necessitate the use of
restrictions to ensure, inter alia, the maintenance of a
level of financial reserves adequate for the implementation
of its programme of economic development. 



2. 	The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) shall be applied by a Party on a national
treatment basis and such that the other Party is
treated no less favourably than any non-Party; 



(b) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other 
Party; 



(d) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances described in paragraph 1; and 



(e) shall be temporary and be phased out
progressively as the situation specified in
paragraph 1 improves. 


3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a
Party may give priority to the supply of services which are
more essential to its economic or development programmes.
However, such restrictions shall not be adopted or
maintained for the purposes of protecting a particular
service sector. 



4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph
1, or any changes therein, shall be promptly notified to
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Subsidies" article_identifier="13567">1. Each Party shall review the treatment of subsidies
related to trade in services taking into account the
development of the multilateral disciplines pursuant to
paragraph 1 of Article XV of the GATS. 



2. In the event that either Party considers that its
interests have been adversely affected by a subsidy of the
other Party, the Parties shall, upon request by the former
Party, enter into consultations with a view to resolving
the matter. 



3. During the consultations referred to in paragraph 2,
the Party granting a subsidy shall, if it deems fit,
consider a request of the other Party for information
relating to the subsidy programme such as: 



(a) domestic laws and regulations under which the
subsidy is granted; 



(b) form of the subsidy (e.g. grant, loan, tax
concession); 



(c) policy objective and/or purpose of the subsidy; 



(d) dates and duration of the subsidy and any other
time limits attached to it; and 



(e) eligibility requirements of the subsidy including
those with respect to potential beneficiaries. 


4. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Review Of Commitments" article_identifier="13568">1. The Parties shall review commitments on trade in 
services with the first review within three years from the
date of entry into force of this Agreement, with the aim of
improving the overall commitments undertaken by the Parties
under this Agreement. 



2. In reviewing the commitments in accordance with
paragraph 1, the Parties shall take into account paragraph
1 of Article IV of the GATS.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Services" article_identifier="13569">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Trade in
Services (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the
Sub-Committee”) shall be established on the date of entry
into force of this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing the implementation and operation of
this Chapter; 



(b) exchanging information on domestic laws and
regulations; 



(c) discussing any issue related to this Chapter as
may be agreed upon; 



(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(e) carrying out other functions which may be
delegated by the Joint Committee pursuant to
Article 14.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="1648">
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="General Principles" article_identifier="13570">1. This Chapter reflects the preferential trading
relationship between the Parties, the mutual desire of the
Parties to facilitate entry and temporary stay of natural
persons on a comparable basis and to establish transparent
criteria and procedures for entry and temporary stay, and
the need to ensure border security in each Party. 



2. Each Party shall apply its measures relating to the
provisions of this Chapter in accordance with paragraph 1,
and, in particular, shall apply expeditiously those
measures so as to avoid unduly impairing or delaying trade
in goods or services or investment activities under this
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Scope" article_identifier="13571">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting the
movement of natural persons of a Party who enter the other
Party and fall under one of the categories referred to in
Annex 7. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting
natural persons of a Party seeking access to the employment
market of the other Party, nor shall it apply to measures
regarding nationality or citizenship, or residence or
employment on a permanent basis. 



3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applying
measures to regulate the entry of natural persons of the
other Party into, or their temporary stay in, the former
Party, including those measures necessary to protect the
territorial integrity and to ensure the orderly movement of
natural persons across its borders, provided that such
measures are not applied in such a manner so as to nullify
or impair the benefits accruing to the other Party under 
the terms of specific commitments. 

Note: The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural 
persons of the other Party and not for those of
non-Parties shall not be regarded as nullifying
or impairing benefits under specific commitments
set out in Annex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Definition" article_identifier="13572">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “natural


persons of a Party” means natural persons who under the law


of the Party: 



(a) in respect of India, are citizens of India; and 



(b) in respect of Japan, are nationals of Japan.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Specific Commitments" article_identifier="13573">1. Each Party shall grant entry and temporary stay to
natural persons of the other Party in accordance with this
Chapter including the terms and conditions for each
category set out in Annex 7, provided that the natural 
persons comply with the immigration laws and regulations 
applicable to entry and temporary stay which are not
inconsistent with the provisions of this Chapter. 



2. Neither Party shall impose or maintain any limitations
on the total number of visas to be granted in the Parties
to natural persons of the other Party under paragraph 1,
unless otherwise specified in Annex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Regulatory Transparency" article_identifier="13574">1. Each Party shall maintain or establish appropriate
mechanisms to respond to inquiries from interested persons
of the other Party regarding regulations affecting entry
and temporary stay of natural persons of the other Party.
Such inquiries may include those on special difficulties
which natural persons of the other Party encounter in the
process of seeking entry into and temporary stay in the
former Party. 



2. To the extent possible, each Party shall allow
reasonable time between the date of the publication through
electronic or other means of regulations affecting the
entry and temporary stay of natural persons of the other
Party and their effective date. 



3. On the date of entry into force of this Agreement,
each Party shall exchange information on procedures
relating to the processing of applications for entry and
temporary stay which exist at that date. Each Party shall 
also, without undue delay, provide the other Party updates
of information on procedures relating to the processing of
applications for entry and temporary stay. 



4. Each Party shall notify natural persons of the other
Party, regarding the application for entry and temporary
stay, either directly or through their prospective
employers, of its final determination, including the period
of temporary stay and conditions thereof. 



5. Each Party shall endeavour, to the maximum extent
possible, to take measures to simplify the requirements and
to facilitate and expedite the procedures relating to the
movement of natural persons of the other Party within the
framework of its laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="General Principles For Grant Of Entry And Temporary Stay And Related Issues" article_identifier="13575">1. Each Party shall process without delay applications
for entry and temporary stay from natural persons of the
other Party, including requests for further extensions of
the temporary stay. 



2. The Parties shall hold consultations on the 
feasibility of concluding a social security agreement.
After such consultations, the Parties shall enter into
negotiations in order to complete the consultations and
negotiations within 36 months after the commencement of the
consultations or the date of entry into force of this
Agreement, whichever comes earlier.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Accompanying Spouse And Dependent" article_identifier="13576">Each Party shall ensure that spouse or dependent who
accompanies a natural person of the other Party granted
entry and temporary stay pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article
76 shall be allowed to work through change of the status of
residence, provided that such spouse or dependent fulfils
requirements under its laws and regulations. The Parties 
agree that spouse or dependent shall not be barred from
working solely on the ground that he or she has accompanied
a natural person of the other Party. 


Note: For the purposes of this Article, the term “spouse” 
or “dependent” means spouse or dependent recognised
as such in accordance with the laws and regulations
of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="13577">1. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter unless: 



(a) the matter involves a pattern of practice; and 



(b) the natural persons of a Party affected by that
matter have exhausted the available domestic 
administrative remedies of the other Party. 

2. The remedies referred to in subparagraph 1(b) shall be
deemed to be exhausted if a final determination in the 
matter has not been issued by the competent authority of
the other Party within one year after the date of the
institution of the administrative remedy, and the failure
to issue such a determination is not attributable to the 
delay caused by the natural person.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Reservations" article_identifier="13578">The commitments made by each Party under this Chapter
shall be subject to any terms, limitations, conditions and
qualifications which the Party specified in its Schedule of
Specific Commitments in Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="13579">The Parties shall, after the date of entry into force
of this Agreement, enter into negotiations in accordance
with Annex 7.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="1649">
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Scope" article_identifier="13580">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or
maintained by a Party relating to investors of the other
Party and to their investments in the Area of the former
Party. 


Note: For greater certainty, this Chapter shall also 
apply to measures adopted or maintained by a
Party relating to investments made by investors
of the other Party in the Area of the former
Party prior to the entry into force of this
Agreement. 


2. An investor of a Party whose investments are not made
in compliance with the laws and regulations of the other
Party which are consistent with this Agreement shall not be
entitled to submit an investment dispute to conciliations
or arbitrations referred to in paragraph 4 of Article 96. 



3. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter
and Chapter 6: 



(a) with respect to matters covered by Articles 85,
86 and 89, Chapter 6 shall prevail to the extent
of the inconsistency; and 



(b) with respect to matters not falling under
subparagraph (a), this Chapter shall prevail to
the extent of the inconsistency. 


4. Nothing in this Chapter shall impose any obligation on
either Party regarding measures pursuant to immigration
laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13581">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “financial services” shall have the same 
meaning as in subparagraph 5(a) of the Annex on
Financial Services of the GATS; 



(b) the term “freely usable currencies” means freely
usable currencies as defined under the Articles 
of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) the term “measure adopted or maintained by a
Party” means any measure adopted or maintained
by: 


(i) central, regional or local governments or
authorities of a Party; and 


(ii) non-governmental bodies in the exercise of
powers delegated by central, regional or
local governments or authorities of a Party; 


(d) the term “natural person of a Party” means a
natural person who under the law of the Party: 


(i) in respect of India, is a citizen of India;
and 


(ii) in respect of Japan, is a national of Japan; 


(e) 	the term “New York Convention” means the United 
Nations Convention on the Recognition and
Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards, done at
New York, June 10, 1958; and 



(f) 	the term “transfers” means transfers and 
international payments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13582">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other
Party and to their investments treatment no less favourable
than that it accords in like circumstances to its own 
investors and to their investments with respect to
investment activities in its Area. 



2. The treatment accorded by a Party under paragraph 1
means, with respect to a regional or local government or
authority, treatment no less favourable than the most
favourable treatment accorded, in like circumstances, by
that regional or local government or authority to
investors, and to investments of investors, of the Party of
which it forms a part.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="13583">Each Party shall accord to investors of the other
Party and to their investments treatment no less favourable
than that it accords, in like circumstances, to investors
of any non-Party and to their investments with respect to
the management, conduct, operation, maintenance, use,
enjoyment and sale or other disposition of investments in
its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="13584">1. Each Party shall accord to investments of investors of
the other Party treatment in accordance with international
law, including fair and equitable treatment and full
protection and security. 


Note: This paragraph prescribes the customary 
international law minimum standard of treatment 
of aliens as the minimum standard of treatment 
to be afforded to investments of investors of 
the other Party. The concepts of “fair and 
equitable treatment” and “full protection and
security” do not require treatment in addition
to or beyond that which is required by the
customary international law minimum standard of
treatment of aliens. A determination that there 
has been a breach of another provision of this
Agreement, or of a separate international
agreement, does not establish that there has
been a breach of this paragraph. 


2. Each Party shall observe any obligation it may have
entered into with regard to investment activities in its
Area of investors of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Access To The Courts Of Justice" article_identifier="13585">Each Party shall in its Area accord to investors of
the other Party treatment no less favourable than that it
accords in like circumstances to its own investors or 
investors of a non-Party, with respect to access to its
courts of justice and administrative tribunals and agencies
in all degrees of jurisdiction, both in pursuit and in
defence of such investors’ rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Prohibition Of Performance Requirements" article_identifier="13586">1. Neither Party shall impose or enforce any of the
following requirements, in connection with investment
activities in its Area of an investor of the other Party: 



(a) to export a given level or percentage of goods or
services; 



(b) to achieve a given level or percentage of
domestic content; 



(c) to purchase, use or accord a preference to goods
produced or services provided in its Area, or to
purchase goods or services from natural or legal
persons or any other entity in its Area; 



(d) to relate in any way the volume or value of
imports to the volume or value of exports or to
the amount of foreign exchange inflows associated
with investments of the investor; 



(e) to restrict sales of goods or services in its
Area that investments of the investor produce or
provide by relating such sales in any way to the
volume or value of its exports or foreign
exchange earnings; 



(f) to restrict the exportation or sale for export; 



(g) to appoint, as executives, managers or members of
board of directors, individuals of any particular
nationality; 



(h) to transfer technology, a production process or
other proprietary knowledge to natural or legal
persons or any other entity in its Area, except
when the requirement: 


(i) is imposed or enforced by a court of
justice, administrative tribunal or
competition authority to remedy an alleged
violation of competition laws and
regulations; or 


(ii) 	concerns the transfer of intellectual 
property which is undertaken in a manner not
inconsistent with the Agreement on Trade-
Related Aspects of Intellectual Property
Rights in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to as “the TRIPS
Agreement”); or 


(i) to supply to a specific region or the world
market exclusively from its Area, one or more of
the goods that the investor produces or the
services that the investor provides. 

2. Paragraph 1 does not preclude either Party from
conditioning the receipt or continued receipt of an
advantage, in connection with investment activities in its
Area of an investor of the other Party, on compliance with
any of the requirements set forth in subparagraphs 1 (h)
and (i).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Reservations And Exceptions" article_identifier="13587">1. Articles 85, 86 and 89 shall not apply to: 



(a) any existing non-conforming measure that is
maintained by the following, as set out in
Schedules in Annex 8: 


(i) the central government of a Party; or 


(ii) a prefecture of Japan or a state or an Union
territory of India; 


(b) any existing non-conforming measure that is
maintained by a local government other than a
prefecture and a state or an Union territory
referred to in subparagraph (a)(ii); 



(c) the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs


(a) and (b); or 


(d) an amendment or modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs

(a) and (b), provided that the amendment or
modification does not decrease the conformity of
the measure, as it existed immediately before the
amendment or modification, with Articles 85, 86
and 89. 


2. Articles 85, 86 and 89 shall not apply to any measure
that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to sectors,
sub-sectors and activities set out in its Schedule in Annex 


9. 



3. Neither Party shall, under any measure adopted after
the date of entry into force of this Agreement and covered
by its Schedule in Annex 9, require an investor of the
other Party, by reason of its nationality, to sell or
otherwise dispose of an investment that exists at the time
the measure becomes effective. 



4. In cases where a Party makes an amendment or a
modification to any existing non-conforming measure set out
in its Schedule in Annex 8 or where a Party adopts any new
or more restrictive measure with respect to sectors, sub-
sectors or activities set out in its Schedule in Annex 9 
after the entry into force of this Agreement, the Party
shall, prior to the implementation of the amendment or
modification or the new or more restrictive measure, or in
exceptional circumstances, as soon as possible thereafter: 



(a) notify the other Party of detailed information on
such amendment, modification or measure; and 



(b) hold, upon request by the other Party,
consultations in good faith with that other Party
with a view to achieving mutual satisfaction. 


5. Each Party shall endeavour, where appropriate, to
reduce or eliminate the exceptions specified in its
Schedules in Annexes 8 and 9 respectively. 



6. Articles 85 and 86 shall not apply to any measure
covered by the exceptions to, or derogations from,
obligations under Articles 3 and 4 of the TRIPS Agreement,
as specifically provided in Articles 3 through 5 of the
TRIPS Agreement. 



7. Articles 85, 86 and 89 shall not apply to any measure
that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to government
procurement. 

Note: For greater certainty, the term “existing” in this 
Article means being in effect on the date of entry
into force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Special Formalities And Information Requirements" article_identifier="13588">1. Nothing in Article 85 shall be construed to prevent a
Party from prescribing special formalities in connection
with investment activities of investors of the other Party
and their investments in the Area of the former Party,
provided that such special formalities do not materially
impair the protections afforded by the former Party to
investors of the other Party and their investments pursuant
to this Chapter. 



2. Notwithstanding Articles 85 and 86, a Party may
require an investor of the other Party or its investments
in the Area of the former Party, to provide business
information concerning those investments, to be used solely
for informational or statistical purposes. The former 
Party shall protect such business information that is
confidential from disclosure that would prejudice the
competitive position of the investor or the investments.
Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to prevent a
Party from otherwise obtaining or disclosing information in
connection with the equitable and good faith application of
its laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="13589">1. Neither Party shall take any measure of expropriation
or nationalisation against investments in its Area of
investors of the other Party or take any measure tantamount
to expropriation or nationalisation (hereinafter referred
to in this Chapter as “expropriation”) except: 



(a) for a public purpose; 



(b) on a non-discriminatory basis; 



(c) in accordance with due process of law; and 



(d) upon payment of prompt, adequate and effective
compensation pursuant to paragraphs 2 through 4. 


2. The compensation shall be equivalent to the fair
market value of the expropriated investments at the time
when the expropriation was publicly announced or when the
expropriation occurred, whichever is the earlier. The fair 
market value shall not reflect any change in market value
occurring because the expropriation had become publicly
known earlier. 



3. The compensation shall be paid without delay and shall
include interest at an appropriate commercial rate, taking
into account the length of time from the time of
expropriation to the time of payment. Such compensation 
shall be effectively realisable and freely transferable and
shall be freely convertible, at the market exchange rate
prevailing on the date of expropriation, into the currency
of the Party of the investors concerned and freely usable
currencies. 



4. Without prejudice to Article 96, the investors
affected by expropriation shall have a right of access to
the courts of justice or the administrative tribunals or
agencies of the Party making the expropriation to seek
prompt review of the investors’ case and the amount of
compensation in accordance with the principles set out in
this Article. 



5. This Article shall not apply with respect to the grant
of compulsory licences concerning intellectual property in
accordance with the TRIPS Agreement. 



6. This Article shall be interpreted in accordance with
Annex 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="13590">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other
Party that have suffered loss or damage relating to their
investments in the Area of the former Party due to armed
conflict or state of emergency such as revolution,
insurrection, civil disturbance or any other similar event
in the Area of that former Party, treatment, as regards
restitution, indemnification, compensation or any other
settlement, that is no less favourable than that it accords
to its own investors or to investors of a non-Party. 



2. Any payments as a means of settlement referred to in
paragraph 1 shall be effectively realisable, freely
transferable and freely convertible at the market exchange
rate into the currency of the Party of the investors
concerned and freely usable currencies. 



3. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 11, neither
Party shall be relieved of its obligation under paragraph 1
by reason of its measures taken pursuant to that Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Transfers" article_identifier="13591">1. Each Party shall ensure that all transfers relating to
investments in its Area of an investor of the other Party
may be made freely into and out of its Area without delay.
Such transfers shall include, though not limited to, those
of: 



(a) the initial capital and additional amounts to
maintain or increase investments; 



(b) profits, capital gains, dividends, royalties,
interests, fees and other current incomes
accruing from investments; 



(c) proceeds from the total or partial sale or
liquidation of investments; 



(d) payments made under a contract including payments
made pursuant to loan agreements; 



(e) earnings and remuneration of personnel from the
other Party who work in connection with
investments in the Area of the former Party; 



(f) payments made in accordance with Articles 92 and
93; and 



(g) payments arising out of the settlement of a
dispute under Article 96. 


2. Each Party shall further ensure that such transfers
may be made in freely usable currencies at the market
exchange rate prevailing on the date of each transfer. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, a Party may delay
or prevent such transfers through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good faith application of its laws
relating to: 



(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of the
rights of creditors; 



(b) issuing, trading or dealing in securities or
derivatives including futures and options; 



(c) criminal or penal offenses; 



(d) ensuring compliance with orders or judgments in
judicial proceedings or administrative rulings;
or 



(e) obligations of investors arising from social
security, and public retirement or compulsory
savings scheme. 

Note: With respect to India, obligations of 
investors referred to in this subparagraph
include, inter alia, those arising from
provident funds, and retirement
gratuity/allowance and employees’ state
insurance programmes under the laws and
regulations of India.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="13592">1. If a Party or its designated agency makes a payment to
any of its investors pursuant to an indemnity, guarantee or
insurance contract pertaining to an investment of that
investor within the Area of the other Party, that other
Party shall: 



(a) recognise the assignment, to the former Party or
its designated agency, of any right or claim of
the investor that formed the basis of such 
payment; and 



(b) recognise the right of the former Party or its
designated agency to exercise by virtue of
subrogation such right or claim to the same
extent as the original right or claim of the
investor. 


2. Articles 92, 93 and 94, shall apply mutatis mutandis 
as regards payment to be made to the Party or its
designated agency mentioned in paragraph 1 by virtue of
such assignment of right or claim, and the transfer of such
payment. 



3. An investor shall not be entitled to seek any relief
in an investment dispute under Article 96, to the extent of
indemnification or other compensation received by that
investor under paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Settlement Of Investment Disputes Between A Party And An Investor Of The Other Party" article_identifier="13593">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, an “investment
dispute” is a dispute between a Party and an investor of
the other Party that has incurred loss or damage by reason
of, or arising out of, an alleged breach of any obligation
under this Chapter and other provisions of this Agreement
as applicable with respect to the investor and its
investments. 



2. Nothing in this Article shall be construed so as to
prevent an investor who is a party to an investment dispute
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “disputing
investor”) from seeking settlement by domestic
administrative or judicial fora of the Party that is the
other party to the investment dispute (hereinafter referred
to in this Article as “disputing Party”). However, in the 
event that the disputing investor has submitted the
investment dispute for resolution under one of the
international conciliations or arbitrations referred to in 
paragraph 4, no proceedings may be initiated by the
disputing investor for the resolution of the investment
dispute before courts of justice or administrative
tribunals or agencies. 



3. An investment dispute shall, as far as possible, be
settled amicably through consultations or negotiations
between the disputing investor and the disputing Party
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the disputing
parties”). 



4. If the investment dispute cannot be settled through
such consultation or negotiation within six months from the
date on which the disputing investor requested for the
consultation or negotiation in writing, the disputing
investor may submit the investment dispute to one of the
following international conciliations or arbitrations: 



(a) 	conciliation or arbitration in accordance with 
the Convention on the Settlement of Investment 
Dispute between States and Nationals of Other
States (hereinafter referred to as “the ICSID
Convention”), so long as the ICSID Convention is
in force between the Parties; 



(b) 	conciliation or arbitration under the Additional 
Facility Rules of the International Centre for
Settlement of Investment Disputes, so long as the
ICSID Convention is not in force between the 
Parties; 



(c) 	conciliation under the Conciliation Rules of the 
United Nations Commission on International Trade 
Law or arbitration under the Arbitration Rules of 
the United Nations Commission on International 
Trade Law; or 



(d) any arbitration in accordance with other
arbitration rules if agreed with the disputing
Party. 


5. The applicable conciliation or arbitration rules shall
govern the conciliation or arbitration set forth in
paragraph 4 except to the extent modified in this Article. 



6. No investment dispute may be submitted to
international conciliation or arbitration referred to in 
paragraph 4 if the disputing investor has initiated any
proceedings for the resolution of the investment dispute
before courts of justice or administrative tribunals or
agencies. However, in the event that those proceedings are 
withdrawn within 30 days from the date of filing the case,
the disputing investor may submit the investment dispute to
such international conciliations or arbitrations. 



7. The disputing investor who intends to submit the
investment dispute to conciliation or arbitration pursuant
to paragraph 4 shall give to the disputing Party written
notice of intent to do so at least 90 days before the
investment dispute is submitted. The notice of intent 
shall specify: 



(a) the name and address of the disputing investor; 



(b) the specific measures of the disputing Party at
issue and a brief summary of the factual and
legal basis of the investment dispute sufficient
to present the problem clearly, including the
obligations under this Agreement alleged to have
been breached; 



(c) 	conciliation or arbitration set forth in 
paragraph 4 which the disputing investor chooses
to invoke; and 



(d) the relief sought and the approximate amount of
damages claimed. 


8. 	(a) Each Party hereby consents to the submission of 
investment disputes by a disputing investor to
conciliation or arbitration set forth in 
paragraph 4 chosen by the disputing investor. 


(b) The consent given under subparagraph (a) and the
submission by a disputing investor of an
investment dispute to conciliation or arbitration
shall satisfy the requirements of: 


(i) Chapter II of the ICSID Convention or the
Additional Facility Rules of the
International Centre for Settlement of 
Investment Disputes, for written consent of
the parties to a dispute; and 


(ii) 	Article II of the New York Convention for an 
agreement in writing. 


9. Notwithstanding paragraph 8, no investment dispute may
be submitted to conciliation or arbitration set forth in 
paragraph 4, if more than three years have elapsed since
the date on which the disputing investor acquired or should
have first acquired, whichever is the earlier, the
knowledge that the disputing investor had incurred loss or
damage referred to in paragraph 1. 



10. Notwithstanding paragraph 6, the disputing investor
may initiate or continue an action that seeks interim
injunctive relief not involving the payment of damages or
resolution in substance of the dispute before an
administrative tribunal or agency or a court of justice
under the law of the disputing Party. 



11. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, an
arbitral tribunal established under paragraph 4 shall
comprise three arbitrators, one arbitrator appointed by
each of the disputing parties and the third, who shall be
the presiding arbitrator, appointed by agreement of the
disputing parties. If the disputing investor or the 
disputing Party fails to appoint an arbitrator or
arbitrators within 60 days from the date on which the
investment dispute was submitted to arbitration, the
Secretary-General of the International Centre for
Settlement of Investment Disputes in the case of
arbitration referred to in subparagraph 4 (a) or (b), or
the Secretary-General of the Permanent Court of
Arbitration, at The Hague in the case of arbitration
referred to in subparagraph 4 (c) or (d), may be requested
by either of the disputing parties, to appoint the
arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed, subject to the
requirements of paragraph 12. 



12. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the
third arbitrator shall not be a national of Japan nor
citizen of India, nor have his or her usual place of
residence in either Party, nor be employed by either of the
disputing parties, nor have dealt with the investment
dispute in any capacity. 



13. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the
arbitration shall be held in a country that is a party to
the New York Convention. 



14. An arbitral tribunal established under paragraph 4
shall decide the issues in dispute in accordance with this
Chapter and other provisions of this Agreement as
applicable and applicable rules of international law. 



15. The disputing Party shall deliver to the other Party: 



(a) written notice of the investment dispute
submitted to the arbitration no later than 30 
days after the date on which the investment
dispute was submitted; and 



(b) copies of all pleadings filed in the arbitration. 


16. On written notice to the disputing parties, the Party
which is not the disputing Party may make submission to the
arbitral tribunal on a question of interpretation of this
Chapter and other provisions of this Agreement as
applicable. 



17. The arbitral tribunal may order an interim measure of
protection to preserve the rights of the disputing
investor, or to facilitate the conduct of arbitral
proceedings, including an order to preserve evidence in the
possession or control of either of the disputing parties.
The arbitral tribunal shall not order attachment or enjoin
the application of the measure alleged to constitute a
breach referred to in paragraph 1. 



18. The award rendered by the arbitral tribunal shall
include: 


(a) 	a decision whether or not there has been a breach 
by the disputing Party of any obligation under
this Chapter and other provisions of this
Agreement as applicable with respect to the
disputing investor and its investments, together
with the basis and the reasons for such decision;
and 



(b) a remedy if there has been such breach. 	The 
remedy shall be limited to one or both of the
following: 

(i) payment of monetary damages and applicable
interest; and 


(ii) restitution of property, in which case the
award shall provide that the disputing Party
may pay monetary damages and any applicable
interest in lieu of restitution. Costs may
also be awarded in accordance with the 
applicable arbitration rules. 


Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, it is 
understood that where the disputing Party
asserts as a defence that the measure alleged to
constitute a breach referred to in paragraph 1
is within the scope of a security exception as
set out in Article 11, the arbitral tribunal
shall not review the merits of any such measure
in its award. However, the arbitral tribunal
shall not be prevented from assessing the remedy
referred to in subparagraph (b) in the light of
the treatment as set out in paragraph 1 of
Article 93 for any loss or damage relating to
the investments caused by the measure in
question. 



19. The award rendered in accordance with paragraph 18
shall be final and binding upon the disputing parties. The 
disputing Party shall carry out without delay the
provisions of the award and provide in its Area for the
enforcement of the award in accordance with its relevant 
laws and regulations. 



20. Neither Party shall give diplomatic protection, or
bring an international claim, in respect of an investment
dispute which the other Party and an investor of the former
Party have consented to submit or submitted to arbitration
set forth in paragraph 4, unless the other Party has failed
to abide by and comply with the award rendered in such
investment dispute. Diplomatic protection, for the 
purposes of this paragraph, shall not include informal
diplomatic exchanges for the sole purpose of facilitating a
settlement of the investment dispute. 



21. An arbitral tribunal shall address and decide as a 
preliminary question any objection by the disputing Party
that the investment dispute is not within the competence of
the arbitral tribunal, provided that the disputing Party so
requests immediately after the establishment of the
arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="13594">1. A Party may adopt or maintain measures not conforming
with its obligations under Article 85 relating to cross-
border capital transactions and Article 94: 



(a) in the event of serious balance-of-payments and
external financial difficulties or threat 
thereof; or 



(b) in cases where, in exceptional circumstances,
movements of capital cause or threaten to cause
serious difficulties for macroeconomic management
in particular, monetary and exchange rate
policies. 

2. Measures referred to in paragraph 1 shall: 



(a) be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of
the International Monetary Fund; 



(b) not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances set out in paragraph 1; 



(c) be temporary and eliminated as soon as conditions
permit; 



(d) be promptly notified to the other Party; and 



(e) avoid unnecessary damages to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other 
Party. 


3. The Party adopting any measures under paragraph 1
shall, on request by the other Party, commence
consultations in order to examine the possibility of
reviewing the measures adopted by the former Party. 



4. Nothing in this Article shall be regarded as altering
the rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party as
a party to the Articles of Agreement of the International
Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Prudential Measures" article_identifier="13595">Where a Party takes measures relating to financial
services for prudential reasons, the provisions of
paragraph 1 of Section 2 in Annex 4 shall apply
accordingly.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Environmental Measures" article_identifier="13596">Each Party recognises that it is inappropriate to
encourage investment activities in its Area of investors of
the other Party by relaxing its environmental measures. To 
this effect each Party should not waive or otherwise
derogate from such environmental measures as an
encouragement for establishment, acquisition or expansion
of investments in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Relation To Other Obligations" article_identifier="13597">Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed so as to
derogate from laws and regulations of each Party or any
other international agreements that entitle investors of
the other Party and to their investments treatment more
favourable than that accorded by this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Duration And Termination" article_identifier="13598">In respect of investments made prior to the date of
termination of this Agreement, the provisions of this
Chapter, as well as provisions of this Agreement which are
directly related to this Chapter, shall continue to be
effective for a period of ten years from the date of
termination of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="1650">
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="13599">1. The Parties shall ensure adequate, effective, and nondiscriminatory protection of intellectual property, in
accordance with the provisions of the TRIPS Agreement. 



2. Intellectual property referred to in this Chapter
shall mean all categories of intellectual property that are
under the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Streamlining Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="13600">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administration
of the intellectual property protection system, each Party
shall take appropriate measures to streamline its
administrative procedures concerning intellectual property. 



2. Neither Party shall require the certification, by any
person other than the applicant or its representative, of a
translation of an earlier application whose priority is
claimed except in cases where the competent authority of
the Party may reasonably doubt the accuracy of the
translation. 



3. Neither Party shall require that submission of a power
of attorney be completed together with the filing of the
application as a condition for according a filing date to
the application.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="13601">The Parties shall endeavour to take such measures as 
deemed appropriate to enhance public awareness of
protection of intellectual property including educational
and dissemination projects on the use of intellectual
property as well as on the enforcement of intellectual
property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Patents" article_identifier="13602">1. Neither Party shall require the rejection of any
application for patent solely on the ground that the
subject matter claimed in the application includes, among
other things, a computer programme. 


Note: This paragraph shall not prejudice the 
patentability or non-patentability of computer
programmes per se which shall be determined in 
accordance with the laws and regulations of each
Party. 


2. Where the competent authority of a Party intends to
render its decision to the effect that an application for a
patent is to be refused, it shall notify the applicant for
the patent of the reasons for refusal and give the said
applicant an opportunity to present, in accordance with the
laws and regulations of the Party, its case against the
reasons for refusal within a reasonable period of time. 



3. Each Party shall provide that a patent owner may file
a request in accordance with its laws and regulations for
correction of the description, the scope of the claims, or
the drawings, that are attached to the patent application,
to the competent authority for patents for the purpose of
restriction of the scope of the claims.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="13603">1. Each Party shall protect well-known trademarks in
accordance with the following subparagraphs: 



(a) Each Party may determine in accordance with its
laws whether a trademark is a well-known 
trademark. 



(b) Each Party shall, ex officio if its legislation
so permits, or on the objection or request for
invalidation raised in opposition or
rectification or cancellation or invalidation 
proceedings by the proprietor of the well-known
trademark, in accordance with its laws, refuse
the application for or rectify or cancel or
invalidate the registration of a trademark which
is identical with or similar to a well-known 
trademark. 

Note: For greater certainty, for the purposes of 
this subparagraph, each Party may in 
accordance with its laws take into account 
either of the following conditions and
where appropriate other relevant factors: 


(i) the use of the trademark in question is
for unfair intentions; or 


(ii) 	the use of that trademark would take 
unfair advantage of or be detrimental to
the distinctive character or repute of
the well-known trademark. 


(c) For the purposes of subparagraphs (a) and (b),
each Party shall in accordance with its laws
determine that a trademark is a well-known 
trademark in either one or both of the following
circumstances and where appropriate taking into
account other relevant factors: 


(i) 	if a trademark is well known in the other 
Party; or 


(ii) 	if a trademark is well known in both 
Parties; 


as indicating the goods or services of the


proprietor of that trademark. 


Note: The protection of a well-known trademark shall 
also extend, subject to the laws of each Party,
to goods or services which are not similar to
those goods or services which are covered by the
well-known trademark. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that an applicant may file a
request to the competent authority that its application for
registration of a trademark be examined in preference to
other applications, subject to reasonable grounds and
procedural requirements. Where such a request has been 
filed, the competent authority shall take the request into
consideration and endeavour to examine the application in
preference to other applications, where appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Geographical Indications" article_identifier="13604">Each Party shall ensure protection of geographical
indications in accordance with its laws and regulations and
in conformity with the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="13605">Each Party shall provide for protection against acts
of unfair competition in accordance with Article 10 bis of 
the Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial 
Property (1967).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="13606">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article 73 of the
TRIPS Agreement is incorporated into and forms part of this
Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="1651">
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Procurement Principle" article_identifier="13607">Recognising the importance of government procurement
in furthering the expansion of production and trade so as
to promote growth and employment, each Party shall ensure
transparency of the measures regarding government
procurement in accordance with its national laws and
regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="13608">With respect to any measure regarding government
procurement, each Party shall provide to the goods,
services and suppliers of the other Party treatment no less
favourable than that it accords to non-Party’s goods,
services and suppliers in accordance with its laws and
regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="13609">1. The Parties shall at the national level, subject to
their respective laws and regulations, exchange
information, to the extent possible in the English language
and in a timely manner, on their respective laws and
regulations, policies and practices on government
procurement, as well as on any reforms to their existing
government procurement regimes. 



2. Each Party shall endeavour to designate a contact
point for the exchange of information and for providing
information to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="13610">The Parties shall enter into negotiations to review
this Chapter with a view to achieving a comprehensive
Chapter on Government Procurement including the provisions
of challenge procedures, when India expresses its intention
to become a Party to the Agreement on Government
Procurement in the Annex 4 to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to as “the GPA”). 


Note: If the GPA is amended or is superseded by another 


agreement, “the GPA”, for the purposes of this


Chapter, shall refer to the GPA as amended or such


other agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Negotiations On Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="13611">In the event that, after the entry into force of this
Agreement, a Party offers a non-Party any advantageous
treatment concerning the measures regarding government
procurement, including access to its government procurement
market, the former Party shall, upon the request of the
other Party, afford adequate opportunity to enter into
negotiation with the other Party with a view to extending
such advantageous treatment to the other Party on a
reciprocal basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="13612">1. The provisions of this Chapter shall not be applicable
to: 



(a) with respect to India, state governments and
their entities and local governments; and 



(b) with respect to Japan, local governments. 

2. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent
any Party from taking any action or not disclosing any
information that it considers necessary for the protection
of its essential security interests relating to the
procurement of arms, ammunition, or war materials, or to
procurement indispensable for national security or for
national defence purposes.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="1652">
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="13613">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate
against anticompetitive activities, in order to facilitate
trade and investment flows between the Parties and the 
efficient functioning of its market.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13614">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term
“competition laws and regulations” means: 



(a) for India, the Competition Act, 2002, No. 12 of
2003, as amended by the Competition (Amendment)
Act, 2007, and its implementing regulations as
well as any amendment thereto; and 



(b) for Japan, the Law Concerning Prohibition of
Private Monopoly and Maintenance of Fair Trade
(Law No. 54 of 1947) and its implementing
regulations as well as any amendment thereto.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Cooperation On Controlling Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="13615">The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, endeavour to cooperate in the field
of controlling anticompetitive activities subject to their
respective available resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="13616">Each Party shall apply its competition laws and
regulations in a manner which does not discriminate between
persons in like circumstances on the basis of their
nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Procedural Fairness" article_identifier="13617">Each Party shall implement administrative and judicial
procedures in a fair manner to control anticompetitive
activities, pursuant to its relevant laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13618">Each Party shall promote transparency of the
implementation of its competition laws and regulations and
its competition policy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="13619">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Improvement Of Business Environment" chapter_identifier="1653">
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="13620">1. With a view to promoting trade and investment between
the Parties, each Party shall, in accordance with its laws
and regulations, take appropriate measures to further
improve the business environment for the enterprises of the
other Party conducting their business activities in its
Area. 



2. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, promote cooperation to further
improve the business environment in their respective Areas.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Sub-Committee On Improvement Of Business Environment" article_identifier="13621">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Improvement
of Business Environment (hereinafter referred to in this
Chapter as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established on the
date of entry into force of this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) supervising the activities of each Consultative
Group established in accordance with Article 125; 



(b) addressing and resolving issues that the Sub-
Committee considers appropriate taking into
account, as necessary, the findings reported by
each Consultative Group and each Liaison Office
designated in accordance with Article 126; 



(c) reporting the findings and making recommendations
to the Parties including the measures to be taken
by the Parties, regarding such functions as
referred to in subparagraphs (a) and (b) and
relevant issues. Such recommendations shall be 
taken into consideration by the Parties; 



(d) where appropriate, reviewing the measures taken
by the Parties in relation to the recommendations
referred to in subparagraph (c); 



(e) making available to those concerned, in an
appropriate manner, the recommendations referred
to in subparagraph (c) and the results of the
review referred to in subparagraph (d), to the
extent allowed by the respective laws and
regulations of the Parties; and 



(f) reporting the findings and recommendations
referred to in subparagraph (c) and other
findings in relation to the implementation and
operation of this Chapter to the Joint Committee
as fully and expeditiously as possible. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. The Sub-Committee may,
by mutual consent of the Parties, invite representatives of
local governments of the Parties and invite representatives
of other relevant entities including those from the private
sector with the necessary expertise relevant to the issues
to be addressed. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venues and times 
as may be agreed by the Parties. 



5. The Sub-Committee shall cooperate with other relevant
Sub-Committees in an appropriate manner with a view to
avoiding unnecessary duplication of works with those of
other relevant Sub-Committees. 



6. The other details of the Sub-Committee shall be set 
forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Consultative Group" article_identifier="13622">1. Each Party shall establish a Consultative Group as a
subsidiary body of the Sub-Committee. 



2. The composition, functions, and frequency of meetings
of the Consultative Groups shall be set forth in the
Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Liaison Office" article_identifier="13623">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, each Party shall
designate and maintain a Liaison Office. 



2. The functions and other details of the Liaison Offices 
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="13624">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1654">
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Basic Principle And Objectives" article_identifier="13625">1. The Parties shall promote cooperation for their mutual
benefits in order to liberalise and facilitate trade and 
investment between the Parties, to strengthen wide-ranging
relations between the Parties and to promote the well-being
of the peoples of the Parties. For this purpose, the 
Parties shall, where necessary and appropriate, encourage
and facilitate cooperation between their relevant entities. 



2. 	The main objectives of this Chapter include: 



(a) 	liberalisation and facilitation of investment and 
trade between the Parties through cooperation in
the mutually identified fields; 



(b) strengthening economic competitiveness of the
Parties; 



(c) ensuring long-term sustainable development of the
Parties; 



(d) promoting the Parties’ human resource development
and capacity building; and 



(e) improving overall well-being of the peoples of
the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Fields Of Cooperation" article_identifier="13626">The fields of cooperation under this Chapter shall
include: 



(a) 	environment; 



(b) trade and investment promotion; 



(c) 	infrastructure; 



(d) information and communications technology; 



(e) science and technology; 



(f) energy; 



(g) tourism; 



(h) textiles; 



(i) small and medium enterprises; 



(j) health; 



(k) entertainment and information; 



(l) metallurgy; and 



(m) other fields to be mutually agreed upon by the
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Scope And Forms Of Cooperation" article_identifier="13627">The scope and forms of cooperation under each
identified field mutually agreed to by the Parties as
referred to in Article 129 may be set forth in the
Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Implementation And Costs" article_identifier="13628">1. The Parties shall, as soon as possible after the entry
into force of this Agreement, initiate and promote
discussions between their relevant implementing entities
with a view to exploring potential cooperation activities
in the respective fields referred to in Article 129. The 
Parties shall respect the established consultation
mechanisms between them to ensure effective and efficient 
implementation of cooperation under this Chapter. 



2. Cooperation under this Chapter may be implemented by
the relevant entities through separate work plans,
arrangements or any other means as deemed appropriate, to
be drawn up on mutual consultation in due course. The 
Parties shall provide each other with the list of their
relevant entities to be involved in the implementation of
cooperation in the respective fields referred to in Article

129. 



3. For the purposes of coordinating cooperation
activities under this Chapter and promoting discussions
referred to in paragraph 1, a Sub-Committee on Cooperation
may be established pursuant to Article 14. The Sub-
Committee may hold meetings at such frequency as mutually
agreed upon by the Parties. 



4. Cooperation in various fields need not be limited in
scope and forms to those mentioned in Article 130. 



5. The implementation of cooperation under this Chapter
shall be subject to the availability of funds and the
applicable laws and regulations of each Party. 



6. Expenses incurred in the implementation of cooperation
activities under this Chapter shall be borne in an
equitable manner to be mutually agreed upon by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="13629">The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="1655">
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Scope" article_identifier="13630">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, this
Chapter shall apply with respect to the settlement of
disputes between the Parties concerning the interpretation
or application of this Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any right of
the Parties to have recourse to dispute settlement
procedures available under the WTO Agreement. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, once the establishment of
an arbitral tribunal under this Chapter or a panel under
Article 6 of the Understanding on Rules and Procedures
Governing the Settlement of Disputes in Annex 2 to the WTO
Agreement is requested with respect to a particular
dispute, the arbitral tribunal or panel selected shall be
used to the exclusion of any other procedure for that
particular dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Consultations" article_identifier="13631">1. Either Party may request in writing to the other Party
for consultations concerning any matter on the
interpretation or application of this Agreement. 



2. When a Party requests consultations pursuant to
paragraph 1, the other Party shall reply to the request and
enter into consultations in good faith within 30 days after
the date of receipt of the request, with a view to reaching
a mutually satisfactory solution of the matter. In cases 
of urgency, including those concerning perishable goods,
the other Party shall enter into consultations within 15
days after the date of receipt of the request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="13632">1. Good offices, conciliation or mediation may be
requested at any time by either Party. They may begin at 
any time by agreement of the Parties, and be terminated at
any time upon the request of either Party. 



2. If the Parties agree, good offices, conciliation or
mediation may continue while procedures of the arbitral
tribunal provided for in this Chapter are in progress.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13633">1. The complaining Party that requested consultations
under Article 134 may request in writing the establishment
of an arbitral tribunal to the Party complained against: 



(a) if the Party complained against does not enter
into such consultations within 30 days, or within
15 days in cases of urgency including those
concerning perishable goods, after the date of
receipt of the request for such consultations; or 



(b) if the Parties fail to resolve the dispute
through such consultations within 60 days, or
within 30 days in cases of urgency including
those concerning perishable goods, after the date
of receipt of the request for such consultations, 

provided that the complaining Party considers that any
benefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under this
Agreement is being nullified or impaired as a result of the
failure of the Party complained against to carry out its
obligations under this Agreement, or as a result of the
application by the Party complained against of measures
which are in conflict with its obligations under this
Agreement. 


2. Any request for the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal pursuant to this Article shall identify: 



(a) the factual basis for the complaint; and 



(b) the legal basis of the complaint including the
provisions of this Agreement alleged to have been
breached. 


3. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date of
receipt of the request for the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal, appoint one arbitrator who may be its national
and propose up to three candidates to serve as the third
arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. 
The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either 
Party, nor have his or her usual place of residence in
either Party, nor be employed by either Party, nor have
dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 



4. The Parties shall agree on and appoint the third
arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of the
request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,
taking into account the candidates proposed pursuant to
paragraph 3. 



5. If a Party has not appointed an arbitrator pursuant to
paragraph 3 or if the Parties fail to agree on and appoint
the third arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 4, the
arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed shall be chosen
within seven days by lot-drawing from the candidates
proposed pursuant to paragraph 3. 



6. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal 
shall be the date on which the chair is appointed. 



7. An arbitral tribunal should be composed of arbitrators
with relevant technical or legal expertise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13634">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article


136: 



(a) should consult with the Parties as appropriate
and provide adequate opportunities for the
development of a mutually satisfactory solution; 



(b) 	shall make its award in accordance with this 
Agreement and applicable rules of international
law; 



(c) shall set out in its award, its findings of law
and fact, together with the reasons therefor; and 



(d) may, apart from giving its findings, include in
its award suggested implementation options for
the Parties to consider in conjunction with
Article 140. 


2. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Parties, such
relevant information as it considers necessary and
appropriate. The Parties shall respond promptly and fully 
to any request by the arbitral tribunal for such
information as the arbitral tribunal considers necessary
and appropriate. 



3. With respect to factual issues concerning a scientific
or other technical matter raised by a Party, the arbitral
tribunal may request information or advisory reports in
writing from experts. The arbitral tribunal may, at the 
request of a Party or on its own initiative, select, in
consultation with the Parties, no fewer than two scientific
or technical experts who shall assist the arbitral tribunal
throughout its proceedings and provide information or
advice upon request by the arbitral tribunal, but who shall
not have the right to vote in respect of any decision to be
made by the arbitral tribunal, including its award. 



4. Any information or advice obtained by the arbitral
tribunal pursuant to paragraph 3 shall be made available to
the Parties. Each Party may make written submissions on
the handling of such information or advice by the arbitral
tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13635">1. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 



2. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the 
documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, either Party may make
public statements as to its views regarding the dispute,
but shall treat as confidential, information and written
submissions submitted by the other Party to the arbitral
tribunal which that other Party has designated as
confidential. Where a Party has provided information or
written submissions designated as confidential, that Party
shall, upon request of the other Party, provide a non-
confidential summary of the information or written
submissions which may be disclosed publicly. 



4. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend
any of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the
proceedings. Any information or written submissions 
submitted by a Party to the arbitral tribunal, including
any comments on the descriptive part of the draft award and
responses to questions put by the arbitral tribunal, shall
be made available to the other Party. 



5. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted 
without the presence of the Parties, and in the light of
the information provided and the statements made. 



6. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 120 days, or
within 60 days in cases of urgency including those 
concerning perishable goods, after the date of its
establishment, submit to the Parties its draft award,
including both the descriptive part and its findings and
conclusions, for the purposes of enabling the Parties to
review precise aspects of the draft award. When the 
arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit its draft 
award within the aforementioned 120 days or 60 days period, 
it may extend that period with the consent of the Parties.
A Party may submit comments in writing to the arbitral
tribunal on the draft award within 15 days after the date
of submission of the draft award. 



7. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award, within 30
days after the date of submission of the draft award. 



8. The arbitral tribunal shall attempt to make its
decisions, including its award, by consensus. Failing such 
consensus, it may make its decisions, including its award,
by majority vote. In case of majority vote, opinions 
expressed by individual arbitrators shall be anonymous. 



9. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and 

binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="13636">1. The Parties may agree to terminate the proceedings of
the arbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of
the award to the Parties. 



2. When the Parties jointly notify the chair of the
arbitral tribunal of the agreement under paragraph 1, the
chair shall terminate the proceedings of the arbitral
tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="13637">1. The Party complained against shall promptly comply
with the award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant to
Article 138. 



2. If the prompt compliance with the award is
impracticable, the Party complained against shall, within
20 days after the date of issuance of the award, notify the
complaining Party of the period of time required for
implementing the award. If the complaining Party considers 
that the period of time notified is unacceptable, it may
refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal which then shall 
determine the reasonable implementation period. 



3. If the Party complained against considers it
impracticable to comply with the award within the
implementation period as determined pursuant to paragraph
2, the Party complained against shall, no later than the
expiry of that implementation period, enter into
consultations with the complaining Party, with a view to
developing mutually satisfactory compensation. If no 
satisfactory compensation has been agreed within 30 days
after the date of expiry of that implementation period, the
complaining Party may notify the Party complained against
that it intends to suspend the application to the Party
complained against of concessions or other obligations
under this Agreement. 



4. If the complaining Party considers that the Party
complained against has failed to comply with the award
within the implementation period as determined pursuant to
paragraph 2, it may refer the matter to an arbitral
tribunal. 



5. If the arbitral tribunal to which the matter is 
referred pursuant to paragraph 4 confirms that the Party
complained against has failed to comply with the award
within the implementation period as determined pursuant to
paragraph 2, the complaining Party may, within 30 days
after the date of such confirmation by the arbitral
tribunal, notify the Party complained against that it
intends to suspend the application to the Party complained
against of concessions or other obligations under this
Agreement. 



6. The suspension of the application of concessions or
other obligations under paragraphs 3 and 5 may only be
implemented at least 30 days after the date of the
notification in accordance with those paragraphs. Such 
suspension shall: 



(a) not be effected if, in respect of the dispute to
which the suspension relates, consultations or
proceedings before the arbitral tribunal are in
progress; 



(b) be temporary, and be discontinued when the
Parties reach a mutually satisfactory resolution
or where compliance with the original award is
effected; 



(c) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification 
or impairment that is attributable to the failure
to comply with the original award; and 



(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to 
which the nullification or impairment relates,
unless it is not practicable or effective to
suspend the application of concessions or
obligations in such sector or sectors. 


7. If the Party complained against considers that the
requirements for the suspension of the application to it of
concessions or other obligations under this Agreement by
the complaining Party set out in paragraph 3, 5 or 6 have
not been met, it may request consultations with the
complaining Party. The complaining Party shall enter into 
consultations within 10 days after the date of receipt of
the request. If the Parties fail to resolve the matter 
within 30 days after the date of receipt of the request for
consultations pursuant to this paragraph, the Party
complained against may refer the matter to an arbitral
tribunal. 



8. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the 
purposes of this Article shall, wherever possible, have, as
its arbitrators, the arbitrators of the original arbitral
tribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators to
the arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes
of this Article shall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 3
through 5 of Article 136. 



9. Unless the Parties agree to a different time period, 
the arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall 
issue its award within 60 days after the date when the
matter is referred to it. Such award shall be binding on
the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Expenses" article_identifier="13638">1. Unless otherwise agreed by the Parties, the expenses
of the arbitral tribunal other than those referred to in 
paragraph 2, shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares. 



2. Each Party shall bear the expenses of its
representation in the proceedings of the arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Language" article_identifier="13639">All proceedings of the arbitral tribunal and all
documents and information submitted to the arbitral 
tribunal shall be in the English language.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1656">
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="13640">The table of contents and headings of the Chapters and
Articles of this Agreement are inserted for convenience of
reference only and shall not affect the interpretation of
this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="13641">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall form an
integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Amendment" article_identifier="13642">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between the
Parties. 



2. Such amendment shall be approved by the Parties in
accordance with their respective legal procedures, and
shall enter into force on the date to be agreed upon by the
Parties. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, amendments relating only
to the following may be made by diplomatic notes exchanged
between the Governments of the Parties: 



(a) Annex 1, provided that the amendments to the
Schedule of a Party are made in accordance with 
the amendment of the Harmonized System, and
include no change on the rates of customs duty to
be applied to the originating goods of the other
Party in accordance with Annex 1; or 



(b) Annex 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="13643">This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day
of the second month following the month in which the
Governments of the Parties exchange diplomatic notes
informing each other that their respective legal procedures
necessary for entry into force of this Agreement have been
completed. It shall remain in force unless terminated as 
provided for in Article 147.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Termination" article_identifier="13644">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving
one year’s advance notice in writing to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1657">
      <article article_identifier="13645">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly
authorised by their respective Governments, have signed
this Agreement. 


DONE at Tokyo on this sixteenth day of February in the
year 2011 in duplicate in the English language. 


For Japan: For the Republic of India: 


前原誠司 Anand Sharma</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
