<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU - Cameroon</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>680</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>391</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2009-01-15</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2014-08-04</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2009-09-24</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2023-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CMR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CMR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Europe; Africa</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399560086045&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A0228(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/ES/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22009A0228(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22009A0303(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399560086045&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A0228(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399560086045&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A0228(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399560086045&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A0228(01)</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="616">
      <article article_identifier="31757">Interim Agreement

  with a view to an Economic Partnership Agreement between the European
  Community and its Member States, of the one part, and the Central
  Africa Party, of the other part

  "CENTRAL AFRICA" WHICH, FOR THE PURPOSE OF THIS AGREEMENT,
  COMPRISES:

  THE REPUBLIC OF CAMEROON,

  of the one part,

  THE KINGDOM OF BELGIUM,

  THE REPUBLIC OF BULGARIA,

  THE CZECH REPUBLIC,

  THE KINGDOM OF DENMARK,

  THE FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY,

  THE REPUBLIC OF ESTONIA,

  IRELAND,

  THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC,

  THE KINGDOM OF SPAIN,

  THE FRENCH REPUBLIC,

  THE ITALIAN REPUBLIC,

  THE REPUBLIC OF CYPRUS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF LATVIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF LITHUANIA,

  THE GRAND DUCHY OF LUXEMBOURG,

  THE REPUBLIC OF HUNGARY,

  MALTA,

  THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS,

  THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF POLAND,

  THE PORTUGUESE REPUBLIC,

  ROMANIA,

  THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA,

  THE SLOVAK REPUBLIC,

  THE REPUBLIC OF FINLAND,

  THE KINGDOM OF SWEDEN,

  THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND,

  and

  THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY,

  of the other part

  PREAMBLE

  HAVING regard to the Partnership Agreement between the Members of the
  Group of African, Caribbean and Pacific States, of the one part, and
  the European Community and its Member States, of the other part,
  signed in Cotonou on 23 June 2000 and revised in Luxembourg on 25 June
  2005, hereinafter "the Cotonou Agreement";

  CONVINCED that the Economic Partnership Agreement (EPA) will create a
  new and more favourable climate for their relations in the areas of
  economic governance, trade and investments and create new
  opportunities for growth and development;

  WHEREAS the liberalisation of trade, of establishment and of trade in
  services between the Parties must be based on the regional integration
  of the Central African States, have the objective of fostering their
  smooth and gradual integration into the global economy, with due
  regard for their political choices and their development priorities,
  and fulfil the conditions laid down in the World Trade Organisation
  (WTO) agreements;

  WHEREAS the Parties shall not encourage foreign direct investment by
  making their domestic environmental, labour or occupational health and
  safety legislation and regulations less stringent or by relaxing their
  domestic labour legislation and regulations or regulations designed to
  protect and promote cultural diversity. The Parties therefore reaffirm
  their commitment to comply with these domestic laws or regulations or
  to propose to do so in order to encourage the establishment,
  acquisition, expansion or retention in their territory of an
  investment or of an investor,

  HAVE DECIDED AS FOLLOWS:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="Objectives" chapter_identifier="617">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Interim Agreement" article_identifier="31758">This Agreement establishes an initial framework for an Economic
  Partnership Agreement (EPA).

  By "initial framework", the Parties mean an Interim
  Agreement comprising, on the one hand, actual and enforceable
  commitments according to the provisions of this Agreement and, on the
  other hand, negotiations on incorporating additional elements in order
  to arrive at a full EPA in accordance with the Cotonou Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Objectives And Scope" article_identifier="31759">The general objectives of this Agreement are to:

  (a) contribute to the reduction and eventual eradication of poverty by
  establishing a trade partnership consistent with the objective of
  sustainable development, the Millennium Development Goals and the
  Cotonou Agreement;

  (b) promote a regional economy in Central Africa that is more
  competitive and diversified, and stronger growth;

  (c) foster regional integration, economic cooperation and good
  governance in the Central African region;

  (d) promote the gradual integration of the Central Africa Party into
  the global economy, in accordance with its political choices and its
  development priorities;

  (e) improve the capacities of the Central Africa Party in terms of
  trade policy and trade-related issues;

  (f) establish and implement an effective, predictable and transparent
  regulatory framework for trade and investment in the Central African
  region, thus supporting the conditions for increasing investment and
  private-sector initiatives, and enhance capacity for the supply of
  products and services, competitiveness and economic growth in the
  region;

  (g) strengthen existing relations between the Parties on the basis of
  solidarity and mutual interest. To this end, in line with the WTO
  obligations, the Agreement will enhance commercial and economic
  relations, support a new trading dynamic between the Parties by means
  of the progressive, asymmetrical liberalisation of trade between them
  and reinforce, broaden and deepen cooperation in all areas relevant to
  trade;

  (h) promote private-sector development and employment growth.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Specific Objectives" article_identifier="31760">In accordance with Articles 34 and 35 of the Cotonou Agreement, the
  specific objectives of this Agreement are to:

  (a) establish a basis for the negotiation of an EPA which will help
  reduce poverty, promote regional integration, economic cooperation and
  good governance in Central Africa and increase Central Africa's
  production, export and supply capacities, as well as its ability to
  attract foreign investment and its capacities in terms of trade policy
  and trade-related issues;

  (b) foster the smooth and gradual integration of Central Africa into
  the global economy, in accordance with its political choices and its
  development priorities;

  (c) strengthen existing relations between the Parties on the basis of
  solidarity and mutual interest;

  (d) create an Agreement that is compatible with the rules of the WTO;

  (e) establish a basis for negotiating and implementing an effective,
  predictable and transparent regulatory framework for trade,
  investment, competition, intellectual property, public procurement and
  sustainable development in the Central African region, thus supporting
  the conditions for increasing investment and private-sector
  initiatives, and enhance capacity for the supply of goods and
  services, competitiveness and economic growth in the region;

  (f) provide a roadmap for negotiations on the areas referred to in
  paragraph (e) for which it was not possible to complete negotiations
  in 2007.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE II" name="Partnership For Development" chapter_identifier="618">
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Framework For Capacity Building In Central Africa" article_identifier="31761">The Parties affirm their commitment to promote capacity building and
  economic modernisation in Central Africa using the various instruments
  at their disposal, for example by setting up an economic and
  institutional framework at national and regional levels that is
  conducive to growth in economic activity in Central Africa, by means
  of trade policy instruments and development cooperation instruments as
  set out in Article 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Priority Areas For Capacity Building And Modernisation" article_identifier="31762">1. The Central African Party, in partnership with the EC Party and by
  means of the cooperation instruments set out in Article 7, shall
  promote a quantitative and qualitative increase in the goods and
  services produced and exported by the Central African region,
  particularly in the following areas:

  (a) Development of basic regional infrastructure

  - Transport

  - Energy

  - Telecommunications

  (b) Agriculture and food safety

  - Agricultural production

  - Agro-industry

  - Fisheries

  - Stock farming

  - Aquaculture and fish stocks

  (c) Industry, diversification and competitiveness of economies

  - Modernisation of businesses

  - Industry

  - Standards and certification (sanitary and phytosanitary (SPS)
  measures, quality, zootechnical standards, etc.)

  (d) Strengthening of regional integration

  - Development of the regional common market

  - Taxation and customs

  (e) Improvement of the business environment

  - Harmonisation of national trade policies

  2. In implementing this partnership, the Parties shall refer to the
  joint guidance document in Annex I to this Agreement.

  3. In the implementation of this Agreement, the Parties affirm their
  commitment to promote the modernisation of the productive sectors in
  Central Africa affected by this Agreement, by means of the cooperation
  instruments set out in Article 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Business Environment" article_identifier="31763">The Parties consider that the business environment is an essential
  vehicle for economic development, and that the provisions of this
  Agreement are therefore geared towards achieving this common
  objective. The signatory Central African States, which are also
  signatories of the OHADA Treaty (Organisation for the Harmonisation of
  Business Law in Africa), undertake to apply and implement the
  provisions of this Treaty effectively and without discrimination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Development Finance Cooperation" article_identifier="31764">1. The provisions of the Cotonou Agreement which relate to economic
  and regional integration and cooperation shall be implemented in order
  to maximise the benefits provided for in this Agreement.

  2. European Community [1] financing pertaining to development
  cooperation between the Central Africa Party and the European
  Community supporting the implementation of this Agreement shall be
  within the framework of the relevant rules and procedures provided for
  by the Cotonou Agreement, in particular the programming procedures of
  the European Development Fund (EDF), and within the framework of the
  relevant instruments financed by the General Budget of the European
  Union. In this context, supporting the implementation of this
  Agreement shall be one of the priorities.

  3. The Member States of the European Community collectively undertake
  to support, by means of their respective development policies and
  instruments — including aid for trade — development activities for
  regional economic cooperation and for the implementation of this
  Agreement, at both national and regional levels, in accordance with
  the principles of effectiveness and complementarity of aid.

  4. The Parties shall cooperate in order to facilitate the
  participation of other donors willing to support the efforts of the
  Central Africa Party to achieve the objectives of this Agreement.

  5. The Parties recognise the usefulness of specific regional financing
  mechanisms which support the implementation of this Agreement, and
  will support the region's efforts in this direction.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Supporting The Implementation Of Trade-Related Rules" article_identifier="31765">The Parties agree that the implementation of trade-related rules, for
  which the areas of cooperation are detailed in the individual Chapters
  of this Agreement, shall help to achieve the objectives of this
  Agreement. Cooperation in this area shall be in accordance with the
  arrangements set out in Article 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Financing Of The Partnership" article_identifier="31766">1. The Parties agree on the creation of an EPA regional fund, set up
  by and for the Central African region, to coordinate support which
  will help to finance effectively the priority measures intended to
  build productive capacity in the Central African States, as indicated
  in Article 5, and the measures referred to in Article 10. The detailed
  rules for the operation and management of the EPA regional fund shall
  be decided by the region by the end of 2008. The EC Party shall use
  this period to complete its assessment of these rules.

  2. The EPA regional fund shall be financed by resources secured by the
  Parties, for example contributions from EDF funds, contributions from
  European Union Member States and, potentially, contributions from
  other donors.

  3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, the European Community Party
  undertakes to channel its support either via the financing mechanisms
  specific to the region or via those chosen by the countries signatory
  to this Interim Agreement, with due regard for the rules and
  procedures provided for in the Cotonou Agreement, and in accordance
  with the principles of aid effectiveness.

  4. The Parties shall cooperate in order to facilitate contributions
  from other donors to the EPA regional fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Cooperation On Fiscal Adjustment" article_identifier="31767">1. The Parties recognise the challenges which the elimination or
  substantial reduction of the customs duties provided for in this
  Agreement may pose for signatory Central African States, and they
  agree to establish a dialogue and cooperation in this area.

  2. In the light of the dismantling schedule approved by the Parties to
  this Agreement, the latter agree to establish an in-depth dialogue on
  the fiscal adjustment measures to be taken which could restore budget
  balance in the long term.

  3. Further to paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, the Parties agree to
  cooperate, within the framework of Article 7, and undertake to
  implement technical and financial assistance measures in the following
  areas:

  (a) contribution to absorbing the net fiscal impact in full
  complementarity with the fiscal reforms;

  (b) support for fiscal reform together with dialogue in this area.

  4. The Parties undertake to agree, within the EPA Committee and as
  soon as possible, on the methodology for estimating net fiscal impact.
  In this same context the Parties shall subsequently agree on the
  complementary measures and studies to be undertaken.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Cooperation In International Fora" article_identifier="31768">The Parties shall endeavour to cooperate in all international fora
  where issues of interest to this partnership are discussed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Review Of The Partnership For Development" article_identifier="31769">The Parties agree to review in greater detail in 2008 the partnership
  for development established by this Title, including the details of
  its implementation.

  TRADE REGIME FOR GOODS</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Customs Duties And Non-Tariff Measures" chapter_identifier="619">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="31770">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, "originating" shall
  apply to goods that conform with the rules of origin in force on 1
  January 2008 in the territories of the Parties.

  2. A common reciprocal regime governing the rules of origin shall be
  annexed to this Agreement by the EPA Committee, and shall enter into
  force as of the date of provisional application of this Agreement.

  3. Not later than three years after the date of this Agreement's entry
  into force, the Parties shall review the provisions in force governing
  the rules of origin, with a view to simplifying the concepts and
  methods used for the purpose of determining origin in the light of
  Central Africa's development goals. As part of this review, the
  Parties shall take into account technological development, production
  processes and all other factors including reforms under way in
  relation to rules of origin which could require amendments to the
  negotiated reciprocal regime. Any amendment or replacement shall be
  effected by decision of the EPA Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Customs Duties" article_identifier="31771">"Customs duties" shall mean duties or charges of any kind,
  including any form of surcharge or supplement, imposed on or in
  connection with the import or export of goods. These do not include:

  (a) charges equivalent to taxes or other internal charges imposed in
  accordance with Article 23, below, on national treatment;

  (b) antidumping, countervailing or safeguard measures applied in
  accordance with the provisions of the Chapter on trade defence
  instruments;

  (c) fees or other charges imposed in accordance with Article 18.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties On Exports" article_identifier="31772">1. No new customs duties on exports shall be introduced in trade
  between the Parties, nor shall those already applied be increased, as
  of the date of this Agreement's entry into force.

  2. However, in the event of a serious public finance problem or the
  need for greater environmental protection, the Central Africa Party
  may, after consultation with the EC Party, introduce customs duties on
  exports for a limited number of additional goods.

  3. The EPA Committee shall undertake a regular evaluation in order to
  examine the impact and relevance of customs duties on exports applied
  under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Movement Of Products" article_identifier="31773">1. Products originating in the European Community or in the Central
  African region shall be assessed duties only once in the territory of
  the other Party.

  2. For products originating in the European Community, the customs
  duty to be paid in accordance with this Agreement shall be levied on
  behalf of the signatory Central African State whose territory
  constitutes the place of consumption.

  3. The Central Africa Party shall take all necessary measures to
  ensure the effective implementation of the provisions of this Article
  and to promote the free movement of goods in the signatory Central
  African States. The two Parties agree to cooperate in relation to this
  matter as per Articles 7 and 8. This cooperation shall be adapted
  according to the type of mechanism ultimately chosen by the Central
  African region.

  4. The Parties agree to cooperate with a view to facilitating the
  movement of goods and simplifying customs procedures as provided for
  under Chapter 3 of Title III.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Classification Of Products" article_identifier="31774">The classification of products covered by this Agreement shall be that
  set out in each Party's respective tariff nomenclature in conformity
  with the Harmonised Commodity Description and Coding System
  ("HS").</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Fees And Other Charges" article_identifier="31775">1. Fees and other charges referred to in Article 14(c) shall be
  limited in amount to the approximate cost of services rendered and
  shall not constitute indirect protection for domestic products or
  taxation of imports or exports for fiscal purposes. They shall be
  subject to specific tariffs corresponding to the approximate cost of
  services rendered and shall not be calculated on an ad valorem basis.
  The fees and other charges shall not be imposed for consular
  formalities, such as consular certificates and invoices (exhaustive
  list to be drawn up by the EPA Committee).

  2. In order to promote regional integration and ensure clarity for
  economic operators, the Central Africa Party agrees to introduce, not
  later than 1 January 2013, standardised provisions relating to the
  area covered by this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="More Favourable Treatment On The Basis Of Economic Integration Agreements" article_identifier="31776">1. With regard to the areas covered by this Chapter, the EC Party
  shall grant the Central Africa Party any more favourable treatment
  which could result from the EC Party becoming party to an economic
  integration agreement with third parties after this Agreement has been
  signed.

  2. With regard to the areas covered by this Chapter, the EC Party
  shall grant the Central Africa Party any more favourable treatment
  which could result from the EC Party becoming party to an economic
  integration agreement with a major trading partner after this
  Agreement has been signed.

  3. If the Central Africa Party has received substantially more
  favourable treatment from a major trading partner than that provided
  by the EC Party in an economic integration agreement concluded by the
  Central Africa Party with that same partner, the Parties shall enter
  into consultations and decide together on the implementation of the
  provisions of paragraph 2.

  4. For the purposes of this Article, "economic integration
  agreement" shall mean an agreement which substantially
  liberalises trade and abolishes or eliminates discrimination between
  the Parties by eliminating existing discriminatory measures and/or
  prohibiting new or more discriminatory measures, either upon entry
  into force of this Agreement or on the basis of a reasonable
  time-frame.

  5. For the purposes of this Article, "major trading partner"
  shall signify any developed country or any country accounting for more
  than 1 % of world trade in the year before the entry into force of the
  economic integration agreement referred to in paragraph 2, or any
  group of countries acting individually, collectively or through an
  economic integration agreement accounting collectively for more than
  1,5 % of world trade in the year before the entry into force of the
  economic integration agreement referred to in paragraph 2 [2].

  6. The provisions of this Chapter shall not be so construed as to
  oblige the Parties to extend reciprocally any preferential treatment
  applicable as a result of one of the Parties being party to a regional
  economic integration agreement with a third party on the date of
  signature of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The Signatory Central African States" article_identifier="31777">1. Products originating from the Central Africa Party shall be
  imported into the EC Party free of customs duties, with the exception
  of the products indicated, and under the conditions set out in Annex
  II.

  2. No new customs duties shall be introduced in trade between the
  Parties, nor shall those already applied be increased.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The European Community" article_identifier="31778">1. For each product, the basic customs duty shall be that specified in
  Annex III.

  2. No new customs duties shall be introduced in trade between the
  Parties, nor shall those specified in Annex III be increased.

  3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, in the context of introducing a common
  external tariff as of 1 January 2013 at the latest, and insofar as the
  general incidence of these duties is no higher than that of the duties
  specified in Annex III, Central Africa may revise the basic customs
  duties specified in Annex III which are applicable to products
  originating in the European Community. In that case, the EPA Committee
  shall modify Annex III accordingly.

  4. Customs duties on imports of products defined as originating in the
  European Community and listed in Annex III under categories
  "1", "2" and "3" shall be definitively
  eliminated as per the table below. The tariff reduction percentages
  set out in the table below shall be applied either to the tariffs laid
  down in paragraph 1 or to any new tariffs laid down under the
  conditions of paragraph 3.

  Category | 1/01/2008 | 1/01/2009 | 1/01/2010 | 1/01/2011 | 1/01/2012 |
  1/01/2013 | 1/01/2014 |

  1 | 0 % | 0 % | 25 % | 50 % | 75 % | 100 % | |

  2 | 0 % | 0 % | 0 % | 15 % | 30 % | 45 % | 60 % |

  3 | 0 % | 0 % | 0 % | 0 % | 0 % | 0 % | 10 % |

  Category | 1/01/2015 | 1/01/2016 | 1/01/2017 | 1/01/2018 | 1/01/2019 |
  1/01/2020 | 1/01/2021 |

  1 | | | | | | | |

  2 | 75 % | 90 % | 100 % | | | | |

  3 | 20 % | 30 % | 40 % | 50 % | 60 % | 70 % | 80 % |

  Category | 1/01/2022 | 1/01/2023 |

  1 | | |

  2 | | |

  3 | 90 % | 100 % |

  5. Imports of products originating in the European Community and
  listed in Annex III under category "5" shall comprise
  products for which customs duties are determined in accordance with
  the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 3 above; customs duties in this
  category shall be neither reduced nor eliminated.

  6. In the event of serious difficulties in respect of imports of a
  given product, the schedule for tariff reduction and dismantling may
  be reviewed by the EPA Committee by common accord with a view to
  possibly extending the period of reduction or elimination. During a
  review of this kind, the calendar period for which the review has been
  requested may not be extended, for the product concerned, beyond the
  maximum transitional period for the reduction or elimination of
  tariffs provided for this same product. If the EPA Committee has not
  made a decision within 30 days of an application to review the
  timetable, the Central Africa Party may suspend the timetable
  provisionally for a period which may not exceed one year.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Prohibition Of Quantitative Restrictions" article_identifier="31779">Upon entry into force of this Agreement, all prohibitions or
  restrictions on imports or exports affecting trade between the two
  Parties shall be eliminated, apart from the customs duties, taxes,
  fees and other charges referred to under Article 18 of this Chapter,
  whether made effective through quotas, import or export licenses or
  other measures. No new measures may be introduced. The provisions of
  this Article shall apply without prejudice to the provisions of the
  Chapter of this Agreement on trade defence instruments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="National Treatment On Internal Regulations And Taxation" article_identifier="31780">1. Imported products originating in the territory of the other Party
  shall not be subject, either directly or indirectly, to internal taxes
  or other internal charges of any kind in excess of those applied,
  directly or indirectly, to like national products. Moreover, the
  Parties shall not otherwise apply internal taxes or other internal
  charges so as to afford protection to national production.

  2. Imported products originating in the territory of the other Party
  shall be accorded treatment no less favourable than that accorded to
  like national products in respect of all laws, regulations and
  requirements affecting their internal sale, offering for sale,
  purchase, transportation, distribution or use. The provisions of this
  paragraph shall not prevent the application of differential internal
  transportation charges which are based exclusively on the economic
  operation of the means of transport and not on the origin of the
  product.

  3. Neither Party shall establish or maintain any internal regulation
  relating to the mixture, processing or use of products in specified
  amounts or proportions which requires, directly or indirectly, that
  any specified amount or proportion of any product which is the subject
  of the regulation must be supplied from national sources. Moreover,
  neither Party shall otherwise apply internal quantitative regulations
  so as to afford protection to national production.

  No internal quantitative regulation relating to the mixture,
  processing or use of products in specified amounts or proportions
  shall be applied in such a manner as to allocate any such amount or
  proportion among external sources of supply.

  4. In accordance with Article III.8(b) of the General Agreement on
  Trade and Tariffs of 1994 (GATT 1994), the provisions of this Article
  shall not prevent the payment of subsidies exclusively to national
  producers, including payments derived from the proceeds of internal
  taxes or charges applied consistently with the provisions of this
  Article and subsidies effected through governmental purchases of
  national products.

  5. The provisions of this Article shall not apply to laws,
  regulations, procedures or practices governing public procurement.

  6. The provisions of this Article shall apply without prejudice to the
  provisions of the Chapter of this Agreement on trade defence
  instruments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Agricultural Export Subsidies" article_identifier="31781">1. No Party or signatory Central African State may introduce new
  export subsidies or increase any existing subsidy of this nature on
  agricultural products destined for the territory of the other Party.
  With regard to existing subsidies, this paragraph shall not prohibit
  increases due to variations in the world prices of the products in
  question.

  2. For any group of products, as defined in paragraph 3, which receive
  an export refund under EC legislation for the same basic product for
  which the Central Africa Party has undertaken to eliminate its
  tariffs, the EC Party undertakes to dismantle all existing subsidies
  for exports of this group of products — corresponding to the same
  basic product — to the territory of the Central Africa Party. In the
  context of this paragraph, the Parties shall hold consultations by 31
  December 2008 in order to establish the details of this dismantling
  process.

  3. This Article shall apply to products covered by Annex I of the WTO
  Agreement on Agriculture.

  4. This Article shall be without prejudice to the application by the
  Central Africa Party of Article 9.4 of the WTO Agreement on
  Agriculture and Article 27 of WTO Agreement on Subsidies and
  Countervailing Measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Food Security" article_identifier="31782">Should the implementation of this Agreement lead to problems with the
  availability of, or access to, the foodstuffs necessary to ensure food
  security, and where this situation gives rise or is likely to give
  rise to major difficulties for the Central Africa Party or a signatory
  Central African State, the Central Africa Party or this signatory
  Central African State may take appropriate measures in accordance with
  the procedures laid down in Article 31.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Special Provisions On Administrative Cooperation" article_identifier="31783">1. The Parties agree that administrative cooperation is essential for
  the implementation and control of the preferential treatment granted
  under this Title and underline their commitment to tackle
  irregularities and fraud in customs and related matters.

  2. Where one party obtains proof, based on objective information, of a
  failure to provide administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities
  or fraud, the Party concerned may temporarily suspend the preferential
  treatment of the product(s) concerned in accordance with this Article.

  3. For the purposes of this Article, a failure to provide
  administrative cooperation shall be defined, inter alia, as:

  (a) a recurrent failure to respect the obligation to verify the
  originating status of the product(s) concerned;

  (b) a repeated refusal or undue delay in carrying out and/or
  communicating the results of subsequent verification of the proof of
  origin;

  (c) a repeated refusal or undue delay in granting authorisation to
  conduct a cooperation mission to verify the authenticity of documents
  or accuracy of information relevant to the granting of the
  preferential treatment in question.

  4. The application of a temporary suspension shall be subject to the
  following conditions:

  (a) The Party which obtains proof, based on objective information, of
  a failure to provide administrative cooperation and/or of
  irregularities or fraud shall without undue delay notify the EPA
  Committee of this proof together with the objective information and
  enter into consultations within the EPA Committee with a view to
  reaching a solution acceptable to both Parties, on the basis of all
  relevant information and objective findings.

  (b) Where the Parties have entered into consultations in the EPA
  Committee as provided for above and have not been able to agree on an
  acceptable solution within three months of notification, the Party
  concerned may temporarily suspend the preferential treatment of the
  product(s) concerned. A temporary suspension shall be notified to the
  EPA Committee without undue delay.

  (c) Temporary suspensions under this Article shall be limited to that
  necessary to protect the financial interests of the Party concerned.
  They shall not exceed a period of six months, which may be renewed.
  The EPA Committee shall be notified of temporary suspensions
  immediately after their adoption. Such suspensions shall be the
  subject of periodic consultations within the EPA Committee,
  particularly with a view to their termination as soon as the
  conditions for their application no longer exist.

  5. At the same time as the notification of the EPA Committee provided
  for in paragraph 4(a) of this Article, the Party concerned shall
  publish a notice to importers in its Official Journal or Gazette. This
  notice to importers shall indicate that, for the product concerned,
  proof has been obtained, based on objective information, of a failure
  to provide administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities or
  fraud.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Management Of Administrative Errors" article_identifier="31784">In case of error by the competent authorities in the management of
  preferential systems for exports, and in particular in the application
  of rules defining the concept of "originating" products and
  methods of administrative cooperation, where this error leads to
  consequences in terms of imports and exports the Party facing such
  consequences may request the EPA Committee to examine the possibility
  of adopting all appropriate measures with a view to resolving the
  situation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="31785">In accordance with the provisions of Article 7, the Parties agree to
  cooperate in the following areas inter alia:

  - supporting the implementation of trade policy commitments arising
  from this Agreement;

  - training/support in the interpretation and application of these
  rules.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade Defence Instruments" chapter_identifier="3703">
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Anti-Dumping And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="31786">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the EC Party or the signatory
  Central African States, individually or collectively, from adopting
  anti-dumping or countervailing measures in accordance with the
  relevant WTO Agreements. For the purposes of this Article, origin
  shall be determined in accordance with the Parties' non-preferential
  rules of origin.

  2. Before imposing definitive anti-dumping or countervailing duties in
  respect of products from signatory Central African States, the EC
  Party shall consider the possibility of constructive remedies as
  provided for in the relevant WTO Agreements.

  3. Where an anti-dumping or countervailing measure has been imposed on
  two signatory Central African States at least by a regional or
  sub-regional authority, there shall be one single instance of judicial
  review, including the stage of appeals.

  4. Where anti-dumping or countervailing measures may be imposed on a
  regional or sub-regional basis and on a national basis, the Parties
  guarantee that these measures shall not be applied simultaneously to
  the same product by the regional or sub-regional authorities and the
  national authorities.

  5. The EC Party shall notify the signatory Central African States of
  the receipt of a properly documented complaint before initiating any
  investigation.

  6. The provisions of this Article shall be applicable in all
  investigations initiated after this Agreement enters into force.

  7. The provisions of this Article shall not be subject to the dispute
  settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Multilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="31787">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the signatory Central African
  States or the EC Party from adopting measures in accordance with
  Article XIX of the GATT 1994, the WTO Agreement on Safeguards and
  Article 5 of the WTO Agreement on Agriculture. For the purposes of
  this Article, origin shall be determined in accordance with the
  Parties' non-preferential rules of origin.

  2. Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraph 1, in the light of
  the overall development objectives of this Agreement and the small
  size of the economies of the signatory Central African States, the EC
  Party shall exclude imports from signatory Central African States from
  any measures taken pursuant to Article XIX of GATT 1994, the WTO
  Agreement on Safeguards and Article 5 of the WTO Agreement on
  Agriculture.

  3. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall apply for a period of five
  years, beginning on the date on which this Agreement enters into
  force. Not later than 120 days before the end of this period, the EPA
  Committee shall review the implementation of these provisions in the
  light of the development needs of the signatory Central African
  States, with a view to determining whether to extend their application
  for a further period.

  4. The provisions of paragraph 1 shall not be subject to the dispute
  settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="31788">1. Without prejudice to the provisions of Article 30, after having
  examined alternative solutions, a Party may apply safeguard measures
  of limited duration which derogate from the provisions of Articles 20
  and 21, under the conditions and in accordance with the procedures
  laid down in this Article.

  2. Safeguard measures as referred to in paragraph 1 may be taken where
  a product originating in the territory of one Party is being imported
  into the territory of the other Party in such increased quantities and
  under such conditions as to cause or threaten to cause:

  (a) serious damage to the domestic industry producing like or directly
  competitive products in the territory of the importing Party, or

  (b) disruption in a sector of the economy, particularly where this
  disruption gives rise to major social problems or difficulties which
  could seriously jeopardise the economic situation of the importing
  Party, or

  (c) disruption in the markets of like or directly competitive
  agricultural products [3] or in the mechanisms regulating those
  markets.

  3. The safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall not exceed
  what is necessary to remedy or prevent the serious damage or
  disruption, as defined in paragraphs 2 and 5(b). Those safeguard
  measures of the importing Party may only consist of one or more of the
  following:

  (a) the suspension of any further reduction of the applicable import
  duty provided for under this Agreement for the product concerned,

  (b) an increase in the customs duty on the product concerned to a
  level which does not exceed the customs duty applied to other WTO
  Members, and

  (c) the introduction of tariff quotas on the product concerned.

  4. Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraphs 1, 2 and 3, where
  a product originating in one or more signatory Central African States
  is being imported in such increased quantities and under such
  conditions as to cause or threaten to cause one of the situations
  referred to under paragraph 2(a), (b) and (c) to one or more of the EC
  Party's outermost regions, the EC Party may take surveillance or
  safeguard measures limited to the region or regions concerned in
  accordance with the procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  5. (a) Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraphs 1, 2 and 3,
  where a product originating in the EC Party is being imported in such
  increased quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten
  to cause one of the situations referred to under paragraph 2(a), (b)
  and (c) above to a signatory Central African State, this signatory
  Central African State may take surveillance or safeguard measures
  limited to its territory in accordance with the procedures laid down
  in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  (b) A signatory Central African State may take safeguard measures
  where a product originating in the EC Party, following the reduction
  of customs duties, is being imported into its territory in such
  increased quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten
  to cause disruption to an infant industry producing like or directly
  competitive products. This clause shall be applicable for a period of
  fifteen years from the date on which this Agreement enters into force.
  Measures must be taken in accordance with the provisions of paragraphs
  6 to 9.

  6. (a) The safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall be
  maintained only for such time as is necessary to prevent or remedy the
  serious damage or disruption as defined in paragraphs 2, 4 and 5
  above.

  (b) The safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall be
  applied for a period not exceeding two years. Where the circumstances
  warranting the imposition of safeguard measures continue to exist,
  such measures may be extended for a further period of no more than two
  years. Where the signatory Central African States or a signatory
  Central African State applies a safeguard measure, or where the EC
  Party takes safeguard measures limited to the territory of one or more
  of its outermost regions, such measures may nevertheless be applied
  for a period not exceeding four years and, where the circumstances
  warranting the imposition of safeguard measures continue to exist, be
  extended for a further maximum period of four years.

  (c) The safeguard measures referred to in this Article which exceed
  one year shall have a clear timetable for being phased out by the end
  of the set period, at the latest.

  (d) No safeguard measure referred to in this Article shall be applied
  to a product that has previously been subject to such a measure for a
  period of at least one year since the expiry of the measure.

  7. For the implementation of paragraph 1 to 6, the following
  provisions shall apply:

  (a) Where a Party is of the opinion that one of the circumstances
  referred to in paragraphs 2, 4 and/or 5 exists, it shall immediately
  refer the matter to the EPA Committee.

  (b) The EPA Committee may make recommendations to remedy the
  circumstances which have arisen. If the EPA Committee has not made
  recommendations to remedy the circumstances, or if a satisfactory
  solution has not been reached within 30 days of the matter being
  referred, the importing Party may adopt the appropriate measures to
  remedy the situation in accordance with this Article.

  (c) Before taking any measure provided for in this Article or, in the
  cases to which paragraph 8 applies, the Party concerned shall, as soon
  as possible, supply the EPA Committee with all information required
  for a thorough examination of the situation, with a view to seeking a
  solution acceptable to the Parties concerned.

  (d) In selecting safeguard measures, priority must be given to those
  which solve the problem rapidly and effectively and disturb the
  functioning of this Agreement as little as possible.

  (e) All safeguard measures taken in accordance with this Article shall
  be notified immediately to the EPA Committee and shall be the subject
  of periodic consultations within that body, particularly with a view
  to establishing a timetable for their termination as soon as
  circumstances permit.

  8. Where exceptional circumstances require immediate measures, the
  importing Party concerned, whether the EC Party, the signatory Central
  African States or a signatory Central African State, may take the
  measures provided for in paragraphs 3, 4 and/or 5 on a provisional
  basis without complying with the requirements of paragraph 7. Such
  action may be taken for a maximum period of 180 days where measures
  are taken by the EC Party and 200 days where measures are taken by the
  signatory Central African States or a signatory Central African State,
  or where measures taken by the EC Party are limited to the territory
  of one or more of its outermost regions. The duration of any such
  provisional measure shall be counted as part of the period of duration
  of the measures and of any extension as referred to in paragraph 6.
  When taking such provisional measures, the interests of all
  stakeholders shall be taken into account. The importing Party
  concerned shall inform the other Party and shall refer the matter to
  the EPA Committee for examination.

  9. If an importing Party subjects imports of a product to an
  administrative procedure having as its purpose the rapid provision of
  information on the trend of trade flows liable to give rise to the
  problems referred to in this Article, it shall inform the EPA
  Committee without delay.

  10. The WTO Agreement shall not be invoked to prevent a Party from
  adopting safeguard measures in accordance with the provisions of this
  Article.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Customs And Trade Facilitation" chapter_identifier="3704">
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Objectives" article_identifier="31789">1. The Parties acknowledge the importance of customs and of trade
  facilitation in the evolving global trading environment. The Parties
  agree to increase cooperation in this area with a view to ensuring
  that the relevant legislation and procedures, as well as the
  administrative capacity of the relevant administrations, fulfil the
  objectives of effective controls and facilitation of trade, and help
  promote the development and regional integration of the EPA signatory
  countries.

  2. The Parties agree that legitimate public policy objectives,
  including those relating to security and the prevention of fraud,
  shall not be compromised in any way.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Customs And Administrative Cooperation" article_identifier="31790">1. In order to ensure compliance with the provisions of this Agreement
  and effectively respond to the objectives laid down in Article 32, the
  Parties shall:

  (a) exchange information concerning customs legislation, regulations
  and procedures;

  (b) develop joint initiatives relating to import, export and transit
  procedures, and initiatives designed to provide an effective service
  for the business community;

  (c) cooperate on the automation of customs and trade procedures, and
  adopt, for the purpose of information exchange, the Customs Data Model
  of the World Customs Organisation (WCO);

  (d) cooperate in the planning and implementation of assistance with a
  view to facilitating customs reforms and implementing trade
  facilitation; and

  (e) encourage consultations and cooperation between all bodies
  concerned with international trade.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the Parties' customs administrations
  shall provide mutual administrative assistance in accordance with the
  provisions of the Protocol on Mutual Administrative Assistance in
  Customs Matters. As of 2008, the EPA Committee shall make any
  amendments which it considers necessary to Protocol 1 by consensus.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Terms Of Cooperation" article_identifier="31791">1. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation as regards
  customs and trade facilitation measures for the implementation of this
  Agreement.

  2. In accordance with the provisions of Article 7, the Parties agree
  to cooperate in the following areas, inter alia:

  (a) the application of modern customs techniques, including risk
  analysis and risk management, binding information, simplified
  procedures for imports and exports of products, subsequent
  verifications and company audit methods;

  (b) the introduction of procedures which reflect where possible the
  international instruments and standards applicable in the field of
  customs and trade, including WTO rules on customs valuation and WCO
  instruments and standards, inter alia the International Convention on
  the Simplification and Harmonisation of Customs Procedures, concluded
  at Kyoto on 18 May 1973, and revised at Brussels on 26 June 1999 (the
  "revised Kyoto Convention") and the WCO Framework of
  Standards to Secure and Facilitate Global Trade; and

  (c) the computerisation of customs and trade procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Customs And Trade Standards" article_identifier="31792">1. The Parties agree that their legislation, regulations and
  procedures, in the fields of customs and international trade, shall be
  based on:

  (a) international standards and instruments, including the revised
  Kyoto Convention, the WCO Framework of Standards to Secure and
  Facilitate Global Trade, the WCO Customs Data Model and the
  International Convention on the Harmonised Commodity Description and
  Coding System ("HS");

  (b) the introduction of a single administrative document, or an
  electronic equivalent, for the purpose of establishing customs
  declarations at the import and export stages;

  (c) modern customs techniques, including risk analysis and risk
  management, simplified procedures for imports and exports of products,
  subsequent verifications and company audit methods. Procedures should
  be transparent, efficient and simplified, in order to reduce costs and
  increase predictability for economic operators, including small and
  medium-sized enterprises;

  (d) non-discrimination in terms of requirements and procedures
  concerning imports, exports and products in transit, although it shall
  be accepted that consignments may be treated differently in accordance
  with objective risk management criteria;

  (e) regulations and procedures containing binding information,
  particularly on tariff classification, and origin;

  (f) simplified procedures for authorised traders;

  (g) the gradual development of information systems to facilitate the
  electronic exchange of data between traders, customs administrations
  and other bodies involved;

  (h) the facilitation of transit movements;

  (i) rules ensuring that penalties imposed for minor breaches of
  customs regulations or the requirements of international trade
  procedures are proportionate and non-discriminatory and that their
  application does not result in unwarranted delays;

  (j) regular evaluation of the system of mandatory use of customs
  brokers in order to improve performance and efficiency, and if
  necessary move towards the elimination of this system;

  2. The system of mandatory pre-shipment inspections of products shall
  be the subject of negotiations within the negotiations on a full EPA.

  3. In order to improve working methods, as well as to ensure
  non-discrimination, transparency, efficiency, integrity and
  accountability of operations, the Parties shall:

  (a) take the necessary measures, based on the relevant international
  recommendations, to simplify and standardise the data and
  documentation required by customs and the other institutions involved
  with international trade;

  (b) simplify administrative formalities and requirements wherever
  possible in order to reduce the time needed for clearance, release and
  removal of products;

  (c) implement effective, prompt and non-discriminatory procedures
  enabling the right of appeal against rulings, decisions and actions by
  customs and other administrations which affect imports, exports or
  goods in transit. Procedures for appeal shall be easily accessible and
  any costs shall be reasonable and not in excess of the costs necessary
  to process them;

  (d) ensure that the highest standards of integrity are maintained by
  applying measures in line with the principles of the relevant
  international instruments and conventions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Transit Of Products" article_identifier="31793">1. The Parties shall ensure freedom of transit through their territory
  via the route most convenient for transit. Any restrictions, controls
  or requirements must be non-discriminatory, proportionate and applied
  uniformly.

  2. Without prejudice to legitimate customs control, the Parties shall
  accord to products in transit from the territory of one Party
  treatment not less favourable than that accorded to domestic products,
  in particular with respect to exports and imports and their movement.

  3. The Parties shall operate bonded transport regimes that allow the
  transit of products without payment of duties or other charges,
  subject to the provision of an appropriate guarantee.

  4. The Parties shall promote and implement regional transit
  arrangements.

  5. The Parties shall use international standards and instruments
  relevant to transit.

  6. The Parties shall ensure cooperation and coordination across all
  relevant agencies in their territories to facilitate traffic in
  transit and promote cross-border cooperation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Relations With The Business Community" article_identifier="31794">The Parties agree:

  (a) to ensure that all information on legislation, regulations,
  procedures and required documents, duties and taxes, fees and other
  charges may be made publicly available, where possible electronically;

  (b) on the need for regular consultations with the business community
  on the drafting of texts related to customs and international trade
  issues. To this end, appropriate mechanisms for regular consultation
  shall be put in place by the Parties;

  (c) that a sufficient period of time must elapse between the
  publication and entry into force of any legislation, procedure, duty
  or charge, whether new or amended.

  The Parties shall make publicly available relevant notices of an
  administrative nature, including agency requirements, procedures,
  opening hours and operating procedures for customs offices at entry
  and/or exit points, and contact or information points;

  (d) to foster cooperation between operators and relevant
  administrations via the use of non-arbitrary and accessible
  procedures, such as memoranda of understanding based on the protocols
  promulgated by the WCO;

  (e) to ensure that administrations' requirements in terms of
  international trade continue to meet the needs of the business
  community, follow best practices, and remain as unrestrictive to trade
  as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="31795">1. Article VII of the GATT (1994) and the WTO Agreement on the
  implementation of Article VII of the GATT (1994) shall govern customs
  valuation rules applied to reciprocal trade between the Parties.

  2. The Parties shall cooperate with a view to achieving a common
  approach to issues relating to customs valuation, including problems
  relating to transfer pricing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Regional Integration In Central Africa" article_identifier="31796">In taking forward customs reforms, and in order to facilitate trade,
  the Parties shall promote regional integration, including in terms of
  developing standardised:

  - requirements,

  - documentation,

  - data requirements,

  - procedures,

  - authorised trader schemes,

  - border procedures and opening hours,

  - transit requirements, bonded transport and guarantee schemes.

  This should involve close cooperation between all relevant agencies
  and be based, wherever possible, on the use of relevant international
  standards.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Technical Barriers To Trade, And Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="3705">
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Objectives" article_identifier="31797">The objectives of this Chapter are to facilitate trade in products
  between the Parties while increasing the capacity of the Parties to
  identify, prevent and eliminate obstacles to trade as a result of
  technical regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures
  applied by either Party, and increasing the capacity of the Parties to
  protect plants, animals and public health.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Multilateral Obligations And General Background" article_identifier="31798">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations under the WTO
  Agreement, and in particular the WTO Agreements on the Application of
  Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures (SPS Agreement) and on Technical
  Barriers to Trade (TBT Agreement). The Parties which are not members
  of the WTO also confirm their commitment to comply with the
  obligations set out in the SPS and TBT Agreements with regard to all
  matters concerning relations between the Parties.

  2. The Parties reaffirm their commitment to improve public health in
  the territories of the signatory Central African States, in particular
  by strengthening their capacity to identify unsafe products, pursuant
  to Article 47.

  3. These commitments, rights and obligations shall inform the
  activities of the Parties under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Scope And Definitions" article_identifier="31799">1. This Chapter shall apply to those measures within the scope of the
  WTO TBT and SPS Agreements.

  2. Unless specified otherwise, for the purposes of this Chapter, the
  definitions of the SPS and TBT Agreements, CODEX Alimentarius, the
  International Plant Protection Convention and the World Organisation
  for Animal Health shall apply, also for all references to
  "products" in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Competent Authorities" article_identifier="31800">With regard to SPS measures, the authorities in the EC Party and the
  signatory Central African States which are responsible for the
  implementation of the measures referred to in this Chapter are
  described in Appendix II.

  The Parties shall inform each other in a timely manner of any
  significant changes to the competent authorities listed in Appendix
  II. The EPA Committee shall adopt any necessary amendment of Appendix
  II.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Zoning" article_identifier="31801">When defining import conditions, the Parties may, on a case-by-case
  basis, propose and identify zones with a defined sanitary or
  phytosanitary status, taking account of international standards.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Transparency Of Trade Conditions And Information Exchange" article_identifier="31802">1. The Parties shall inform each other of any changes to their legal
  and administrative import requirements for products (including
  products of animals and/or vegetable origin).

  2. The Parties reconfirm their obligations under the WTO SPS and TBT
  Agreements to inform each other of changes to the relevant standards
  or technical regulations through the mechanisms established under
  those Agreements.

  3. The Parties shall also directly exchange information on other
  topics agreed by both Parties to be of potential importance for their
  trade relations, as and when necessary.

  4. The Parties agree to collaborate in epidemiological surveillance on
  animal disease. Also in the domain of plant health, the Parties shall
  exchange information on the occurrence of pests of known and immediate
  danger to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Regional Integration" article_identifier="31803">1. The Central Africa Party undertakes to harmonise the standards and
  other measures within the scope of this Chapter at regional level
  within four years of this Agreement's entry into force.

  2. With a view to facilitating trade between the Parties and in
  conformity with Article 40, the signatory Central African States agree
  on the need to harmonise import conditions applicable to products
  originating in the territory of the EC Party when these products enter
  a signatory Central African State. Where national import conditions
  already exist at the time of this Agreement's entry into force, and
  pending the introduction of harmonised import conditions, the existing
  import conditions shall be implemented by the signatory Central
  African States on the basis that a product from the EC Party legally
  placed on the market of a signatory Central African State may also be
  legally placed on the market of all other signatory Central African
  States without any further restriction or administrative requirement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Capacity-Building And Technical Assistance" article_identifier="31804">In accordance with the provisions of Article 7, the Parties agree to
  cooperate in the following areas inter alia:

  (a) For products referred to in Appendix IA, the Parties agree to
  cooperate with a view to strengthening both regional integration
  within the signatory Central African States and control capacity in
  accordance with the objectives of this Agreement, and in such a manner
  as to facilitate trade between the signatory Central African States.

  (b) For the products referred to in Appendix IB, the Parties agree to
  cooperate with a view to improving the competitiveness and quality of
  their products.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Forestry Governance And Trade In Timber And Forest Products" chapter_identifier="3706">
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Definitions" article_identifier="31805">Unless specified otherwise, for the purposes of this Chapter the
  description "forest products" shall also include non-timber
  forest products and their derivatives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Scope" article_identifier="31806">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to trade in timber and
  forest products originating in Central Africa and to the sustainable
  management of the forests from which these products are extracted.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Trade In Timber, Non-Timber Forest Products And Derivatives" article_identifier="31807">1. The Parties shall work together to facilitate trade between the EC
  Party and the Central Africa Party in timber and forest products which
  come from objectively verifiable legal sources and help to achieve
  sustainable development. The Parties agree to:

  (a) implement measures to increase market confidence regarding the
  origin of forest products, particularly their legal and/or sustainable
  origin. These measures may include systems to improve the traceability
  of timber and forest products sold both within Central Africa and
  between the Central Africa Party and the EC Party;

  (b) put in place an audit and surveillance system that is independent
  of the control chain.

  2. The Parties shall explore possible ways of improving commercial
  opportunities for timber and forest products with a legal or
  sustainable origin in Central Africa on the market of the EC Party.
  These measures may include, inter alia, stronger public procurement
  policies, measures to raise consumer awareness, measures to promote
  the processing of forest products in Central Africa, and activities
  and initiatives in association with private-sector operators.

  3. The Parties undertake to develop non-discriminatory policies and/or
  legislation within the scope of this Chapter; they also undertake to
  ensure the effective and non-discriminatory implementation of these
  policies and/or legislation, in accordance with WTO provisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Regional Integration" article_identifier="31808">1. The Central Africa Party undertakes to build and implement a
  regional framework to govern trade in timber and forest products
  originating in Central Africa, including the appropriate cooperation
  mechanisms and legislation to ensure that it is applied and
  implemented effectively.

  2. The Central Africa Party shall develop protocols and/or guidelines
  for cooperation between the competent authorities in Central Africa
  which are responsible for implementation, to ensure that
  intra-regional trade in timber and forest products from Central Africa
  come from objectively verifiable legal sources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Capacity-Building And Technical Assistance" article_identifier="31809">In accordance with the provisions of Article 7, the Parties agree to
  cooperate in the following areas inter alia:

  (a) facilitating assistance with a view to strengthening regional
  integration, for example the implementation of the Treaty on the
  Conservation and Sustainable Management of Forests in Central Africa
  (COMIFAC) and the Sub-regional Convergence Plan, and with a view to
  building capacity in order to fulfil the commitments set out in this
  Chapter;

  (b) supporting public and private commercial initiatives, particularly
  in terms of exports to the market of the EC Party, for local
  processing of timber and forest products originating in Central Africa
  which come from objectively verifiable legal sources and help to
  achieve sustainable development.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Other Agreements" article_identifier="31810">Without prejudice to the provisions of this Chapter, trade in timber
  and forest products shall be governed in line with the Convention on
  International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora
  (CITES) and any voluntary partnership agreements to which signatory
  Central African States might adhere individually or collectively with
  the European Community under the European Union's action plan on
  forest law enforcement, governance and trade (FLEGT).</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IV" name="Establishment, Trade In Services And E-Commerce" chapter_identifier="3707">
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Framework" article_identifier="31811">1. The Parties reaffirm their respective commitments under the General
  Agreement on Trade in Services.

  2. The Parties undertake to extend the scope of this Agreement, not
  later than 1 January 2009, by negotiating the necessary provisions for
  the gradual, asymmetrical and reciprocal liberalisation of
  establishment and trade in services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="31812">The Parties, recognising that strengthening trade capacity can support
  the development of economic activities, particularly in the services
  sectors, and strengthen their regulatory framework, reaffirm their
  respective obligations arising from the Cotonou Agreement, in
  particular Articles 34 to 39, 41 to 43, 45 and 74 to 78.

  TRADE-RELATED RULES</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Current Payments And Capital Movements" chapter_identifier="3708">
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Continuation Of Negotiations On Current Payments And Movement Of Capital" article_identifier="31813">1. The Parties recognise the need to guarantee that cross-border flows
  of the funds necessary for the liberalisation of trade in products and
  services, and for investments by one of the Parties in the region of
  the other Party, cannot be restricted or prevented by one of the
  Parties. Any obstacle to these flows would be contrary to the
  objectives of liberalisation, given that trade or investment, although
  itself permissible, could not give rise to payment or financing from
  abroad.

  2. To achieve this objective, the Parties undertake to conclude
  negotiations by 1 January 2009 on a series of issues related to the
  following:

  (a) liberalisation of flows of funds relating to trade in products and
  services, known as "current payments";

  (b) liberalisation of flows of funds relating to
  "investments", known as "movements of capital relating
  to investments", including repatriation of investments and
  profits;

  (c) a safeguard clause, granting a short-term derogation from freedom
  of capital movement, on grounds of serious difficulties as regards
  monetary situation or balance of payments;

  (d) a development clause, providing for the liberalisation of other
  types of capital movements not related to investment.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="3709">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Continuation Of Negotiations On Competition" article_identifier="31814">1. The Parties recognise the importance of free and undistorted
  competition in their trade relations and the fact that certain
  anti-competitive practices may restrict trade between the Parties and
  thus hinder the achievement of the objectives of this Agreement.

  2. The Parties therefore agree to take part in the negotiations on a
  chapter on competition in the EPA, which will include the following in
  particular:

  (a) anti-competitive practices which are considered incompatible with
  the proper functioning of this Agreement, insofar as they can affect
  trade between the Parties;

  (b) provisions on the effective implementation of competition rules
  and policies and of regional policies in Central Africa which govern
  the anti-competitive practices identified in accordance with paragraph
  2(a);

  (c) provisions on technical assistance by independent experts to
  ensure that the Chapter's objectives are achieved and that Central
  Africa's competition policies are properly implemented at regional
  level.

  3. The negotiations shall be based on a two-step approach, first
  applying the rules in the context of regional integration in Central
  Africa and, after a transition period to be determined jointly,
  applying the rules bilaterally.

  4. The negotiations on the competition chapter shall be concluded by 1
  January 2009.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="3710">
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Continuation Of Negotiations On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="31815">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations arising from the
  Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights
  (TRIPs), and recognise the need to ensure an adequate and effective
  level of protection of intellectual, industrial and commercial
  property rights, and other rights covered by the TRIPS Agreement, in
  line with international standards and with a view to reducing
  distortions and impediments to bilateral trade.

  2. With due regard for the powers transferred to the African
  Intellectual Property Organisation (OAPI), the Parties undertake to
  conclude negotiations by 1 January 2009 on a series of commitments
  regarding intellectual property rights.

  3. The Parties also agree to strengthen their cooperation in the area
  of intellectual property rights. Such cooperation shall be directed at
  supporting the implementation of each Party's commitments and shall
  extend to the following areas inter alia:

  (a) reinforcement of regional integration initiatives in Central
  Africa with a view to improving regional regulatory capacity, regional
  laws and regulations;

  (b) prevention of the abuse of such rights by right-holders and the
  infringement of such rights by competitors;

  (c) support in the preparation of national laws and regulations in
  Central Africa for the protection and enforcement of intellectual
  property rights.

  4. The negotiations shall be based on a two-step approach, first
  applying the rules in the context of regional integration in Central
  Africa and, after a transition period to be determined jointly,
  applying the rules bilaterally.

  5. In conducting the negotiations, the different levels of development
  in the signatory Central African States should be taken into account.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Public Procurement" chapter_identifier="3711">
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Continuation Of Negotiations On Public Procurement" article_identifier="31816">1. The Parties recognise the contribution of transparent and
  competitive tendering to economic development. They therefore agree to
  negotiate the gradual and mutual opening of their public procurement
  markets, while recognising their different levels of development,
  under the conditions set out in paragraph 3.

  2. To achieve this objective, the Parties shall conclude negotiations
  by 1 January 2009 on a set of potential commitments on procurement,
  which shall include in particular the following:

  (a) transparent and non-discriminatory rules, procedures and
  principles to be applied;

  (b) lists of the products covered and the thresholds applied;

  (c) effective challenge procedures;

  (d) measures to support capacities to implement these commitments,
  including making use of opportunities created by information
  technologies.

  3. The negotiations shall be based on a two-step approach, first
  applying the rules in the context of regional integration in Central
  Africa and, after a transition period to be determined jointly,
  applying the rules bilaterally.

  4. In conducting the negotiations, the EC Party shall take into
  account the development, financial and trade needs of the signatory
  Central African States, which may take the form of the following
  measures in the interest of special and differential treatment:

  (a) appropriate implementation periods, where required, to bring
  government procurement measures into line with any specific procedural
  requirements;

  (b) adoption or retention of transitional measures such as a price
  preference programme or offset, in accordance with a phasing-out
  schedule.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Sustainable Development" chapter_identifier="3712">
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Continuation Of Negotiations On Sustainable Development" article_identifier="31817">1. The Parties recognise that sustainable development is an overall
  objective of the EPA. They therefore agree to ensure that
  sustainability considerations are reflected in all titles of the EPA
  and to draft specific chapters covering environmental and social
  issues.

  2. To achieve this objective, the Parties shall conclude negotiations
  by 1 January 2009 on a set of potential commitments on sustainable
  development, which shall include in particular the following:

  (a) level of protection and right to regulate;

  (b) regional integration in Central Africa, use of international
  environmental standards and of the International Labour Organisation
  and promotion of decent work;

  (c) upholding levels of protection;

  (d) consultation and monitoring procedures.

  3. In conducting the negotiations, the EC Party shall take into
  account the development needs of the signatory Central African States,
  which may take the form of provisions on cooperation in this field.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Protection Of Personal Data" chapter_identifier="3713">
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Overall Objective" article_identifier="31818">The Parties, recognising:

  (a) their common interest in protecting the fundamental rights and
  freedoms of natural persons, and in particular their right to privacy,
  with respect to the processing of personal data;

  (b) the importance of maintaining effective data protection regimes as
  a means of protecting the interests of consumers, stimulating investor
  confidence and facilitating cross-border flows of personal data;

  (c) the need to collect and process personal data in a transparent and
  fair manner, with due respect accorded to the data subject, agree to
  establish appropriate legal and regulatory regimes, and the
  appropriate administrative capacity to implement them, including
  independent supervisory authorities, in order to ensure an adequate
  level of protection of individuals with regard to the processing of
  personal data, in line with the highest international standards [4].</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Definitions" article_identifier="31819">For the purposes of this Chapter:

  (a) "personal data" shall mean any information relating to
  an identified or identifiable natural person (data subject);

  (b) "processing of personal data" shall mean any operation
  or set of operations which is performed upon personal data, such as
  collection, recording, organisation, storage, alteration, retrieval,
  consultation, use, disclosure, combination, blocking, erasure or
  destruction, as well as transfers of personal data across national
  borders;

  (c) "data controller" shall mean the natural or legal
  person, authority or any other body which determines the purposes and
  means of the processing of personal data.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Principles And General Rules" article_identifier="31820">The Parties agree that the legal and regulatory regimes and
  administrative capacity to be established shall, at a minimum, include
  the following content principles and enforcement mechanisms:

  (a) Content principles

  (i) The purpose limitation principle — data should be processed for a
  specific purpose and subsequently used or further communicated only
  insofar as this is not incompatible with the purpose of the transfer.
  The only exemptions to these rights should be those provided for in
  legislation and necessary in a democratic society for the protection
  of important public interests.

  (ii) The data quality and proportionality principle — data should be
  accurate and, where necessary, kept up to date. The data should be
  adequate, relevant and not excessive in relation to the purposes for
  which they are transferred or further processed.

  (iii) The transparency principle — individuals should be provided with
  information as to the purpose of the processing and the identity of
  the data controller in the third country, and other information
  insofar as this is necessary to ensure fairness. The only exemptions
  to these rights should be those provided for in legislation and
  necessary in a democratic society for the protection of important
  public interests.

  (iv) The security principle — the data controller should take
  technical and organisational security measures that are appropriate to
  the risks presented by the processing. Any person acting under the
  authority of the data controller, including a processor, must not
  process data except on instructions from the controller.

  (v) The rights of access, rectification and opposition — the data
  subject should have the right to obtain a copy of all data relating to
  him/her that are processed, and the right to rectify those data where
  they are shown to be inaccurate. In certain situations he/she should
  also be able to object to the processing of the data relating to
  him/her. The only exemptions to these rights should be those provided
  for in legislation and necessary in a democratic society for the
  protection of important public interests.

  (vi) Restrictions on onward transfers — as a matter of principle,
  further transfers of the personal data by the recipient of the
  original data transfer should be permitted only where the second
  recipient (i.e. the recipient of the onward transfer) is also subject
  to rules affording an adequate level of protection.

  (vii) Sensitive data — where special categories of data are involved,
  revealing racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or
  philosophical beliefs or trade-union membership, data concerning
  health and sex, and data relating to offences, criminal convictions or
  security measures, additional safeguards should be in place.

  (b) Enforcement mechanisms

  Appropriate mechanisms should be in place to ensure that the following
  objectives are achieved:

  (i) to ensure a good level of compliance with the rules, including a
  high degree of awareness among data controllers of their obligations,
  and among data subjects of their rights and the means of exercising
  them; the existence of effective and dissuasive sanctions; and systems
  of verification by authorities, auditors or independent data
  protection officials;

  (ii) to provide support and help to individual data subjects in the
  exercise of their rights, which they must be able to enforce rapidly
  and effectively, and without prohibitive cost, including through an
  appropriate institutional mechanism allowing independent investigation
  of complaints;

  (iii) to provide appropriate redress to the injured party where rules
  are not complied with, allowing compensation to be paid and sanctions
  imposed where appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Consistency With International Commitments" article_identifier="31821">1. The Parties shall keep each other informed, via the EPA Committee,
  of the multilateral commitments and agreements with third countries in
  which they may participate, or of any obligation by which they may be
  bound and which could be relevant to the application of this Chapter,
  and in particular of any agreement providing for the processing of
  personal data, such as personal data being collected, stored or
  accessed by third parties or transferred to third parties.

  2. The Parties may request consultations to discuss any matter which
  may arise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="31822">The Parties acknowledge the importance of cooperation in order to
  facilitate the development of appropriate legislative, judicial and
  institutional frameworks and to ensure an adequate level of protection
  of personal data that is consistent with the objectives and principles
  contained in this Chapter.

  DISPUTE AVOIDANCE AND SETTLEMENT</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Objective And Scope" chapter_identifier="3714">
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Objective" article_identifier="31823">The objective of this Title is to avoid and settle any dispute between
  the Parties with a view to arriving, where possible, at a mutually
  agreed solution.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Scope" article_identifier="31824">1. This Title shall apply to any dispute relating to the
  interpretation or application of this Agreement, except where
  specifically provided otherwise.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the procedure provided for in Article
  98 of the Cotonou Agreement shall be applicable in the case of
  disputes relating to development finance cooperation as defined in the
  Cotonou Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Consultations And Mediation" chapter_identifier="3715">
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Consultations" article_identifier="31825">1. The Parties shall endeavour to resolve disputes under this
  Agreement by entering into good faith consultations with the aim of
  reaching a mutually acceptable solution.

  2. A Party seeking consultations shall do so by means of a written
  request to the other Party, copied to the EPA Committee, identifying
  the measure at issue and the provisions of the Agreement with which it
  considers the measure not to be in conformity.

  3. The consultations shall be held within 40 days of the date on which
  the request is submitted. The consultations shall be deemed concluded
  within 60 days of the date of submission of the request unless both
  Parties agree to continue. All information disclosed during the
  consultations shall remain confidential.

  4. Consultations on matters of urgency, including those regarding
  perishable or seasonal goods, shall be held within 15 days of the date
  of submission of the request, and shall be deemed concluded within 30
  days of the date of submission of the request.

  5. If consultations are not held within the time limits laid down in
  paragraph 3 or paragraph 4 respectively, or if consultations have been
  concluded and no agreement has been reached on a mutually agreed
  solution, the complaining Party may request that an arbitration panel
  be established in accordance with Article 70.

  Article 69⊥

  Mediation</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Procedures For The Settlement Of Disputes" chapter_identifier="3716">
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Initiation Of The Arbitration Procedure" article_identifier="31826">1. Where the Parties have failed to resolve the dispute by recourse to
  consultations as provided for in Article 68, or by recourse to
  mediation as provided for in Article 69, the complaining Party may
  request that an arbitration panel be established.

  2. A request for the establishment of an arbitration panel shall be
  addressed in writing to the Party which is the subject of the
  complaint and to the EPA Committee. The complaining Party shall
  identify in its request the specific measures at issue, and it shall
  explain how such measures constitute a breach of the provisions
  referred to in Article 67.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Establishment Of An Arbitration Panel" article_identifier="31827">1. An arbitration panel shall be composed of three arbitrators.

  2. Within 10 days of the date on which the request for the
  establishment of an arbitration panel is submitted, the Parties shall
  consult each other in order to reach an agreement on the composition
  of the arbitration panel.

  3. In the event that the Parties are unable to agree on the panel's
  composition within the time limit laid down in paragraph 2, either
  Party may request that the chairperson of the EPA Committee, or his or
  her delegate, select all three members by lot from the list drawn up
  under Article 85: one from among the individuals proposed by the
  complaining Party, one from among the individuals proposed by the
  Party complained against and one from among the individuals selected
  by both Parties to act as chairperson. Where the Parties agree on one
  or more of the members of the arbitration panel, any remaining members
  shall be selected by the same procedure.

  4. The chairperson of the EPA Committee, or his or her delegate, shall
  select the arbitrators within five days of the request referred to in
  paragraph 3 being submitted by either Party and in the presence of a
  representative of each Party.

  5. The date of establishment of the arbitration panel shall be the
  date on which the three arbitrators are selected.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Interim Report By The Panel" article_identifier="31828">The arbitration panel shall submit to the Parties an interim report
  containing both the descriptive sections and the panel's findings and
  conclusions, as a general rule not later than 120 days from the date
  of establishment of the arbitration panel. Any Party may submit
  written comments to the arbitration panel on specific aspects of its
  interim report within 15 days of submission of the report.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Arbitration Panel Ruling" article_identifier="31829">1. The arbitration panel shall notify the Parties and the EPA
  Committee of its ruling within 150 days from the date on which the
  arbitration panel is established. Where it considers that this
  deadline cannot be met, the chairperson of the arbitration panel shall
  notify the Parties and the EPA Committee in writing, stating the
  reasons for the delay and the date on which the panel plans to
  conclude its work. Under no circumstances should the ruling be
  notified later than 180 days from the date of establishment of the
  arbitration panel.

  2. In urgent cases, including those involving perishable or seasonal
  goods, the arbitration panel shall make every effort to issue its
  ruling within 75 days of the date of its establishment. Under no
  circumstance should it take longer than 90 days from the date of its
  establishment to issue the ruling. The arbitration panel may give a
  preliminary ruling within ten days of its establishment on whether it
  deems the case to be urgent.

  3. Either Party may ask an arbitration panel to make recommendations
  on how the Party complained against could comply.

  Compliance</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Compliance With The Arbitration Panel Ruling" article_identifier="31830">Each Party or, as appropriate, the signatory Central African States,
  shall take any measure necessary to implement the arbitration panel
  ruling, and the Parties shall endeavour to agree on a deadline for
  compliance with the ruling.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Reasonable Period Of Time For Compliance" article_identifier="31831">1. No later than 30 days after the Parties have been notified of the
  arbitration panel ruling, the Party complained against shall notify
  the complaining Party and the EPA Committee of the time it will
  require for compliance (reasonable period of time).

  2. In the event of disagreement between the Parties on the reasonable
  period of time to comply with the arbitration panel ruling, the
  complaining Party shall, within 20 days of the notification made under
  paragraph 1 by the Party complained against, request in writing that
  the arbitration panel determine the length of the reasonable period of
  time. This request shall be communicated simultaneously to the other
  Party and to the EPA Committee. The arbitration panel shall notify the
  Parties and the EPA Committee of its ruling within 30 days of the date
  of submission of the request.

  3. In determining the length of the reasonable period of time, the
  arbitration panel shall take into consideration the length of time
  that it should take the Party complained against or, as appropriate,
  the signatory Central African States, to adopt comparable legislative
  or administrative measures to those identified by the Party complained
  against or, as appropriate, the signatory Central African States, as
  being necessary to ensure compliance. The arbitration panel may also
  take into consideration demonstrable capacity constraints which may
  affect the adoption of the necessary measures by the Party complained
  against.

  4. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures set out in Article
  71 shall apply. The deadline for issuing a ruling shall be 45 days
  from the date of submission of the request referred to in paragraph 2
  of this Article.

  5. The reasonable period may be extended by mutual agreement of the
  Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Review Of Measures Taken To Comply With The Arbitration Panel Ruling" article_identifier="31832">1. The Party complained against shall notify the other Party and the
  EPA Committee, before the end of the reasonable period of time, of any
  measure that it has taken to comply with the arbitration panel ruling.

  2. In the event of disagreement between the Parties concerning the
  compatibility of any measure notified under paragraph 1 with the
  provisions of this Agreement, the complaining Party may request in
  writing that the arbitration panel rule on the matter. Such request
  shall identify the specific measure at issue and explain how such
  measure is incompatible with the provisions of this Agreement. The
  arbitration panel shall issue its ruling within 90 days of the date of
  submission of the request. In urgent cases, including those involving
  perishable or seasonal goods, the arbitration panel shall issue its
  ruling within 45 days of the date of submission of the request.

  3. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures set out in Article
  71 shall apply. The period for issuing the ruling shall be 105 days
  from the date of submission of the request referred to in paragraph 2
  of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Temporary Provisions In Case Of Non-Compliance" article_identifier="31833">1. If the Party complained against fails to give notification of any
  measure taken to comply with the arbitration panel ruling before the
  expiry of the reasonable period of time, or if the arbitration panel
  rules that the measures notified under Article 76(1) are not
  compatible with that Party's obligations under the provisions of this
  Agreement, the Party complained against or, as appropriate, the
  signatory Central African State concerned shall, if so requested by
  the complaining Party, present an offer for temporary compensation.
  This compensation may include or consist of financial compensation.
  However, nothing in this Agreement shall oblige the Party complained
  against or, as appropriate, the signatory Central African State
  concerned, to offer such financial compensation.

  2. If no agreement on compensation is reached within 30 days of the
  end of the reasonable period of time or of the arbitration panel's
  ruling under Article 76 that a measure taken to comply is not
  compatible with the provisions of this Agreement, the complaining
  Party shall be entitled, after notifying the other Party, to adopt
  appropriate measures. These measures may be adopted by the complaining
  Party or, as appropriate, the signatory Central African State
  concerned.

  3. In adopting these measures, the complaining Party or, as
  appropriate, the signatory Central African State concerned, shall aim
  to select measures proportionate to the infringement which least
  affect the achievement of this Agreement's objectives and take into
  consideration their impact on the economy of the Party complained
  against and on the various signatory Central African States.

  4. The EC Party shall show restraint when asking for compensation or
  adopting appropriate measures in accordance with paragraph 1 or 2 of
  this Article.

  5. The compensation or appropriate measures shall be temporary and
  shall be applied only until any measure found to violate the
  provisions of this Agreement has been withdrawn or amended so as to
  bring it into conformity with those provisions or until the Parties
  have agreed to settle the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Review Of Measures Taken To Comply Following The Adoption Of Appropriate Measures" article_identifier="31834">1. The Party complained against shall notify the other Party and the
  EPA Committee of any measure it has taken to comply with the
  arbitration panel ruling and, in that notification, request an end to
  the application of appropriate measures by the complaining Party or,
  as appropriate, the signatory Central African State concerned.

  2. If the Parties do not reach an agreement, within 30 days of the
  date of submission of the notification, on the compatibility of the
  notified measures with the provisions of this Agreement, the
  complaining Party shall request in writing that the arbitration panel
  rule on the matter. The other Party and the EPA Committee shall be
  notified of the request. The Parties and the EPA Committee shall be
  notified of the arbitration panel ruling within 45 days of submission
  of the request. If the arbitration panel rules that any measure taken
  to comply is not in conformity with the relevant provisions of this
  Agreement, the arbitration panel shall determine whether the
  complaining Party or, as appropriate, the signatory Central African
  State concerned may continue to apply appropriate measures. If the
  arbitration panel rules that any measure taken to comply is in
  conformity with the provisions referred to in Article 67, the
  appropriate measures shall be terminated.

  3. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures laid down in
  Article 71 shall apply. The period for issuing the ruling shall be 60
  days from the date of submission of the request referred to in
  paragraph 2 of this Article.

  Common provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Mutually Agreed Solution" article_identifier="31835">Under this Title the Parties may at any time reach a mutually agreed
  solution to a dispute. They shall notify the EPA Committee of any such
  solution. When a mutually agreed solution is adopted, the procedure
  must be terminated.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Rules Of Procedure And Code Of Conduct" article_identifier="31836">1. Dispute settlement procedures under Chapter 3 shall be governed by
  the rules of procedure and code of conduct to be adopted by the EPA
  Committee.

  2. Meetings of the arbitration panel shall be open to the public in
  accordance with the rules of procedure, which also provide for the
  protection of confidential business information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Information And Technical Advice" article_identifier="31837">At the request of a Party, or upon its own initiative, the arbitration
  panel may obtain information from any source, including the Parties
  involved in the dispute, which it deems appropriate for the
  arbitration procedure. The arbitration panel also has the right to
  seek the opinion of experts as it deems appropriate. Any information
  obtained in this manner must be disclosed to each of the Parties and
  submitted for their comments. Interested parties are authorised to
  submit amicus curiae briefs to the arbitration panel in accordance
  with the rules of procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Languages For Communications" article_identifier="31838">The written and oral submissions of the Central Africa Party shall be
  made in French and English, and those of the European Communities in
  any of the official languages of the institutions of the European
  Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Rules Of Interpretation" article_identifier="31839">Any arbitration panel shall interpret the provisions of this Agreement
  in accordance with customary rules of interpretation of public
  international law, including the Vienna Convention on the Law of
  Treaties. The rulings of the arbitration panel cannot add to or
  diminish the rights and obligations provided for in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Arbitration Panel Rulings" article_identifier="31840">1. The arbitration panel shall make every effort to reach its
  decisions by consensus. Where, nevertheless, a decision cannot be
  arrived at by consensus, the matter at issue shall be decided by
  majority vote. However, under no circumstances shall the dissenting
  opinions of arbitrators be published.

  2. The ruling shall set out the findings of fact, the applicability of
  the relevant provisions of this Agreement and the basic rationale
  behind any findings and conclusions of the arbitration panel. The EPA
  Committee shall make the arbitration panel ruling publicly available
  unless it decides not to do so.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="3717">
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="List Of Arbitrators" article_identifier="31841">1. The EPA Committee shall, no later than six months after this
  Agreement's entry into force, establish a list of 15 individuals who
  are willing and able to serve as arbitrators. Each of the Parties
  shall select five individuals to serve as arbitrators. The two Parties
  shall also agree on five individuals who are not nationals of either
  Party and who may be called upon to act as chairperson to the
  arbitration panel. The EPA Committee shall ensure that a full list is
  always maintained.

  2. Arbitrators shall have specialised knowledge or experience of law
  and international trade. They shall be independent, serve in their
  individual capacities and not take instructions from any organisation
  or government or be affiliated with the government of any of the
  Parties, and shall comply with the code of conduct adopted by the EPA
  Committee.

  3. The EPA Committee may draw up an additional list of 15 individuals
  with sectoral expertise in specific matters covered by the Agreement.
  Where recourse is made to the selection procedure under Article 71(2),
  the chairperson of the EPA Committee may use this type of sectoral
  list with the agreement of both Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Relationship To Wto Obligations" article_identifier="31842">1. Arbitration bodies set up under this Agreement shall not adjudicate
  disputes concerning each Party's rights and obligations under the
  Agreement establishing the WTO.

  2. Recourse to the dispute settlement provisions of this Agreement
  shall be without prejudice to any action in the WTO framework,
  including dispute settlement action. However, where a Party or, as
  appropriate, the signatory Central African States has/have instituted
  a dispute settlement proceeding with regard to a particular measure,
  either under Article 70(1) or under the WTO Agreement, it/they may not
  institute a dispute settlement proceeding with regard to the same
  measure in the other forum until the first proceeding has ended. For
  the purposes of this paragraph, dispute settlement proceedings under
  the WTO Agreement shall be deemed to be initiated by the request of a
  Party or, as appropriate, of the signatory Central African States for
  the establishment of a panel under Article 6 of the Understanding on
  Rules and Procedures Governing the Settlement of Disputes of the WTO.

  3. Nothing in this Agreement shall preclude a Party or, as
  appropriate, the signatory Central African States from implementing
  the suspension of obligations authorised by the Dispute Settlement
  Body of the WTO.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Time Limits" article_identifier="31843">1. All time limits laid down in this Title, including the deadlines
  for the arbitration panels to issue their rulings, shall be counted in
  calendar days from the day following the act or fact to which they
  refer.

  2. Any time limit provided for in this Title may be extended by mutual
  agreement of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Amendment Of Title Vi" article_identifier="31844">The EPA Committee may decide to amend this Title and its Annexes.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VII" name="General Exceptions" chapter_identifier="3718">
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="General Exception Clause" article_identifier="31845">Subject to the requirement that such measures are not to be applied in
  a manner which would constitute a means of arbitrary or unjustifiable
  discrimination between the Parties where like conditions must prevail,
  or a disguised restriction on trade in goods, services or
  establishment, nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to prevent
  the adoption or enforcement by the Parties of measures which:

  (a) are necessary to protect public security or public morality or to
  maintain public order;

  (b) are necessary to protect the health or life of humans, animals or
  plants;

  (c) are necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations which
  are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement, including
  those relating to:

  (i) prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or ways of
  dealing with the effects of a default on contracts;

  (ii) protection of the privacy of individuals in relation to the
  processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of
  confidentiality of individual records and accounts;

  (iii) security;

  (iv) the application of customs regulations and procedures; or

  (v) protection of intellectual property rights;

  (d) relate to imports or exports of gold or silver;

  (e) are necessary to protect national treasures of artistic,
  historical or archaeological value;

  (f) relate to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources if
  such measures involve restrictions on domestic production or
  consumption of goods or the provision or consumption of domestic
  services, and on domestic investors;

  (g) relate to the products of prison labour; or

  (h) are inconsistent with the articles of this Agreement on national
  treatment, provided that the difference in treatment is intended to
  ensure the effective or equitable imposition or collection of direct
  taxes in respect of the economic activities of investors or of service
  providers of the other Party [5].</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="31846">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed:

  (a) to require the Parties to furnish any information the disclosure
  of which they consider contrary to their essential security interests;

  (b) to prevent the Parties from taking any action which they consider
  necessary for the protection of their essential security interests:

  (i) relating to fissionable and fusionable materials or the materials
  from which they are derived;

  (ii) relating to economic activities carried out directly or
  indirectly for the purpose of supplying or provisioning a military
  establishment;

  (iii) relating to the production of, or trade in, arms, munitions or
  war materials;

  (iv) relating to government procurement indispensable for national
  security or for national defence purposes; or

  (v) taken in time of war or other emergency in international
  relations; or

  (c) to prevent the Parties from taking any action in pursuance of the
  obligations they accepted in order to maintain international peace and
  security.

  2. The EPA Committee shall be informed to the fullest extent possible
  of measures taken under paragraphs 1(b) and 1(c) and of their
  termination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Taxation" article_identifier="31847">1. Nothing in this Agreement or in any agreement adopted in
  implementation of this Agreement shall be construed to prevent the
  Parties from distinguishing, in the application of the relevant
  provisions of their fiscal legislation, between taxpayers who are not
  in the same situation, in particular with regard to their place of
  residence or with regard to the place where their capital is invested.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement or in any agreement adopted in
  implementation of this Agreement shall be construed to prevent the
  adoption or enforcement of any measure intended to prevent the
  avoidance or evasion of taxes pursuant to the tax provisions of
  agreements to avoid double taxation or other tax agreements or
  domestic fiscal legislation.

  3. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations
  of the Parties under any tax convention. In the event of any
  inconsistency between this Agreement and any such convention, that
  convention shall prevail to the extent of the inconsistency.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VIII" name="General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="3719">
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Epa Committee" article_identifier="31848">1. To implement this Agreement, an EPA Committee shall be set up
  within three months of the signature of this Agreement.

  2. The Parties agree on the composition, organisation and functioning
  of the EPA Committee.

  3. The EPA Committee shall be responsible for the administration of
  all areas covered by this Agreement and for the completion of all
  tasks referred to in this Agreement.

  4. The EPA Committee shall reach its decisions by consensus.

  5. In order to facilitate communication and ensure the effective
  implementation of this Agreement, each Party shall designate a focal
  point.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Regional Organisations" article_identifier="31849">The Commission of the Economic and Monetary Community of Central
  Africa (CEMAC) and the General Secretariat of the Economic Community
  of Central African States (CEEAC) shall be invited to attend all
  meetings of the EPA Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Continuation Of Negotiations And Implementation Of The Agreement" article_identifier="31850">1. The Parties shall continue the negotiations in accordance with the
  schedule set out in this Agreement, within the existing negotiation
  structures.

  2. When the negotiations are concluded, the resulting draft amendments
  shall be submitted to the relevant national authorities for approval.

  3. Pending the establishment of the EPA Committee and of other
  institutions and committees of relevance for the full EPA referred to
  in Article 1, the Parties shall take the necessary measures for the
  administration and implementation of this Agreement and carry out the
  tasks of the EPA Committee each time reference is made to this
  Committee in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Definition Of The Parties And Fulfilment Of Obligations" article_identifier="31851">1. The Contracting Parties to this Agreement shall be the Republic of
  Cameroon [hereinafter "Central Africa Party"], of the one
  part, and the European Community or its Member States or the European
  Community and its Member States, within their respective areas of
  competence as derived from the Treaty establishing the European
  Community [hereinafter "EC Party"], of the other part.

  2. For the purposes of this Agreement, the Central Africa Party agrees
  to act collectively.

  3. For the purposes of this Agreement, "Party" shall refer
  to the Central African States acting collectively or the EC Party, as
  appropriate. "Parties" shall refer to the Central African
  States acting collectively and the EC Party.

  4. In cases where individual action is provided for or required to
  exercise rights or comply with obligations under this Agreement,
  reference is made to the "signatory Central African States".

  5. The Parties or the signatory Central African States, as
  appropriate, shall adopt any general or specific measures required for
  them to fulfil their obligations under this Agreement and shall ensure
  that they comply with the objectives laid down in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Coordinators And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="31852">1. In order to facilitate communication and ensure the effective
  implementation of this Agreement, each Party shall designate a
  coordinator upon this Agreement's entry into force. The designation of
  coordinators shall be without prejudice to the specific designation of
  competent authorities under specific titles or chapters of this
  Agreement.

  2. At the request of either Party, the coordinator of the other Party
  shall indicate the office or official responsible for any matter
  pertaining to the implementation of the Agreement and provide the
  support necessary to facilitate communication with the requesting
  Party.

  3. At the request of either Party, and to the extent legally possible,
  each Party through its coordinator shall provide information and reply
  promptly to any question from the other Party relating to an actual or
  proposed measure or an international agreement that might affect trade
  between the Parties.

  4. Each Party shall ensure that its laws, regulations, procedures and
  administrative rulings of general application relating to any trade
  matter covered by this Agreement are promptly published or made
  publicly available and brought to the attention of the other Party.

  5. Without prejudice to specific transparency provisions in this
  Agreement, the information referred to under this Article shall be
  considered to have been provided when the information has been made
  available by appropriate notification to the WTO or when the
  information has been made available on the official, public and
  fee-free website of the Party concerned.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Regional Preference" article_identifier="31853">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall oblige a Party to extend to the
  other Party to this Agreement any more favourable treatment than that
  applied within each of the Parties as part of its respective regional
  integration process.

  2. Any more favourable treatment or advantage that may be granted
  under this Agreement by any signatory Central African State to the
  European Community shall immediately and unconditionally also be
  enjoyed by each signatory Central African State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="31854">1. This Agreement shall be signed, ratified or approved in accordance
  with constitutional or domestic rules and applicable procedures.

  2. This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the month
  following that in which the depositories of the Agreement have been
  notified of the last instrument of ratification, acceptance or
  approval.

  3. Notifications shall be sent to the Secretary-General of the Council
  of the European Union and the President of the Commission of the
  Economic and Monetary Community of Central Africa, who shall be the
  depositories of this Agreement.

  4. Pending this Agreement's entry into force, the EC Party and the
  Central Africa Party agree to apply the provisions of this Agreement
  in accordance with their respective powers ("provisional
  application"). This may be done either by provisional
  application, where such application is possible, or via ratification
  of the Agreement.

  5. The depositories of the Agreement shall be notified of such
  provisional application. The Agreement shall be applied provisionally
  10 days after receipt of this notification of provisional application
  by the European Community and after receipt of the notification,
  either by ratification or by provisional application, by all signatory
  Central African States.

  6. Notwithstanding paragraph 4, the EC Party and the signatory Central
  African States may unilaterally take measures to apply the Agreement,
  before provisional application, to the extent that this is possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Duration" article_identifier="31855">1. This Agreement is concluded for an unlimited period.

  2. Either Party, or a signatory Central African State, may give
  written notice to the other Party of its intention to denounce this
  Agreement.

  3. Denunciation shall take effect six months after the other Party has
  been notified.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Territorial Application" article_identifier="31856">This Agreement shall apply to the territories in which the Treaty
  establishing the European Community is applied and under the
  conditions laid down in that Treaty, and to the territories of the
  signatory Central African States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Accession Of States Or Of Regional Organisations In Central Africa" article_identifier="31857">1. This Agreement shall be open to accession by any State or regional
  organisation in Central Africa. A request for accession shall be
  submitted to the EPA Committee. Any State which submits a request for
  accession shall attend the meetings of the EPA Committee as an
  observer.

  2. The request shall be examined and negotiations begun in order to
  propose the necessary amendments to this Agreement. The accession
  protocol shall be submitted to the competent authorities for approval.

  3. The Parties shall examine the effects of the accession on this
  Agreement. The EPA Committee may rule on the transitional measures or
  the necessary amendments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Accession Of New Member States To The European Union" article_identifier="31858">1. The EPA Committee shall be informed of any application from a third
  country to join the European Union. During the negotiations between
  the European Union and the candidate country, the EC Party shall
  provide the Central Africa Party with any relevant information, and
  the Central Africa Party shall inform the EC Party of its concerns so
  that they can be taken fully into account. The Central Africa Party
  shall be notified of any accession to the European Union (EU).

  2. Any new Member State of the European Union shall accede to this
  Agreement as of the date of its accession to the European Union by
  means of a clause to this effect in the Act of Accession. If the act
  of accession to the European Union does not provide for such automatic
  accession of the new EU Member State to this Agreement, the Member
  State concerned shall accede to this Agreement by depositing an act of
  accession with the General Secretariat of the Council of the European
  Union, which shall send certified copies to the Central Africa Party.

  3. The Parties shall review the effects of the accession of new Member
  States of the European Union on this Agreement. The EPA Committee may
  rule on any transitional measures or amendments necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Outermost Regions Of The European Community" article_identifier="31859">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent the EC Party from applying
  existing measures to improve the structural, social and economic
  situation of the outermost regions in accordance with Article 299(2)
  of the Treaty establishing the European Community.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Dialogue On Financial Matters" article_identifier="31860">The Parties and the signatory Central African States agree to promote
  dialogue and transparency and to share best practice on tax policy and
  administration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Collaboration In Tackling Illegal Financial Activities" article_identifier="31861">The Parties undertake to prevent and tackle fraudulent and corrupt
  illegal activities, money laundering and the financing of terrorism,
  and shall take the necessary legislative and administrative measures
  to comply with international standards, including those set out in the
  United Nations Convention against Corruption, the United Nations
  Convention against Transnational Organised Crime and its Protocols,
  the United Nations Convention for the Suppression of the Financing of
  Terrorism and the recommendations of the Financial Action Task Force.
  The Parties agree to exchange information and to cooperate in these
  areas.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Relationship To Other Agreements" article_identifier="31862">1. With the exception of the Articles on development cooperation
  provided for in Part III, Title II, of the Cotonou Agreement, in the
  event of inconsistency between the provisions of this Agreement and
  the provisions of Part III, Title II, of the Cotonou Agreement, the
  provisions of this Agreement shall take precedence.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed so as to prevent the
  adoption by the European Community or by one of the signatory Central
  African States of any measures, including trade measures, deemed
  appropriate as provided for under Articles 11b, 96 and 97 of the
  Cotonou Agreement.

  3. The Parties agree that nothing in this Agreement requires them to
  act in a manner inconsistent with their WTO obligations.

  4. The Parties agree to examine, in 2008, whether the provisions of
  this Agreement are consistent with the customs unions to which the
  signatories to this Agreement belong.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Authentic Texts" article_identifier="31863">This Agreement shall be drawn up in duplicate in the Bulgarian, Czech,
  Danish, Dutch, English, Estonian, Finnish, French, German, Greek,
  Hungarian, Italian, Latvian, Lithuanian, Maltese, Polish, Portuguese,
  Romanian, Slovak, Slovenian, Spanish and Swedish languages, each text
  being equally authentic.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Annexes And Protocol" article_identifier="31864">The Annexes and the Protocol to this Agreement shall form an integral
  part thereof.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="3720">
      <article article_identifier="31865">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have affixed
  their signatures below this Agreement.

  Съставено съответно в Яунде на петнадесети януари две хиляди и девета
  година и в Брюксел на двадесет и втори януари две хиляди и девета
  година.

  Hecho en Yaundé el quince de enero de dos mil nueve, y en Bruselas el
  veintidós de enero de dos mil nueve.

  V Yaoundé dne patnáctého ledna dva tisíce devět a v Bruselu dne
  dvacátého druhého ledna dva tisíce devět.

  Udfærdiget henholdsvis i Yaoundé, den femtende januar to tusind og ni,
  og i Bruxelles, den toogtyvende januar to tusind og ni.

  Geschehen zu Jaunde am fünfzehnten Januar zweitausendneun und zu
  Brüssel am zweiundzwanzigsten Januar zweitausendneun.

  Sõlmitud vastavalt viieteistkümnendal jaanuaril kahe tuhande
  üheksandal aastal Yaoundés ja kahekümne teisel jaanuaril kahe tuhande
  üheksandal aastal Brüsselis.

  Έγινε στο Γιαουντέ στις δεκαπέντε Ιανουαρίου δύο χιλιάδες εννιά και
  στις Βρυξέλλες στις είκοσι δύο Ιανουαρίου δύο χιλιάδες εννιά.

  Done at Yaoundé on the fifteenth day of January, two thousand and nine
  and at Brussels on the twenty-second day of January, two thousand and
  nine, respectively.

  Fait respectivement à Yaoundé le quinze janvier deux mille neuf et à
  Bruxelles le vingt-deux janvier deux mille neuf.

  Fatto a Yaoundé, il quindici gennaio duemilanove, e a Bruxelles, il
  ventidue gennaio duemilanove, rispettivamente.

  Jaundē, divtūkstoš devītā gada piecpadsmitajā janvārī, un Briselē,
  divtūkstoš devītā gada divdesmit otrajā janvārī.

  Pasirašyta atitinkamai Jaundėje du tūkstančiai devintųjų metų sausio
  15 d. ir Briuselyje du tūkstančiai devintųjų metų sausio 22 d.

  Kelt Yaoundéban, a kettőezerkilencedik év január havának tizenötödik
  napján, illetve Brüsszelben, a kettőezerkilencedik év január havának
  huszonkettedik napján.

  Magħmul f'Yaoundé fil-ħmistax-il jum ta' Jannar tas-sena elfejn u
  disgħa u fi Brussell fit-tnejn u għoxrin jum ta' Jannar tas-sena
  elfejn u disgħa, rispettivament.

  Gedaan te Yaoundé, vijftien januari tweeduizend negen, respectievelijk
  te Brussel, tweeëntwintig januari tweeduizend negen.

  Sporządzono, odpowiednio, w Jaunde dnia piętnastego stycznia dwa
  tysiące dziewiątego roku i w Brukseli dnia dwudziestego drugiego
  stycznia dwa tysiące dziewiątego roku.

  Feito em Iaundé, em quinze de Janeiro de dois mil e nove, e em
  Bruxelas, em vinte e dois de Janeiro de dois mil e nove.

  Încheiat la Yaoundé în a cincisprezecea zi a lunii ianuarie două mii
  nouă şi, respectiv, la Bruxelles în a douăzeci şi doua zi a lunii
  ianuarie două mii nouă.

  V Yaoundé pätnásteho januára dvetisícdeväť a v Bruseli dvadsiateho
  druhého januára dvetisícdeväť.

  V Yaoundeju, petnajstega januarja dva tisoč devet, in v Bruslju,
  dvaindvajsetega januarja dva tisoč devet.

  Tehty Yaoundéssa viidentenätoista päivänä tammikuuta vuonna
  kaksituhattayhdeksän ja Brysselissä kahdentenakymmenentenätoisena
  päivänä tammikuuta vuonna kaksituhattayhdeksän.

  Utfärdat i Yaoundé den femtonde januari tjugohundranio samt i Bryssel
  den tjugoandra januari tjugohundranio.

  Pour la République du Cameroun

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  За Европейската общност

  Por la Comunidad Europea

  Za Evropské společenství

  For Det Europæiske Fællesskab

  Für die Europäische Gemeinschaft

  Euroopa Ühenduse nimel

  Για την Ευρωπαϊκή Κοινότητα

  For the European Community

  Pour la Communauté européenne

  Per la Comunità europea

  Eiropas Kopienas vārdā

  Europos bendrijos vardu

  az Európai Közösség részéről

  Għall-Komunità Ewropea

  Voor de Europese Gemeenschap

  W imieniu Wspólnoty Europejskiej

  Pela Comunidade Europeia

  Pentru Comunitatea Europeană

  Za Európske spoločenstvo

  za Evropsko skupnost

  Euroopan yhteisön puolesta

  På Europeiska gemenskapens vägnar

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Voor het Koninkrijk België

  Pour le Royaume de Belgique

  Für das Königreich Belgien

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Deze handtekening verbindt eveneens de Vlaamse Gemeenschap, de Franse
  Gemeenschap, de Duitstalige Gemeenschap, het Vlaamse Gewest, het
  Waalse Gewest en het Brussels Hoofdstedelijk Gewest.

  Cette signature engage également la Communauté française, la
  Communauté flamande, la Communauté germanophone, la Région wallonne,
  la Région flamande et la Région de Bruxelles-Capitale.

  Diese Unterschrift bindet zugleich die Deutschsprachige Gemeinschaft,
  die Flämische Gemeinschaft, die Französische Gemeinschaft, die
  Wallonische Region, die Flämische Region und die Region
  Brüssel-Hauptstadt.

  За Република България

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Za Českou republiku

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  På Kongeriget Danmarks vegne

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Für die Bundesrepublik Deutschland

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Eesti Vabariigi nimel

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Thar cheann Na hÉireann

  For Ireland

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Για την Ελληνική Δημοκρατία

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Por el Reino de España

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Pour la République française

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Per la Repubblica italiana

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Για την Κυπριακή Δημοκρατία

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Latvijas Republikas vārdā

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Lietuvos Respublikos vardu

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Pour le Grand-Duché de Luxembourg

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  A Magyar Köztársaság részéről

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Għal Malta

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Voor het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Für die Republik Österreich

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  W imieniu Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Pela República Portuguesa

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Pentru România

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Za Republiko Slovenijo

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Za Slovenskú republiku

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  Suomen tasavallan puolesta

  För Republiken Finland

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  För Konungariket Sverige

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  For the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland

  +++++ TIFF +++++

  [1] Member States not included.

  [2] For this calculation, official WTO data on the world's leading
  exporters of products (excluding intra-EU trade) shall be used.

  [3] For the purposes of this Article, agricultural products shall be
  those covered by Annex I of the WTO Agreement on Agriculture.

  [4] Standards to be taken into account include the following
  international instruments:(i)Guidelines on computerised personal data
  files, as amended by the United Nations General Assembly on 20
  November 1990.(ii)Recommendation of the OECD Council of 23 September
  1980 concerning guidelines governing the protection of privacy and
  trans-border flows of personal data.

  [5] Measures aimed at ensuring the effective or equitable imposition
  or collection of direct taxes shall include measures taken by one of
  the Parties under its tax system which:(i)apply to non-resident
  investors and service providers in recognition of the fact that the
  tax obligation of non-residents is determined with respect to taxable
  entities outsourcing from or located in the territory of one of the
  Parties;(ii)apply to non-residents in order to ensure the imposition
  or collection of taxes in the territory of one of the
  Parties;(iii)apply to non-residents or residents in order to prevent
  tax evasion or avoidance, including measures taken to comply;(iv)apply
  to consumers of services supplied in or from the territory of the
  other Party in order to ensure the imposition or collection of taxes
  on such consumers derived from sources in the territory of one of the
  Parties;(v)distinguish investors and service providers subject to
  taxes on global taxable entities from other investors and service
  providers, in recognition of the differences between their tax bases;
  or(vi)determine, allocate or apportion income, profit, gain, loss,
  deduction or credit of resident persons or branches, or between
  related persons or branches of the same person, in order to safeguard
  the Parties' tax bases.

  --------------------------------------------------</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
