<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EC Treaty</name>
    <type>Customs Union &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>120</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>110</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>1957-03-25</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1958-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1957-04-24</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>1970-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">NLD</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:12012M/TXT</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1234">
      <article article_identifier="10068">Consolidated version of the Treaty on European Union

  PREAMBLE

  HIS MAJESTY THE KING OF THE BELGIANS, HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN OF
  DENMARK, THE PRESIDENT OF THE FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY, THE
  PRESIDENT OF IRELAND, THE PRESIDENT OF THE HELLENIC REPUBLIC, HIS
  MAJESTY THE KING OF SPAIN, THE PRESIDENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC, THE
  PRESIDENT OF THE ITALIAN REPUBLIC, HIS ROYAL HIGHNESS THE GRAND DUKE
  OF LUXEMBOURG, HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN OF THE NETHERLANDS, THE PRESIDENT
  OF THE PORTUGUESE REPUBLIC, HER MAJESTY THE QUEEN OF THE UNITED
  KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND [1],

  RESOLVED to mark a new stage in the process of European integration
  undertaken with the establishment of the European Communities,

  DRAWING INSPIRATION from the cultural, religious and humanist
  inheritance of Europe, from which have developed the universal values
  of the inviolable and inalienable rights of the human person, freedom,
  democracy, equality and the rule of law,

  RECALLING the historic importance of the ending of the division of the
  European continent and the need to create firm bases for the
  construction of the future Europe,

  CONFIRMING their attachment to the principles of liberty, democracy
  and respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms and of the rule
  of law,

  CONFIRMING their attachment to fundamental social rights as defined in
  the European Social Charter signed at Turin on 18 October 1961 and in
  the 1989 Community Charter of the Fundamental Social Rights of
  Workers,

  DESIRING to deepen the solidarity between their peoples while
  respecting their history, their culture and their traditions,

  DESIRING to enhance further the democratic and efficient functioning
  of the institutions so as to enable them better to carry out, within a
  single institutional framework, the tasks entrusted to them,

  RESOLVED to achieve the strengthening and the convergence of their
  economies and to establish an economic and monetary union including,
  in accordance with the provisions of this Treaty and of the Treaty on
  the Functioning of the European Union, a single and stable currency,

  DETERMINED to promote economic and social progress for their peoples,
  taking into account the principle of sustainable development and
  within the context of the accomplishment of the internal market and of
  reinforced cohesion and environmental protection, and to implement
  policies ensuring that advances in economic integration are
  accompanied by parallel progress in other fields,

  RESOLVED to establish a citizenship common to nationals of their
  countries,

  RESOLVED to implement a common foreign and security policy including
  the progressive framing of a common defence policy, which might lead
  to a common defence in accordance with the provisions of Article 42,
  thereby reinforcing the European identity and its independence in
  order to promote peace, security and progress in Europe and in the
  world,

  RESOLVED to facilitate the free movement of persons, while ensuring
  the safety and security of their peoples, by establishing an area of
  freedom, security and justice, in accordance with the provisions of
  this Treaty and of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European
  Union,

  RESOLVED to continue the process of creating an ever closer union
  among the peoples of Europe, in which decisions are taken as closely
  as possible to the citizen in accordance with the principle of
  subsidiarity,

  IN VIEW of further steps to be taken in order to advance European
  integration,

  HAVE DECIDED to establish a European Union and to this end have
  designated as their Plenipotentiaries:

  (List of plenipotentiaries not reproduced)

  WHO, having exchanged their full powers, found in good and due form,
  have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="Common Provisions" chapter_identifier="1235">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="10069">By this Treaty, the HIGH CONTRACTING PARTIES establish among
  themselves a EUROPEAN UNION, hereinafter called "the Union",
  on which the Member States confer competences to attain objectives
  they have in common.

  This Treaty marks a new stage in the process of creating an ever
  closer union among the peoples of Europe, in which decisions are taken
  as openly as possible and as closely as possible to the citizen.

  The Union shall be founded on the present Treaty and on the Treaty on
  the Functioning of the European Union (hereinafter referred to as
  "the Treaties"). Those two Treaties shall have the same
  legal value. The Union shall replace and succeed the European
  Community.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="10070">The Union is founded on the values of respect for human dignity,
  freedom, democracy, equality, the rule of law and respect for human
  rights, including the rights of persons belonging to minorities. These
  values are common to the Member States in a society in which
  pluralism, non-discrimination, tolerance, justice, solidarity and
  equality between women and men prevail.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="10071">1. The Union's aim is to promote peace, its values and the well-being
  of its peoples.

  2. The Union shall offer its citizens an area of freedom, security and
  justice without internal frontiers, in which the free movement of
  persons is ensured in conjunction with appropriate measures with
  respect to external border controls, asylum, immigration and the
  prevention and combating of crime.

  3. The Union shall establish an internal market. It shall work for the
  sustainable development of Europe based on balanced economic growth
  and price stability, a highly competitive social market economy,
  aiming at full employment and social progress, and a high level of
  protection and improvement of the quality of the environment. It shall
  promote scientific and technological advance.

  It shall combat social exclusion and discrimination, and shall promote
  social justice and protection, equality between women and men,
  solidarity between generations and protection of the rights of the
  child.

  It shall promote economic, social and territorial cohesion, and
  solidarity among Member States.

  It shall respect its rich cultural and linguistic diversity, and shall
  ensure that Europe's cultural heritage is safeguarded and enhanced.

  4. The Union shall establish an economic and monetary union whose
  currency is the euro.

  5. In its relations with the wider world, the Union shall uphold and
  promote its values and interests and contribute to the protection of
  its citizens. It shall contribute to peace, security, the sustainable
  development of the Earth, solidarity and mutual respect among peoples,
  free and fair trade, eradication of poverty and the protection of
  human rights, in particular the rights of the child, as well as to the
  strict observance and the development of international law, including
  respect for the principles of the United Nations Charter.

  6. The Union shall pursue its objectives by appropriate means
  commensurate with the competences which are conferred upon it in the
  Treaties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="10072">1. In accordance with Article 5, competences not conferred upon the
  Union in the Treaties remain with the Member States.

  2. The Union shall respect the equality of Member States before the
  Treaties as well as their national identities, inherent in their
  fundamental structures, political and constitutional, inclusive of
  regional and local self-government. It shall respect their essential
  State functions, including ensuring the territorial integrity of the
  State, maintaining law and order and safeguarding national security.
  In particular, national security remains the sole responsibility of
  each Member State.

  3. Pursuant to the principle of sincere cooperation, the Union and the
  Member States shall, in full mutual respect, assist each other in
  carrying out tasks which flow from the Treaties.

  The Member States shall take any appropriate measure, general or
  particular, to ensure fulfilment of the obligations arising out of the
  Treaties or resulting from the acts of the institutions of the Union.

  The Member States shall facilitate the achievement of the Union's
  tasks and refrain from any measure which could jeopardise the
  attainment of the Union's objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="10073">1. The limits of Union competences are governed by the principle of
  conferral. The use of Union competences is governed by the principles
  of subsidiarity and proportionality.

  2. Under the principle of conferral, the Union shall act only within
  the limits of the competences conferred upon it by the Member States
  in the Treaties to attain the objectives set out therein. Competences
  not conferred upon the Union in the Treaties remain with the Member
  States.

  3. Under the principle of subsidiarity, in areas which do not fall
  within its exclusive competence, the Union shall act only if and in so
  far as the objectives of the proposed action cannot be sufficiently
  achieved by the Member States, either at central level or at regional
  and local level, but can rather, by reason of the scale or effects of
  the proposed action, be better achieved at Union level.

  The institutions of the Union shall apply the principle of
  subsidiarity as laid down in the Protocol on the application of the
  principles of subsidiarity and proportionality. National Parliaments
  ensure compliance with the principle of subsidiarity in accordance
  with the procedure set out in that Protocol.

  4. Under the principle of proportionality, the content and form of
  Union action shall not exceed what is necessary to achieve the
  objectives of the Treaties.

  The institutions of the Union shall apply the principle of
  proportionality as laid down in the Protocol on the application of the
  principles of subsidiarity and proportionality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="10074">1. The Union recognises the rights, freedoms and principles set out in
  the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union of 7 December
  2000, as adapted at Strasbourg, on 12 December 2007, which shall have
  the same legal value as the Treaties.

  The provisions of the Charter shall not extend in any way the
  competences of the Union as defined in the Treaties.

  The rights, freedoms and principles in the Charter shall be
  interpreted in accordance with the general provisions in Title VII of
  the Charter governing its interpretation and application and with due
  regard to the explanations referred to in the Charter, that set out
  the sources of those provisions.

  2. The Union shall accede to the European Convention for the
  Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms. Such accession
  shall not affect the Union's competences as defined in the Treaties.

  3. Fundamental rights, as guaranteed by the European Convention for
  the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms and as they
  result from the constitutional traditions common to the Member States,
  shall constitute general principles of the Union's law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="10075">1. On a reasoned proposal by one third of the Member States, by the
  European Parliament or by the European Commission, the Council, acting
  by a majority of four fifths of its members after obtaining the
  consent of the European Parliament, may determine that there is a
  clear risk of a serious breach by a Member State of the values
  referred to in Article 2. Before making such a determination, the
  Council shall hear the Member State in question and may address
  recommendations to it, acting in accordance with the same procedure.

  The Council shall regularly verify that the grounds on which such a
  determination was made continue to apply.

  2. The European Council, acting by unanimity on a proposal by one
  third of the Member States or by the Commission and after obtaining
  the consent of the European Parliament, may determine the existence of
  a serious and persistent breach by a Member State of the values
  referred to in Article 2, after inviting the Member State in question
  to submit its observations.

  3. Where a determination under paragraph 2 has been made, the Council,
  acting by a qualified majority, may decide to suspend certain of the
  rights deriving from the application of the Treaties to the Member
  State in question, including the voting rights of the representative
  of the government of that Member State in the Council. In doing so,
  the Council shall take into account the possible consequences of such
  a suspension on the rights and obligations of natural and legal
  persons.

  The obligations of the Member State in question under the Treaties
  shall in any case continue to be binding on that State.

  4. The Council, acting by a qualified majority, may decide
  subsequently to vary or revoke measures taken under paragraph 3 in
  response to changes in the situation which led to their being imposed.

  5. The voting arrangements applying to the European Parliament, the
  European Council and the Council for the purposes of this Article are
  laid down in Article 354 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="10076">1. The Union shall develop a special relationship with neighbouring
  countries, aiming to establish an area of prosperity and good
  neighbourliness, founded on the values of the Union and characterised
  by close and peaceful relations based on cooperation.

  2. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the Union may conclude specific
  agreements with the countries concerned. These agreements may contain
  reciprocal rights and obligations as well as the possibility of
  undertaking activities jointly. Their implementation shall be the
  subject of periodic consultation.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE II" name="Provisions On Democratic Principles" chapter_identifier="1236">
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="10077">In all its activities, the Union shall observe the principle of the
  equality of its citizens, who shall receive equal attention from its
  institutions, bodies, offices and agencies. Every national of a Member
  State shall be a citizen of the Union. Citizenship of the Union shall
  be additional to and not replace national citizenship.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="10078">1. The functioning of the Union shall be founded on representative
  democracy.

  2. Citizens are directly represented at Union level in the European
  Parliament.

  Member States are represented in the European Council by their Heads
  of State or Government and in the Council by their governments,
  themselves democratically accountable either to their national
  Parliaments, or to their citizens.

  3. Every citizen shall have the right to participate in the democratic
  life of the Union. Decisions shall be taken as openly and as closely
  as possible to the citizen.

  4. Political parties at European level contribute to forming European
  political awareness and to expressing the will of citizens of the
  Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="10079">1. The institutions shall, by appropriate means, give citizens and
  representative associations the opportunity to make known and publicly
  exchange their views in all areas of Union action.

  2. The institutions shall maintain an open, transparent and regular
  dialogue with representative associations and civil society.

  3. The European Commission shall carry out broad consultations with
  parties concerned in order to ensure that the Union's actions are
  coherent and transparent.

  4. Not less than one million citizens who are nationals of a
  significant number of Member States may take the initiative of
  inviting the European Commission, within the framework of its powers,
  to submit any appropriate proposal on matters where citizens consider
  that a legal act of the Union is required for the purpose of
  implementing the Treaties.

  The procedures and conditions required for such a citizens' initiative
  shall be determined in accordance with the first paragraph of Article
  24 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="10080">National Parliaments contribute actively to the good functioning of
  the Union:

  (a) through being informed by the institutions of the Union and having
  draft legislative acts of the Union forwarded to them in accordance
  with the Protocol on the role of national Parliaments in the European
  Union;

  (b) by seeing to it that the principle of subsidiarity is respected in
  accordance with the procedures provided for in the Protocol on the
  application of the principles of subsidiarity and proportionality;

  (c) by taking part, within the framework of the area of freedom,
  security and justice, in the evaluation mechanisms for the
  implementation of the Union policies in that area, in accordance with
  Article 70 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, and
  through being involved in the political monitoring of Europol and the
  evaluation of Eurojust's activities in accordance with Articles 88 and
  85 of that Treaty;

  (d) by taking part in the revision procedures of the Treaties, in
  accordance with Article 48 of this Treaty;

  (e) by being notified of applications for accession to the Union, in
  accordance with Article 49 of this Treaty;

  (f) by taking part in the inter-parliamentary cooperation between
  national Parliaments and with the European Parliament, in accordance
  with the Protocol on the role of national Parliaments in the European
  Union.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE III" name="Provisions On The Institutions" chapter_identifier="1237">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="10081">1. The Union shall have an institutional framework which shall aim to
  promote its values, advance its objectives, serve its interests, those
  of its citizens and those of the Member States, and ensure the
  consistency, effectiveness and continuity of its policies and actions.

  The Union's institutions shall be:

  - the European Parliament,

  - the European Council,

  - the Council,

  - the European Commission (hereinafter referred to as "the
  Commission"),

  - the Court of Justice of the European Union,

  - the European Central Bank,

  - the Court of Auditors.

  2. Each institution shall act within the limits of the powers
  conferred on it in the Treaties, and in conformity with the
  procedures, conditions and objectives set out in them. The
  institutions shall practice mutual sincere cooperation.

  3. The provisions relating to the European Central Bank and the Court
  of Auditors and detailed provisions on the other institutions are set
  out in the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  4. The European Parliament, the Council and the Commission shall be
  assisted by an Economic and Social Committee and a Committee of the
  Regions acting in an advisory capacity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="10082">1. The European Parliament shall, jointly with the Council, exercise
  legislative and budgetary functions. It shall exercise functions of
  political control and consultation as laid down in the Treaties. It
  shall elect the President of the Commission.

  2. The European Parliament shall be composed of representatives of the
  Union's citizens. They shall not exceed seven hundred and fifty in
  number, plus the President. Representation of citizens shall be
  degressively proportional, with a minimum threshold of six members per
  Member State. No Member State shall be allocated more than ninety-six
  seats.

  The European Council shall adopt by unanimity, on the initiative of
  the European Parliament and with its consent, a decision establishing
  the composition of the European Parliament, respecting the principles
  referred to in the first subparagraph.

  3. The members of the European Parliament shall be elected for a term
  of five years by direct universal suffrage in a free and secret
  ballot.

  4. The European Parliament shall elect its President and its officers
  from among its members.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="10083">1. The European Council shall provide the Union with the necessary
  impetus for its development and shall define the general political
  directions and priorities thereof. It shall not exercise legislative
  functions.

  2. The European Council shall consist of the Heads of State or
  Government of the Member States, together with its President and the
  President of the Commission. The High Representative of the Union for
  Foreign Affairs and Security Policy shall take part in its work.

  3. The European Council shall meet twice every six months, convened by
  its President. When the agenda so requires, the members of the
  European Council may decide each to be assisted by a minister and, in
  the case of the President of the Commission, by a member of the
  Commission. When the situation so requires, the President shall
  convene a special meeting of the European Council.

  4. Except where the Treaties provide otherwise, decisions of the
  European Council shall be taken by consensus.

  5. The European Council shall elect its President, by a qualified
  majority, for a term of two and a half years, renewable once. In the
  event of an impediment or serious misconduct, the European Council can
  end the President's term of office in accordance with the same
  procedure.

  6. The President of the European Council:

  (a) shall chair it and drive forward its work;

  (b) shall ensure the preparation and continuity of the work of the
  European Council in cooperation with the President of the Commission,
  and on the basis of the work of the General Affairs Council;

  (c) shall endeavour to facilitate cohesion and consensus within the
  European Council;

  (d) shall present a report to the European Parliament after each of
  the meetings of the European Council.

  The President of the European Council shall, at his level and in that
  capacity, ensure the external representation of the Union on issues
  concerning its common foreign and security policy, without prejudice
  to the powers of the High Representative of the Union for Foreign
  Affairs and Security Policy.

  The President of the European Council shall not hold a national
  office.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="10084">1. The Council shall, jointly with the European Parliament, exercise
  legislative and budgetary functions. It shall carry out policy-making
  and coordinating functions as laid down in the Treaties.

  2. The Council shall consist of a representative of each Member State
  at ministerial level, who may commit the government of the Member
  State in question and cast its vote.

  3. The Council shall act by a qualified majority except where the
  Treaties provide otherwise.

  4. As from 1 November 2014, a qualified majority shall be defined as
  at least 55 % of the members of the Council, comprising at least
  fifteen of them and representing Member States comprising at least 65
  % of the population of the Union.

  A blocking minority must include at least four Council members,
  failing which the qualified majority shall be deemed attained.

  The other arrangements governing the qualified majority are laid down
  in Article 238(2) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European
  Union.

  5. The transitional provisions relating to the definition of the
  qualified majority which shall be applicable until 31 October 2014 and
  those which shall be applicable from 1 November 2014 to 31 March 2017
  are laid down in the Protocol on transitional provisions.

  6. The Council shall meet in different configurations, the list of
  which shall be adopted in accordance with Article 236 of the Treaty on
  the Functioning of the European Union.

  The General Affairs Council shall ensure consistency in the work of
  the different Council configurations. It shall prepare and ensure the
  follow-up to meetings of the European Council, in liaison with the
  President of the European Council and the Commission.

  The Foreign Affairs Council shall elaborate the Union's external
  action on the basis of strategic guidelines laid down by the European
  Council and ensure that the Union's action is consistent.

  7. A Committee of Permanent Representatives of the Governments of the
  Member States shall be responsible for preparing the work of the
  Council.

  8. The Council shall meet in public when it deliberates and votes on a
  draft legislative act. To this end, each Council meeting shall be
  divided into two parts, dealing respectively with deliberations on
  Union legislative acts and non-legislative activities.

  9. The Presidency of Council configurations, other than that of
  Foreign Affairs, shall be held by Member State representatives in the
  Council on the basis of equal rotation, in accordance with the
  conditions established in accordance with Article 236 of the Treaty on
  the Functioning of the European Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="10085">1. The Commission shall promote the general interest of the Union and
  take appropriate initiatives to that end. It shall ensure the
  application of the Treaties, and of measures adopted by the
  institutions pursuant to them. It shall oversee the application of
  Union law under the control of the Court of Justice of the European
  Union. It shall execute the budget and manage programmes. It shall
  exercise coordinating, executive and management functions, as laid
  down in the Treaties. With the exception of the common foreign and
  security policy, and other cases provided for in the Treaties, it
  shall ensure the Union's external representation. It shall initiate
  the Union's annual and multiannual programming with a view to
  achieving interinstitutional agreements.

  2. Union legislative acts may only be adopted on the basis of a
  Commission proposal, except where the Treaties provide otherwise.
  Other acts shall be adopted on the basis of a Commission proposal
  where the Treaties so provide.

  3. The Commission's term of office shall be five years.

  The members of the Commission shall be chosen on the ground of their
  general competence and European commitment from persons whose
  independence is beyond doubt.

  In carrying out its responsibilities, the Commission shall be
  completely independent. Without prejudice to Article 18(2), the
  members of the Commission shall neither seek nor take instructions
  from any Government or other institution, body, office or entity. They
  shall refrain from any action incompatible with their duties or the
  performance of their tasks.

  4. The Commission appointed between the date of entry into force of
  the Treaty of Lisbon and 31 October 2014, shall consist of one
  national of each Member State, including its President and the High
  Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy
  who shall be one of its Vice-Presidents.

  5. As from 1 November 2014, the Commission shall consist of a number
  of members, including its President and the High Representative of the
  Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, corresponding to two
  thirds of the number of Member States, unless the European Council,
  acting unanimously, decides to alter this number.

  The members of the Commission shall be chosen from among the nationals
  of the Member States on the basis of a system of strictly equal
  rotation between the Member States, reflecting the demographic and
  geographical range of all the Member States. This system shall be
  established unanimously by the European Council in accordance with
  Article 244 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  6. The President of the Commission shall:

  (a) lay down guidelines within which the Commission is to work;

  (b) decide on the internal organisation of the Commission, ensuring
  that it acts consistently, efficiently and as a collegiate body;

  (c) appoint Vice-Presidents, other than the High Representative of the
  Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, from among the members
  of the Commission.

  A member of the Commission shall resign if the President so requests.
  The High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy shall resign, in accordance with the procedure set out in
  Article 18(1), if the President so requests.

  7. Taking into account the elections to the European Parliament and
  after having held the appropriate consultations, the European Council,
  acting by a qualified majority, shall propose to the European
  Parliament a candidate for President of the Commission. This candidate
  shall be elected by the European Parliament by a majority of its
  component members. If he does not obtain the required majority, the
  European Council, acting by a qualified majority, shall within one
  month propose a new candidate who shall be elected by the European
  Parliament following the same procedure.

  The Council, by common accord with the President-elect, shall adopt
  the list of the other persons whom it proposes for appointment as
  members of the Commission. They shall be selected, on the basis of the
  suggestions made by Member States, in accordance with the criteria set
  out in paragraph 3, second subparagraph, and paragraph 5, second
  subparagraph.

  The President, the High Representative of the Union for Foreign
  Affairs and Security Policy and the other members of the Commission
  shall be subject as a body to a vote of consent by the European
  Parliament. On the basis of this consent the Commission shall be
  appointed by the European Council, acting by a qualified majority.

  8. The Commission, as a body, shall be responsible to the European
  Parliament. In accordance with Article 234 of the Treaty on the
  Functioning of the European Union, the European Parliament may vote on
  a motion of censure of the Commission. If such a motion is carried,
  the members of the Commission shall resign as a body and the High
  Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy
  shall resign from the duties that he carries out in the Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" article_identifier="10086">1. The European Council, acting by a qualified majority, with the
  agreement of the President of the Commission, shall appoint the High
  Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy.
  The European Council may end his term of office by the same procedure.

  2. The High Representative shall conduct the Union's common foreign
  and security policy. He shall contribute by his proposals to the
  development of that policy, which he shall carry out as mandated by
  the Council. The same shall apply to the common security and defence
  policy.

  3. The High Representative shall preside over the Foreign Affairs
  Council.

  4. The High Representative shall be one of the Vice-Presidents of the
  Commission. He shall ensure the consistency of the Union's external
  action. He shall be responsible within the Commission for
  responsibilities incumbent on it in external relations and for
  coordinating other aspects of the Union's external action. In
  exercising these responsibilities within the Commission, and only for
  these responsibilities, the High Representative shall be bound by
  Commission procedures to the extent that this is consistent with
  paragraphs 2 and 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="10087">1. The Court of Justice of the European Union shall include the Court
  of Justice, the General Court and specialised courts. It shall ensure
  that in the interpretation and application of the Treaties the law is
  observed.

  Member States shall provide remedies sufficient to ensure effective
  legal protection in the fields covered by Union law.

  2. The Court of Justice shall consist of one judge from each Member
  State. It shall be assisted by Advocates-General.

  The General Court shall include at least one judge per Member State.

  The Judges and the Advocates-General of the Court of Justice and the
  Judges of the General Court shall be chosen from persons whose
  independence is beyond doubt and who satisfy the conditions set out in
  Articles 253 and 254 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European
  Union. They shall be appointed by common accord of the governments of
  the Member States for six years. Retiring Judges and Advocates-General
  may be reappointed.

  3. The Court of Justice of the European Union shall, in accordance
  with the Treaties:

  (a) rule on actions brought by a Member State, an institution or a
  natural or legal person;

  (b) give preliminary rulings, at the request of courts or tribunals of
  the Member States, on the interpretation of Union law or the validity
  of acts adopted by the institutions;

  (c) rule in other cases provided for in the Treaties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IV" name="Provisions On Enhanced Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1238">
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" article_identifier="10088">1. Member States which wish to establish enhanced cooperation between
  themselves within the framework of the Union's non-exclusive
  competences may make use of its institutions and exercise those
  competences by applying the relevant provisions of the Treaties,
  subject to the limits and in accordance with the detailed arrangements
  laid down in this Article and in Articles 326 to 334 of the Treaty on
  the Functioning of the European Union.

  Enhanced cooperation shall aim to further the objectives of the Union,
  protect its interests and reinforce its integration process. Such
  cooperation shall be open at any time to all Member States, in
  accordance with Article 328 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union.

  2. The decision authorising enhanced cooperation shall be adopted by
  the Council as a last resort, when it has established that the
  objectives of such cooperation cannot be attained within a reasonable
  period by the Union as a whole, and provided that at least nine Member
  States participate in it. The Council shall act in accordance with the
  procedure laid down in Article 329 of the Treaty on the Functioning of
  the European Union.

  3. All members of the Council may participate in its deliberations,
  but only members of the Council representing the Member States
  participating in enhanced cooperation shall take part in the vote. The
  voting rules are set out in Article 330 of the Treaty on the
  Functioning of the European Union.

  4. Acts adopted in the framework of enhanced cooperation shall bind
  only participating Member States. They shall not be regarded as part
  of the acquis which has to be accepted by candidate States for
  accession to the Union.

  TITLE V

  GENERAL PROVISIONS ON THE UNION'S EXTERNAL ACTION AND SPECIFIC
  PROVISIONS ON THE COMMON FOREIGN AND SECURITY POLICY</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions On The Union's External Action" chapter_identifier="1239">
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" article_identifier="10089">1. The Union's action on the international scene shall be guided by
  the principles which have inspired its own creation, development and
  enlargement, and which it seeks to advance in the wider world:
  democracy, the rule of law, the universality and indivisibility of
  human rights and fundamental freedoms, respect for human dignity, the
  principles of equality and solidarity, and respect for the principles
  of the United Nations Charter and international law.

  The Union shall seek to develop relations and build partnerships with
  third countries, and international, regional or global organisations
  which share the principles referred to in the first subparagraph. It
  shall promote multilateral solutions to common problems, in particular
  in the framework of the United Nations.

  2. The Union shall define and pursue common policies and actions, and
  shall work for a high degree of cooperation in all fields of
  international relations, in order to:

  (a) safeguard its values, fundamental interests, security,
  independence and integrity;

  (b) consolidate and support democracy, the rule of law, human rights
  and the principles of international law;

  (c) preserve peace, prevent conflicts and strengthen international
  security, in accordance with the purposes and principles of the United
  Nations Charter, with the principles of the Helsinki Final Act and
  with the aims of the Charter of Paris, including those relating to
  external borders;

  (d) foster the sustainable economic, social and environmental
  development of developing countries, with the primary aim of
  eradicating poverty;

  (e) encourage the integration of all countries into the world economy,
  including through the progressive abolition of restrictions on
  international trade;

  (f) help develop international measures to preserve and improve the
  quality of the environment and the sustainable management of global
  natural resources, in order to ensure sustainable development;

  (g) assist populations, countries and regions confronting natural or
  man-made disasters; and

  (h) promote an international system based on stronger multilateral
  cooperation and good global governance.

  3. The Union shall respect the principles and pursue the objectives
  set out in paragraphs 1 and 2 in the development and implementation of
  the different areas of the Union's external action covered by this
  Title and by Part Five of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union, and of the external aspects of its other policies.

  The Union shall ensure consistency between the different areas of its
  external action and between these and its other policies. The Council
  and the Commission, assisted by the High Representative of the Union
  for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, shall ensure that consistency
  and shall cooperate to that effect.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" article_identifier="10090">1. On the basis of the principles and objectives set out in Article
  21, the European Council shall identify the strategic interests and
  objectives of the Union.

  Decisions of the European Council on the strategic interests and
  objectives of the Union shall relate to the common foreign and
  security policy and to other areas of the external action of the
  Union. Such decisions may concern the relations of the Union with a
  specific country or region or may be thematic in approach. They shall
  define their duration, and the means to be made available by the Union
  and the Member States.

  The European Council shall act unanimously on a recommendation from
  the Council, adopted by the latter under the arrangements laid down
  for each area. Decisions of the European Council shall be implemented
  in accordance with the procedures provided for in the Treaties.

  2. The High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and
  Security Policy, for the area of common foreign and security policy,
  and the Commission, for other areas of external action, may submit
  joint proposals to the Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Specific Provisions On The Common Foreign And Security Policy" chapter_identifier="1240">
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" article_identifier="10091">The Union's action on the international scene, pursuant to this
  Chapter, shall be guided by the principles, shall pursue the
  objectives of, and be conducted in accordance with, the general
  provisions laid down in Chapter 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" article_identifier="10092">1. The Union's competence in matters of common foreign and security
  policy shall cover all areas of foreign policy and all questions
  relating to the Union's security, including the progressive framing of
  a common defence policy that might lead to a common defence.

  The common foreign and security policy is subject to specific rules
  and procedures. It shall be defined and implemented by the European
  Council and the Council acting unanimously, except where the Treaties
  provide otherwise. The adoption of legislative acts shall be excluded.
  The common foreign and security policy shall be put into effect by the
  High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy and by Member States, in accordance with the Treaties. The
  specific role of the European Parliament and of the Commission in this
  area is defined by the Treaties. The Court of Justice of the European
  Union shall not have jurisdiction with respect to these provisions,
  with the exception of its jurisdiction to monitor compliance with
  Article 40 of this Treaty and to review the legality of certain
  decisions as provided for by the second paragraph of Article 275 of
  the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  2. Within the framework of the principles and objectives of its
  external action, the Union shall conduct, define and implement a
  common foreign and security policy, based on the development of mutual
  political solidarity among Member States, the identification of
  questions of general interest and the achievement of an
  ever-increasing degree of convergence of Member States' actions.

  3. The Member States shall support the Union's external and security
  policy actively and unreservedly in a spirit of loyalty and mutual
  solidarity and shall comply with the Union's action in this area.

  The Member States shall work together to enhance and develop their
  mutual political solidarity. They shall refrain from any action which
  is contrary to the interests of the Union or likely to impair its
  effectiveness as a cohesive force in international relations.

  The Council and the High Representative shall ensure compliance with
  these principles.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" article_identifier="10093">The Union shall conduct the common foreign and security policy by:

  (a) defining the general guidelines;

  (b) adopting decisions defining:

  (i) actions to be undertaken by the Union;

  (ii) positions to be taken by the Union;

  (iii) arrangements for the implementation of the decisions referred to
  in points (i) and (ii);

  and by

  (c) strengthening systematic cooperation between Member States in the
  conduct of policy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" article_identifier="10094">1. The European Council shall identify the Union's strategic
  interests, determine the objectives of and define general guidelines
  for the common foreign and security policy, including for matters with
  defence implications. It shall adopt the necessary decisions.

  If international developments so require, the President of the
  European Council shall convene an extraordinary meeting of the
  European Council in order to define the strategic lines of the Union's
  policy in the face of such developments.

  2. The Council shall frame the common foreign and security policy and
  take the decisions necessary for defining and implementing it on the
  basis of the general guidelines and strategic lines defined by the
  European Council.

  The Council and the High Representative of the Union for Foreign
  Affairs and Security Policy shall ensure the unity, consistency and
  effectiveness of action by the Union.

  3. The common foreign and security policy shall be put into effect by
  the High Representative and by the Member States, using national and
  Union resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" article_identifier="10095">1. The High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and
  Security Policy, who shall chair the Foreign Affairs Council, shall
  contribute through his proposals to the development of the common
  foreign and security policy and shall ensure implementation of the
  decisions adopted by the European Council and the Council.

  2. The High Representative shall represent the Union for matters
  relating to the common foreign and security policy. He shall conduct
  political dialogue with third parties on the Union's behalf and shall
  express the Union's position in international organisations and at
  international conferences.

  3. In fulfilling his mandate, the High Representative shall be
  assisted by a European External Action Service. This service shall
  work in cooperation with the diplomatic services of the Member States
  and shall comprise officials from relevant departments of the General
  Secretariat of the Council and of the Commission as well as staff
  seconded from national diplomatic services of the Member States. The
  organisation and functioning of the European External Action Service
  shall be established by a decision of the Council. The Council shall
  act on a proposal from the High Representative after consulting the
  European Parliament and after obtaining the consent of the Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" article_identifier="10096">1. Where the international situation requires operational action by
  the Union, the Council shall adopt the necessary decisions. They shall
  lay down their objectives, scope, the means to be made available to
  the Union, if necessary their duration, and the conditions for their
  implementation.

  If there is a change in circumstances having a substantial effect on a
  question subject to such a decision, the Council shall review the
  principles and objectives of that decision and take the necessary
  decisions.

  2. Decisions referred to in paragraph 1 shall commit the Member States
  in the positions they adopt and in the conduct of their activity.

  3. Whenever there is any plan to adopt a national position or take
  national action pursuant to a decision as referred to in paragraph 1,
  information shall be provided by the Member State concerned in time to
  allow, if necessary, for prior consultations within the Council. The
  obligation to provide prior information shall not apply to measures
  which are merely a national transposition of Council decisions.

  4. In cases of imperative need arising from changes in the situation
  and failing a review of the Council decision as referred to in
  paragraph 1, Member States may take the necessary measures as a matter
  of urgency having regard to the general objectives of that decision.
  The Member State concerned shall inform the Council immediately of any
  such measures.

  5. Should there be any major difficulties in implementing a decision
  as referred to in this Article, a Member State shall refer them to the
  Council which shall discuss them and seek appropriate solutions. Such
  solutions shall not run counter to the objectives of the decision
  referred to in paragraph 1 or impair its effectiveness.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" article_identifier="10097">The Council shall adopt decisions which shall define the approach of
  the Union to a particular matter of a geographical or thematic nature.
  Member States shall ensure that their national policies conform to the
  Union positions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" article_identifier="10098">1. Any Member State, the High Representative of the Union for Foreign
  Affairs and Security Policy, or the High Representative with the
  Commission's support, may refer any question relating to the common
  foreign and security policy to the Council and may submit to it,
  respectively, initiatives or proposals.

  2. In cases requiring a rapid decision, the High Representative, of
  his own motion, or at the request of a Member State, shall convene an
  extraordinary Council meeting within 48 hours or, in an emergency,
  within a shorter period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" article_identifier="10099">1. Decisions under this Chapter shall be taken by the European Council
  and the Council acting unanimously, except where this Chapter provides
  otherwise. The adoption of legislative acts shall be excluded.

  When abstaining in a vote, any member of the Council may qualify its
  abstention by making a formal declaration under the present
  subparagraph. In that case, it shall not be obliged to apply the
  decision, but shall accept that the decision commits the Union. In a
  spirit of mutual solidarity, the Member State concerned shall refrain
  from any action likely to conflict with or impede Union action based
  on that decision and the other Member States shall respect its
  position. If the members of the Council qualifying their abstention in
  this way represent at least one third of the Member States comprising
  at least one third of the population of the Union, the decision shall
  not be adopted.

  2. By derogation from the provisions of paragraph 1, the Council shall
  act by qualified majority:

  - when adopting a decision defining a Union action or position on the
  basis of a decision of the European Council relating to the Union's
  strategic interests and objectives, as referred to in Article 22(1),

  - when adopting a decision defining a Union action or position, on a
  proposal which the High Representative of the Union for Foreign
  Affairs and Security Policy has presented following a specific request
  from the European Council, made on its own initiative or that of the
  High Representative,

  - when adopting any decision implementing a decision defining a Union
  action or position,

  - when appointing a special representative in accordance with Article
  33.

  If a member of the Council declares that, for vital and stated reasons
  of national policy, it intends to oppose the adoption of a decision to
  be taken by qualified majority, a vote shall not be taken. The High
  Representative will, in close consultation with the Member State
  involved, search for a solution acceptable to it. If he does not
  succeed, the Council may, acting by a qualified majority, request that
  the matter be referred to the European Council for a decision by
  unanimity.

  3. The European Council may unanimously adopt a decision stipulating
  that the Council shall act by a qualified majority in cases other than
  those referred to in paragraph 2.

  4. Paragraphs 2 and 3 shall not apply to decisions having military or
  defence implications.

  5. For procedural questions, the Council shall act by a majority of
  its members.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" article_identifier="10100">Member States shall consult one another within the European Council
  and the Council on any matter of foreign and security policy of
  general interest in order to determine a common approach. Before
  undertaking any action on the international scene or entering into any
  commitment which could affect the Union's interests, each Member State
  shall consult the others within the European Council or the Council.
  Member States shall ensure, through the convergence of their actions,
  that the Union is able to assert its interests and values on the
  international scene. Member States shall show mutual solidarity.

  When the European Council or the Council has defined a common approach
  of the Union within the meaning of the first paragraph, the High
  Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy
  and the Ministers for Foreign Affairs of the Member States shall
  coordinate their activities within the Council.

  The diplomatic missions of the Member States and the Union delegations
  in third countries and at international organisations shall cooperate
  and shall contribute to formulating and implementing the common
  approach.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" article_identifier="10101">The Council may, on a proposal from the High Representative of the
  Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, appoint a special
  representative with a mandate in relation to particular policy issues.
  The special representative shall carry out his mandate under the
  authority of the High Representative.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" article_identifier="10102">1. Member States shall coordinate their action in international
  organisations and at international conferences. They shall uphold the
  Union's positions in such forums. The High Representative of the Union
  for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy shall organise this
  coordination.

  In international organisations and at international conferences where
  not all the Member States participate, those which do take part shall
  uphold the Union's positions.

  2. In accordance with Article 24(3), Member States represented in
  international organisations or international conferences where not all
  the Member States participate shall keep the other Member States and
  the High Representative informed of any matter of common interest.

  Member States which are also members of the United Nations Security
  Council will concert and keep the other Member States and the High
  Representative fully informed. Member States which are members of the
  Security Council will, in the execution of their functions, defend the
  positions and the interests of the Union, without prejudice to their
  responsibilities under the provisions of the United Nations Charter.

  When the Union has defined a position on a subject which is on the
  United Nations Security Council agenda, those Member States which sit
  on the Security Council shall request that the High Representative be
  invited to present the Union's position.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" article_identifier="10103">The diplomatic and consular missions of the Member States and the
  Union delegations in third countries and international conferences,
  and their representations to international organisations, shall
  cooperate in ensuring that decisions defining Union positions and
  actions adopted pursuant to this Chapter are complied with and
  implemented.

  They shall step up cooperation by exchanging information and carrying
  out joint assessments.

  They shall contribute to the implementation of the right of citizens
  of the Union to protection in the territory of third countries as
  referred to in Article 20(2)(c) of the Treaty on the Functioning of
  the European Union and of the measures adopted pursuant to Article 23
  of that Treaty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" article_identifier="10104">The High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy shall regularly consult the European Parliament on the main
  aspects and the basic choices of the common foreign and security
  policy and the common security and defence policy and inform it of how
  those policies evolve. He shall ensure that the views of the European
  Parliament are duly taken into consideration. Special representatives
  may be involved in briefing the European Parliament.

  The European Parliament may address questions or make recommendations
  to the Council or the High Representative. Twice a year it shall hold
  a debate on progress in implementing the common foreign and security
  policy, including the common security and defence policy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" article_identifier="10105">The Union may conclude agreements with one or more States or
  international organisations in areas covered by this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" article_identifier="10106">Without prejudice to Article 240 of the Treaty on the Functioning of
  the European Union, a Political and Security Committee shall monitor
  the international situation in the areas covered by the common foreign
  and security policy and contribute to the definition of policies by
  delivering opinions to the Council at the request of the Council or of
  the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy or on its own initiative. It shall also monitor the
  implementation of agreed policies, without prejudice to the powers of
  the High Representative.

  Within the scope of this Chapter, the Political and Security Committee
  shall exercise, under the responsibility of the Council and of the
  High Representative, the political control and strategic direction of
  the crisis management operations referred to in Article 43.

  The Council may authorise the Committee, for the purpose and for the
  duration of a crisis management operation, as determined by the
  Council, to take the relevant decisions concerning the political
  control and strategic direction of the operation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" article_identifier="10107">In accordance with Article 16 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union and by way of derogation from paragraph 2 thereof, the
  Council shall adopt a decision laying down the rules relating to the
  protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal
  data by the Member States when carrying out activities which fall
  within the scope of this Chapter, and the rules relating to the free
  movement of such data. Compliance with these rules shall be subject to
  the control of independent authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" article_identifier="10108">The implementation of the common foreign and security policy shall not
  affect the application of the procedures and the extent of the powers
  of the institutions laid down by the Treaties for the exercise of the
  Union competences referred to in Articles 3 to 6 of the Treaty on the
  Functioning of the European Union.

  Similarly, the implementation of the policies listed in those Articles
  shall not affect the application of the procedures and the extent of
  the powers of the institutions laid down by the Treaties for the
  exercise of the Union competences under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" article_identifier="10109">1. Administrative expenditure to which the implementation of this
  Chapter gives rise for the institutions shall be charged to the Union
  budget.

  2. Operating expenditure to which the implementation of this Chapter
  gives rise shall also be charged to the Union budget, except for such
  expenditure arising from operations having military or defence
  implications and cases where the Council acting unanimously decides
  otherwise.

  In cases where expenditure is not charged to the Union budget, it
  shall be charged to the Member States in accordance with the gross
  national product scale, unless the Council acting unanimously decides
  otherwise. As for expenditure arising from operations having military
  or defence implications, Member States whose representatives in the
  Council have made a formal declaration under Article 31(1), second
  subparagraph, shall not be obliged to contribute to the financing
  thereof.

  3. The Council shall adopt a decision establishing the specific
  procedures for guaranteeing rapid access to appropriations in the
  Union budget for urgent financing of initiatives in the framework of
  the common foreign and security policy, and in particular for
  preparatory activities for the tasks referred to in Article 42(1) and
  Article 43. It shall act after consulting the European Parliament.

  Preparatory activities for the tasks referred to in Article 42(1) and
  Article 43 which are not charged to the Union budget shall be financed
  by a start-up fund made up of Member States' contributions.

  The Council shall adopt by a qualified majority, on a proposal from
  the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy, decisions establishing:

  (a) the procedures for setting up and financing the start-up fund, in
  particular the amounts allocated to the fund;

  (b) the procedures for administering the start-up fund;

  (c) the financial control procedures.

  When the task planned in accordance with Article 42(1) and Article 43
  cannot be charged to the Union budget, the Council shall authorise the
  High Representative to use the fund. The High Representative shall
  report to the Council on the implementation of this remit.

  PROVISIONS ON THE COMMON SECURITY AND DEFENCE POLICY</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" article_identifier="10110">1. The common security and defence policy shall be an integral part of
  the common foreign and security policy. It shall provide the Union
  with an operational capacity drawing on civilian and military assets.
  The Union may use them on missions outside the Union for
  peace-keeping, conflict prevention and strengthening international
  security in accordance with the principles of the United Nations
  Charter. The performance of these tasks shall be undertaken using
  capabilities provided by the Member States.

  2. The common security and defence policy shall include the
  progressive framing of a common Union defence policy. This will lead
  to a common defence, when the European Council, acting unanimously, so
  decides. It shall in that case recommend to the Member States the
  adoption of such a decision in accordance with their respective
  constitutional requirements.

  The policy of the Union in accordance with this Section shall not
  prejudice the specific character of the security and defence policy of
  certain Member States and shall respect the obligations of certain
  Member States, which see their common defence realised in the North
  Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO), under the North Atlantic Treaty
  and be compatible with the common security and defence policy
  established within that framework.

  3. Member States shall make civilian and military capabilities
  available to the Union for the implementation of the common security
  and defence policy, to contribute to the objectives defined by the
  Council. Those Member States which together establish multinational
  forces may also make them available to the common security and defence
  policy.

  Member States shall undertake progressively to improve their military
  capabilities. The Agency in the field of defence capabilities
  development, research, acquisition and armaments (hereinafter referred
  to as "the European Defence Agency") shall identify
  operational requirements, shall promote measures to satisfy those
  requirements, shall contribute to identifying and, where appropriate,
  implementing any measure needed to strengthen the industrial and
  technological base of the defence sector, shall participate in
  defining a European capabilities and armaments policy, and shall
  assist the Council in evaluating the improvement of military
  capabilities.

  4. Decisions relating to the common security and defence policy,
  including those initiating a mission as referred to in this Article,
  shall be adopted by the Council acting unanimously on a proposal from
  the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy or an initiative from a Member State. The High Representative
  may propose the use of both national resources and Union instruments,
  together with the Commission where appropriate.

  5. The Council may entrust the execution of a task, within the Union
  framework, to a group of Member States in order to protect the Union's
  values and serve its interests. The execution of such a task shall be
  governed by Article 44.

  6. Those Member States whose military capabilities fulfil higher
  criteria and which have made more binding commitments to one another
  in this area with a view to the most demanding missions shall
  establish permanent structured cooperation within the Union framework.
  Such cooperation shall be governed by Article 46. It shall not affect
  the provisions of Article 43.

  7. If a Member State is the victim of armed aggression on its
  territory, the other Member States shall have towards it an obligation
  of aid and assistance by all the means in their power, in accordance
  with Article 51 of the United Nations Charter. This shall not
  prejudice the specific character of the security and defence policy of
  certain Member States.

  Commitments and cooperation in this area shall be consistent with
  commitments under the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation, which, for
  those States which are members of it, remains the foundation of their
  collective defence and the forum for its implementation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" article_identifier="10111">1. The tasks referred to in Article 42(1), in the course of which the
  Union may use civilian and military means, shall include joint
  disarmament operations, humanitarian and rescue tasks, military advice
  and assistance tasks, conflict prevention and peace-keeping tasks,
  tasks of combat forces in crisis management, including peace-making
  and post-conflict stabilisation. All these tasks may contribute to the
  fight against terrorism, including by supporting third countries in
  combating terrorism in their territories.

  2. The Council shall adopt decisions relating to the tasks referred to
  in paragraph 1, defining their objectives and scope and the general
  conditions for their implementation. The High Representative of the
  Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, acting under the
  authority of the Council and in close and constant contact with the
  Political and Security Committee, shall ensure coordination of the
  civilian and military aspects of such tasks.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" article_identifier="10112">1. Within the framework of the decisions adopted in accordance with
  Article 43, the Council may entrust the implementation of a task to a
  group of Member States which are willing and have the necessary
  capability for such a task. Those Member States, in association with
  the High Representative of the Union for Foreign Affairs and Security
  Policy, shall agree among themselves on the management of the task.

  2. Member States participating in the task shall keep the Council
  regularly informed of its progress on their own initiative or at the
  request of another Member State. Those States shall inform the Council
  immediately should the completion of the task entail major
  consequences or require amendment of the objective, scope and
  conditions determined for the task in the decisions referred to in
  paragraph 1. In such cases, the Council shall adopt the necessary
  decisions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" article_identifier="10113">1. The European Defence Agency referred to in Article 42(3), subject
  to the authority of the Council, shall have as its task to:

  (a) contribute to identifying the Member States' military capability
  objectives and evaluating observance of the capability commitments
  given by the Member States;

  (b) promote harmonisation of operational needs and adoption of
  effective, compatible procurement methods;

  (c) propose multilateral projects to fulfil the objectives in terms of
  military capabilities, ensure coordination of the programmes
  implemented by the Member States and management of specific
  cooperation programmes;

  (d) support defence technology research, and coordinate and plan joint
  research activities and the study of technical solutions meeting
  future operational needs;

  (e) contribute to identifying and, if necessary, implementing any
  useful measure for strengthening the industrial and technological base
  of the defence sector and for improving the effectiveness of military
  expenditure.

  2. The European Defence Agency shall be open to all Member States
  wishing to be part of it. The Council, acting by a qualified majority,
  shall adopt a decision defining the Agency's statute, seat and
  operational rules. That decision should take account of the level of
  effective participation in the Agency's activities. Specific groups
  shall be set up within the Agency bringing together Member States
  engaged in joint projects. The Agency shall carry out its tasks in
  liaison with the Commission where necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" article_identifier="10114">1. Those Member States which wish to participate in the permanent
  structured cooperation referred to in Article 42(6), which fulfil the
  criteria and have made the commitments on military capabilities set
  out in the Protocol on permanent structured cooperation, shall notify
  their intention to the Council and to the High Representative of the
  Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy.

  2. Within three months following the notification referred to in
  paragraph 1 the Council shall adopt a decision establishing permanent
  structured cooperation and determining the list of participating
  Member States. The Council shall act by a qualified majority after
  consulting the High Representative.

  3. Any Member State which, at a later stage, wishes to participate in
  the permanent structured cooperation shall notify its intention to the
  Council and to the High Representative.

  The Council shall adopt a decision confirming the participation of the
  Member State concerned which fulfils the criteria and makes the
  commitments referred to in Articles 1 and 2 of the Protocol on
  permanent structured cooperation. The Council shall act by a qualified
  majority after consulting the High Representative. Only members of the
  Council representing the participating Member States shall take part
  in the vote.

  A qualified majority shall be defined in accordance with Article
  238(3)(a) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  4. If a participating Member State no longer fulfils the criteria or
  is no longer able to meet the commitments referred to in Articles 1
  and 2 of the Protocol on permanent structured cooperation, the Council
  may adopt a decision suspending the participation of the Member State
  concerned.

  The Council shall act by a qualified majority. Only members of the
  Council representing the participating Member States, with the
  exception of the Member State in question, shall take part in the
  vote.

  A qualified majority shall be defined in accordance with Article
  238(3)(a) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  5. Any participating Member State which wishes to withdraw from
  permanent structured cooperation shall notify its intention to the
  Council, which shall take note that the Member State in question has
  ceased to participate.

  6. The decisions and recommendations of the Council within the
  framework of permanent structured cooperation, other than those
  provided for in paragraphs 2 to 5, shall be adopted by unanimity. For
  the purposes of this paragraph, unanimity shall be constituted by the
  votes of the representatives of the participating Member States only.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VI" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1241">
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" article_identifier="10115">The Union shall have legal personality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" article_identifier="10116">1. The Treaties may be amended in accordance with an ordinary revision
  procedure. They may also be amended in accordance with simplified
  revision procedures.

  Ordinary revision procedure

  2. The Government of any Member State, the European Parliament or the
  Commission may submit to the Council proposals for the amendment of
  the Treaties. These proposals may, inter alia, serve either to
  increase or to reduce the competences conferred on the Union in the
  Treaties. These proposals shall be submitted to the European Council
  by the Council and the national Parliaments shall be notified.

  3. If the European Council, after consulting the European Parliament
  and the Commission, adopts by a simple majority a decision in favour
  of examining the proposed amendments, the President of the European
  Council shall convene a Convention composed of representatives of the
  national Parliaments, of the Heads of State or Government of the
  Member States, of the European Parliament and of the Commission. The
  European Central Bank shall also be consulted in the case of
  institutional changes in the monetary area. The Convention shall
  examine the proposals for amendments and shall adopt by consensus a
  recommendation to a conference of representatives of the governments
  of the Member States as provided for in paragraph 4.

  The European Council may decide by a simple majority, after obtaining
  the consent of the European Parliament, not to convene a Convention
  should this not be justified by the extent of the proposed amendments.
  In the latter case, the European Council shall define the terms of
  reference for a conference of representatives of the governments of
  the Member States.

  4. A conference of representatives of the governments of the Member
  States shall be convened by the President of the Council for the
  purpose of determining by common accord the amendments to be made to
  the Treaties.

  The amendments shall enter into force after being ratified by all the
  Member States in accordance with their respective constitutional
  requirements.

  5. If, two years after the signature of a treaty amending the
  Treaties, four fifths of the Member States have ratified it and one or
  more Member States have encountered difficulties in proceeding with
  ratification, the matter shall be referred to the European Council.

  Simplified revision procedures

  6. The Government of any Member State, the European Parliament or the
  Commission may submit to the European Council proposals for revising
  all or part of the provisions of Part Three of the Treaty on the
  Functioning of the European Union relating to the internal policies
  and action of the Union.

  The European Council may adopt a decision amending all or part of the
  provisions of Part Three of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union. The European Council shall act by unanimity after
  consulting the European Parliament and the Commission, and the
  European Central Bank in the case of institutional changes in the
  monetary area. That decision shall not enter into force until it is
  approved by the Member States in accordance with their respective
  constitutional requirements.

  The decision referred to in the second subparagraph shall not increase
  the competences conferred on the Union in the Treaties.

  7. Where the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union or Title
  V of this Treaty provides for the Council to act by unanimity in a
  given area or case, the European Council may adopt a decision
  authorising the Council to act by a qualified majority in that area or
  in that case. This subparagraph shall not apply to decisions with
  military implications or those in the area of defence.

  Where the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union provides for
  legislative acts to be adopted by the Council in accordance with a
  special legislative procedure, the European Council may adopt a
  decision allowing for the adoption of such acts in accordance with the
  ordinary legislative procedure.

  Any initiative taken by the European Council on the basis of the first
  or the second subparagraph shall be notified to the national
  Parliaments. If a national Parliament makes known its opposition
  within six months of the date of such notification, the decision
  referred to in the first or the second subparagraph shall not be
  adopted. In the absence of opposition, the European Council may adopt
  the decision.

  For the adoption of the decisions referred to in the first and second
  subparagraphs, the European Council shall act by unanimity after
  obtaining the consent of the European Parliament, which shall be given
  by a majority of its component members.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" article_identifier="10117">Any European State which respects the values referred to in Article 2
  and is committed to promoting them may apply to become a member of the
  Union. The European Parliament and national Parliaments shall be
  notified of this application. The applicant State shall address its
  application to the Council, which shall act unanimously after
  consulting the Commission and after receiving the consent of the
  European Parliament, which shall act by a majority of its component
  members. The conditions of eligibility agreed upon by the European
  Council shall be taken into account.

  The conditions of admission and the adjustments to the Treaties on
  which the Union is founded, which such admission entails, shall be the
  subject of an agreement between the Member States and the applicant
  State. This agreement shall be submitted for ratification by all the
  contracting States in accordance with their respective constitutional
  requirements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" article_identifier="10118">1. Any Member State may decide to withdraw from the Union in
  accordance with its own constitutional requirements.

  2. A Member State which decides to withdraw shall notify the European
  Council of its intention. In the light of the guidelines provided by
  the European Council, the Union shall negotiate and conclude an
  agreement with that State, setting out the arrangements for its
  withdrawal, taking account of the framework for its future
  relationship with the Union. That agreement shall be negotiated in
  accordance with Article 218(3) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the
  European Union. It shall be concluded on behalf of the Union by the
  Council, acting by a qualified majority, after obtaining the consent
  of the European Parliament.

  3. The Treaties shall cease to apply to the State in question from the
  date of entry into force of the withdrawal agreement or, failing that,
  two years after the notification referred to in paragraph 2, unless
  the European Council, in agreement with the Member State concerned,
  unanimously decides to extend this period.

  4. For the purposes of paragraphs 2 and 3, the member of the European
  Council or of the Council representing the withdrawing Member State
  shall not participate in the discussions of the European Council or
  Council or in decisions concerning it.

  A qualified majority shall be defined in accordance with Article
  238(3)(b) of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.

  5. If a State which has withdrawn from the Union asks to rejoin, its
  request shall be subject to the procedure referred to in Article 49.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" article_identifier="10119">The Protocols and Annexes to the Treaties shall form an integral part
  thereof.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" article_identifier="10120">1. The Treaties shall apply to the Kingdom of Belgium, the Republic of
  Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, the Kingdom of Denmark, the Federal
  Republic of Germany, the Republic of Estonia, Ireland, the Hellenic
  Republic, the Kingdom of Spain, the French Republic, the Italian
  Republic, the Republic of Cyprus, the Republic of Latvia, the Republic
  of Lithuania, the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg, the Republic of Hungary,
  the Republic of Malta, the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the Republic of
  Austria, the Republic of Poland, the Portuguese Republic, Romania, the
  Republic of Slovenia, the Slovak Republic, the Republic of Finland,
  the Kingdom of Sweden and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and
  Northern Ireland.

  2. The territorial scope of the Treaties is specified in Article 355
  of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" article_identifier="10121">This Treaty is concluded for an unlimited period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" article_identifier="10122">1. This Treaty shall be ratified by the High Contracting Parties in
  accordance with their respective constitutional requirements. The
  instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Government of
  the Italian Republic.

  2. This Treaty shall enter into force on 1 January 1993, provided that
  all the Instruments of ratification have been deposited, or, failing
  that, on the first day of the month following the deposit of the
  Instrument of ratification by the last signatory State to take this
  step.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" article_identifier="10123">1. This Treaty, drawn up in a single original in the Bulgarian, Czech,
  Danish, Dutch, English, Estonian, Finnish, French, German, Greek,
  Hungarian, Irish, Italian, Latvian, Lithuanian, Maltese, Polish,
  Portuguese, Romanian, Slovak, Slovenian, Spanish and Swedish
  languages, the texts in each of these languages being equally
  authentic, shall be deposited in the archives of the Government of the
  Italian Republic, which will transmit a certified copy to each of the
  governments of the other signatory States.

  2. This Treaty may also be translated into any other languages as
  determined by Member States among those which, in accordance with
  their constitutional order, enjoy official status in all or part of
  their territory. A certified copy of such translations shall be
  provided by the Member States concerned to be deposited in the
  archives of the Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1242">
      <article article_identifier="10124">IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have signed this
  Treaty.

  Done at Maastricht on the seventh day of February in the year one
  thousand nine hundred and ninety-two.

  (List of signatories not reproduced)

  [1] The Republic of Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, the Republic of
  Estonia, the Republic of Cyprus, the Republic of Latvia, the Republic
  of Lithuania, the Republic of Hungary, the Republic of Malta, the
  Republic of Austria, the Republic of Poland, Romania, the Republic of
  Slovenia, the Slovak Republic, the Republic of Finland and the Kingdom
  of Sweden have since become members of the European Union.

  [2] These references are merely indicative. For more ample
  information, please refer to the tables of equivalences between the
  old and the new numbering of the Treaties.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
