<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EFTA - Albania</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>600</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>365</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2009-12-17</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2010-11-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2011-02-07</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2010-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">ALB</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">CHE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">ISL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">LIE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">NOR</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">ALB</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">CHE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">ISL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">LIE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">NOR</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.efta.int/free-trade/free-trade-agreements/media/documents/legal-texts/free-trade-relations/albania/EFTA-Albania Free Trade Agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.efta.int/free-trade/free-trade-agreements/albania/annexes-protocols.aspx</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="3267">
      <article article_identifier="27450">FREE TRADE AGREEMENT 
BETWEEN 
THE REPUBLIC OF ALBANIA 
AND 
THE EFTA STATES 


PREAMBLE 

The Republic of Albania (hereinafter referred to as “Albania”), on the one part, 

and Iceland, the Principality of Liechtenstein, the Kingdom of Norway, the Swiss Confederation (hereinafter referred to as “the EFTA States”), on the other, 

hereinafter each individual State referred to as a “Party” or collectively referred to as the “Parties”: 

RECOGNISING the common wish to strengthen the links between Albania on the one part and the EFTA States on the other by establishing close and lasting relations; 

RECALLING their intention to participate actively in the process of Euro Mediterranean economic integration and expressing their preparedness to co-operate in seeking ways and means to strengthen this process; 

REAFFIRMING their commitment to democracy, human rights and fundamental freedoms, and to the political and economic freedoms, in accordance with their obligations under international law, including the United Nations Charter and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights; 

REAFFIRMING their commitment to economic and social development, the protection of health and safety, and the respect for the fundamental rights of workers, including the principles set out in the relevant International Labour Organisation (ILO) Conventions; 

AIMING to create new employment opportunities, and improve health and living standards in their respective territories; 

DESIRING to create favourable conditions for the development and diversification of trade between them and for the promotion of commercial and economic co-operation in areas of common interest on the basis of equality, mutual benefit, non-discrimination and international law; 

DETERMINED to promote and further strengthen the multilateral trading system, building on their respective rights and obligations under the Marrakesh Agreement establishing the World Trade Organisation (hereinafter referred to as “the WTO”) and the other agreements negotiated thereunder, thereby contributing to the harmonious development and expansion of world trade; 

CONSIDERING that no provision of this Agreement may be interpreted as exempting the Parties from their obligations under other international agreements, especially the Marrakesh Agreement establishing the WTO and the other agreements negotiated thereunder; 

DETERMINED to implement this Agreement with the objectives to preserve and protect the environment and to ensure the use of natural resources in accordance with the principle of sustainable development; 

AFFIRMING their commitment to the rule of law, to prevent and combat corruption in international trade and investment and to promote the principles of transparency and good governance; 

ACKNOWLEDGING the significance of responsible corporate conduct and its contribution to sustainable economic development and affirming their support to efforts for the promotion of relevant international standards; 

DECLARING their readiness to examine the possibility of developing and deepening their economic relations in order to extend them to fields not covered by this Agreement; 

CONVINCED that this Agreement will enhance the competitiveness of their firms in global markets and create conditions encouraging economic, trade and investment relations between them; 

HAVE DECIDED, in pursuit of the above, to conclude the following Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “this Agreement”):</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="3268">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="27451">1. Albania and the EFTA States shall establish a free trade area by means of this Agreement and the complementary agreements on trade in agricultural products, concurrently concluded between Albania and each individual EFTA State, with a view to spurring prosperity and economic development in their territories. 


2. The objectives of this Agreement, which is based on trade relations between market economies and on the respect of democratic principles and human rights, are: 


(a) 	to achieve the liberalisation of trade in goods, in conformity with Article XXIV of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (hereinafter referred to as “the GATT 1994”); 


(b) 	to mutually increase investment opportunities between the Parties, and to gradually develop an environment conducive to enhanced trade in services; 


(c) 	to provide fair conditions of competition for trade between the Parties and to ensure adequate and effective protection of intellectual property rights; 


(d) 	to gradually achieve further liberalisation on a mutual basis of the government procurement markets of the Parties; and 


(e) 	to contribute in this way to the harmonious development and expansion of world trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Trade Relations Governed By This Agreement" article_identifier="27452">This Agreement shall apply to trade relations between Albania, on the one side, and the individual EFTA States, on the other side, but not to the trade relations between individual EFTA States, unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Territorial Application" article_identifier="27453">1. Without prejudice to Protocol B, this Agreement shall apply: 


(a) 	to the land territory, internal waters, and the territorial sea of a Party, and the air-space above the territory of a Party, in accordance with international law; as well as 


(b) 	beyond the territorial sea, with respect to measures taken by a Party in the exercise of its sovereign right or jurisdiction in accordance with international law. 
2. This Agreement shall not apply to the Norwegian territory of Svalbard, with the exception of trade in goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Central, Regional And Local Government" article_identifier="27454">Each Party shall ensure within its territory the observance of all obligations and commitments under this Agreement by its respective central, regional and local governments and authorities, and by non-governmental bodies in the exercise of governmental powers delegated to them by central, regional and local governments or authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Transparency" article_identifier="27455">1. The Parties shall publish or otherwise make publicly available their laws, regulations, judicial decisions, administrative rulings of general application and their respective international agreements that may affect the operation of this Agreement. 


2. Each Party commits to make every effort to publish in advance, in particular on the Internet, the laws relevant for international trade in goods and related services that it aims to adopt and shall offer interested persons the opportunity to submit comments prior to such an adoption. 


3. The Parties shall promptly respond to specific questions and provide, upon request, information to each other on matters referred to in paragraph 1. They are not required to disclose confidential information. 


4. The Parties shall administer in a uniform and impartial manner all their laws, regulations and administrative decisions relevant for international trade in goods and related services.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="3269">
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Scope" article_identifier="27456">1. This Chapter applies to the following products originating in Albania or in an EFTA State: 


(a) 	all products classified under Chapters 25 to 97 of the Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding System (HS), excluding the products listed in Annex I; 


(b) 	processed agricultural products specified in Protocol A, with due regard to the arrangements provided for in that Protocol; and 


(c) 	fish and other marine products as provided for in Annex II. 
2. Albania and each EFTA State have concluded agreements on trade in agricultural products on a bilateral basis. These agreements form part of the instruments establishing a free trade area between Albania and the EFTA States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Rules Of Origin And Methods Of Administrative Co-Operation" article_identifier="27457">1. The provisions on rules of origin and methods of administrative co-operation are set out in Protocol B. 


2. The Parties agree to consider favourably requests for negotiations aiming at concluding bilateral Agreements on Mutual Administrative Assistance in Customs Matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Customs Duties" article_identifier="27458">1. Upon entry into force of this Agreement, the Parties shall abolish all customs duties on imports and exports of products originating in Albania or in an EFTA State covered by paragraph 1 of Article 6, except as otherwise provided for in the relevant Annexes and Protocols. No new customs duties shall be introduced, nor shall those 

already applied be increased in trade between the Parties from the entry into force of this Agreement, except as provided for in Article 1 of Protocol A. 

2. A customs duty includes any duty or charge of any kind imposed in connection with the importation or exportation of a product, including any form of surtax or surcharge, but does not include any charge imposed in conformity with Articles III and VIII of the GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="27459">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of export and import restrictions shall be governed by Article XI of the GATT 1994, which is hereby incorporated into and made part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Internal Taxation And Regulations" article_identifier="27460">1. The Parties commit themselves to apply any internal taxes and other charges and regulations in accordance with Article III of the GATT 1994 and other relevant WTO Agreements. 


2. Exporters may not benefit from repayment of internal taxes in excess of the amount of indirect taxation imposed on products exported to the territory of a Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="27461">1. The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of sanitary and phytosanitary measures shall be governed by the WTO Agreement on the Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures. 


2. The Parties shall exchange names and addresses of contact points with sanitary and phytosanitary expertise in order to facilitate communication and the exchange of information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Technical Regulations" article_identifier="27462">1. The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of technical regulations, standards and conformity assessment shall be governed by the WTO Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade. 


2. The Parties shall strengthen their co-operation in the field of technical regulations, standards and conformity assessment, with a view to increasing the mutual understanding of their respective systems and facilitating access to their respective markets.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Trade Facilitation" article_identifier="27463">The Parties, in accordance with the provisions set out in Annex III, with the aim to facilitate trade between Albania and the EFTA States, shall: 


(a) 	simplify, to the greatest extent possible, procedures for trade in goods and related services; 


(b) 	promote co-operation among them in order to enhance their participation in the development and implementation of international conventions and recommendations on trade facilitation; and 


(c) 	co-operate on trade facilitation within the framework of the Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin, Customs Procedures And Trade Facilitation" article_identifier="27464">1. With reference to Articles 7, 8 and 13, a Sub-Committee of the Joint Committee on Rules of Origin, Customs Procedures and Trade Facilitation (hereinafter referred to as “the Sub-Committee”) is hereby established. 


2. 	The mandate of the Sub-Committee is set out in Annex IV.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="State Trading Enterprises" article_identifier="27465">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of state trading enterprises shall be governed by Article XVII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Interpretation of Article XVII of the GATT 1994, which are hereby incorporated into and made part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Subsidies And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="27466">1. The rights and obligations of the Parties relating to subsidies and countervailing measures shall be governed by Articles VI and XVI of the GATT 1994 and the WTO Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures, except as provided for in paragraph 2. 


2. Before Albania or an EFTA State, as the case may be, initiates an investigation to determine the existence, degree and effect of any alleged subsidy in Albania or in an EFTA State, as provided for in Article 11 of the WTO Agreement on Subsidies and Countervailing Measures, the Party considering initiating an investigation shall notify in writing the Party whose goods are subject to investigation and allow for a 45 day period with a view to finding a mutually acceptable solution. The consultations shall take place in the Joint Committee if any Party so requests within 20 days from the receipt of the notification.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Anti-Dumping" article_identifier="27467">1. A Party shall not apply anti-dumping measures as provided for under Article VI of the GATT 1994 and the WTO Agreement on Implementation of Article VI of the GATT 1994 in relation to products originating in another Party. 


2. The Parties recognise that the effective implementation of competition rules may address economic causes leading to dumping.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Rules Of Competition Concerning Undertakings" article_identifier="27468">1. The following are incompatible with the proper functioning of this Agreement in so far as they may affect trade between Albania and an EFTA State: 


(a) 	all agreements between undertakings, decisions by associations of undertakings and concerted practices between undertakings which have as their object or effect the prevention, restriction or distortion of competition; and 


(b) 	abuse by one or more undertakings of a dominant position in the territory of a Party as a whole or in a substantial part thereof. 

2. The provisions of paragraph 1 shall apply to the activities of public undertakings and undertakings for which the Parties grant special or exclusive rights, in so far as the application of these provisions does not obstruct the performance, in law or in fact, of the particular public tasks assigned to them. 


3. The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not be construed to create any direct obligations for undertakings. 


4. If a Party considers that a given practice is incompatible with the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2, the Parties concerned shall give to the Joint Committee all the assistance required in order to examine the case and, where appropriate, eliminate the practice objected to. If the Party concerned fails to put an end to the practice objected to within the period set by the Joint Committee, or if the Joint Committee fails to reach an agreement after consultations, or after thirty days following referral for such consultations, the other Party may adopt appropriate measures to deal with the difficulties resulting from the practice in question.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="General Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="27469">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of general safeguards shall be governed by Article XIX of GATT 1994 and the WTO Agreement on Safeguards. In taking measures under these WTO provisions, a Party shall exclude imports of an originating product from one or several Parties if such imports do not in and of themselves cause or threaten to cause serious injury. The Party taking the measure shall demonstrate that such exclusion is in accordance with WTO jurisprudence.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="27470">1. Where, as a result of the reduction or elimination of a customs duty under this Agreement, any product originating in a Party is being imported into the territory of another Party in such increased quantities, in absolute terms or relative to domestic production, and under such conditions as to constitute a substantial cause of serious 

injury or threat thereof to the domestic industry of like or directly competitive products in the territory of the importing Party, the importing Party may take bilateral safeguard measures to the minimum extent necessary to remedy or prevent the injury, subject to the provisions of paragraphs 2 to 10. 

2. Bilateral safeguard measures shall only be taken upon clear evidence that increased imports have caused or are threatening to cause serious injury pursuant to an investigation in accordance with the procedures laid down in the WTO Agreement on Safeguards. 


3. The Party intending to take a bilateral safeguard measure under this Article shall immediately, and in any case before taking a measure, make notification to the other Parties and the Joint Committee. The notification shall contain all pertinent information, which shall include evidence of serious injury or threat thereof caused by increased imports, a precise description of the product involved and the proposed measure, as well as the proposed date of introduction, expected duration and timetable for the progressive removal of the measure. A Party that may be affected by the measure shall be offered compensation in the form of substantially equivalent trade liberalisation in relation to the imports from any such Party. 


4. If the conditions set out in paragraph 1 are met, the importing Party may take measures consisting in increasing the rate of customs duty for the product to a level not to exceed the lesser of: 


(a) 	the MFN rate of duty applied at the time the action is taken; or 


(b) 	the MFN rate of duty applied on the day immediately preceding the date of the entry into force of this Agreement. 

5. Bilateral safeguard measures shall be taken for a period not exceeding one year. In very exceptional circumstances, after review by the Joint Committee, measures may be taken up to a total maximum period of three years. No measure shall be applied to the import of a product which has previously been subject to such a measure. 


6. The Joint Committee shall within 30 days from the date of notification examine the information provided under paragraph 3 in order to facilitate a mutually acceptable resolution of the matter. In the absence of such resolution, the importing Party may adopt a measure pursuant to paragraph 4 to remedy the problem, and, in the absence of mutually agreed compensation, the Party against whose product the measure is taken may take compensatory action. The bilateral safeguard measure and the compensatory action shall be immediately notified to the other Parties and the Joint Committee. In the selection of the bilateral safeguard measure and the compensatory action, priority must be given to the measure which least disturbs the functioning of this Agreement. The compensatory action shall normally consist of suspension of concessions having substantially equivalent trade effects or concessions substantially equivalent to the value of the additional duties expected to result from the bilateral safeguard measure. The Party taking compensatory action shall apply the action only for the minimum period 

necessary to achieve the substantially equivalent trade effects and in any event, only while the measure under paragraph 4 is being applied. 

7. Upon the termination of the measure, the rate of customs duty shall be the rate which would have been in effect but for the measure. 


8. In critical circumstances, where delay would cause damage which would be difficult to repair, a Party may take a provisional emergency measure pursuant to a preliminary determination that there is clear evidence that increased imports constitute a substantial cause of serious injury, or threat thereof, to the domestic industry. The Party intending to take such a measure shall immediately notify the other Parties and the Joint Committee thereof. Within 30 days of the date of the notification, the procedures set out in paragraphs 2 to 6, including for compensatory action, shall be initiated. Any compensation shall be based on the total period of application of the provisional emergency measure and of the emergency measure. 


9. Any provisional measure shall be terminated within 200 days at the latest. The period of application of any such provisional measure shall be counted as part of the duration of the measure set out in paragraph 5 and any extension thereof. Any tariff increases shall be promptly refunded if the investigation described in paragraph 2 does not result in a finding that the conditions of paragraph 1 are met. 


10. Five years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the Parties shall review in the Joint Committee whether there is need to maintain the possibility to take safeguard measures between them. If the Parties decide, after the first review, to maintain such possibility, they shall thereafter conduct biennial reviews of this matter in the Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="27471">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of general exceptions shall be governed by Article XX of the GATT 1994, which is hereby incorporated into and made part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="27472">The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of security exceptions shall be governed by Article XXI of the GATT 1994, which is hereby incorporated into and made part of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Protection Of Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="3270">
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="27473">1. The Parties shall grant and ensure adequate, effective and non-discriminatory protection of intellectual property rights, and provide for measures for the enforcement of such rights against infringement thereof, counterfeiting and piracy, in accordance with the provisions of this Article, Annex V and the international agreements referred to therein. 


2. The Parties shall accord to each other’s nationals treatment no less favourable than that they accord to their own nationals. Exemptions from this obligation must be in accordance with the substantive provisions of Articles 3 and 5 of the WTO Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights (hereinafter referred to as “the TRIPS Agreement”). 


3. The Parties shall grant to each other’s nationals treatment no less favourable than that accorded to nationals of any other State. Exemptions from this obligation must be in accordance with the substantive provisions of the TRIPS Agreement, in particular Articles 4 and 5 thereof. 


4. The Parties agree, upon request of any Party to the Joint Committee, to review the provisions on the protection of intellectual property rights contained in the present Article and in Annex V, with a view to further improving the level of protection they provide for and to avoiding or remedying trade distortions caused by actual levels of protection of intellectual property rights.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Investment, Services And Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="3271">
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Investment" article_identifier="27474">1. The Parties shall endeavour to provide in their territories stable, equitable and transparent investment conditions for investors of the other Parties that are making or seeking to make investments in their territories. 


2. The Parties shall admit investments by investors of the other Parties in accordance with their laws and regulations. They recognise that it is inappropriate to encourage investment by relaxing health, safety or environmental standards. 


3. The Parties recognise the importance of promoting investment and technology flows as a means for achieving economic growth and development. Co-operation in this respect may include: 


(a) 	appropriate means of identifying investment opportunities and information channels on investment regulations; 


(b) 	exchange of information on measures to promote investment abroad; and 


(c) 	the furthering of a legal environment conducive to increased investment flows. 

4. The Parties affirm their commitment to review issues related to investment in the Joint Committee no later than five years after the entry into force of this Agreement, including the right of establishment of investors of one Party in the territory of another Party. 


5. Albania, on the one part, and Iceland, the Principality of Liechtenstein, and the Swiss Confederation, on the other, shall refrain from arbitrary or discriminatory measures regarding investments by investors of another Party mentioned in this paragraph and shall observe any obligation they have entered into with regard to a specific investment by an investor of another Party mentioned in this paragraph.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Trade In Services" article_identifier="27475">1. The Parties shall aim at achieving gradual liberalisation and the opening of their markets for trade in services in accordance with the provisions of the General Agreement on Trade in Services (hereinafter referred to as “the GATS”), taking into account ongoing work under the auspices of the WTO. 


2. If a Party grants to a non-Party, after the entry into force of this Agreement, additional benefits with regard to the access to its services markets, it shall afford adequate opportunities for negotiations with a view to extending these benefits to another Party on a reciprocal basis. 


3. The Parties undertake to keep under review paragraphs 1 and 2 with a view to establishing an agreement on liberalisation of trade in services in accordance with Article V of the GATS.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Government Procurement" article_identifier="27476">1. The Parties shall enhance their mutual understanding of their government procurement laws and regulations with a view to progressively liberalising their respective procurement markets on the basis of non-discrimination and reciprocity. 


2. In order to improve transparency, the Parties shall publish their laws, or otherwise make publicly available their laws, regulations and administrative rulings of general application as well as their respective international agreements that may affect their procurement markets. The Parties shall promptly respond to specific questions and provide, upon request, information to each other on matters referred to in this paragraph. 


3. If a Party grants to a non-Party, after the entry into force of this Agreement, additional benefits with regard to the access to its procurement markets, it shall agree to enter into negotiations with a view to extending these benefits to another Party on a reciprocal basis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Payments And Capital Movements" chapter_identifier="3272">
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Payments For Current Transactions" article_identifier="27477">Subject to the provisions of Article 29, the Parties undertake to allow all payments for current transactions to be made in a freely convertible currency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Capital Movements" article_identifier="27478">1. The Parties shall ensure that capital for investments made in companies formed in accordance with their laws, any returns stemming therefrom, and the amounts resulting from liquidations of investments are freely transferable. 


2. The Parties shall hold consultations with a view to facilitating the movement of capital between Albania and the EFTA States and achieve its complete liberalisation as soon as conditions permit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Balance Of Payments Difficulties" article_identifier="27479">Where Albania or an EFTA State is in serious balance of payments difficulties, or under threat thereof, Albania or the EFTA State concerned, respectively, may, in conformity with the conditions laid down within the framework of the GATT and in Articles VIII and XIV of the Statutes of the International Monetary Fund, take restrictive measures with regard to current payments if such measures are strictly necessary. Albania or the EFTA State concerned, as the case may be, shall inform the other Parties immediately of such a measure and shall provide as soon as possible a timetable for their removal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Clarifications" article_identifier="27480">It is understood that the obligations stated in this Chapter are without prejudice to the equitable, non-discriminatory and good faith application of measures pursuant to court orders or judgements and administrative proceedings. It is also understood that the right of an investor to freely transfer amounts in relation to his investment is without prejudice to any fiscal obligation such an investor may have.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Institutional Provisions" chapter_identifier="3273">
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="The Joint Committee" article_identifier="27481">1. The Parties hereby establish the Albania-EFTA Joint Committee. It shall be composed of representatives of the Parties, which shall be headed by Ministers or by senior officials delegated by them for this purpose. 


2. 	The Joint Committee shall: 


(a) 	supervise and review the implementation of this Agreement, inter alia by means of a comprehensive review of the application of the provisions of this Agreement, with due regard to any specific reviews contained in this Agreement; 


(b) 	keep under review the possibility of further removal of barriers to trade and other restrictive measures concerning trade between Albania and the EFTA States; 


(c) 	oversee the further development of this Agreement; 


(d) 	supervise the work of all sub-committees and working groups established under this Agreement; 


(e) 	endeavour to resolve disputes that may arise regarding the interpretation or application of this Agreement; 


(f) 	oversee the implementation of Article 5; and 


(g) 	consider any other matter that may affect the operation of this Agreement. 

3. The Joint Committee may decide to set up such sub-committees and working groups as it considers necessary to assist it in accomplishing its tasks. Except where otherwise provided for in this Agreement, the sub-committees and working groups shall work under a mandate established by the Joint Committee. 


4. The Joint Committee shall take decisions as provided for in this Agreement, and may make recommendations, by consensus. 


5. The Joint Committee shall meet within one year of the entry into force of this Agreement. Thereafter, it shall meet whenever necessary upon mutual agreement but normally every two years. Its meetings shall be chaired jointly by Albania and one of the EFTA States. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules of procedure. 


6. Each Party may request at any time, through a notice in writing to the other Parties, that a special meeting of the Joint Committee be held. Such a meeting shall take place within 30 days of receipt of the request, unless the Parties agree otherwise. 


7. The Joint Committee may decide to amend the Annexes and Protocols to this Agreement. Subject to paragraph 8, it may set a date for the entry into force of such decisions. 


8. If a representative of a Party in the Joint Committee has accepted a decision subject to the fulfilment of constitutional requirements, the decision shall enter into force on the date that the last Party notifies that its internal requirements have been fulfilled, unless the decision itself specifies a later date. The Joint Committee may decide that the decision shall enter into force for those Parties that have fulfilled their internal requirements, provided that Albania is one of those Parties. A Party may apply a decision of the Joint Committee provisionally until such decision enters into force for that Party, subject to its constitutional requirements.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="3274">
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Consultations" article_identifier="27482">1. In case of any divergence with respect to the interpretation, implementation and application of this Agreement, the Parties shall make every attempt through cooperation and consultations to arrive at a mutually satisfactory solution. 


2. Any Party may request in writing consultations with any other Party regarding any actual or proposed measure or any other matter that it considers might affect the operation of this Agreement. The Party requesting consultations shall at the same time notify the other Parties in writing thereof and supply all relevant information. 


3. The consultations shall take place in the Joint Committee if any of the Parties so requests within 20 days from the receipt of the notification referred to in paragraph 2, with a view to finding a commonly acceptable solution. If the Party to which a request in accordance with paragraph 2 or this paragraph is made does not reply within ten days or does not enter into consultations within 20 days after receipt of the request, the Party making the request is entitled to request the establishment of an arbitration panel in accordance with Article 33.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Arbitration" article_identifier="27483">1. Disputes between the Parties relating to the interpretation of rights and obligations under this Agreement, which have not been settled through direct consultations or in the Joint Committee within 60 days from the date of the receipt of the request for consultations, may be referred to arbitration by the complaining Party by means of a written notification addressed to the Party complained against. A copy of this notification shall be communicated to all other Parties so that each of those Parties may determine whether to participate in the dispute. 


2. Where more than one Party requests the establishment of an arbitration panel relating to the same matter, a single arbitration panel may, whenever feasible, be established to consider such disputes. 1 


3. A Party that is not a party to the dispute shall be entitled, on delivery of a written request to the parties to the dispute, to make written submissions to the arbitration panel, receive written submissions, including annexes, from the parties to the dispute, attend hearings and make oral statements. 


4. The arbitration panel shall comprise three members. In its written notification pursuant to paragraph 1 of this Article the Party referring the dispute to arbitration shall designate one member, who may be its national or resident. Within 30 days from the receipt of the notification referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, the Party to which it was addressed shall, in turn, designate one member, who may be its national or resident. 


5. Within 60 days from the receipt of the notification referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, the two members already designated shall agree on the designation of a third member. The third member shall not be a national of either party to the dispute, nor permanently reside on the territory of either party to the dispute. The member thus appointed shall be the President of the arbitration panel. 


6. If all three members have not been designated or appointed within 60 days from the receipt of the notification referred to in paragraph 1, either party to the dispute may request the Secretary–General of the Permanent Court of Arbitration at the Hague to designate an appointing authority. 


7. The arbitration panel shall examine the matter referred to it in the request for the establishment of an arbitration panel in light of the provisions of this Agreement applied and interpreted in accordance with the rules of interpretation of public international law. The award of the arbitration panel shall be final and binding upon the parties to the dispute. 


8. Unless otherwise specified in this Agreement or agreed between the parties to the dispute, the Optional Rules for Arbitrating Disputes between Two States of the Permanent Court of Arbitration (PCA), effective 20 October 1992, shall apply. 
For the purpose of this Chapter, the terms ”Party” and ”party to the dispute” are used regardless of whether two or more Parties are involved in a dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Implementation Of The Award" article_identifier="27484">1. The Party concerned shall promptly comply with the award of the arbitration panel. If it is impracticable to comply immediately, the parties to the dispute shall endeavour to agree on a reasonable period of time to do so. In the absence of such agreement within 30 days from the date of the award, either party to the dispute may, within 10 days from the expiration of such period, request the original arbitration panel to determine the length of the reasonable period of time. 


2. The Party concerned shall notify the other party to the dispute of the measure adopted in order to implement the award. 


3. If the Party concerned fails to comply with the award within a reasonable period of time and the parties to the dispute have not agreed on any compensation, the other party to the dispute may, until the award has been properly implemented or the dispute has been otherwise resolved, and subject to a prior notification of 30 days, suspend the application of benefits granted under this Agreement, but only equivalent to those affected by the measure that the arbitration panel has found to violate this Agreement. 


4. Any dispute regarding the implementation of the award or the notified suspension shall be decided by the arbitration panel upon request of either party to the dispute before compensation can be sought or suspension of benefits can be applied. The arbitration panel may also rule on the conformity with the award of any implementing measures adopted after the suspension of benefits and whether the suspension of benefits should be terminated or modified. The ruling of the arbitration panel under this paragraph shall normally be given within 45 days from the date of receipt of the request.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="3275">
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Fulfilment Of Obligations" article_identifier="27485">The Parties shall take any general or specific measures required to fulfil their obligations under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Annexes And Protocols" article_identifier="27486">The Annexes and Protocols to this Agreement, including their Appendices, are an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Evolutionary Clause" article_identifier="27487">1. The Parties undertake to review this Agreement in light of further developments in international economic relations, inter alia, in the framework of the WTO, and to examine in this context and in light of any relevant factor the possibility of further developing and deepening their co-operation under this Agreement and to extend it to areas not covered therein. The Joint Committee may examine this possibility and, where appropriate, make recommendations to the Parties, particularly with a view to opening up negotiations. 


2. Agreements resulting from the procedure referred to in paragraph 1 shall be subject to ratification, acceptance or approval by the Parties in accordance with their own procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Amendments" article_identifier="27488">1. The Parties may agree on any amendment to this Agreement. Unless otherwise agreed by the Parties, amendments shall enter into force on the first day of the third month following the deposit of the last instrument of ratification, acceptance or approval. 


2. The text of the amendments as well as the instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval shall be deposited with the Depositary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Relation To Other International Agreements" article_identifier="27489">1. The provisions of this Agreement shall be without prejudice to the rights and obligations of the Parties under the WTO Agreement and the other agreements negotiated thereunder, to which they are a party, and any other international agreement, to which they are a party. 


2. This Agreement shall not preclude the maintenance or establishment of customs unions, free trade areas, arrangements for frontier trade and other preferential agreements insofar as they do not have the effect of altering the trade arrangements provided for in this Agreement. 


3. When a Party enters into a customs union or free trade agreement with a third party it shall, upon request by any other Party, be prepared to enter into consultations with the requesting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Accession" article_identifier="27490">1. Any State, becoming a Member of the European Free Trade Association may accede to this Agreement, provided that the Joint Committee approves its accession, on terms and conditions to be agreed upon by the Parties. The instrument of accession shall be deposited with the Depositary. 


2. In relation to an acceding State, this Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the third month following the deposit of its instrument of accession, or the approval of the terms of accession by the existing Parties, whichever is later.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Withdrawal And Expiration" article_identifier="27491">1. Each Party may withdraw from this Agreement by means of a written notification to the Depositary. The withdrawal shall take effect six months after the date on which the notification is received by the Depositary. 


2. If Albania withdraws, this Agreement shall expire when its withdrawal becomes effective. 


3. Any EFTA State which withdraws from the Convention establishing the European Free Trade Association shall, ipso facto on the same day as the withdrawal takes effect, cease to be a Party to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="27492">1. This Agreement is subject to ratification, acceptance or approval in accordance with the respective constitutional requirements of the Parties. The instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval shall be deposited with the Depositary. 


2. This Agreement shall enter into force on 1 April 2010 in relation to those Parties which have deposited their instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval, or notified provisional application to the Depositary, at least two months before that date, and provided that Albania is among those Parties. 


3. In case this Agreement does not enter into force on 1 April 2010 it shall enter into force on the first day of the third month after Albania and at least one EFTA State have deposited their instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval, or notified provisional application to the Depositary. 


4. In relation to an EFTA State depositing its instrument of ratification, acceptance or approval after this Agreement has entered into force, this Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the third month following the deposit of its instrument of ratification, acceptance or approval. 


5. If its constitutional requirements permit, Albania or any EFTA State may apply this Agreement provisionally pending ratification, acceptance or approval by that Party. Provisional application of this Agreement shall be notified to the Depositary. 


6. This Agreement shall not enter into force or be applied provisionally between Albania and an EFTA State unless the complementary agreement on trade in agricultural products between Albania and that EFTA State enters into force or is applied provisionally simultaneously. It shall remain in force between Albania and that EFTA State as long as the complementary agreement remains in force between them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Depositary" article_identifier="27493">The Government of Norway shall act as Depositary.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="3276">
      <article article_identifier="27494">IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorised thereto, have signed this Agreement. 

Done at Geneva, this 17th day of December 2009, in one original. The Depositary shall transmit certified copies to all the Parties. 

For the Republic of Albania  

For Iceland 
........................................... 

........................................... 


For the Principality of Liechtenstein 


........................................... 


For the Kingdom of Norway 


........................................... 


For the Swiss Confederation 


...........................................</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
