<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Switzerland</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>179</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>155</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2009-02-19</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2009-09-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2009-09-01</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2024-12-30</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">CHE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">CHE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">JPN</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia; Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/europe/switzerland/epa0902/agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/europe/switzerland/epa0902/index.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1721">
      <article article_identifier="14287">Preamble 


Japan and the Swiss Confederation (hereinafter referred to
as “Switzerland”), 


hereinafter referred to as "the Parties", 


RECOGNISING that a dynamic and rapidly changing global
environment brought about by globalisation and technological
progress presents various economic and strategic challenges and
opportunities to the Parties; 


CONSCIOUS of their longstanding friendship and ties that
have developed through many years of fruitful and mutually
beneficial cooperation and convinced that this Agreement will
open a new era for their relationship; 


REAFFIRMING their commitment to democracy, the rule of law,
human rights and fundamental freedoms in accordance with their
obligations under international law, including those set out in
the United Nations Charter, and with the principles of the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights; 


BELIEVING that their bilateral relationship will be
enhanced by forging a mutually beneficial economic partnership
through trade liberalisation, trade facilitation and
cooperation; 


CONVINCED that the economic partnership will provide a
useful framework for enhanced cooperation, serve their common
interests in various fields as agreed in this Agreement and
lead to the improvement of economic efficiency and the
development of trade, investment and human resources; 


RECOGNISING that such a partnership will create larger and
new markets, and enhance the attractiveness and dynamism of
their markets; 


RECALLING Article XXIV of the General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General Agreement on Trade
in Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B, respectively, to the
Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization,
done at Marrakesh on 15 April 1994; 


RECOGNISING the importance of ensuring security in
international trade without creating unnecessary obstacles to
trade and of further deepening cooperation between the Parties
in that field; 


DETERMINED, in implementing this Agreement, to seek to
preserve and protect the environment, to promote the optimal
use of natural resources in accordance with the objective of
sustainable development and to adequately address the
challenges of climate change; 


BELIEVING that this Agreement lays the foundation for
further invigoration of cooperation between them in various
economic fields; and 


DETERMINED to establish a legal framework for an economic
partnership between them; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1722">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="14288">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 



(a) liberalise and facilitate trade in goods and services
between the Parties; 



(b) increase investment opportunities and strengthen
protection for investments and investment activities
in the Parties; 



(c) promote cooperation and coordination for the effective
enforcement of competition laws and regulations in
each Party; 



(d) ensure protection of intellectual property and promote
cooperation in this field; 



(e) enhance opportunities for suppliers of the Parties to
participate in government procurement in the Parties;
and 



(f) create effective procedures for the implementation of
this Agreement and for the resolution of disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Scope Of Application" article_identifier="14289">Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, wherever
applicable, this Agreement shall apply to the territories of
the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="14290">For the purposes of this Agreement: 



(a) “Area” of a Party means: 



(i) with respect to Japan, the territory of Japan,
and all the area beyond its territorial sea,
including the sea-bed and subsoil thereof, over
which Japan exercises sovereign rights or
jurisdiction in accordance with international
law and the laws and regulations of Japan; and 



(ii) with respect to Switzerland, the territory of
Switzerland; 


(b) “customs territory” of a Party means the territory
with respect to which the customs laws of the Party
are in force. The customs territory of Switzerland
includes the territory of the Principality of
Liechtenstein, as long as the Customs Union Treaty of
29 March 1923 between the Swiss Confederation and the 
Principality of Liechtenstein remains in force; 



(c) 	“GATS” means the General Agreement on Trade in
Services in Annex 1B to the WTO Agreement; 



(d) 	“GATT 1994” means the General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. For
the purposes of this Agreement, references to
articles in the GATT 1994 include the interpretative
notes; 



(e) “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the Harmonized
Commodity Description and Coding System set out in
the Annex to the International Convention on the 
Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding System,
and adopted and implemented by the Parties in their
respective laws; 



(f) “TRIPS Agreement” means the Agreement on Trade-
Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights in
Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement; and 



(g) 	“WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh Agreement
Establishing the World Trade Organization, done at
Marrakesh on 15 April 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Transparency" article_identifier="14291">1. Each Party shall promptly publish, or otherwise make
publicly available, its laws, regulations, administrative
procedures, judicial decisions and administrative rulings of
general application as well as international agreements to
which the Party is a party, which pertain to or affect the
operation of this Agreement. 



2. Each Party shall make its best efforts to ensure that the
public obtains, upon request, the names and addresses of the
competent authorities responsible for laws, regulations,
administrative procedures and administrative rulings, referred
to in paragraph 1. 



3. Each Party shall, upon request by the other Party, within
a reasonable period of time, respond to specific questions from, 
and provide information to, the other Party with respect to
matters referred to in paragraph 1. 



4. When introducing or changing its laws, regulations, or
administrative procedures that significantly affect the
operation of this Agreement, each Party shall endeavour to
provide, except in emergency situations, a reasonable interval
between the time when such laws, regulations, or administrative
procedures are published or made publicly available and the
time when they enter into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="14292">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, nothing
in this Agreement shall require a Party to provide confidential
information, the disclosure of which would impede the
enforcement of its laws and regulations or otherwise be
contrary to the public interest, or which would prejudice the
legitimate commercial interests of particular enterprises,
public or private. 



2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, maintain the confidentiality of information
provided in confidence by the other Party pursuant to this
Agreement. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, the information provided
pursuant to this Agreement may be transmitted to a third party,
subject to prior consent of the Party which provided the
information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Taxation" article_identifier="14293">1. The following provisions in this Agreement are relevant
to taxation measures: 



(a) Article 14, and such other provisions as are
necessary to give effect to that Article to the same
extent as Article III of the GATT 1994; 



(b) Chapter 6; 



(c) Chapter 9, as provided for in Article 100; 



(d) Chapter 11; and 



(e) Chapter 12. 


2. Without prejudice to Chapters 6, 9 and 11, nothing in
this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations of
either Party under any agreement on the avoidance of double
taxation. In the event of any inconsistency between this
Agreement and any such agreement, that agreement shall prevail
to the extent of the inconsistency. 



3. If a Party considers that a taxation measure applied by
the other Party adversely affects the implementation or the
functioning of provisions of this Agreement other than those
referred to in paragraph 1, the Parties shall, upon request of
the former Party, hold consultations with a view to finding a
mutually satisfactory solution without having recourse to the
dispute settlement procedures provided for in Chapter 14.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="14294">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations under
the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which both Parties
are parties. 



2. In the event of any inconsistency arising between this
Agreement and the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to
which both Parties are parties, the Parties shall immediately
consult with each other with a view to finding a mutually
satisfactory solution, taking into consideration general
principles of international law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Preferential Agreements" article_identifier="14295">1. This Agreement shall not prevent the maintenance or
establishment of customs unions, free trade areas, arrangements
for frontier trade and other preferential agreements, to the
extent that they do not adversely affect the rights and
obligations provided for by this Agreement. 



2. In case a Party establishes a customs union with a non-
Party, it shall inform the other Party. Upon request of the
other Party, the Parties shall enter into consultations with a
view to examining the possible impact of the customs union on
the implementation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Promotion Of Trade In Environmental Products And Environment-Related Services" article_identifier="14296">1. The Parties shall encourage trade and dissemination of
environmental products and environment-related services in
order to facilitate access to technologies and products that
support the environmental protection and development goals,
such as improved sanitation, pollution prevention, sustainable
promotion of renewable energy and climate-change-related goals. 



2. The Parties shall periodically review in the Joint
Committee progress achieved in pursuing the objectives set out
in paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="14297">The Governments of the Parties shall conclude a separate
agreement (hereinafter referred to as “the Implementing
Agreement”), which sets forth details and procedures for the
implementation of certain provisions of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="1723">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14298">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) “bilateral safeguard measure” means a bilateral
safeguard measure provided for in paragraph 2 of
Article 20; 



(b) “customs duty on exports” means any duty and a
charge of any kind, including any form of surtax or
surcharge, imposed in connection with the
exportation of a product, but does not include any
fee or other charge commensurate with the cost of
services rendered, imposed consistently with the
provisions of Article VIII of the GATT 1994; 



(c) “customs duty on imports” means any duty and a
charge of any kind, including any form of surtax or
surcharge, imposed in connection with the
importation of a product, but does not include any: 



(i) charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed
consistently with the provisions of paragraph 2
of Article III of the GATT 1994, in respect of
like products or directly competitive or
substitutable products of the customs territory
of a Party, or in respect of products from
which the imported products have been
manufactured or produced in whole or in part; 



(ii) anti-dumping or countervailing duty applied
pursuant to the laws and regulations of a Party
and applied consistently with the provisions of
Article VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on
Implementation of Article VI of the General
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A
to the WTO Agreement and the Agreement on
Subsidies and Countervailing Measures in Annex
1A to the WTO Agreement; or 

(iii) fee or other charge commensurate with the cost
of services rendered, imposed consistently with
the provisions of Article VIII of the GATT
1994; 


(d) “customs value of products” means the value of
products for the purposes of levying ad valorem 
customs duties on imports; 



(e) “domestic industry” means the producers as a whole
of the like or directly competitive products
operating in the customs territory of a Party, or
those whose collective output of the like or
directly competitive products constitutes a major
proportion of the total domestic production of those
products; 



(f) “export subsidies” means export subsidies listed in
subparagraphs 1(a) to 1(f) of Article 9 of the
Agreement on Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO
Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “the Agreement
on Agriculture”); 



(g) “originating product” means a product which
qualifies as an originating product under Annex II; 



(h) “serious injury” means a significant overall
impairment in the position of a domestic industry;
and 



(i) “threat of serious injury” means serious injury that,
on the basis of facts and not merely on allegation,
conjecture or remote possibility, is clearly
imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Scope" article_identifier="14299">This Chapter shall apply, as specified therein, to any
product traded between the customs territories of the Parties,
falling within any chapter of the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Classification Of Products" article_identifier="14300">The classification of products traded between the customs
territories of the Parties shall be in conformity with the
Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="14301">Each Party shall accord national treatment to the products
of the customs territory of the other Party in accordance with
Article III of the GATT 1994, which is hereby incorporated
into and made part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Customs Duty On Imports" article_identifier="14302">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, each
Party shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties on imports
on originating products of the Party and the other Party,
imported from the customs territory of the other Party, in
accordance with the terms and conditions set out in its 
Schedule in Annex I. 



2. In cases where its most-favoured-nation applied rate of
customs duty on imports on a particular product is lower than
the rate of customs duty on imports to be applied in
accordance with paragraph 1 on an originating product which is
classified under the same tariff line as that particular
product, each Party shall apply the lower rate with respect to
that originating product. 



3. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,
neither Party shall increase any customs duty on imports on
originating products of the Party and the other Party,
imported from the customs territory of the other Party, above
the rate to be applied in accordance with the terms and
conditions set out in its Schedule in Annex I.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Customs Duty On Exports" article_identifier="14303">Neither Party shall introduce or maintain any customs
duty on exports on products exported from the customs
territory of the Party into the customs territory of the other
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="14304">For the purposes of determining the customs value of
products traded between the customs territories of the Parties,
the provisions of Part I of the Agreement on Implementation of
Article VII of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994
in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as
“the Agreement on Customs Valuation”), which is hereby
incorporated into and made part of this Agreement, mutatis 
mutandis, shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="14305">Each Party shall ensure that no prohibition or restriction
other than customs duties on imports and customs duties on
exports inconsistent with its obligations under Article XI of
the GATT 1994 and other relevant provisions under the WTO
Agreement are introduced or maintained in the customs
territory of the Party on the importation of any product of
the customs territory of the other Party or on the exportation
or sale for export of any product destined for the customs
territory of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Export Subsidies" article_identifier="14306">Unless otherwise provided for in Annex I, no export
subsidies shall be introduced or maintained in the customs 
territory of a Party on any agricultural product which is
listed in Annex 1 to the Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="14307">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, a Party may
apply a bilateral safeguard measure, to the minimum extent
necessary to prevent or remedy serious injury to its domestic
industry and to facilitate adjustment thereof, if an
originating product of the other Party, as a result of the
elimination or reduction of a customs duty on imports in
accordance with Article 15, is being imported into the customs
territory of the former Party in such increased quantities, in
absolute terms or relative to domestic production, and under
such conditions that the imports of that originating product
constitute a substantial cause of serious injury, or threat of
serious injury, to the domestic industry in the customs
territory of the former Party. 



2. A Party may, unless otherwise provided for in Annex I, as
a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) 	suspend the further reduction of the rate of customs
duty on imports on the originating product of the
other Party referred to in paragraph 1; or 



(b) 	increase the rate of customs duty on imports on the
originating product of the other Party referred to
in paragraph 1 to a level not to exceed the lesser
of: 



(i) the most-favoured-nation applied rate of
customs duty on imports in effect on the day
when the bilateral safeguard measure is taken;
and 



(ii) the most-favoured-nation applied rate of
customs duty on imports in effect on the day
immediately preceding the date of entry into
force of this Agreement. 


3. A Party shall not apply a bilateral safeguard measure to
originating products imported up to the limit of quota
quantities granted under tariff rate quotas applied in
accordance with the terms and conditions set out in its 
Schedule in Annex I. 



4. A Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure only after
an investigation has been carried out by its competent
authorities in accordance with the same procedures as provided
for in Article 3 and paragraph 2 of Article 4 of the Agreement
on Safeguards in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter
referred to as “the Agreement on Safeguards”). Such
investigation shall in all cases be completed within one year
following its date of initiation. 



5. The following conditions and limitations shall apply with
regard to a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) A Party shall immediately make a written notice to
the other Party upon: 



(i) initiating an investigation referred to in
paragraph 4 relating to serious injury, or
threat of serious injury, and the reasons for
it; and 



(ii) taking a decision to apply or extend a
bilateral safeguard measure. 


(b) 	The Party making the written notice referred to in
subparagraph (a) shall provide the other Party with
all pertinent information in that notice, including: 



(i) in respect of subparagraph (a)(i), in addition
to the reason for the initiation of the 
investigation, a precise description of the
originating product subject to the
investigation and its subheading under the
Harmonized System, the period to be covered by
the investigation and the date of initiation of
the investigation; and 



(ii) in respect of subparagraph (a)(ii), evidence of
serious injury or threat of serious injury
caused by the increased imports of the
originating product, a precise description of
the originating product subject to the proposed
bilateral safeguard measure and its subheading
under the Harmonized System, a precise
description of the proposed bilateral safeguard
measure, and the proposed date of introduction
and expected duration of the bilateral
safeguard measure. 


(c) 	A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral
safeguard measure shall provide adequate opportunity
for prior consultations with the other Party with a
view to reviewing the information gained from the
investigation referred to in paragraph 4, exchanging
views on the bilateral safeguard measure and
reaching an agreement on compensation provided for
in paragraph 6. 



(d) 	No bilateral safeguard measure shall be maintained
except to the extent and for such period of time as
may be necessary to prevent or remedy serious injury
and to facilitate adjustment, provided that such
period of time does not exceed two years. However,
in highly exceptional circumstances, a bilateral
safeguard measure may be extended, provided that the
total duration of the bilateral safeguard measure,
including such extensions, does not exceed three
years. In order to facilitate adjustment in a
situation where the expected duration of a bilateral
safeguard measure exceeds one year, the Party
maintaining the bilateral safeguard measure shall
progressively liberalise it at regular intervals
during the period of application. 



(e) 	No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied
again to the import of a particular originating
product which has been subject to such a bilateral
safeguard measure, for a period of time equal to the
duration of the previous bilateral safeguard measure
or one year, whichever is longer. 



(f) 	Upon termination of a bilateral safeguard measure,
the rate of customs duty on imports on the
originating product concerned shall be the rate
which would have been in effect but for the 
bilateral safeguard measure. 


6. 	(a) A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral 
safeguard measure shall provide to the other Party
mutually agreed adequate means of trade compensation
in the form of concessions of customs duties on 
imports whose value is substantially equivalent to
that of the additional customs duties on imports
expected to result from the bilateral safeguard
measure. 


(b) 	If the Parties are unable to agree on compensation
within 30 days after the commencement of
consultations pursuant to subparagraph 5(c), the
Party to whose originating product the bilateral
safeguard measure is applied shall be free to
suspend the application of concessions of customs
duties on imports under this Chapter which are
substantially equivalent to the bilateral safeguard
measure. The Party exercising the right of
suspension may suspend the application of
concessions of customs duties on imports only for
the minimum period necessary to achieve the
substantially equivalent effects and only while the
bilateral safeguard measure is maintained. 


7. Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial and
reasonable administration of its laws and regulations relating
to bilateral safeguard measures. 



8. In applying a bilateral safeguard measure, each Party
shall follow equitable, timely, transparent and effective
procedures. 



9. 	(a) In critical circumstances, where delay would cause 
damage which it would be difficult to repair, a
Party may apply a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure, unless otherwise provided for in Annex I,
which shall take the form of a measure set out in 
subparagraph 2(a) or 2(b), pursuant to a preliminary
determination that there is clear evidence that 
increased imports of an originating product of the
other Party have caused serious injury or threat of
serious injury to a domestic industry in the customs
territory of the former Party. 



(b) A Party shall make a written notice to the other
Party prior to applying a provisional bilateral
safeguard measure referred to in subparagraph (a).
Consultations between the Parties on the application
of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall
be initiated immediately after it is applied. 



(c) The duration of the provisional bilateral safeguard
measure referred to in subparagraph (a) shall not
exceed 200 days. During that period, the pertinent
requirements of paragraph 4 shall be met. The
duration of the provisional bilateral safeguard
measure shall be counted as a part of the period
referred to in subparagraph 5(d). 



(d) Subparagraph 5(f) and paragraphs 7 and 8 shall
apply, mutatis mutandis, to the provisional
bilateral safeguard measure referred to in
subparagraph (a). The customs duty on imports
imposed as a result of the provisional bilateral
safeguard measure shall be refunded if the
subsequent investigation referred to in paragraph 4
does not determine that increased imports of an
originating product of the other Party have caused
serious injury or threat of serious injury to a
domestic industry. 


10. A written notice referred to in subparagraphs 5(a) and
9(b) and any other communication between the Parties pursuant
to this Article shall be made in the English language. 



11. The Parties shall review the provisions of this Article,
if necessary, ten years after the date of entry into force of
this Agreement or thereafter. 



12. Nothing in this Chapter shall prevent a Party from
applying safeguard measures to an originating product of the
other Party in accordance with: 



(a) Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
Safeguards; or 



(b) Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="14308">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be so construed as to
prevent a Party from taking any measure for balance-ofpayments purposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in
accordance with the conditions and procedures established
under Article XII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on
the Balance-of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude the use by a Party
of exchange controls or exchange restrictions in accordance
with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary
Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="14309">For the purposes of this Chapter, Articles XX and XXI of
the GATT 1994, which are hereby incorporated into and made
part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis, shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="14310">The provisions on Rules of Origin are set out in Annex II.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Operational Procedures For Trade In Goods" article_identifier="14311">Upon entry into force of this Agreement, the Joint
Committee shall adopt Operational Procedures for Trade in
Goods that provide detailed regulations pursuant to which the
relevant authorities of the Parties shall implement their
functions under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="General Review" article_identifier="14312">The Parties shall undertake a general review of the
provisions of this Chapter and the Schedules of the Parties in
Annex I in the fifth calendar year following the calendar year
in which this Agreement enters into force. As a result of such
a review, the Parties may, if they agree, enter into
negotiations on possible improvement of market access under
this Chapter and the Schedules of the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Customs Procedures And Trade Facilitation" chapter_identifier="1724">
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Scope" article_identifier="14313">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures required
for the clearance of products traded between the customs
territories of the Parties. 



2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties in
accordance with their respective laws and regulations and
within the available resources of their respective customs
authorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14314">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	“A.T.A. Convention” means the Customs Convention on 
the A.T.A. Carnet for the Temporary Admission of
Goods, done at Brussels on 6 December 1961; 



(b) 	“customs authority” means the customs authority as
defined in paragraph (c) of Article I of Annex II;
and 



(c) 	“customs laws” means the laws and regulations
administered and enforced by the customs authority
of each Party concerning the importation,
exportation and transit of products, relating to
customs duties, charges and other taxes, or to
prohibitions, restrictions and other similar
controls, falling under the competence of the
customs authority of the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Transparency" article_identifier="14315">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant information of
general application pertaining to its customs laws is readily
available to any interested person. 



2. When information that has been made available must be 
revised due to changes in its customs laws, each Party shall
make the revised information readily available sufficiently in
advance of the entry into force of the changes to enable
interested persons to take account of them, unless such an
advance notice is precluded. 



3. At the request of any interested person of the Parties,
each Party shall provide, as quickly and as accurately as
possible, information relating to the specific customs matters
raised by the interested person and pertaining to its customs
laws. Each Party shall supply not only the information
specifically requested but also any other pertinent
information which it considers the interested person should be
made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="14316">1. The Parties shall apply their respective customs
procedures in a predictable, consistent and transparent manner. 



2. For prompt customs clearance of products traded between
the customs territories of the Parties, each Party shall: 



(a) 	make use of information and communications 
technology; 



(b) 	simplify its customs procedures; 



(c) 	harmonise its customs procedures, to the extent
possible, with relevant international standards and
recommended practices such as those adopted under
the auspices of the Customs Co-operation Council;
and 



(d) 	promote cooperation, wherever appropriate, between
its customs authority and: 



(i) other national authorities of the Party; 



(ii) the trading communities of the Party; and 

(iii) the customs authorities of non-Parties. 


3. Each Party shall provide affected parties with easily
accessible means of administrative and judicial review of its
administrative actions relating to customs matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Temporary Admission And Products In Transit" article_identifier="14317">1. Each Party shall continue to facilitate the procedures
for the temporary admission of products traded between the
customs territories of the Parties in accordance with the 


A.T.A. Convention. 



2. Each Party shall continue to facilitate customs clearance
of products in transit from or to the customs territory of the
other Party in accordance with paragraph 3 of Article V of the
GATT 1994. 



3. The Parties shall endeavour to promote, through seminars
and courses, the use of A.T.A. carnets pursuant to the A.T.A.
Convention for the temporary admission of products and the
facilitation of customs clearance of products in transit in
the customs territories of the Parties or non-Parties. 



4. For the purposes of this Article, “temporary admission”
means customs procedures under which certain products may be
brought into a customs territory conditionally, relieved
totally or partially from the payment of customs duties. Such
products shall be imported for a specific purpose, and shall
be intended for re-exportation within a specified period and
without having undergone any change except normal depreciation
due to the use made of them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Cooperation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="14318">1. The Parties shall cooperate and exchange information in
the field of customs procedures, including the enforcement
against the trafficking of prohibited products and the
importation and exportation of products suspected of
infringing intellectual property rights. 



2. Paragraph 1 of Article 5 shall not apply to the exchange
of information under this Article. 



3. Chapter 2 of the Implementing Agreement provides for the
details and procedures for the implementation of cooperation
and exchange of information, including exchange of
confidential information, under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin, Customs Procedures And Trade Facilitation" article_identifier="14319">For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Rules of
Origin, Customs Procedures and Trade Facilitation established
under Article XXX of Annex II shall perform the functions
provided for in the said Article.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="1725">
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Scope" article_identifier="14320">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary and
phytosanitary (hereinafter referred to as “SPS”) measures of
the Parties under the Agreement on the Application of Sanitary
and Phytosanitary Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to as “the SPS Agreement”), that may,
directly or indirectly, affect trade in goods between the
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="14321">With regard to the rights and obligations of the Parties
in respect of SPS measures, the SPS Agreement shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Consultations On Sps Matters" article_identifier="14322">1. The Parties shall hold science-based consultations to 
identify and address specific issues that may arise from the
application of SPS measures with the objective of finding
mutually acceptable solutions, at such time and venue as may
be agreed by the Parties. 



2. The consultations referred to in paragraph 1 shall be held
between officials of the Governments of the Parties with the 
necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be discussed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="14323">Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="1726">
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Scope" article_identifier="14324">1. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures as defined in
the Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A to
the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to as “the TBT
Agreement”). 



2. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures with respect to
any product irrespective of its origin. 



3. This Chapter shall not apply to purchasing specifications
prepared by governmental bodies for production or consumption
requirements of governmental bodies and sanitary and
phytosanitary measures as defined in the SPS Agreement. 



4. With regard to the rights and obligations of the Parties
in respect of technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures, the TBT Agreement shall apply, unless
otherwise provided for in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="14325">1. In order to ensure that technical regulations, standards
and conformity assessment procedures do not create unnecessary
obstacles to trade in goods between the Parties, the Parties
shall, where possible, strengthen their cooperation in the
field of technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures. When appropriate, this shall result in
sector-specific arrangements. 



2. Cooperation pursuant to paragraph 1 may include the
following: 



(a) 	exchanging information on technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures of
the Parties, including information regarding the
harmonisation of the regulations of the Parties with
international standards; 



(b) 	jointly contributing, where appropriate, to
activities related to technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures in
international and regional fora; and 



(c) 	reinforcing the role of international standards as a
basis for technical regulations and conformity
assessment procedures; and, in particular, promoting
the accreditation of conformity assessment bodies
and the acceptance of the results of conformity
assessment procedures, on the basis of the relevant
international standards.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Enquiry Point" article_identifier="14326">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point to answer all
reasonable enquiries from the other Party regarding technical
regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures
and, if appropriate, provide the other Party with other
relevant information which it considers the other Party should
be made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Acceptance Of Results Of Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="14327">1. Each Party shall ensure that, in cases where a positive
assurance of conformity with technical regulations is required
for a particular product, suppliers of such product imported
from the other Party shall be granted access on a nondiscriminatory basis. 



2. Each Party shall ensure, whenever possible, that results
of the conformity assessment procedures in the other Party are
accepted, even when those procedures differ from its own,
provided it is satisfied that the procedures offer an
assurance of conformity with applicable technical regulations
or standards equivalent to its own procedures. In this regard,
accreditation of conformity assessment bodies in accordance
with relevant standards or guides issued by the international
standardising bodies shall establish a rebuttable presumption
of adequate technical competence. 



3. The Parties recognise that prior consultations may be
necessary in order to arrive at a mutually satisfactory
understanding with regard to such matters as provided for in
paragraphs 1.1 and 1.2 of Article 6 of the TBT Agreement. Such
consultations shall take place in the Sub-Committee on
Technical Regulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment
Procedures provided for in Article 41. 



4. A Party shall, upon request of the other Party and where
appropriate, explain the reasons why it has not accepted the
results of conformity assessment procedures in the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="14328">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Technical
Regulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment Procedures
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-
Committee”) is hereby established. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) coordinating and facilitating cooperation pursuant
to this Chapter; 



(b) reviewing the implementation and operation of this
Chapter; 



(c) discussing any issues related to this Chapter with
the objective of finding mutually acceptable
solutions; 



(d) undertaking consultations on issues related to
technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures; 



(e) reporting its findings to the Joint Committee; and 



(f) carrying out other tasks assigned to it by the Joint
Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives of
the Governments of the Parties, and may invite representatives
of relevant entities other than the Governments of the Parties. 
All such representatives shall have the necessary expertise
relevant to the issues to be discussed. The Sub-Committee may
establish ad hoc working groups to accomplish specific tasks. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as may
be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="14329">Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="1727">
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="14330">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Party affecting
trade in services taken by central, regional or local
governments and authorities as well as by non-governmental
bodies in the exercise of powers delegated by central, regional
or local governments or authorities. It shall apply to all
services sectors. 



2. In respect of air transport services, this Chapter shall
not apply to measures affecting traffic rights, however 
granted, or measures affecting services directly related to
the exercise of traffic rights, other than those affecting: 



(a) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 



(b) the selling and marketing of air transport services;
or 



(c) computer reservation system (CRS) services. 


3. Articles 45 to 47 shall not apply to laws, regulations or
requirements governing the procurement by governmental
agencies of services purchased for governmental purposes and
not for commercial resale or for use in the supply of services
for commercial sale.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14331">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) “aircraft repair and maintenance services” means
such activities when undertaken on an aircraft or a 
part thereof while it is withdrawn from service and
does not include so-called line maintenance; 



(b) “commercial presence” means any type of business or
professional establishment, including through: 



(i) the constitution, acquisition or maintenance of
a juridical person; or 



(ii) the creation or maintenance of a branch or a 
representative office; 

within the Area of a Party for the purposes of
supplying a service; 



(c) “computer reservation system (CRS) services” means
services provided by computerised systems that
contain information about air carriers’ schedules,
availability, fares and fare rules, through which
reservations can be made or tickets may be issued; 



(d) “direct taxes” comprises all taxes on total income,
on total capital or on elements of income or of
capital, including taxes on gains from the
alienation of property, taxes on estates,
inheritances and gifts, and taxes on the total
amounts of wages or salaries paid by enterprises, as
well as taxes on capital appreciation; 



(e) “juridical person” means any legal entity duly
constituted or otherwise organised under applicable
law, whether for profit or otherwise, and whether
privately-owned or governmentally-owned, including
any corporation, trust, partnership, joint venture,
sole proprietorship or association; 



(f) a juridical person is: 



(i) “owned” by persons of a Party if more than 50
per cent of the equity interest in it is
beneficially owned by persons of that Party; 



(ii) “controlled” by persons of a Party if such
persons have the power to name a majority of its
directors or otherwise to legally direct its
actions; 

(iii) “affiliated” with another person when it controls,
or is controlled by, that other person; or when
it and the other person are both controlled by
the same person; 


(g) “juridical person of a Party” means a juridical
person which is either: 



(i) constituted or otherwise organised under the law
of that Party, and is engaged in substantive
business operations in the Area of: 



(A) either Party; or 



(B) 	any Member of the World Trade Organization
and is owned or controlled by natural
persons of that Party or by juridical
persons that meet all the conditions of
subparagraph (A); or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service through
commercial presence, owned or controlled by: 



(A) 	natural persons of that Party; or 



(B) 	juridical persons of that Party identified
under subparagraph (i); 


(h) “measure” means any measure by a Party, whether in
the form of a law, regulation, rule, procedure,
decision, administrative action or any other form; 



(i) “measures by a Party affecting trade in services”
includes measures in respect of: 



(i) the purchase, payment or use of a service; 



(ii) the access to and use of, in connection with the
supply of a service, services which are required
by that Party to be offered to the public
generally; 

(iii) the presence, including commercial presence, of
persons of the other Party for the supply of a
service in the Area of the Party; 


(j) “monopoly supplier of a service” means any person,
public or private, which in the relevant market of
the Area of a Party is authorised or established
formally or in effect by that Party as the sole
supplier of that service; 



(k) “natural person of a Party” means a natural person
who, under the legislation of that Party, is: 



(i) in respect of Japan, a national of Japan; or 



(ii) in respect of Switzerland: 



(A) 	a national of Switzerland; or 



(B) 	a permanent resident who resides in
Switzerland; 


(l) “person” means either a natural person or a
juridical person; 



(m) “selling and marketing of air transport services”
means opportunities for the air carrier concerned to
sell and market freely its air transport services
including all aspects of marketing such as market
research, advertising and distribution. These
activities do not include the pricing of air
transport services nor the applicable conditions; 



(n) “services” includes any service in any sector except
services supplied in the exercise of governmental
authority; 



(o) “service consumer” means any person that receives or
uses a service; 



(p) “service of the other Party” means a service which
is supplied: 



(i) from or in the Area of the other Party, or in
the case of maritime transport, by a vessel
registered under the laws of the other Party, or
by a person of the other Party which supplies
the service through the operation of a vessel
and/or its use in whole or in part; or 



(ii) in the case of the supply of a service through
commercial presence or through the presence of
natural persons, by a service supplier of the
other Party; 


(q) “a service supplied in the exercise of governmental
authority” means any service which is supplied
neither on a commercial basis nor in competition
with one or more service suppliers; 



(r) “service supplier” means any person that supplies,
or seeks to supply, a service; 


Note: Where the service is not supplied or sought to 
be supplied directly by a juridical person but
through other forms of commercial presence
such as a branch or a representative office,
the service supplier (i.e. the juridical
person) shall, nonetheless, through such
commercial presence be accorded the treatment
provided for service suppliers under this
Chapter. Such treatment shall be extended to
the commercial presence through which the
service is supplied or sought to be supplied
and need not be extended to any other parts of
the service supplier located outside the Area
of a Party where the service is supplied or
sought to be supplied. 


(s) “supply of a service” includes the production,
distribution, marketing, sale and delivery of a
service; 



(t) “trade in services” means the supply of a service: 



(i) from the Area of a Party into the Area of the
other Party (“cross-border supply mode”); 



(ii) in the Area of a Party to the service consumer
of the other Party (“consumption abroad mode”); 

(iii) by a service supplier of a Party, through
commercial presence in the Area of the other
Party (“commercial presence mode”); 


(iv) by a service supplier of a Party, through
presence, in the Area of the other Party, of
natural persons of a Party (“presence of natural
persons mode”); and 


(u) “traffic rights” means the rights for scheduled and
non-scheduled services to operate and/or to carry
passengers, cargo and mail for remuneration or hire
from, to, within, or over a Party, including points
to be served, routes to be operated, types of
traffic to be carried, capacity to be provided,
tariffs to be charged and their conditions, and
criteria for designation of airlines, including such
criteria as number, ownership and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="14332">1. Without prejudice to measures taken in accordance with
Article VII of the GATS, and unless otherwise specified in its
List of Reservations referred to in Article 57, a Party shall
accord immediately and unconditionally, in respect of all
measures affecting the supply of services, to services and
service suppliers of the other Party treatment no less
favourable than that it accords to like services and service 
suppliers of any non-Party. 



2. The provisions of this Chapter shall not be so construed
as to prevent either Party from conferring or according
advantages to adjacent countries in order to facilitate
exchanges limited to contiguous frontier zones of services
that are both locally produced and consumed. 



3. Treatment granted under other agreements concluded by a
Party and notified under Article V or Article Vbis of the GATS 
shall not be subject to paragraph 1. 



4. If a Party concludes or amends an agreement of the type
referred to in paragraph 3, it shall notify the other Party
without delay and endeavour to accord to the other Party
treatment no less favourable than that provided under that
agreement. The former Party shall, upon request by the other
Party, negotiate the incorporation into this Agreement of
treatment no less favourable than that provided under the
former agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Market Access" article_identifier="14333">1. With respect to market access through the modes of supply
identified in paragraph (t) of Article 44, a Party shall
accord services and service suppliers of the other Party
treatment in conformity with its List of Reservations referred
to in Article 57. 


Note: Unless otherwise specified in its List of 
Reservations referred to in Article 57 in respect of
market access, where the cross-border movement of
capital is an essential part of a service supplied
through the mode of supply referred to in
subparagraph (t)(i) of Article 44, a Party is hereby
committed to allow such movement of capital. Unless
otherwise specified in its List of Reservations
referred to in Article 57 in respect of market
access, where a service is supplied through the mode
of supply referred to in subparagraph (t)(iii) of
Article 44, a Party is hereby committed to allow
related transfers of capital into its Area. 


2. Unless otherwise specified in its List of Reservations
referred to in Article 57, a Party shall not maintain or adopt
either on the basis of a regional subdivision or on the basis
of its entire Area measures defined as: 



(a) limitations on the number of service suppliers
whether in the form of numerical quotas, monopolies,
exclusive service suppliers or the requirements of
an economic needs test; 



(b) 	limitations on the total value of service 
transactions or assets in the form of numerical 
quotas or the requirement of an economic needs test; 



(c) 	limitations on the total number of service 
operations or on the total quantity of service
output expressed in terms of designated numerical
units in the form of quotas or the requirement of an
economic needs test; 


Note: This subparagraph does not cover measures of a 
Party which limit inputs for the supply of
services. 


(d) limitations on the total number of natural persons
that may be employed in a particular service sector
or that a service supplier may employ and who are
necessary for, and directly related to, the supply of
a specific service in the form of numerical quotas or
the requirement of an economic needs test; 



(e) measures which restrict or require specific types of
legal entity or joint venture through which a service
supplier may supply a service; and 



(f) limitations on the participation of foreign capital
in terms of maximum percentage limit on foreign
shareholding or the total value of individual or
aggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="14334">1. Unless otherwise specified in its List of Reservations
referred to in Article 57, each Party shall accord to services
and service suppliers of the other Party, in respect of all
measures affecting the supply of services, treatment no less
favourable than that it accords to its own like services and 
service suppliers. 


Note: This Article shall not be so construed as to require a
Party to compensate for any inherent competitive
disadvantage which results from the foreign character of
the relevant services and service suppliers. 


2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 by
according to services and service suppliers of the other Party,
either formally identical treatment or formally different
treatment to that it accords to its own like services and 
service suppliers. 



3. Formally identical or formally different treatment shall
be considered to be less favourable if it modifies the 
conditions of competition in favour of services or service
suppliers of a Party compared to like services or service 
suppliers of the other Party. 



4. A Party may not invoke this Article in dispute settlement
procedures under Chapter 14 with respect to a measure of the
other Party that falls within the scope of an international
agreement between the Parties relating to the avoidance of
double taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="14335">1. Each Party shall ensure that all measures of general
application affecting trade in services are administered in a
reasonable, objective and impartial manner. 



2. Where authorisation is required by a Party for the supply
of a service, the competent authorities of that Party shall,
within a reasonable period of time after the submission of an
application is considered complete under that Party’s laws and
regulations, inform the applicant of the decision concerning
the application. At the request of the applicant, the
competent authorities of that Party shall provide, without
undue delay, information concerning the status of the
application. 



3. Each Party shall provide for adequate procedures to
verify the competence of professionals of the other Party. 



4. 	(a) Each Party shall apply licensing and qualification 
requirements and procedures and technical standards
in a manner which: 



(i) is based on objective and transparent criteria,
such as competence and the ability to supply the
service; 



(ii) is not more burdensome than necessary to ensure
the quality of the service; and 

(iii) in the case of licensing procedures and of
verification procedures related to technical
standards and to qualification requirements, is
not in itself a restriction on the supply of the
service. 


(b) In determining whether a Party is in conformity with
the obligation under subparagraph (a), account shall
be taken of international standards of relevant 
international organisations applied by that Party. 


Note: “Relevant international organisations” refers
to international bodies whose membership is
open to the relevant bodies of both Parties. 



5. Paragraphs 1 to 4 are binding upon a Party only in
sectors in which it has undertaken specific commitments in its
Schedule under the GATS. 


Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, “sector” means 
one or more, or all, sub-sectors of the service
concerned, as specified in a Party’s Schedule under
the GATS. 


6. Each Party shall maintain or institute as soon as
practicable judicial, arbitral or administrative tribunals or
procedures which provide, at the request of an affected
service supplier of the other Party, for the prompt review of,
and where justified, appropriate remedies for, administrative
decisions affecting trade in services. Where such procedures
are not independent of the agency entrusted with the
administrative decision concerned, the Party shall ensure that
the procedures in fact provide for an objective and impartial
review. 



7. The Parties shall jointly review the results of the
negotiations provided for in paragraph 4 of Article VI of the
GATS with a view to incorporating into this Chapter, as
appropriate, any disciplines agreed in such negotiations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Recognition" article_identifier="14336">1. For the purposes of the fulfilment, in whole or in part,
of its relevant standards or criteria for the authorisation,
licensing or certification of service suppliers, each Party
shall give due consideration to any requests by the other
Party to recognise the education or experience obtained,
requirements met, or licences or certifications granted, in
that other Party. Such recognition may be based upon an
agreement or arrangement with that other Party, or be accorded
autonomously. 



2. Where a Party recognises, by an agreement or arrangement,
the education or experience obtained, requirements met, or
licences or certifications granted, in a non-Party, it shall
afford the other Party adequate opportunity to negotiate its
accession to such an agreement or arrangement, whether
existing or future, or to negotiate a comparable agreement or
arrangement with it. Where a Party accords recognition
autonomously, it shall afford adequate opportunity for the
other Party to demonstrate that the education or experience
obtained, requirements met, or licences or certifications
granted, in the other Party should also be recognised. 



3. A Party shall not accord recognition in a manner which
would constitute a means of discrimination between countries 
in the application of its standards or criteria for the
authorisation, licensing or certification of service suppliers,
or a disguised restriction on trade in services.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="14337">1. This Article shall apply to measures affecting natural
persons who are service suppliers of a Party, and natural
persons of a Party who are employed by a service supplier of a
Party, in respect of the supply of a service. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting natural
persons seeking access to the employment market of a Party,
nor shall it apply to measures regarding nationality or
citizenship, residence or employment on a permanent basis. 



3. Specific commitments of a Party applying to measures
affecting the movement of natural persons of the other Party
supplying services are contained in Annex VIII. Natural
persons covered by Annex VIII shall be allowed to supply the
service in accordance with the terms of this Chapter. 



4. For the purposes of this Chapter, paragraph 3 of Article
62 shall apply, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="14338">1. A Party shall ensure that any monopoly supplier of a
service in its Area does not, in the supply of the monopoly
service in the relevant market, act in a manner inconsistent
with that Party’s obligations under Articles 45 to 47. 



2. Where a Party’s monopoly supplier competes, either
directly or through an affiliated company, in the supply of a
service outside the scope of its monopoly rights, that Party
shall ensure that such a supplier does not abuse its monopoly
position to act in its Area in a manner inconsistent with that
Party’s obligations under Articles 46 and 47. 



3. This Article shall also apply to cases of exclusive
service suppliers, where a Party, formally or in effect: 



(a) 	authorises or establishes a small number of service 
suppliers; and 



(b) substantially prevents competition among those
suppliers in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Business Practices" article_identifier="14339">1. The Parties recognise that certain business practices of
service suppliers, other than those falling under Article 51,
may restrain competition and thereby restrict trade in
services. 



2. Without prejudice to Chapter 10, a Party shall, at the
request of the other Party, enter into consultations with a
view to eliminating practices referred to in paragraph 1. The
Party addressed shall accord full and sympathetic
consideration to such a request and shall cooperate through
the supply of publicly available non-confidential information
of relevance to the matter in question. The Party addressed
shall also provide other information available to the
requesting Party, subject to its law and to the conclusion of
a satisfactory agreement concerning the safeguarding of its
confidentiality by the requesting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="14340">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article 54, a
Party shall not apply restrictions on international transfers
and payments for current transactions and capital transactions
relating to trade in services. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and
obligations of the Parties as members of the International
Monetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of the
International Monetary Fund, including the use of exchange
actions which are in conformity with the Articles of Agreement
of the International Monetary Fund, provided that a Party
shall not impose restrictions on any capital transactions
inconsistently with the obligations under this Chapter
regarding such transactions, except under Article 54, or at
the request of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="14341">1. The Parties endeavour to avoid the imposition of
restrictions to safeguard the balance of payments. 



2. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and external
financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party may adopt or
maintain restrictions on trade in services, including on
payments or transfers for transactions. 



3. The restrictions adopted or maintained by a Party
referred to in paragraph 2: 



(a) shall ensure that the other Party is treated as
favourably as any non-Party; 



(b) shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement
of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other Party; 



(d) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances described in paragraph 2; and 



(e) shall be temporary and be phased out progressively
as the situation specified in paragraph 2 improves. 


4. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a
Party may give priority to the supply of services which are
more essential to its economic programme. However, such
restrictions shall not be adopted or maintained for the
purposes of protecting a particular service sector. 



5. Any restrictions adopted or maintained by a Party under
paragraph 2, or any changes therein, shall be promptly
notified to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="14342">Subject to the requirement that such measures are not
applied in a manner which would constitute a means of arbitrary
or unjustifiable discrimination between countries where like
conditions prevail, or a disguised restriction on trade in
services, nothing in this Chapter shall be so construed as to
prevent the adoption or enforcement by either Party of
measures: 



(a) necessary to protect public morals or maintain
public order; 


Note: The public order exception may be invoked only 
where a genuine and sufficiently serious threat
is posed to one of the fundamental interests of
society. 


(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or
health; 



(c) necessary to secure compliance with laws or
regulations of the Party which are not inconsistent
with the provisions of this Chapter including those
relating to: 



(i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent
practices or to deal with the effects of a
default on services contracts; 



(ii) the protection of the privacy of individuals in
relation to the processing and dissemination of
personal data and the protection of
confidentiality of individual records and
accounts; and 

(iii) safety; 


(d) inconsistent with Article 47, provided that the
difference in treatment is aimed at ensuring the
equitable or effective imposition or collection of
direct taxes in respect of services or service
suppliers of the other Party; 

Note: Measures that are aimed at ensuring the 
equitable or effective imposition or collection
of direct taxes include measures taken by a
Party under its taxation system which: 



(i) apply to non-resident service suppliers in
recognition of the fact that the tax
obligation of non-residents is determined
with respect to taxable items sourced or
located in the Area of the Party; 



(ii) apply to non-residents in order to ensure
the imposition or collection of taxes in the
Area of the Party; 

(iii) apply to non-residents or residents in order
to prevent the avoidance or evasion of taxes, 
including compliance measures; 



(iv) apply to consumers of services supplied in
or from the Area of the other Party in order
to ensure the imposition or collection of
taxes on such consumers derived from sources 
in the Area of the Party; 



(v) distinguish service suppliers subject to tax
on worldwide taxable items from other 
service suppliers, in recognition of the
difference in the nature of the tax base 
between them; or 



(vi) determine, allocate or apportion income,
profit, gain, loss, deduction or credit of
resident persons or branches, or between
related persons or branches of the same
person, in order to safeguard the Party’s
tax base. 

Tax terms or concepts in this paragraph and
this Note are determined according to tax
definitions and concepts, or equivalent or
similar definitions and concepts, under the law
of the Party taking the measure. 


(e) inconsistent with Article 45, provided that the
difference in treatment is the result of an 
agreement on the avoidance of double taxation or
provisions on the avoidance of double taxation in
any other international agreement or arrangement by
which the Party is bound.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="14343">Nothing in this Chapter shall be so construed as: 



(a) to require either Party to furnish any information,
the disclosure of which it considers contrary to its
essential security interests; 



(b) to prevent either Party from taking any action which
it considers necessary for the protection of its
essential security interests: 



(i) relating to the supply of services as carried
out directly or indirectly for the purpose of
provisioning a military establishment; 



(ii) relating to fissionable and fusionable materials
or the materials from which they are derived; 

(iii) taken in time of war or other emergency in
international relations; or 


(c) to prevent either Party from taking any action in
pursuance of its obligations under the United
Nations Charter for the maintenance of international 
peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Lists Of Reservations" article_identifier="14344">1. The List of Reservations of the Parties referred to in 
Articles 45 to 47 shall be set out in Annex III. 



2. The List of Reservations of a Party set out in Annex III
provides for: 



(a) existing measures that the Party may maintain, renew
at any time or modify without reducing their level
of conformity with Articles 45 to 47; and 



(b) 	measures that the Party may adopt, maintain or
modify.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Modification Of Lists Of Reservations" article_identifier="14345">1. A Party shall notify to the other Party its intention to
modify its List of Reservations set out in Annex III. Upon
written request of the other Party within 30 days from the
receipt of the notification, the Parties shall hold
consultations on any necessary compensatory adjustment with
the aim to ensure that the general level of mutually
advantageous commitments under this Chapter is not reduced. If
the Parties fail to reach an agreement on compensation within
60 days after the receipt of the request for consultations,
the Party receiving the notification may refer the matter to
arbitration by an arbitral tribunal established following the
same procedures as provided for in paragraphs 3 to 7 of
Article 141. Such an arbitral tribunal shall present its
findings as to the ways to ensure that the general level of
mutually advantageous commitments under this Chapter is not
reduced. Article 143 shall apply to the proceedings of such an
arbitral tribunal mutatis mutandis. 



2. If no consultations are requested, or once the Party
which made the notification under paragraph 1 has made
compensatory adjustments as agreed upon by the Parties or in
conformity with the outcome of arbitration, the modification
shall be incorporated into Annex III in accordance with the
procedures set out in Article 152. 



3. If a compensatory adjustment has been made by a Party to
the benefit of the other Party as an "affected Member" in
accordance with Article XXI of the GATS with regard to the
same modification as intended for the List of Reservations of 
the former Party set out in Annex III, the Parties shall be
deemed to have reached an agreement on compensation referred
to in paragraph 1 with the same conclusion as agreed in the
said compensatory adjustment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Transparency" article_identifier="14346">1. Each Party shall publish promptly and, except in emergency
situations, at the latest by the time of their entry into
force, all relevant measures of general application which
pertain to or affect the operation of this Chapter.
International agreements pertaining to or affecting trade in
services to which a Party is a signatory shall also be
published. 



2. Where publication as referred to in paragraph 1 is not
practicable, such information shall be made otherwise publicly
available.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Review" article_identifier="14347">1. With the objective of further liberalising trade in
services between them, the Parties shall review at least every
two years, or more frequently if so agreed, their Lists of
Reservations set out in Annex III. The first such review shall 
take place not later than two years after the entry into force 
of this Agreement. 



2. If, after the entry into force of this Agreement, a Party
further liberalises autonomously any of its services sectors,
sub-sectors or activities, it shall consider any requests by
the other Party for the incorporation into this Agreement of
such autonomous liberalisation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Annexes" article_identifier="14348">Annexes III, IV, V, VI and VII form an integral part of
this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="1728">
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Scope" article_identifier="14349">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting the
movement of natural persons of a Party who enter and stay
temporarily in the other Party. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting natural
persons of a Party seeking access to the employment market of
the other Party, nor shall it apply to measures regarding
nationality or citizenship, residence or employment on a
permanent basis. 



3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applying
measures to regulate the entry of natural persons of the other
Party into, or their temporary stay in, the former Party,
including measures necessary to protect the integrity of, and
to ensure the orderly movement of natural persons across, its
borders, provided that such measures are not applied in such a
manner as to nullify or impair the benefits accruing to the
other Party under the terms of the specific commitments set out
in Annex VIII. 

Note: The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural persons 
of a certain nationality and not for those of others
shall not be regarded as nullifying or impairing
benefits under the terms of the specific commitments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="General Principles" article_identifier="14350">1. This Chapter reflects the preferential trading
relationship between the Parties, the desire of the Parties to
facilitate the movement of natural persons on a mutually
beneficial basis and to establish transparent criteria and
procedures for the movement of natural persons, and the need to
ensure border security and to protect the domestic labour force
and permanent employment in either Party. 



2. Each Party shall apply its measures relating to the
provisions of this Chapter in accordance with paragraph 1, and,
in particular, shall apply such measures expeditiously so as to
avoid unduly impairing or delaying trade in goods or services
or conduct of investment activities under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14351">For the purposes of this Chapter, “natural person of a
Party” means a natural person who, under the legislation of
the Party, is: 



(a) in respect of Japan, a national of Japan; or 



(b) in respect of Switzerland, 



(i) a national of Switzerland; or 



(ii) a permanent resident who is a service supplier
in the Area of Switzerland.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Grant Of Entry And Temporary Stay" article_identifier="14352">1. Each Party shall grant entry and temporary stay to natural
persons of the other Party in accordance with this Chapter and
relevant laws and regulations of the former Party, and subject
to the terms of the specific commitments set out in Annex VIII. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that fees charged by its competent
authorities for processing application for entry and temporary
stay of natural persons of the other Party for business
purposes are charged having regard to the administrative costs
involved.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Provision Of Information" article_identifier="14353">1. Each Party shall make publicly available information with
respect to natural persons covered by its specific commitments
set out in Annex VIII, including information necessary for an
effective application for the grant of entry into, and
temporary stay and work in, that Party. Such information shall
be kept updated. 



2. The information referred to in paragraph 1 shall include a
description of, in particular: 

(a) in respect of Japan: 


with respect to all the statuses of residence that
are relevant to the grant of entry into, and
temporary stay and work in, Japan for natural persons
of Switzerland covered in Japan’s specific
commitments in Annex VIII: 



(i) visas and certificates of eligibility; 



(ii) requirements and procedures for application for,
and issuance of, visas and certificates of
eligibility, including information on
documentation required, conditions to be met and
method of application; and 

(iii) requirements and procedures for application for,
and grant of, renewal of period of temporary
stay; or 


(b) in respect of Switzerland: 


with respect to the grant of entry into, and
temporary stay and work in, Switzerland for natural
persons of Japan covered in Switzerland’s specific
commitments in Annex VIII: 



(i) all categories of visas and work permits; 



(ii) requirements and procedures for application for,
and issuance of, visas and work permits,
including information on documentation required,
conditions to be met and method of application;
and 

(iii) requirements and procedures for application for,
and grant of, renewal of temporary stay and work
permits. 



3. Each Party shall provide the other Party with details of
relevant publications or websites where information referred to
in paragraph 2 is made available. 



4. If the implementation of paragraph 1 proves to be
impracticable for a Party, that Party shall provide the
information referred to in paragraph 2, as well as any
subsequent change therein, directly to the other Party. In
addition, that Party shall indicate the contact details of its
authority where persons of the other Party may obtain the
information referred to in paragraph 2. 



5. Each Party shall, to the extent possible, upon request by
the other Party, make available to the other Party statistical
data regarding the grant of entry into and temporary stay in
the former Party for natural persons of the other Party under
this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Expeditious Application Procedures" article_identifier="14354">1. The competent authorities of each Party shall process
without delay applications for the grant of entry and
temporary stay or, where applicable, work permits or
certificates of eligibility submitted for natural persons of
the other Party, including applications for renewal thereof. 



2. If the competent authorities of a Party require
additional information from the applicant in order to process
the application, they shall endeavour to notify the applicant
without undue delay. 



3. Upon request by the applicant, the competent authorities
of a Party shall endeavour to provide, without undue delay,
information concerning the status of the application. 



4. After a decision has been taken, the competent
authorities of a Party shall endeavour to notify without undue
delay the applicant for entry and temporary stay or, where
applicable, work permit or certificate of eligibility, of the
outcome of the application. The notification shall include the
period of stay and any other conditions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Measures Pursuant To Immigration Laws And Regulations" article_identifier="14355">Except for this Chapter and Chapters 1, 14 and 16, nothing
in this Agreement shall impose any obligation on either Party
regarding measures pursuant to immigration laws and
regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="14356">For the purposes of this Chapter, Articles 55 and 56
shall apply mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Electronic Commerce" chapter_identifier="1729">
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Scope" article_identifier="14357">This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Party affecting
electronic commerce, including for goods and services, in the
context of their bilateral trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="14358">1. The Parties recognise the economic growth and opportunity
provided by the increasing use of electronic commerce in trade
in goods and services, among others, in particular for
businesses and consumers, the importance of avoiding barriers
to its use and development and the need to create an
environment of trust and confidence in its use. 



2. The Parties recognise the principle of technological
neutrality in the sense that any provisions related to trade in
services do not distinguish between the different technological
means through which a service may be supplied. 



3. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter and
Chapter 2, 6, 9 or 11, the Chapter other than this Chapter
shall prevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 



4. This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) government procurement; 



(b) subsidies as defined in the Agreement on Subsidies
and Countervailing Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO
Agreement; and 



(c) taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14359">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) “digital products” means such products as computer
programmes, texts, plans, designs, video, images and
sound recordings or any combinations thereof, that
are digitally encoded and transmitted electronically; 


Note 1: For the purposes of this Chapter, digital 
products do not include those that are fixed
on a carrier medium. Digital products that
are fixed on carrier medium shall be subject
to Chapter 2. 


Note 2: For the purposes of this Chapter, digital 
products are those produced for commercial
sale or distribution. 



(b) “electronic certificate” means an electromagnetic
record prepared for certifying that matters used to
confirm that the user has performed the electronic
signature are pertaining to such user; 



(c) “electronic signature” means a measure taken with
respect to information that can be recorded in an
electromagnetic record and which fulfils both of the
following requirements: 



(i) that the measure indicates that such information 
has been approved by a person who has taken such
measure; and 



(ii) that the measure confirms that such information 
has not been altered; 


(d) “parties to an electronic transaction” means at least
one party in each of the Parties, all of them
involved in an electronic transaction or an 
electronic communication that has significant
relevance to that transaction; 



(e) 	“trade administration documents” means forms that a 
Party issues or controls that must be completed: 



(i) by or for an importer or exporter in connection
with the importation or exportation of products;
or 



(ii) by a service supplier in connection with trade in
services; and 

Note: For the purposes of this Chapter, “trade in 
services” shall have the same meaning as “trade
in services” defined in subparagraph (t) of
Article 44. 


(f) “transmitted electronically” means transferred by any
electromagnetic means.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Non-Discriminatory Treatment Of Digital Products" article_identifier="14360">1. Unless otherwise specified in its List of Reservations
referred to in Articles 57 and 90, which shall apply mutatis 
mutandis, each Party shall: 



(a) not adopt measures that accord less favourable
treatment to digital products of the other Party
than it accords to its own like digital products.
When a Party identifies a measure of such nature
that has been adopted before the entry into force of
this Agreement and is maintained by the other Party,
that other Party shall endeavour to eliminate it;
and 



(b) not adopt or maintain measures that accord less
favourable treatment to digital products of the
other Party than it accords to like digital products
of a non-Party. 


2. In implementing its obligations under paragraph 1, each
Party shall, in good faith, determine whether a digital 
product is a digital product of a Party, of the other Party or
of a non-Party. Such determination shall be made in a
transparent, objective, reasonable and fair manner. 



3. Each Party shall, upon request by the other Party,
explain how it determines the origin of a digital product in
implementing its obligations under paragraph 1. 



4. The Parties shall cooperate in international
organisations and fora to foster the development of criteria
determining the origin of a digital product, with a view to
considering the incorporation of such criteria into this
Agreement. 



5. The Parties shall review this Article five years after
the date of entry into force of this Agreement, unless they
agree otherwise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Non-Discriminatory Treatment Of Services" article_identifier="14361">Each Party shall ensure that its measures governing
electronic commerce do not discriminate the supply of services
transmitted electronically against the supply of like services
by other means.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Market Access" article_identifier="14362">Unless otherwise specified in its List of Reservations
referred to in Articles 57 and 90, which shall apply mutatis 
mutandis, each Party shall not adopt or maintain measures that
unduly prohibit or restrict electronic commerce.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Customs Duties" article_identifier="14363">1. Recognising the importance of maintaining the current
practice of not imposing customs duties on electronic
transmissions, the Parties shall cooperate to make this
practice binding within the framework of the World Trade
Organization, with a view to considering its incorporation into
this Agreement. 



2. In the context of paragraph 1, the Parties confirm their
current practice of not imposing customs duties on electronic
transmissions under paragraph 46 of the Hong Kong Ministerial
Declaration of December 2005.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="14364">Each Party shall endeavour to ensure that all its measures
affecting electronic commerce are administered in a transparent,
objective, reasonable and impartial manner, and are not more
burdensome than necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Electronic Signatures And Certification Services" article_identifier="14365">1. Neither Party shall adopt or maintain legislation for
electronic signatures that would: 



(a) prohibit parties to an electronic transaction from
mutually determining the appropriate electronic
signature methods for that transaction or electronic
communication that has significant relevance to that
transaction; 



(b) prevent parties to an electronic transaction from
having the opportunity to prove in court that their
electronic transaction or electronic communication 
that has significant relevance to that transaction
complies with any legal requirements with respect to
electronic signatures; or 



(c) prevent parties to an electronic transaction from
choosing the court or tribunal to which they bring
any dispute concerning the transaction. 

2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, each Party may require that,
for a particular category of electronic transactions or
electronic communications that have significant relevance to
those transactions, the electronic signatures meet certain
performance standards or are based on a specific electronic
certificate issued by a supplier of certification services
accredited or recognised in accordance with the Party’s laws
and regulations, provided that the requirement: 



(a) serves a legitimate policy objective; and 



(b) is substantially related to achieving that objective. 


3. This Article shall not apply to any transactions or
communications that have significant relevance to those
transactions, if those transactions are not permitted to be
made electronically under each Party’s laws and regulations. 



4. Each Party shall, in accordance with its legislation on
electronic signatures and certification services, endeavour to
facilitate the procedure of accreditation or recognition of
suppliers of certification services, which have already
obtained accreditation or recognition under the legislation of
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Paperless Trade Administration" article_identifier="14366">1. Each Party shall endeavour to make all trade
administration documents available to the public in an
electronic form. 



2. Each Party shall endeavour to accept trade administration
documents submitted electronically as the legal equivalent of
the paper versions of such documents. 



3. The Parties shall cooperate bilaterally and in
international fora to enhance the acceptance of electronic
versions of trade administration documents.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Protection Of Online Consumers" article_identifier="14367">1. The Parties recognise the importance of adopting and
maintaining transparent and effective consumer protection
measures for electronic commerce as well as measures conducive 
to the development of consumer confidence. 



2. The Parties recognise the importance of cooperation
between their respective competent authorities in charge of
consumer protection on activities related to electronic
commerce in the context of their bilateral trade in order to 
enhance consumer protection. 



3. The Parties recognise the importance of: 



(a) adopting or maintaining measures, in accordance with
their respective laws and regulations, to protect
the personal data of electronic commerce users; and 



(b) taking international standards and criteria into
account in developing such measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Private Sector Participation" article_identifier="14368">1. Each Party shall endeavour to ensure that regulatory
frameworks governing electronic commerce support industry-led
development of electronic commerce with a view to promoting
bilateral trade between the Parties. 



2. Each Party shall encourage the private sector to adopt
self-regulation, including through codes of conduct,
guidelines and enforcement mechanisms, with a view to
supporting electronic commerce.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="14369">1. The Parties shall cooperate to identify and overcome
obstacles encountered in particular by small and medium-sized
enterprises in using electronic commerce in the context of
their bilateral trade. 



2. The Parties shall endeavour to share information and 
experiences, including on related laws, regulations and best
practices in the field of electronic commerce in relation to,
inter alia: 



(a) data privacy; 



(b) fight against unsolicited commercial messages
transmitted through the Internet such as electronic
mails; 



(c) consumer confidence in electronic commerce; 



(d) cyber-security; 



(e) intellectual property; 



(f) electronic government; and 



(g) public morals, in particular ethics for young
generations. 


3. Each Party shall encourage, through existing means
available to it, the activities of non-profit organisations in
that Party aimed at promoting electronic commerce, including
the exchange of information and views. 



4. The Parties shall, where appropriate, cooperate in
relevant international organisations and fora to contribute to
the development of the international framework for electronic
commerce.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="14370">For the purposes of this Chapter, Articles 22, 55 and 56
shall apply mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="1730">
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="14371">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or maintained
by a Party relating to investors of the other Party and to
their investments in the Area of the former Party. 



2. It is understood that this Chapter shall also apply to
measures adopted or maintained by a Party relating to
investments made by investors of the other Party in the Area
of the former Party prior to the entry into force of this
Agreement. 



3. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter
and Chapter 6 with regard to measures by a Party affecting
trade in services, Chapter 6 shall prevail to the extent of
the inconsistency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Definitions" article_identifier="14372">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) “enterprise” means any entity duly constituted or
organised under applicable law, whether or not for
profit, and whether privately or governmentally
owned or controlled, including any corporation,
partnership, sole proprietorship, company, joint 
venture or other association; 



(b) “freely convertible currency” means any currency
which is widely traded in international foreign
exchange markets and widely used in international
transactions; 



(c) “investment” means any kind of asset, particularly: 



(i) an enterprise or a branch of an enterprise; 



(ii) shares, stocks or any other kind of equity
participation in an enterprise, including rights
derived therefrom; 

(iii) bonds, debentures, loans and other forms of
debt,including rights derived therefrom; 



(iv) claims to money and to any performance
associated with an enterprise and having an
economic value; 



(v) intangible assets such as intellectual property
rights and goodwill; 



(vi) rights conferred pursuant to law or contract
such as concessions, licences, authorisations
and permits, including those for cultivation,
exploration, extraction and exploitation of
natural resources; 

(vii) rights under contracts, including turnkey,
construction, management, production and
revenue-sharing contracts; and 


(viii) any other tangible and intangible, movable and
immovable property, and any related property
rights, such as mortgages, liens and pledges; 


A change in the form of the asset does not affect
its character as an investment; 



(d) “investment activities” means establishment,
acquisition, expansion, management, conduct,
operation, maintenance, use, enjoyment, liquidation,
sale or other disposition of investment; 



(e) 	“investment made” means an investment which an 
investor of a Party has established, acquired or 
expanded in the Area of the other Party; 



(f) “investment of an investor of a Party” means an
investment that is owned or controlled, either
directly or indirectly, by an investor of the Party; 



(g) “investor of a Party” means: 

(i) a natural person, who under the law of the
Party: 



(A) in respect of Japan, is a national of Japan;
or 



(B) in respect of Switzerland: 

(aa) is a national of Switzerland; or 


(bb) has the right of permanent residence; or 


(ii) an enterprise constituted or organised under the
applicable law of the Party and carrying out
substantial business activities in the Area of 
that Party, 


that is in the process of making an investment or
has made an investment in the Area of the other 
Party; and 


(h) “measure” means any measure by a Party, whether in
the form of a law, regulation, rule, procedure,
decision, administrative action or any other form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="General Treatment And Protection" article_identifier="14373">1. Each Party shall accord to investments of investors of
the other Party fair and equitable treatment and full
protection and security. Neither Party shall impair by
unreasonable or arbitrary measures the management, conduct,
operation, maintenance, use, enjoyment, liquidation, sale or
other disposition of such investments. 



2. Each Party shall observe any written obligation it may
have entered into with regard to a specific investment by an
investor of the other Party, which the investor could have
relied on at the time of establishment, acquisition or
expansion of such investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="14374">Each Party shall accord to investors of the other Party
and to their investments, in relation to their investment
activities, treatment no less favourable than that it accords,
in like situations, to its own investors and to their
investments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="14375">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other Party
and to their investments, in relation to their investment
activities, treatment no less favourable than that it accords,
in like situations, to investors of a non-Party and to their
investments. 



2. It is understood that the treatment referred to in 
paragraph 1 does not include treatment accorded to investors
of a non-Party and their investments by provisions concerning
the settlement of investment disputes between a Party and the
non-Party that are provided for in other international
agreements. 



3. If a Party accords more favourable treatment to investors
of a non-Party and their investments by concluding or amending
a free trade agreement, customs union or similar agreement
that provides for substantial liberalisation of investment, it
shall not be obliged to accord such treatment to investors of
the other Party and their investments. Any such treatment
accorded by a Party shall be notified to the other Party
without delay and the former Party shall endeavour to accord
to investors of the latter Party and their investments
treatment no less favourable than that accorded under the 
concluded or amended agreement. The former Party, upon request
by the latter Party, shall enter into negotiations with a view
to incorporating into this Agreement treatment no less
favourable than that accorded under such concluded or amended 
agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Transfers" article_identifier="14376">1. Each Party shall ensure that all transfers relating to
investments in its Area of an investor of the other Party may
be made freely into and out of its Area without delay. Such
transfers shall include, in particular, those of: 



(a) the initial capital and additional amounts to
maintain or increase the investments; 



(b) profits, interests, dividends, capital gains,
royalties, fees and other current incomes accruing
from the investments; 



(c) payments made under a contract, including a loan
agreement; 



(d) proceeds from the total or partial sale or
liquidation of the investments; 



(e) 	earnings and other remuneration of personnel engaged
from abroad in connection with the investments; 



(f) payments made 	in accordance with Articles 91 and 
92; and 



(g) payments arising out of the settlement of a dispute
under Article 94. 


2. Each Party shall further ensure that transfers referred
to in paragraph 1 may be made in a freely convertible currency. 
A transfer shall be able to be made at the market rate of 
exchange prevailing on the date of the transfer. 



3. It is understood that paragraphs 1 and 2 are without
prejudice to the equitable, non-discriminatory and good faith
application by a Party of its laws relating to: 



(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of the
rights of creditors; 



(b) the issuing, trading or dealing in securities; 



(c) criminal or penal offences and the recovery of
proceeds of crimes; 



(d) reports or record keeping of transfers of currency
or other monetary instruments; or 



(e) ensuring compliance with judgments or orders in
adjudicatory proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Reservations" article_identifier="14377">1. Articles 87, 88 and 96 shall not apply to: 



(a) any existing non-conforming measure by a Party as
set out in its List of Reservations in Section 1 of 
Appendix 1 or Section 1 of Appendix 2 to Annex IX,
that is maintained, continued, or renewed at any
time; 



(b) an amendment or modification to any non-conforming
measure covered by subparagraph (a) to the extent
that the amendment or modification does not decrease 
the conformity of the measure with Articles 87, 88
and 96; and 



(c) any measure adopted or maintained by a Party, in
accordance with its List of Reservations in Section 
2 of Appendix 1 or Section 2 of Appendix 2 to Annex
IX, 

to the extent that such measures are inconsistent with 
Articles 87, 88 and 96. 



2. In case of an amendment or modification to any existing
non-conforming measure as referred to in subparagraph 1(b) or
adoption of a measure as referred to in subparagraph 1(c), a
Party shall notify the other Party thereof, providing detailed
information, prior to the amendment, modification or adoption,
or in exceptional circumstances, as soon as possible
thereafter. 



3. Neither Party shall, under any measure adopted after the
date of entry into force of this Agreement and covered by its
List of Reservations set out in Annex IX, require an investor
of the other Party, by reason of its nationality, to sell or
otherwise dispose of an investment that exists at the time the
measure becomes effective. 



4. As part of the review provided for in Article 102, the
Parties undertake to review their Lists of Reservations set 
out in Annex IX with a view to reducing the scope of the
reservations therein or removing them. 



5. A Party may, at any time, either upon request of the
other Party or unilaterally, remove in whole or in part its
reservations set out in Annex IX by a written notification to
that other Party. 



6. Articles 87 and 88 shall not apply to any measure covered
by the exceptions to, or derogations from, obligations under
Articles 3 and 4 of the TRIPS Agreement, as specifically
provided in Articles 3 to 5 of the TRIPS Agreement. 



7. Articles 87, 88 and 96 shall not apply to any measure
that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to government
procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="14378">1. Neither Party shall expropriate or nationalise in its
Area investments of investors of the other Party or take any
measure tantamount to expropriation or nationalisation
(hereinafter referred to as “expropriation”) except: 



(a) for a purpose which is in the public interest; 



(b) in a non-discriminatory manner; 



(c) in accordance with due process of law; and 



(d) against prompt, adequate and effective compensation
pursuant to paragraphs 2 to 4. 


2. The amount of compensation shall be equivalent to the
fair market value of the expropriated investment at the time
when the expropriation was publicly announced or when it
occurred, whichever is the earlier. The fair market value
shall not reflect any change in market value occurring because
the expropriation had become publicly known earlier. 



3. The compensation shall be paid without delay and shall
include interest at a commercial rate established on a market 
basis, taking into account the length of time from the date of
expropriation to the date of payment. It shall be effectively
realisable, freely transferable and freely convertible at the
market exchange rate prevailing on the date of expropriation
into freely convertible currencies. 



4. Without prejudice to Article 94, the investor affected by
the expropriation shall have the right, under the law of the
Party making the expropriation, to prompt review, by a court
of justice, an administrative tribunal or another independent
authority of that Party, of his case and of the valuation of
his investment in accordance with the principles set out in
this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Treatment In Case Of Strife" article_identifier="14379">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other Party
that have suffered loss or damage relating to their
investments in its Area due to armed conflict, revolution,
insurrection, civil disturbance or any other similar event in
its Area, treatment, as regards restitution, indemnification,
compensation or any other settlement, that is no less
favourable than that it accords to investors of its own or of 
a non-Party. 



2. Any payments made as a means of settlement referred to in
paragraph 1 shall be effectively realisable, freely
transferable and freely convertible at the market exchange
rate into freely convertible currencies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="14380">If an investor of a Party receives payment, pursuant to
an insurance, guarantee or indemnity contract, from an insurer
constituted or organised under the law of that Party, the
other Party shall recognise the assignment of any right or
claim of the investor to the insurer, and the right of the
insurer to exercise such right or claim by virtue of
subrogation to the same extent as the predecessor in title.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Settlement Of Investment Disputes Between An Investor And A Party" article_identifier="14381">1. For the purposes of this Chapter, “investment dispute”
means a dispute between a Party and an investor of the other
Party that has incurred loss or damage by reason of, or
arising out of, an alleged breach by the former Party of any
obligation under this Chapter with respect to the investor or
its investment. This Article shall not apply to disputes
arising out of events which occurred prior to the entry into
force of this Agreement. 



2. Any investment dispute shall, as far as possible, be
settled amicably through consultations between the investor
and the disputing Party (hereinafter collectively referred to
in this Article as “the disputing parties”) at the request of
the investor. 



3. If the investment dispute cannot be settled through
consultations within six months from the date on which the 
disputing investor requested such consultations in writing,
the disputing investor may submit the investment dispute to
international conciliation or arbitration at the following
institutions or under the following rules: 



(a) 	the International Centre for Settlement of 
Investment Disputes (hereinafter referred to in this
Article as “ICSID”) established by the Convention on
the Settlement of Investment Disputes between States
and Nationals of other States done at Washington, on
18 March 1965; 



(b) the Additional Facility Rules of ICSID, provided
that either Party, but not both, is a party to the
ICSID Convention; or 



(c) 	an ad hoc arbitral tribunal which, unless otherwise
agreed upon by the disputing parties, shall be
established under the arbitration rules of the 
United Nations Commission on International Trade Law 
(UNCITRAL) adopted on 28 April 1976. 


4. Each Party hereby gives its consent to the submission of
an investment dispute by a disputing investor to international
conciliation or arbitration referred to in paragraph 3
regarding an investment made. 



5. Notwithstanding paragraph 4, no investment dispute may be
submitted to conciliation or arbitration under paragraph 3, if
more than five years have elapsed since the date on which the
disputing investor acquired or should have first acquired,
whichever is the earlier, knowledge of the incurred loss or
damage referred to in paragraph 1. 



6. A disputing investor may submit the investment dispute to
international conciliation or arbitration if: 



(a) the disputing investor has not initiated any
proceedings for the resolution of the investment
dispute before courts of justice or administrative
tribunals or agencies of the disputing Party; or 



(b) where the disputing investor has initiated any
proceedings for the resolution of the investment
dispute before courts of justice or administrative
tribunals or agencies of the disputing Party, the
disputing investor withdraws the investment dispute
from such proceedings. For the purpose of withdrawal,
a written waiver shall be included in the written 
request for conciliation or arbitration by which the
disputing investor waives any right to initiate or
continue before any courts of justice or
administrative tribunals or agencies under the law
of either Party, any proceeding with respect to any
alleged breach of this Chapter. 

It is understood that a disputing investor may initiate
or continue an action that seeks interim injunctive relief and
does not involve the payment of monetary damages before a
judicial or administrative tribunal of the disputing Party,
provided that the action is brought for the sole purpose of
preserving the disputing investor's rights and interests while
the conciliation or arbitration is pending. 



7. Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, the
arbitration shall be held in a country that is a party to the
Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement of Foreign
Arbitral Awards, done at New York on 10 June 1958. 



8. The arbitral tribunal shall decide the investment dispute
in accordance with this Chapter and applicable rules of
international law. Where the investment dispute includes a
claim based on paragraph 2 of Article 86, the arbitral
tribunal shall decide on that claim in accordance with this 
Chapter and the following: 



(a) the rules of law specified in the pertinent
investment contract, or other rules of law the 
disputing parties may agree upon; or 



(b) 	in the absence of rules of law referred to in 
subparagraph (a): 



(i) such rules of international law as may be
applicable; and 



(ii) the law of the respondent, including its rules
on the conflict of laws. 


9. The disputing Party shall notify the other Party in
writing of the investment dispute submitted to international
conciliation or arbitration no later than 30 days after the
date on which it was submitted, and provide that other Party
with copies of all pleadings filed in the arbitration. 



10. Upon written notice to the disputing parties, the Party
which is not the disputing Party may make submissions to the
arbitral tribunal on a question of interpretation of this
Chapter. 



11. The disputing Party may not assert as a defence its
immunity or the fact that the disputing investor has received
or will receive, by virtue of an insurance contract, guarantee
or indemnity, a compensation covering, in whole or in part,
the incurred loss or damage. 



12. Neither Party shall give diplomatic protection, or bring
an international claim, in respect of an investment dispute
submitted to international arbitration, unless the disputing
Party has failed to abide by and comply with the award
rendered. Diplomatic protection, for the purposes of this
paragraph, shall not include informal diplomatic exchanges for
the sole purpose of facilitating a settlement of the
investment dispute. 



13. The decision of arbitration shall be final and binding
upon the disputing parties and shall be executed without delay
in accordance with the law of the disputing Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="14382">1. In respect of the making of investments, Articles XIV and
XIVbis of the GATS, which are hereby incorporated into and
made part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis, shall apply. 



2. Paragraph 1 of Article XIVbis of the GATS shall also 
apply, mutatis mutandis, to investments made. 



3. This Article shall not apply to paragraph 1 of Article 86, 
and Articles 91 and 92. 



4. In exceptional circumstances, where a Party takes a
measure pursuant to paragraphs 1 and 2, that Party shall,
prior to the entry into force of the measure or as soon as
possible thereafter, notify the other Party of the following: 



(a) the sector and sub-sector or activity affected by
the measure; 



(b) the obligation or provisions of this Agreement
affected by the measure; 



(c) the legal basis of the measure; 



(d) a succinct description of the measure; and 



(e) the purpose of the measure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Prohibition Of Performance Requirements" article_identifier="14383">For the purposes of this Chapter, the Annex to the
Agreement on Trade-Related Investment Measures in Annex 1A to
the WTO Agreement is hereby incorporated into and made part of
this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="14384">1. The Parties endeavour to avoid the imposition of
restrictions to safeguard the balance of payments. 



2. A Party may adopt or maintain restrictive measures with
regard to cross-border capital transactions as well as payment
and transfers relating to investment: 



(a) in the event of serious balance-of-payments and
external financial difficulties or threat thereof; 
or 



(b) in exceptional cases where movements of capital
cause or threaten to cause serious difficulties for 
macroeconomic management, in particular monetary and
exchange rate policies. 


3. Restrictive measures adopted or maintained by a Party
under paragraph 2: 



(a) shall ensure that investors of the other Party are
treated as favourably as those of any non-Party; 



(b) shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement
of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances set out in paragraph 2; 



(d) shall be temporary and eliminated as soon as
conditions permit; 



(e) shall be promptly notified to the other Party; and 



(f) shall avoid unnecessary damages to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other Party. 


4. Nothing in this Article shall be so construed as to alter
the rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party as a
party to the Articles of Agreement of the International
Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Prudential Measures" article_identifier="14385">Article VI of Annex VI shall apply to this Chapter,


mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Special Formalities" article_identifier="14386">Nothing in Article 87 shall be so construed as to prevent
a Party from adopting or maintaining a measure that prescribes
special formalities in connection with the establishment of an
investment by investors of the other Party, such as compliance
with requirements on registration on residency, provided that
such formalities do not materially impair the protection
afforded by the former Party to investors of the latter Party
and investment of the investors pursuant to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Taxation Measures" article_identifier="14387">1. The following provisions shall apply to taxation measures
of each Party: 



(a) Articles 87 and 88; and 



(b) Article 91, to the extent that such taxation measures
constitute expropriation as provided for in paragraph
1 of that Article. 


2. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a), subparagraphs (d)
and (e) of Article XIV of the GATS are hereby incorporated
into and made part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 



3. A Party may not invoke Article 87 with respect to a
measure of the other Party that falls within the scope of an
international agreement between the Parties relating to the
avoidance of double taxation. 



4. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a), Article 94 shall
not apply in respect of taxation measures. 



5. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(b), Article 94 shall
apply in respect of taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Health, Safety And Environmental Measures" article_identifier="14388">The Parties recognise that it is inappropriate to
encourage investment activities by relaxing domestic health,
safety or environmental measures or lowering labour standards.
To this effect, each Party should not waive or otherwise
derogate from such measures and standards as an encouragement
for establishment, acquisition or expansion of investments in
its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Review" article_identifier="14389">1. With a view to further progressive liberalisation of
investments, the Parties shall review the legal framework, the
investment climate and the flow of investment between their 
Areas consistent with their commitments under other 
international agreements on investment not later than three
years after the date of entry into force of this Agreement and
in regular intervals thereafter. 



2. The review of the legal framework referred to in
paragraph 1 shall include the review of measures adopted or
maintained by a Party pursuant to subparagraph 1(c) of Article

90.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="1731">
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Measures Against Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="14390">1. Recognising that anticompetitive activities may nullify
or impair the benefits of liberalisation of trade and
investment and impede the efficient functioning of its market,
each Party shall take measures which it considers appropriate
against anticompetitive activities, in accordance with its
laws and regulations. 



2. Any such measures shall be taken in conformity with the
principles of transparency, non-discrimination and procedural
fairness. 



3. For the purposes of this Chapter, “anticompetitive
activity” means any conduct or transaction that may be subject
to penalties, sanctions or other relief under the competition
laws and regulations of either Party. In particular, it
includes: 



(a) private monopolisation, unreasonable restraint of
trade and unfair trade practices under the
competition laws and regulations of Japan; and 



(b) unlawful agreements between enterprises and unlawful
practices of enterprises having a dominant position
under the competition laws and regulations of
Switzerland.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Cooperation On Addressing Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="14391">1. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, cooperate on addressing anticompetitive
activities, subject to their respective available resources,
with the aim of contributing to the effective enforcement of
the competition laws and regulations of each Party through the
development of a cooperative relationship between the
competition authorities of the Parties, thus avoiding or 
lessening the possibility of conflicts between the Parties in
all matters pertaining to the application of the competition
laws and regulations of each Party. 



2. The details and procedures of cooperation under this
Article shall be specified in Chapter 3 of the Implementing
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Consultations" article_identifier="14392">After all applicable procedures under Article 104 have
been undergone, a Party which considers that there remain
adverse trade effects caused by an anticompetitive activity
may request the other Party to enter into consultations in the
Joint Committee with a view to eliminating such adverse trade
effects. The consultations in the Joint Committee shall: 



(a) not examine the appropriateness of the enforcement
of the competition laws and regulations by the
competition authority of either Party; and 



(b) not infringe upon the independence of the
competition authority of either Party in exercising
its authority.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Non-Application Of Paragraph 1 Of Article 5 And Chapter 14" article_identifier="14393">1. Paragraph 1 of Article 5 and Chapter 14 shall not apply
to this Chapter. 



2. Chapter 3 of the Implementing Agreement provides for the
details and procedures for the exchange of information,
including confidential information, under this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="1732">
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="14394">1. The Parties shall grant and ensure adequate, effective
and non-discriminatory protection of intellectual property,
promote efficiency and transparency in the administration of
their respective intellectual property protection systems and
provide for measures for adequate and effective enforcement of
intellectual property rights against infringement,
counterfeiting and piracy, in accordance with the provisions
of this Chapter and the international agreements to which both
Parties are parties. 



2. "Intellectual property" referred to in this Chapter means
all categories of intellectual property: 



(a) that are subject of Articles 114 to 121; and/or 



(b) that are covered by the TRIPS Agreement and/or the
relevant international agreements referred to in the
TRIPS Agreement. 


3. The Parties reaffirm their commitment to comply with the
obligations set out in the international agreements relating
to intellectual property to which both Parties are parties at
the date of entry into force of this Agreement and any
amendment thereto which becomes effective for both Parties,
including the following: 



(a) the TRIPS Agreement; 



(b) 	the Paris Convention for the Protection of 
Industrial Property done at Paris on 20 March 1883,
as revised at Brussels on 14 December 1900, at
Washington on 2 June 1911, at The Hague on 6
November 1925, at London on 2 June 1934, at Lisbon
on 31 October 1958, and at Stockholm on 14 July 1967
and as amended on 28 September 1979 (hereinafter
referred to as “the Paris Convention”); 



(c) the Patent Cooperation Treaty done at Washington on
19 June 1970, amended on 28 September 1979, modified
on 3 February 1984, and on 3 October 2001; 



(d) the Strasbourg Agreement Concerning the
International Patent Classification done at 


Strasbourg on 24 March 1971, as amended on 28
September 1979; 


(e) the Budapest Treaty on the International Recognition
of the Deposit of Microorganisms for the Purposes of
Patent Procedure done at Budapest on 28 April 1977,
and amended on 26 September 1980; 



(f) 	the 1991 Act of the International Convention for the 
Protection of New Varieties of Plants of 2 December 
1961 as revised at Geneva on 10 November 1972, on 23
October 1978, and on 19 March 1991 (hereinafter
referred to as “the 1991 UPOV Convention”); 



(g) the Protocol Relating to the Madrid Agreement
Concerning the International Registration of Marks
adopted at Madrid on 27 June 1989 and amended on 3
October 2006; 



(h) the Trademark Law Treaty adopted at Geneva on 27
October 1994; 



(i) the Nice Agreement Concerning the International
Classification of Goods and Services for the 
Purposes of the Registration of Marks done at Nice
on 15 June 1957, as revised at Stockholm on 14 July
1967, and at Geneva on 13 May 1977, and amended on
28 September 1979; 



(j) the Madrid Agreement for the Repression of False or
Deceptive Indications of Source on Goods done at
Madrid on 14 April 1891; 



(k) the Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary
and Artistic Works done at Berne on 9 September 1886, 
completed at Paris on 4 May 1896, revised at Berlin
on 13 November 1908, completed at Berne on 20 March
1914, revised at Rome on 2 June 1928, at Brussels on
26 June 1948, at Stockholm on 14 July 1967 and at
Paris on 24 July 1971 and amended on 28 September
1979 (hereinafter referred to as “the Berne
Convention”); 



(l) 	the International Convention for the Protection of 
Performers, Producers of Phonograms and Broadcasting
Organisations done at Rome on 26 October 1961
(hereinafter referred to as “the Rome Convention”); 



(m) 	the Convention for the Protection of Producers of 
Phonograms Against Unauthorized Duplication of Their
Phonograms done at Geneva on 29 October 1971; 



(n) WIPO Copyright Treaty adopted in Geneva on 20
December 1996; and 



(o) WIPO Performances and Phonograms Treaty adopted in
Geneva on 20 December 1996 (hereinafter referred to
as “the WPPT”). 

4. In common recognition of the importance of the following
multilateral agreements for international efforts to protect
intellectual property, each Party seeks to ratify or accede to
the following multilateral agreements to which it is not yet a
party: 



(a) the Patent Law Treaty adopted at Geneva on 1 June
2000; 



(b) the Singapore Treaty on the Law of Trademarks
adopted in Singapore on 27 March 2006; and 



(c) the Geneva Act of the Hague Agreement Concerning the
International Registration of Industrial Designs
adopted by the Diplomatic Conference on 2 July 1999.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="14395">1. Each Party shall accord to nationals of the other Party
treatment no less favourable than the treatment it accords to 
its own nationals with regard to the protection of 
intellectual property in accordance with Articles 3 and 5 of
the TRIPS Agreement. 



2. For the purposes of this Article and Article 109,
“nationals” shall have the same meaning as in the TRIPS
Agreement, and "protection" shall include matters affecting
the availability, acquisition, scope, maintenance, and
enforcement of intellectual property rights as well as those
matters affecting the use of intellectual property rights
specifically addressed in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Most-Favoured-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="14396">1. Each Party shall accord to nationals of the other Party
treatment no less favourable than the treatment it accords to 
the nationals of a non-Party with regard to the protection of
intellectual property in accordance with Articles 4 and 5 of
the TRIPS Agreement. 



2. Paragraph 1 shall not be so construed as to oblige either
Party to accord to the nationals of the other Party any
treatment accorded to the nationals of a non-Party by virtue
of any agreement on the avoidance of double taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Enhancement Of Efficiency Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="14397">For the purposes of providing efficient administration of
intellectual property protection system, each Party shall take
appropriate measures to enhance the efficiency of its 
administrative procedures concerning intellectual property.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Acquisition Of Intellectual Property Rights" article_identifier="14398">1. Where the acquisition of an intellectual property right 
is subject to the right being granted or registered, each
Party shall ensure that, irrespective of whether an
application for the granting or registration of an
intellectual property right is filed as a national or as an
international application under the applicable international
agreements, the procedures for granting or registration of the 
right, subject to compliance with the substantive conditions
for acquisition of the right, are conducive to the granting or 
registration within a reasonable period of time so as to avoid
unwarranted curtailment of the period of protection. 



2. Each Party shall make its practice regarding the
examination of the indications of designated products and
services under the classes applied in trademark applications
as transparent as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Transparency" article_identifier="14399">For the purposes of further promoting transparency in the
administration of its intellectual property protection system,
each Party shall take appropriate measures available to the
extent possible under its laws and regulations to: 


(a) publish information on: 



(i) applications for and grant of patents; 



(ii) registrations of utility models and industrial
designs; 

(iii) registrations of trademarks and applications
therefor; 



(iv) registrations of layout-designs of integrated
circuits; and 



(v) registrations of new varieties of plants and
applications therefor, 

and make available to the public information
contained in the dossiers thereof; 



(b) make available to the public information on
applications for the suspension by the competent
authorities of the release of products infringing
intellectual property rights as a border measure;
and 



(c) make available to the public information on its
efforts to ensure effective enforcement of 
intellectual property rights and other information
with regard to its intellectual property protection
system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="14400">The Parties shall take necessary measures to enhance 
public awareness of protection of intellectual property
including educational and dissemination projects on the use of
intellectual property as well as on the enforcement of
intellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Copyrights And Related Rights" article_identifier="14401">1. Without prejudice to the obligations set out in the
international agreements to which both Parties are parties,
each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations,
grant and ensure adequate and effective protection to the
authors of works and to performers, producers of phonograms
and broadcasting organisations for their works, performances,
phonograms and broadcasts, respectively. 



2. In addition to the protection provided for in paragraph 1,
each Party shall grant and ensure protection as provided for
in Articles 5 and 6 of the WPPT to performers for their visual
performances. 



3. Each Party shall ensure that a broadcasting organisation
in the Party has at least the exclusive right of authorising
the following acts: the fixation, the reproduction of
fixations, and the making available to the public of its
broadcasts by wire or wireless means in such a way that
members of the public may access them from a place and at a
time individually chosen by them. 



4. Each Party may, in its national legislation, provide for
the same kinds of limitations or exceptions as in Article 16
of the WPPT with regard to the protection of performers for
their visual performances and to the protection of
broadcasting organisations, to the extent that such
limitations and exceptions are compatible with the Rome
Convention. 



5. Each Party shall ensure that the author has the right,
independently of the author’s economic rights, and even after
the transfer of the said rights, to claim authorship of the
work and to object to any distortion, mutilation or other
modification of, or other derogatory action in relation to,
the said work, which would be prejudicial to his or her honour
or reputation. 



6. The rights granted to the author in accordance with
paragraph 5 shall, after his or her death, be maintained at
least until the expiry of the economic rights, and shall be
exercisable by the persons or institutions authorised by the
legislation of the Party in which protection is claimed. 



7. The rights granted under paragraphs 5 and 6 shall be
granted, mutatis mutandis, to performers as regards their live
aural or visual performances, or performances fixed in
phonograms or audiovisual fixations. 



8. Each Party shall ensure that the general term of
protection granted for works is the life of the author and at
least 50 years after his or her death. 



9. Each Party shall ensure that the term of protection for
related rights, as well as for copyrights whose term of
protection is calculated on a basis other than the life of a
natural person, is no less than 50 years: 



(a) after the authorised publication, or, failing such
authorised publication within 50 years after the
making of the work, no less than 50 years after the
making, for works; 



(b) after the authorised publication, or, failing such
publication within 50 years after the fixation of
the phonogram, no less than 50 years after the
fixation, for phonograms; 



(c) after the performance, for performances; or 



(d) after the broadcast, for broadcasts. 


10. For certain categories of works, each Party shall provide
that the term of protection is the life of the author and no
less than 70 years after his or her death, or no less than 70
years after the authorised publication, or, failing such
authorised publication within 70 years after the making of the
work, no less than 70 years after the making. 



11. A Party may be exempted from its obligations under this
Article where the exemptions as provided for in Articles 7 and
7bis of the Berne Convention may apply. 



12. Each Party shall ensure non-discriminatory treatment for
owners of copyright in the other Party with regard to the
enjoyment and the exercise of copyrights, regardless of
whether such copyrights are registered under the applicable
laws and regulations of the former Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="14402">1. Any sign, or any combination of signs, capable of
distinguishing the products or services of one undertaking
from those of other undertakings, shall be capable of
constituting a trademark. Such signs, in particular words
including personal names, letters, numerals, figurative
elements, three-dimensional shapes and combinations of colours
as well as any combination of such signs, shall be eligible
for registration as trademarks. Where signs are not inherently
capable of distinguishing the relevant products or services,
each Party may make eligibility for registration depend on
distinctiveness acquired through use. Each Party may require,
as a condition of registration, that signs be visually
perceptible. 



2. Each Party shall protect well-known marks in accordance
with Article 6bis of the Paris Convention and paragraphs 2 and
3 of Article 16 of the TRIPS Agreement. 



3. The Parties reaffirm the importance of the Joint
Recommendation Concerning Provisions on the Protection of
Well-Known Marks adopted by the Assembly of the Paris Union
for the Protection of Industrial Property and the General
Assembly of the World Intellectual Property Organization
(hereinafter referred to as “the WIPO”) in 1999 in furtherance
of protection of well-known marks and the Joint Recommendation
Concerning Provisions on the Protection of Marks, and Other
Industrial Property Rights in Signs, on the Internet adopted
by the Assembly of the Paris Union for the Protection of
Industrial Property and the General Assembly of the WIPO in
2001 in furtherance of protection of signs on the Internet. 



4. Each Party shall ensure that the owner of a registered
trademark has the exclusive right to prevent all third parties
not having the owner’s consent from using in the course of
trade identical or similar signs for products or services
which are identical or similar to those in respect of which
the trademark is registered, where such use would result in a
likelihood of confusion. For the purposes of this paragraph,
“using” such sign includes, at least, importing and exporting
products or packages of products to which the sign is affixed. 



5. Paragraph 4 shall also apply if only small quantities of
products are imported or exported, as long as the import or
export constitutes an infringement of the right conferred by a
registered trademark under the laws and regulations of a Party.
In case of the use of an identical sign for identical products
or services, a likelihood of confusion shall be presumed. The
rights described in paragraph 4 shall not prejudice any
existing prior rights, nor shall they affect the possibility
of the Parties making rights available on the basis of use.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="14403">1. Each Party shall ensure that adequate and effective
protection is provided to industrial designs, including to
designs of a part of an article. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that the owner of a protected
industrial design has the right to prevent third parties not
having the owner’s consent from making, selling, importing or
exporting articles bearing or embodying a design which is a
copy, or substantially a copy, of the protected design when
such acts are undertaken for commercial purposes. 



3. Paragraph 2 shall also apply if only small quantities of
products are imported or exported, as long as the import or
export constitutes an infringement of the right conferred by
the protected industrial design under the laws and regulations
of a Party. 



4. Each Party shall ensure that the term of protection
available is no less than 20 years.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Patents" article_identifier="14404">1. Subject to paragraphs 2 and 3, patents shall be available
for any inventions, whether products or processes, in all
fields of technology, including in the field of biotechnology,
provided that they are new, involve an inventive step and are
capable of industrial application. Subject to paragraph 3,
patents shall be available and patent rights enjoyable without
discrimination as to the place of invention, the field of
technology and whether products are imported or locally
produced. 



2. Each Party may exclude from patentability inventions, the
prevention of the commercial exploitation of which within the
Party is necessary to protect ordre public or morality,
including to protect human, animal or plant life or health or
to avoid serious prejudice to the environment, provided that
such exclusion is not made merely because the exploitation is
prohibited by its law. 



3. Each Party may also exclude from patentability: 



(a) diagnostic, therapeutic and surgical methods for the
treatment of humans or animals, with the exception
of products consisting of a substance or a
composition for use in any such method; and 



(b) plant and animal varieties other than microorganisms, and essentially biological processes for
the production of plants or animals other than non-
biological and microbiological processes. 


4. Each Party shall ensure that a patent confers on its
owner exclusive rights: 



(a) where the subject matter of a patent is a product,
to prevent third parties not having the owner’s
consent from making, using, offering for sale,
selling, importing for these purposes or exporting
that product; and 



(b) where the subject matter of a patent is a process,
to prevent third parties not having the owner’s
consent from using the process, and from using,
offering for sale, selling, importing for these
purposes or exporting at least the product obtained
directly by that process. 


5. With respect to the patent which is granted for an
invention related to pharmaceuticals or plant protection
products, each Party shall, subject to the terms and
conditions of its applicable laws and regulations, provide for
a compensatory term of protection for any period during which
the patented invention cannot be worked due to marketing
approval process. 



6. For the purposes of paragraph 5: 



(a) “compensatory term of protection” means, for Japan,
an extension of a term of patent protection and, for
Switzerland, a term specified in a supplementary
protection certificate; 



(b) “marketing approval” means approval or any other
disposition by the competent authorities that is
intended to ensure the safety and, where applicable,
efficacy of the pharmaceuticals or plant protection
products as provided for in the relevant laws and
regulations of each Party; and 



(c) the length of the compensatory term of protection
shall be: 



(i) for Japan, equal to the length of extension
which the patentee requests, provided that the
compensatory term of protection shall not exceed
either the length of time during which the
patented invention cannot be worked due to
marketing approval processes, or a maximum term
as provided for in the laws and regulations of
Japan. As of the date of entry into force of
this Agreement, such maximum term is stipulated
as being five years by the relevant law of
Japan; and 



(ii) for Switzerland, equal to the period which
elapsed between the filing date of the patent
application and the date of the marketing
approval of the product, reduced by a period of
five years. The maximum compensatory term shall
be at least five years.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="New Varieties Of Plants" article_identifier="14405">Each Party shall provide the same level of protection for
new varieties of all plant genera and species as provided
under the 1991 UPOV Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Geographical Indications And Related Indications" article_identifier="14406">1. Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective protection
of geographical indications and related indications in
accordance with this Article. 



2. For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) “geographical indications” means indications which
identify a product as originating in a Party, or a
region or locality in that Party, where a given
quality, reputation or other characteristic of the
product is essentially attributable to its
geographical origin; and 



(b) “related indications” means: 



(i) indications in the designation or presentation
of a service that contain or consist of the name 
of a geographical place of a Party (hereinafter
referred to in this Article as “indications of 
services”); and 



(ii) the country name of a Party, the name of a
canton of Switzerland, armorial bearings, flags
and other State or regional emblems. 


3. 	(a) In respect of geographical indications, each Party 
shall provide the legal means for interested parties
to prevent: 


(i) the use of any 	elements in the designation or
presentation of a product that indicate or
suggest that the product in question originates
in a geographical place other than the true
place of origin in a manner which misleads the
public as to the geographical origin of the
product; 



(ii) any use which constitutes an act of unfair
competition within the meaning of Article 10bis 
of the Paris Convention; and 

(iii) any use of a geographical indication identifying
wines for wines or identifying spirits for
spirits not originating in the place indicated
by the geographical indication in question. 


Note: Nothing in this Article shall be so 
construed as to derogate from any
obligation of a Party under subparagraph
(iii). The Parties may, with respect to
subparagraph (iii), provide for
enforcement by administrative action
instead of judicial procedures. 



(b) Each Party shall provide the legal means for
interested parties to prevent the use of any
indications of services in a manner, as prescribed
in applicable laws and regulations of the Party,
that misleads the public. 



(c) Each Party shall provide the legal means for
interested parties to prevent the use of the country
name of either Party or the name of a canton of
Switzerland for a product or service in a manner, as
prescribed in applicable laws and regulations of the
Party, that misleads the public. 



(d) Each Party shall provide the legal means for
interested parties to prevent the use of the
geographical indication, the indications of services,
the country name of either Party, or the name of a
canton of Switzerland, even where the true origin of
the products is indicated, or where they are used in
translation or accompanied by terms such as “kind”,
“type”, “style”, “way”, “imitation”, “method” or
other analogous expressions, if such use falls under
subparagraphs (a) to (c). This subparagraph shall
also apply to cases where a graphical symbol
referring to a geographical place of a Party is used
on a product or service in a manner, as prescribed
in applicable laws and regulations of the Party,
that misleads the public. 



(e) (i) Each Party shall ensure that the registration of 
a trademark which contains or consists of a 
geographical indication, with respect to
products not originating in the territory
indicated, is refused or invalidated ex officio 
if the legislation of the Party so permits or at
the request of an interested party, if the use
of the indication in the trademark of such 
products in the Party corresponds to a situation
referred to in subparagraph (a)(i), (a)(iii), or


(d) insofar as subparagraph (a)(i) or (a)(iii)
is applicable. 


(ii) Each Party shall ensure that the registration of
a trademark which contains or consists of an 
indication of service, the country name of
either Party, or the name of a canton of
Switzerland, the use of which corresponds to a
situation referred to in subparagraph (b), (c),
or (d) insofar as subparagraph (b) or (c) is
applicable, is refused or invalidated ex officio 
if the legislation of the Party so permits or at
the request of an interested party, where the
trademark misleads the public in a manner as
prescribed in the applicable laws and
regulations of the Party. 


(f) The protection afforded by this Article shall also
apply in cases where products originating in a Party
are destined for exportation. 



(g) (i) Each Party shall, in accordance with its 
obligations under Article 6ter of the Paris 
Convention, ensure that armorial bearings, flags
and other State emblems of the other Party are
not used or registered as trademarks or as
elements of trademarks. 

(ii) Each Party reaffirms its obligations under
paragraph 2 of Article 53 of the Geneva
Convention for the Amelioration of the Condition 
of the Wounded and Sick in Armed Forces in the 
Field of August 12, 1949 which provides that the
use by private individuals, societies or firms,
of the arms of Switzerland, or of marks
constituting an imitation thereof, whether as
trademarks or commercial marks, or as parts of
such marks, or for a purpose contrary to
commercial honesty, or in circumstances capable
of wounding Swiss national sentiment, shall be
prohibited at all times. 


(iii) Each Party shall ensure that armorial bearings,
flags and other State or regional emblems of the
other Party shall not be used in a manner, as
prescribed in applicable laws and regulations of
the Party, that misleads the public. 



4. In proceedings by the relevant authorities of each Party,
whether administrative or judicial, regarding the protection
provided for in this Article, designations listed by a Party
in Annex X shall serve, without prejudice to action or
procedures by the relevant authorities of the other Party, as
a source of information that these designations are protected
by the former Party as geographical indications as provided
for in this Article. 



5. 	(a) The Parties shall, upon request of either Party, 
review in the Joint Committee Annex X with a view to 
updating the list by including in Annex X
geographical indications which received protection
by either Party at its national level. 


(b) Modifications proposed pursuant to subparagraph (a)
shall be incorporated into this Agreement in
accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 152. 


6. Without prejudice to the rights and obligations set out
in the international agreements to which both Parties are
parties, paragraphs 3 to 9 of Article 24 of the TRIPS
Agreement apply to the provisions of this Article in relation
to geographical indications and, mutatis mutandis, to related
indications.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="14407">1. Each Party shall provide for effective protection against
acts of unfair competition. 



2. Any act of competition contrary to honest practices in
industrial or commercial matters constitutes an act of unfair 
competition. The following acts of unfair competition, in
particular, shall be prohibited: 



(a) all acts of such a nature as to create confusion by
any means whatever with the establishment, the
products, the services, or the industrial or
commercial activities, of a competitor; 



(b) false allegations in the course of trade of such a
nature as to discredit the establishment, the
products, the services, or the industrial or
commercial activities, of a competitor; 



(c) indications or allegations, the use of which in the
course of trade is liable to mislead the public as
to the nature, the characteristics, the suitability
for their purpose, or the quantity, of the products
or the services, or the manufacturing process of the
products; 



(d) acts of creating confusion with another person's
products or business by: 



(i) using an indication of products or business
which is identical or similar to that other 
person's indication of products or business
which is well-known among consumers or other
purchasers; or 



(ii) assigning, delivering, displaying for the
purpose of assignment or delivery, exporting,
importing or providing through an electric
telecommunication line, products using such
indication; 


(e) acts of using as one’s own an indication of products
or business which is identical or similar to another 
person's famous indication of products or business,
or acts of assigning, delivering, displaying for the
purpose of assignment or delivery, exporting,
importing, or providing through an electric
telecommunication line, products using such
indication; 



(f) acts of assigning, leasing, displaying for the
purpose of assignment or lease, exporting or
importing products which imitate the configuration,
excluding configuration which is indispensable for
ensuring the function of the products, of another
person's products; 



(g) acts of acquiring or holding a right to use domain
names identical or similar to a specific indication
of products or services of another person, or acts
of using the domain name, with intention to gain
unfair profit or intention of causing damage to
another person; and 



(h) acts by an agent or representative of an owner of a
right relating to a trademark, without a legitimate
reason and the consent of the right-owner, of using
a trademark identical or similar to the trademark 
for products or services identical or similar to
those relating to such right; of using such 
trademark in assigning, delivering, displaying for 
the purpose of assignment or delivery, exporting, 
importing, or providing through an electric
telecommunication line products which are identical
or similar to the products relating to such right;
or of using such trademark in providing services
which are identical or similar to the services 
relating to such right. 


3. For the purposes of this Article, "indication of products
or business" means a name, trade name, trademark, mark, or
container or package of products, used in relation to a
person's business, or any other indication of a person's
products or business. 



4. Each Party shall ensure in its laws and regulations
adequate and effective protection of undisclosed information
in accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 39 of the TRIPS
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Treatment Of Test Data In Marketing Approval Procedure" article_identifier="14408">1. Each Party shall prevent applicants for marketing
approval for pharmaceutical products which utilise new
chemical entities from relying on or from referring to test or
other data submitted to its competent authority by the first
applicant for a certain period of time counted from the date
of approval of that application. As of the date of entry into
force of this Agreement, such period of time is stipulated as
being no less than six years by the relevant laws of each
Party. 



2. Each Party, when requiring, as a condition for approving
the marketing of agricultural chemical products which utilise
new chemical entities, the submission of undisclosed test or
other data, the origination of which involves a considerable
effort, shall ensure that, in accordance with its relevant
laws and regulations, applicants for marketing approval are
either: 



(a) prevented from relying on or from referring to such
data submitted to its competent authority by the
first applicant for a period of at least ten years
counted from the date of approval of that
application; or 



(b) required generally to submit a full set of test
data, even in cases where there was a prior
application for the same product, for a period,
counted from the date of approval of a prior
application, of at least ten years.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Enforcement – General" article_identifier="14409">Each Party shall endeavour to: 



(a) 	encourage the establishment of public and/or private
advisory groups to address issues of counterfeiting
and piracy; and 



(b) 	enhance internal coordination among, and facilitate
joint actions by, its government agencies concerned
with enforcement of intellectual property rights, 
subject to its available resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Enforcement – Border Measures" article_identifier="14410">1. Each Party shall provide for procedures concerning the
suspension at the border by its customs authority, ex officio,
of the release of products infringing rights at least to
patents, utility models where provided for in its laws and
regulations, industrial designs or trademarks, or copyrights
or related rights which are destined for importation into,
exportation from or transit through, the customs territory of
the Party. 



2. For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) “exportation” includes re-exportation; and 



(b) “transit” means transhipment and customs transit, as
defined in the International Convention on the 
Simplification and Harmonization of Customs
Procedures. 


3. Each Party shall provide for procedures concerning the
suspension at the border by its customs authority, upon
request of a right holder, of the release of products
infringing rights at least as referred to in paragraph 1,
which are destined for importation into, exportation from and,
where provided for in its laws and regulations, transit
through, the customs territory of the Party. 



4. In the case of the suspension pursuant to paragraphs 1
and 3 with respect to importation into, exportation from and,
where provided for in the laws and regulations of a Party,
transit through, the customs territory of the Party, the
competent authorities of the Party suspending the release of
the products shall notify the right holder of the name and
addresses of the consignor or consignee, and the importer or
exporter, as applicable, of the products in question. Such
competent authorities shall notify the right holder of the
names and addresses of the producer of the products in
question, when they find that such information is indicated in
the course of customs clearance procedures. 



5. Each Party shall ensure that the products, the release of
which has been suspended pursuant to paragraphs 1 and 3 and
which have been found to be infringing products by the
competent authorities, will not be released into free
circulation without the consent of the right holder and will
be destroyed in accordance with its laws and regulations. 



6. Each Party shall ensure that right holders do not have to
bear an unreasonable burden because of the fees and the cost 
of storage and destruction of the products the release of
which has been suspended pursuant to paragraphs 1 and 3 and
which have been found to be infringing products. 



7. The competent authorities of each Party shall enable the
right holder to analyse samples of the products the release of
which has been suspended pursuant to paragraph 3, as
appropriate and to the extent permitted by the laws and
regulations of the Party, at the expense of the right holder. 



8. Each Party shall adopt simplified procedures, which are
to be used in the absence of objections and subject to the
terms and conditions provided for in its laws and regulations,
for the competent authorities to seize or destroy the products
the release of which has been suspended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Enforcement – Civil Remedies" article_identifier="14411">1. Each Party shall ensure that the right holder has the 
right to claim against the infringer damages adequate to
compensate for the injury the right holder has suffered
because of an infringement of his or her intellectual property
right by an infringer who knowingly, or with reasonable
grounds to know, engaged in the infringing activity. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, “right holder” shall
include holders of interests which are protected under the
laws and regulations of each Party preventing acts of unfair
competition. 



3. Where the right holder claims against the infringer
compensation for damages caused by an intentional or negligent
infringement of his or her intellectual property rights, an
amount calculated, taking into consideration such factors as
the following, may be, where applicable, presumed to be the
amount of such damages, whether or not actual damages can be
calculated: 



(a) the quantity of the products infringing the right
holder’s intellectual property rights and actually
transferred to third persons, and the amount of
profit per unit of products which would have been
sold by the right holder if there had not been the
act of infringement; 



(b) the profits earned by the infringer from the act of
infringement; or 



(c) the amount that the right holder would have been
entitled to receive for the exercise of his or her 
intellectual property rights. 


4. In cases where it is extremely difficult for the right
holder of intellectual property rights to prove the actual
economic harm due to the nature of facts concerned, each Party
shall ensure that, to the extent possible in accordance with
its laws and regulations, its judicial authorities have the
authority to determine the amount of damages based on the
totality of the evidence presented to them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Enforcement – Criminal Remedies" article_identifier="14412">1. Each Party shall provide for criminal procedures and
penalties to be applied at least in cases of the following
acts committed wilfully and on a commercial scale: 



(a) infringement of rights to patents, utility models
where provided for in its laws and regulations,
industrial designs or trademarks, copyrights or
related rights, or rights relating to new varieties
of plants; 



(b) infringement of rights to layout-design of
integrated circuits; 



(c) disclosure of undisclosed information provided for
in paragraph 4 of Article 120 to the extent provided
for in the laws and regulations of the Party; and 



(d) the acts of unfair competition provided for in
subparagraphs 2(c) to 2(f) of Article 120 and the
use of geographical indications and related
indications as prescribed in subparagraphs 3(a)(i),
3(a)(ii), 3(b), 3(c), 3(d) insofar as subparagraph
3(a)(iii) is not applicable, 3(g)(i) and 3(g)(iii)
of Article 119, to the extent provided for in the
laws and regulations of the Party. 


2. Importation, exportation or transit of products which
constitutes an act referred to in subparagraph 1(a) or 1(d)
shall be covered by the criminal procedures and penalties
referred to in paragraph 1. Paragraph 2 of Article 123 shall
apply to this paragraph. 



3. Each Party shall provide for, where permitted by its laws
and regulations, stricter or separate penalties to offences
listed in subparagraphs 1(a), 1(b) and 1(d) committed in
connection with corporate activities or on a commercial scale. 



4. Each Party shall ensure that, in cases of infringement
committed wilfully and on a commercial scale of rights to
patents, utility models where provided in its laws and
regulations, industrial designs, trademarks or new varieties
of plants, or the acts of unfair competition provided for in
subparagraphs 2(c) to 2(f) of Article 120 to the extent
provided for in its laws and regulations committed wilfully
and on a commercial scale, its competent authorities may
institute prosecution ex officio, without the need for a
formal complaint by the right holder whose right has been
infringed. 



5. Each Party shall ensure that, in cases where either (a)
infringement of rights to patents or trademarks, or copyrights
or related rights, or (b) offence of the customs laws in
connection with the infringement of intellectual property
rights, is committed by an organised criminal group, its
judicial authorities have the authority to confiscate crime
proceeds and properties derived from such crime proceeds in
accordance with its laws and regulations. 



6. Each Party shall provide for criminal penalties to be
applied in cases of wilful import conducted on a commercial
scale of labels on which a trademark has been applied that is
identical to a trademark registered in the Party in respect of
certain products, or that is similar to or cannot be
distinguished in its essential aspects from such trademark, if
such labels are intended to be used on the products for which
such trademark is registered or on similar products.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Internet Service Providers" article_identifier="14413">1. For the purposes of encouraging Internet service
providers to cooperate with right holders in protecting their
rights against materials infringing intellectual property
rights, each Party shall provide measures to prevent undue
liabilities of Internet service providers for the removal of
materials that they have put on their Internet websites under
contracts with information senders where a right holder
claims to the Internet service provider that such materials
infringe his or her intellectual property rights, provided
that the Internet service provider complies with the
procedures to be followed by the parties concerned. 



2. Each Party shall enable right holders, who have given
effective notification to an Internet service provider of
materials that they claim with valid reasons to be infringing 
their intellectual property rights, to expeditiously obtain
from that Internet service provider information on the
identity of the information sender.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="14414">1. The Parties, recognising the growing importance of
protection of intellectual property in further promoting trade 
and investment between them, in accordance with their 
respective laws and regulations and subject to their available 
resources, shall cooperate in the field of intellectual
property, including by exchanging information on relations of
the Parties with non-Parties on matters concerning
intellectual property. 



2. The Parties shall seek for cooperation on activities
relating to future international conventions on harmonisation,
administration and enforcement of intellectual property rights
and on activities in international organisations including the
World Trade Organization and the WIPO. 



3. Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Sub-Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="14415">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Intellectual
Property (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-
Committee) is hereby established. 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) discussing any issues related to intellectual
property with a view to enhancing protection of
intellectual property and enforcement of
intellectual property rights and to promoting
efficient and transparent administration of
intellectual property protection system; 



(c) reporting its findings and the outcome of its
discussions to the Joint Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other tasks as may be assigned by the
Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as 
may be agreed by the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) composed of representatives of the Governments of
the Parties, and may invite representatives of
relevant entities other than the Governments of the 
Parties, including those from private sectors, with
the necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be
discussed; and 



(b) co-chaired by officials of the Governments of the
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="14416">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article 73 of the TRIPS
Agreement is hereby incorporated into and made part of this
Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="1733">
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Existing Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="14417">1. The rights and obligations of the Parties in respect of
government procurement shall be governed by the Agreement on
Government Procurement in Annex 4 to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to as “the GPA”). 



2. If the GPA is amended or is superseded by another
agreement, “the GPA”, for the purposes of this Chapter, shall
refer to the GPA as amended or such other agreement, as of
the date on which such amendment or other agreement enters
into force for both Parties. 



3. 	Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="14418">Each Party hereby designates the following governmental
authority as its enquiry point to facilitate communication 
between the Parties on any matter regarding government
procurement: 



(a) 	for Japan, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs; and 



(b) 	for Switzerland, the State Secretariat for Economic
Affairs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="14419">1. The Parties will consult in the Joint Committee with a 
view to increasing mutual understanding of their respective
government procurement systems, effectively implementing them
and further enhancing and expanding access to the government
procurement market of each Party for the suppliers of the
other Party. 



2. In the event that, after the entry into force of this
Agreement, a Party accords to a non-Party additional advantages
of access to its government procurement market beyond those
accorded to the other Party under the GPA, the former Party
shall, upon request of the other Party, enter into negotiations
with a view to extending those advantages to the other Party on
a reciprocal basis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Promotion Of A Closer Economic Relationship" chapter_identifier="1734">
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="14420">1. The Parties, confirming their willingness to promote a
closer economic relationship, shall, whenever the need arises,
hold consultations in order to address issues concerning the
promotion of trade and investment activities of their business
sectors. 



2. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, cooperate and take appropriate measures
to promote a closer economic relationship between themselves
for the benefit of their business sectors.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Sub-Committee On Promotion Of A Closer Economic Relationship" article_identifier="14421">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish the
Sub-Committee on Promotion of a Closer Economic Relationship
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-
Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) discussing ways and means to promote a closer 
economic relationship between the Parties; 



(b) discussing possibilities to further remove obstacles 
to trade and investment between the Parties and to 
facilitate business activities in the Parties; 



(c) 	discussing possibilities to cooperate at government 
and business sector levels in the field of bilateral 
trade and investment promotion activities; 



(d) 	discussing other issues related to promotion of a 
closer economic relationship; 



(e) reporting its findings, and making, as needed, 
recommendations on appropriate measures to be taken
by the Parties, to the Joint Committee; 



(f) reviewing, where appropriate, the implementation of 
the recommendations referred to in subparagraph (e);
and 



(g) carrying out other tasks assigned by the Joint 
Committee. 


3. 	The Sub-Committee: 



(a) shall be composed of government officials of the
Parties; 



(b) 	shall take all its actions by agreement between the 
Parties; 



(c) may, upon agreement by the Parties, invite
representatives of business sectors and other
business-related organisations of the Parties with
the necessary expertise related to the issues to be
discussed; and 



(d) shall be co-chaired by government officials of the
Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as 
may be agreed by the Parties. 



5. The Sub-Committee shall cooperate with other relevant
Sub-Committees with a view to avoiding unnecessary overlap
with their work. The Joint Committee shall, if necessary, give
instructions to this end.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Contact Point" article_identifier="14422">The contact point designated pursuant to Article 149
shall, in regard to the implementation of this Chapter,
perform the functions as set forth in Chapter 4 of the
Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 14" article_identifier="14423">Chapter 14 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="1735">
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="14424">The Parties shall at all times endeavour to reach a 
mutually satisfactory resolution of any matter concerning the
interpretation and application of this Agreement through
cooperation, expert consultations or other means provided for
in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="14425">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, this
Chapter shall apply with respect to the settlement of disputes
between the Parties concerning the interpretation or
application of this Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights of the
Parties to have recourse to dispute settlement procedures
available under any other international agreement to which both
Parties are parties. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, once the complaining Party
has requested the establishment of an arbitral tribunal under
this Chapter or a panel under Article 6 of the Understanding on
Rules and Procedures Governing the Settlement of Disputes in
Annex 2 to the WTO Agreement with respect to a particular
dispute, the arbitral tribunal or panel selected shall be used
to the exclusion of the other procedure for that particular
dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Consultations" article_identifier="14426">1. A Party may request in writing consultations with the
other Party if it considers that a measure applied by that
other Party is inconsistent with this Agreement or that any
benefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under this
Agreement is impaired or nullified by such measure. The Party
requesting consultations shall set out the reasons for the
request, including identification of the measure at issue and
an indication of the legal basis for the complaint. 



2. When a Party requests consultations pursuant to paragraph
1, the other Party shall reply promptly and enter into
consultations in good faith within 30 days after the date of
receipt of the request, with a view to a prompt and
satisfactory resolution of the matter. In case of a matter
concerning perishable products, the other Party shall enter
into consultations within 15 days after the date of receipt of
the request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="14427">1. Good offices, conciliation or mediation may be requested
at any time by either Party. They may begin at any time if the
Parties agree and, at the request of either Party, be
terminated at any time. 



2. If the Parties agree, good offices, conciliation or
mediation may continue while procedures of the arbitral
tribunal provided for in this Chapter are in progress. 



3. Proceedings involving good offices, conciliation or
mediation and positions taken by the Parties during these
proceedings shall be confidential and without prejudice to the
rights of either Party in any further proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="14428">1. The complaining Party that requested consultations under
Article 139 may address a written request to the Party
complained against for the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal: 



(a) if the Party complained against does not enter into
such consultations within 30 days, or within 15 days
in case of a matter concerning perishable products,
after the date of receipt of the request for
consultations under that Article; or 



(b) if the Parties fail to resolve the matter through
such consultations under that Article within 60 days
after the date of receipt of the request for such
consultations. 

2. Any request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal
pursuant to this Article shall identify: 



(a) the specific measures at issue; and 



(b) 	the legal basis of the complaint including, if
applicable, the provisions of this Agreement alleged
to have been breached and any other relevant
provisions. 

The arbitral tribunal may also be requested to propose
implementation options, which will be attached to its award. 



3. The arbitral tribunal shall consist of three arbitrators 
with relevant technical or legal expertise. 



4. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date of receipt
of the request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,
appoint one arbitrator who may be its national and propose up
to three candidates to serve as the third arbitrator who shall 
be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. The third arbitrator 
shall not be a national of either Party, nor have his or her
usual place of residence in either Party, nor be employed by
either Party, nor have dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 



5. The Parties shall agree on and appoint the third
arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of the
request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal, taking
into account the candidates proposed pursuant to paragraph 4. 



6. If a Party has not appointed the one arbitrator pursuant
to paragraph 4, or if the Parties fail to agree on the third
arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 5, the necessary appointments
shall be made at the request of either Party by the Secretary-
General of the Permanent Court of Arbitration within a further 
30 days. 



7. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal 
shall be the date on which the chair of the arbitral tribunal 
is appointed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="14429">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article 141: 



(a) shall examine the matter referred to in the request
for the establishment of the arbitral tribunal 
pursuant to paragraph 2 of Article 141; 



(b) 	shall make its award in accordance with this 
Agreement and applicable rules of international law; 



(c) shall set out, in its award, its findings of law and
fact, together with the reasons therefor; 



(d) shall, if requested by the complaining Party pursuant
to paragraph 2 of Article 141, attach to its award
suggested implementation options for the Parties to
consider in conjunction with Article 145; and 



(e) should consult with the Parties, as appropriate, with
a view to providing adequate opportunities for the
development of a mutually satisfactory resolution. 

2. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and 
binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="14430">1. Unless the Parties have agreed otherwise, the arbitral
tribunal shall decide on whether its proceedings are to be
held in Japan or Switzerland, and the complaining Party shall
provide the secretariat services. The language of the
proceedings and the documents submitted to and produced by the
tribunal, including the award, shall be English. 



2. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 
Hearings shall be open to the public, unless either Party
objects. 



3. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal, the documents
submitted to it and the draft award referred to in paragraph 8
shall be kept confidential. 



4. Notwithstanding paragraph 3, either Party may make public
statements as to its views regarding the dispute, but shall
treat as confidential, information provided and written
submissions made by the other Party to the arbitral tribunal
which that other Party has designated as confidential. Where a
Party has provided information or made written submissions
designated to be confidential, that Party shall, upon request
of the other Party, provide a non-confidential summary of the
information or written submissions which may be disclosed
publicly. 



5. Each Party has the right to at least one hearing before
the arbitral tribunal as well as the opportunity to provide
initial and rebuttal written submissions. The arbitral tribunal 
may seek from the Parties such relevant information as it
considers necessary and appropriate. The Parties shall respond
promptly and fully to any request by an arbitral tribunal for
such information. 



6. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from any
relevant source and may consult experts to obtain their opinion
on certain aspects of the matter. 



7. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend any
of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the proceeding.
Any information provided or written submissions made by a Party
to the arbitral tribunal, including any comments on the
descriptive part of the draft award and responses to questions
put by the arbitral tribunal, shall be made available to the
other Party. 



8. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 90 days after the date
of its establishment, submit to the Parties its draft award,
including both the descriptive part and its findings and
conclusions, for the purpose of enabling the Parties to review
it. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit 
to the Parties its draft award within the afore-mentioned 90 
days period, it may extend that period with the consent of the
Parties. A Party may submit comments in writing to the arbitral
tribunal on the draft award within 15 days after the date of
submission of the draft award. 



9. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award within 30 days
after the date of submission of the draft award. 



10. The arbitral tribunal shall attempt to make its decisions,
including its award, by consensus but may also make such
decisions, including its award, by majority vote. 



11. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be made public.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Suspension Or Termination Of Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="14431">1. The Parties may agree to suspend the work of the arbitral
tribunal at any time before the issuance of the award for a
period not exceeding twelve months following the date of such
agreement. If the work of the tribunal has been suspended for
more than twelve months, the authority of the arbitral
tribunal to examine the dispute shall lapse, unless the
Parties agree otherwise. 



2. The Parties may agree to terminate the proceedings of the
arbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of the award
to the Parties by jointly so notifying the chair of the
arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="14432">1. The Party complained against shall promptly comply with
the award issued by the arbitral tribunal pursuant to Article


143. 



2. The Party complained against shall, within 20 days after
the date of issuance of the award, notify the complaining Party
of the means and the period of time for implementing the award,
taking into account, if applicable, the implementation options
attached to the award. If the complaining Party considers the
notified means or period of time to be unacceptable, it may
request the Party complained against to hold consultations with
a view to reaching a mutually satisfactory solution on the
matter. If no such solution has been agreed upon within 20 days
after the date of receipt of the request, the complaining Party
may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal, which then shall
determine a reasonable means or period of time for implementing
the award. The determination of the arbitral tribunal shall be 
presented within 15 days from the referral of the matter to the
arbitral tribunal. 



3. If the Party complained against considers it impracticable
to comply with the award, it shall notify the complaining Party
accordingly within 20 days after the issuance of the award and
enter into consultations, with a view to agreeing on mutually
satisfactory compensation. If no such compensation has been
agreed upon within 20 days after the date of the notification,
the complaining Party may notify the Party complained against
that it intends to suspend the application of concessions or
other obligations under this Agreement. 



4. If the Party complained against has failed to notify the
means and the period of time for implementing the award
pursuant to paragraph 2 or if the complaining Party considers
that the Party complained against has failed to comply with the
award within the implementation period as specified pursuant to
paragraph 2, the complaining Party may notify the Party
complained against that it intends to suspend the application
of concessions or other obligations under this Agreement. 



5. The notification pursuant to paragraph 3 or 4 shall
indicate when the suspension of the application of concessions
or other obligations under this Agreement shall commence and
the application of what concessions or other obligations under
this Agreement is to be suspended. Such suspension shall: 



(a) only be implemented at least 30 days after the date
of notification; 



(b) not be effected if, in respect of the dispute to
which the suspension relates, consultations or
proceedings before an arbitral tribunal are in
progress; 



(c) be restricted to benefits equivalent to the level of
failure to comply with the award; and 



(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to which 
the inconsistency with the provisions of, or the
nullification or impairment of a benefit under, this
Agreement relates, unless it is not practicable or
effective to suspend the application of concessions
or other obligations in such sector or sectors. 


6. If the Party complained against considers that the
requirements for the suspension of the application of
concessions or other obligations under this Agreement by the
complaining Party set out in paragraph 5 have not been met, it
may request consultations with the complaining Party within ten
days after the receipt of the notification in accordance with
paragraph 3 or 4. The complaining Party shall enter into
consultations within ten days after the date of receipt of the
request. If the Parties fail to resolve the matter within 30
days after the date of receipt of the request for consultations
pursuant to this paragraph, the Party complained against may
refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal. The ruling of the
arbitral tribunal shall be given within 15 days from that
referral. Application of concessions or other obligations under
this Agreement shall not be suspended until the arbitral
tribunal has issued its ruling. 



7. The suspension of the application of concessions or other
obligations under this Agreement following notification
pursuant to paragraph 3 or 4 shall be discontinued when the
Parties reach a mutually satisfactory resolution or where
compliance with the award is effected. 



8. A Party may request an arbitral tribunal to rule on the
conformity with the award of any implementing measures adopted
after the suspension of the application of concessions or other
obligations under this Agreement and, in light of such ruling,
whether the suspension should be terminated or modified. The
ruling of the arbitral tribunal shall be given within 15 days
from the date of such request. 



9. The arbitral tribunal under this Article shall, wherever
possible, be composed of the arbitrators of the original
arbitral tribunal. If any of the arbitrators is not available,
that arbitrator shall be replaced by an arbitrator appointed
pursuant to paragraphs 4 to 6 of Article 141.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Expenses" article_identifier="14433">Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the expenses of the
arbitral tribunal, including the remuneration of the
arbitrators, shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Other Provisions" article_identifier="14434">Any time period mentioned in this Chapter may be modified
by agreement between the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Administration Of The Agreement" chapter_identifier="1736">
      <article number="ARTICLE 148" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="14435">1. The Parties hereby establish the Joint Committee which
shall be co-chaired by senior officials of the Parties. 



2. 	The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Agreement; 



(b) considering and recommending to the Parties any
amendments to this Agreement; 



(c) supervising and coordinating the work of all Sub-
Committees and ad hoc working groups established
pursuant to this Agreement; 



(d) 	endeavouring to resolve disputes between the Parties
about any matter concerning the interpretation or
application of this Agreement; 



(e) adopting the Operational Procedures for Trade in
Goods and the Operational Procedures for Rules of
Origin, referred to in Article 24 and Article XXVIII
of Annex II, respectively; 



(f) 	reviewing and amending, as necessary, the Operational
Procedures referred to in subparagraph (e); 



(g) 	adopting any necessary decisions for the operation of
this Agreement; and 



(h) carrying out other functions as the Parties may agree
or as provided for in this Agreement. 


3. The Joint Committee may establish Sub-Committees or ad hoc 
working groups to assist it in carrying out its functions. The
mandate of the Sub-Committees or ad hoc working groups shall be
established by the Joint Committee except where specifically
provided for in this Agreement. 



4. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules of 
procedures. 



5. The Joint Committee shall meet, in principle, every two
years at such venue as may be agreed by the Parties. Each Party
may, in cases of urgency, request in writing to the other Party
that a special meeting of the Joint Committee be held. Upon
such request, the Parties shall make every effort to hold the
special meeting within 30 days. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, a
special meeting can be held at any appropriate level.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 149" name="Communications" article_identifier="14436">1. Each Party shall designate upon entry into force of this
Agreement a contact point to facilitate communications between
the Parties on any matter relating to this Agreement. 



2. Communications referred to in paragraph 1 shall be made in
English.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 16" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1737">
      <article number="ARTICLE 150" name="Tables Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="14437">The tables of contents and headings of the Chapters and
Articles of this Agreement are inserted for convenience of
reference only and shall not affect the interpretation of this
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 151" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="14438">The Annexes to this Agreement and Notes shall form an
integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 152" name="Amendment" article_identifier="14439">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between the
Parties. Such amendment shall be approved by the Parties in
accordance with their respective legal procedures and shall
enter into force on the date to be agreed on by the Parties. 



2. Without prejudice to the legal procedures of each Party
with respect to the conclusion and amendment of international
agreements, amendments in the following areas may be made by
the Governments of the Parties by means of exchange of
diplomatic notes: 



(a) Annex I, provided that the amendments are made in
accordance with the amendment of the Harmonized 
System, and include no change of the rates of customs
duty on imports applied to the originating products
of the other Party in accordance with Annex I; 



(b) List of Natural Cheeses in paragraph 1 of Attachment
1 to Appendix 1 to Annex I, provided that the
amendment is made as a result of the consultation in 
accordance with paragraph 3 thereof, or made in
accordance with paragraph 4 of Attachment 1 to
Appendix 1 to Annex I; 



(c) Appendices 1, 2 and 3 to Annex II; 



(d) Appendix 2 to Annex III; or 



(e) Annex X.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 153" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="14440">This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of
the second month following the month in which the Governments
of the Parties exchange diplomatic notes informing each other
that their respective legal procedures necessary for entry into
force of this Agreement have been completed. It shall remain in
force unless terminated as provided for in Article 154.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 154" name="Termination" article_identifier="14441">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving one
year’s advance notice in writing to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1738">
      <article article_identifier="14442">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorised
by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement. 


DONE at Tokyo on this nineteenth day of February in the
year 2009, in two originals in the English language. 


For Japan: For the Swiss Confederation: 


中曽根弘文 Doris Leuthard</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
