<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Arab Common Market</name>
    <type>Customs Union</type>
    <wto_rta_id>198</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>172</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1964-08-13</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1965-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1965-03-05</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>1998-12-31</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">EGY</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">IRQ</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">JOR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">LBY</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">MRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">SYR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">YEM</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Africa; Middle East</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=90780034&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="235">
      <article article_identifier="16347">AGREEMENT FOR ECONOMIC UNITY AMONG ARAB LEAGUE STATES 


The Governments of: 


The Hashemite Ringdom of Jordan 


The Tunisian Republic 


The Republic of Sudan 


The Iraqi Republic 


The Saudi Arabian Kingdom 


The Syrian Arab Republic 


The United Arab Republic 


The Lebanese Republic 


The United Libyan Kingdom 


The Yemenite Kingdom 


The Kingdom of Morocco 


The State of Kuwait 


Declare that it is their ardent desire to organize economic relations 
among the Arab League States, to strengthen these relations on such bases as 
shall suit the existing natural and historical ties among them to realize the 
best conditions for the development of their economies, to exploit their wealth, 
and to secure the welfare of their countries. 


They agree to establish a complete unity among themselves and to implement 
it gradually in the shortest possible time that will guarantee the transfer of 
their countries from present to future conditions. without harming fundamental 
interests, in accordance with the following provisions.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER ONE" name="Objectives And Means" chapter_identifier="236">
      <article number="ARTICLE ONE" article_identifier="16348">A complete economic unity shall be established among the Arab League States 
to guarantee, in particular, for these States and for their citizens on the basis 
of complete equality: 



(1) 	freedom of movement of men and capital, 



(2) 	freedom of exchange of national and foreign goods and products, 



(3) 	freedom of residence, work, employment and the practice of economic 
activities, 



(4) 	freedom of transport and transit and the use of means of transport, 
ports, and civil airports, 



(5) 	the rights of ownership, donation and inheritance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE TWO" article_identifier="16349">To achieve the realization of the unity specified in the previous article, 
the contracting parties agree: 



(1) 	to consider their countries a unified customs region subject to a 
unified administration; and to unify the applied customs tariffs, 
legislations, and regulations in eac!i of them, 



(2) 	to unify the policy and systems of import and export, 



(3) 	to unify the transport and transit policies, 



(4) 	to conclude commercial and payments agreements with other countries 
collectively, 



(5) 	to co-ordinate policy regarding agriculture, industry, and internal 
trade and to unify economic legislation in such a manner as shall 
guarantee equal opportunities for citizens of the contracting countries 
engaged in agriculture, industry, commerce, and the progessions, 



(6) 	to co-ordinate legislation concerning labour and social security, 



(7) 	(a) to co-ordinate legislation regarding taxes, government and municipal 
dues, -and all other kinds of taxations and duties on agriculture, 
industry, trade, immovable property, and capital investment in such 

a way as shall guarantee the principal of equal opportunities for 
all, 


(b) 	to prevent double taxation and duties on the citizens of the 
contracting states, 



(8) 	to co-ordinate financial and monetary policies and regulations in the 
countries of the contracting parties with a view to unifying currency 
in them all, 



(9) 	to unify methods of statistical tabulations and classifications, and, 



(10) 	to take any other necessary measures for -the implementation of the 
objectives specified in Articles I and II. 

It is possible to disregard the principle of unification in certain cases 
and countries provided the approval of the Council of Arab Economic Unity shall 
be secured. Article III of this Agreement stipulates the formation of this 
Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER TWO" name="Management" chapter_identifier="237">
      <article number="ARTICLE THREE" article_identifier="16350">A permanent body to be called "the Council of Arab Economic Unity" shall be 
established. Its duties and powers are determined in accordance with the 
stipulations of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE FOUR" article_identifier="16351">(1) 	The Council shall be formed of one or more full time representatives of 
each of the contracting parties. 



(2) 	Cairo shall be the permanent seat for the Council of the Arab Economic 
Unity. The Council has the right to convene at any other place it shall 
determine. 



(3) 	The duration of the chairmanship of the Council shall be for one year 
and in a rotating order among the contracting parties. 



(4) 	The Council shall pass its decisions by a two-thirds majority vote. 
Each contracting country has one single vote.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE FIVE" article_identifier="16352">(1) 	The Council shall be helped in its duties by economic and administrative 
committees which function permanently or temporarily under its supervision. The Council determines their duties. 



(2) 	The following permanent committees shall be preliminarily formed: 



(a) 	the Customs Committee, to consider the technical and administrative 
customs matters, 



(b) 	the Monetary and Financial Committee, to consider matters relating 
to currency, banking, taxation, rates and other financial questions, 
and, 



(c) 	the Economic Committee, to consider matters relating to agriculture, 
industry, trade, transport and communications, labour, and social 
security. 

The Council shall have the right to form other committees when necessary 
and in accordance with the requirements of the situation. 


(3) 	Eaoh of the contracting parties shall appoint its representatives on the 
above mentioned permanent committees. Each party shall have one single 
vote.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE SIX" article_identifier="16353">(1) 	A Permanent Technical Advisory Office shall be established for the 
Council of Arab Economic Unity. It shall be made of experts appointed 
by the Council and shall function under its supervision. 



(2) 	The Permanent Technical Office shall execute the study and research work 
in matters referred to it by the Council or any of its committees. The 
Office shall submit research work and recommendations that will guarantee 
harmony and co-ordination in matters within the jurisdiction of the 
Council. 



(3) 	The Council shall establish a central office for statistics. This office 
shall gather and analyze statistics and publish -them when necessary.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE SEVEN" article_identifier="16354">(1) 	The Council of Arab Economic Unity, together with its subsidiary organs, 
shall constitute one simple unit enjoying financial and administrative 
independence and having its own budget. 


(2). 	The Council shall draft its own regulations and those for its 
subsidiary organs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE EIGHT" article_identifier="16355">During a period not exceeding one month as of the date of the implementation 
of this Agreement, the governments of the contracting parties shall nominate their 
representatives on the Council and on the committees specified in paragraph (2) of 
Article V of this Agreement. The Council shall carry out its functions immediately 
on its formation. Also, the Council shall immediately form its subsidiary organs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE NINE" article_identifier="16356">The Council of Arab Economic Unity shall carry out, in general, all the duties 
and powers specified in this Agreement and its Appendices of which it shall deem 
necessary for its implementation. In particular, the Council shall: 


1. 	In administration 



(a) 	implement the stipulations of this Agreement and its Appendices and all 
the regulations and decisions issued. for the implementation of this 
Agreement and its Appendices, 



(b) 	supervise the working of the committees and the subsidiary organs,. and, 



(c) 	appoint the staff and experts for the Council and its subsidiary organs 
in accordance with the stipulations of this Agreement. 

2. 	In organization and legislation 



(a) 	draft tariffs, laws and regulations which aim: at the establishment of an 
Arab unified customs zone and introduce-the essential modifications to 
them when necessary, 



(b) 	co-ordinate foreign trade policies with a view to co-ordinate the 
economy of the region vis-à-vis world economy, and to attain the 
objectives of economic unity specified in this Agreement. The signing 
of trade and payments agreements with other countries shall. take place 
with the approval of the Council of Arab Economic Unity, 



(c) 	co-ordinate economic development activities and draft plans for the 
execution of the common Arab Development project, 



(d) 	co-ordinate policies regarding agriculture, industry and internal trade, 



(e) 	co-ordinate financial and monetary policies with a view to attain 
monetary unity, 


(f) 	draft unified transport regulations in the contracting countries well 
as transit regulations and co-ordinate policy concerning them, 



(g) 	draft unified labour and social security legislations and modifying them, 



(h) 	co-ordinate legislations for taxes and rates, 



(i) 	draft other legislations concerning matters specified in this Agreement 
and its Appendices which are essential to the implementation of the said 
Agreement and Appendices, 



(j) 	draft and approve the budget of the Council and its subsidiary organs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE TEN" article_identifier="16357">Expenditures of the Council and its subsidiary organs shall be covered by 


common revenues. During the period preceding the realization of such revenues, 


governments shall participate to these expenditures according to rates fixed by 


the Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE ELEVEN" article_identifier="16358">The common revenues of the Council shall be distributed among the governments 
of the contracting parties by agreement among them on the basis of the studies 
carried out by the Council of Economic Unity. These studies shall be made before 
the realization of the customs unity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE TWELVE" article_identifier="16359">The Council shall perform these and ether powers entrusted to it by this 
Agreement and its Appendices by decisions to be issued and implemented by the 
member States in accordance with their own prevailing constitutional principles.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE THIRTEEN" article_identifier="16360">The governments of the contracting parties undertake not to issue in their 
territories any laws, regulations or administrative decisions contradictory to 
this Agreement or its Appendices.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER THREE" name="Transitional Rules" chapter_identifier="1930">
      <article number="ARTICLE FOURTEEN" article_identifier="16361">(1) 	The implementation of this Agreement shall take place in successive 
stages and in the shortest possible time. 



(2) 	The Council of Arab Economic Unity shall, upon its formation, draft a 
practical plan indicating the stages of implementation and terming the 
legislative,-administrative, and technical measures necessary for each 
stage, taking into consideration the appendix concerning "... the 
necessary steps for the realization of Arab Economic Unity ..." attached 
to this Agreement and constituting an integral part of it. 



(3) 	On exercising its duties specified in this Agreemeat, the Council shall 
take into consideration certain specific circumstances existing in some 
of the contracting Countries. This shall not undermine the objectives 
of the Arab Economic Unity. 



(4) 	The Council, as well as the contracting parties, shall carry out the 
measures specified in paragraph (2) of this article according to the 
terms of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE FIFTEEN" article_identifier="16362">Any two or more of the contracting parties shall have the right to conclude 
economic agreements among themselves with the object of realizing a unity, wider 
in range, than that stipulated by this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER FOUR" name="Ratification Of, Membership In, And Withdrawal From The Agreement" chapter_identifier="1931">
      <article number="ARTICLE SIXTEEN" article_identifier="16363">This Agreement shall be ratified by the signatory States according to their 
constitutional systems in the shortest possible time. Documents of ratification 
shall be deposited with the Secretariat-Gonoral of the League of Arab States who 
shall prepare the necessary minutes regarding the ratification document of each 
State and who shall inform the other contracting States of it.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE SEVENTEEN" article_identifier="16364">States of the Arab League who are not party of this Agreement can join it by 
an application addressed to the Secretary-General of the League of Arab States who 
shall announce their membership to the other contracting States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE EIGHTEEN" article_identifier="16365">Arab countries which are not members in the League of Arab States can join 
this Agreement subject to the approval of the contracting States. Such countries 
shall apply for membership to the Secretary-General of the League of Arab States 
who shall inform the contracting States and request their approval.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE NINETEEN" article_identifier="16366">Any of the contracting parties can withdraw from this Agreement after the 
lapse of five years as from the end of the transitional period. The withdrawal 
shall be effective after the lapse of one year from the date of the application 
for withdrawal to the Secretariat-General of the League of Arab States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE TWENTY" article_identifier="16367">This Agreement shall enter into force three months as from the date of deposit 
of the ratification documents by three of the signatory States. Regarding other 
States, the Agreement shall enter into force after one month as from the date of 
deposit of their ratification documents or their application for membership. 


In confirmation of the aforementioned stipulations, the delegated members, 
whose names are specified hereinafter, have signed this Agreement on behalf and 
in -the name of their governments. 


This Agreement is written in Arabic on 5 June 1957. 


One original form to be kept with the Secretariat-General of the League of 
Arab States, copies of which shall be given to each of the contracting States to 
this Agreement or joining it.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1932">
      <article article_identifier="16368">On 6.June 1962, the delegates of the following States have signed this 
Agreement: 



1. The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan 



2. The Syrian Arab Republic 

23. The United Arab Republic



4. The Kingdom of Morocco 



5. The State of Kuwait</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
