<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Central European Free Trade Agreement (CEFTA) - Accession of Slovenia</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>218</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>192</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1995-11-25</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1996-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1998-01-08</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>2004-05-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">SVN</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://docsonline.wto.org/imrd/gen_redirectsearchdirect.asp?RN=0&amp;searchtype=browse&amp;query=@meta_Symbol"WT/REG11/4"&amp;language=1&amp;ct=DDFEnglish</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://docsonline.wto.org/imrd/gen_redirectsearchdirect.asp?RN=0&amp;searchtype=browse&amp;query=@meta_Symbol"WT/REG11/4"&amp;language=3&amp;ct=DDFSpanish</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://docsonline.wto.org/imrd/gen_redirectsearchdirect.asp?RN=0&amp;searchtype=browse&amp;query=@meta_Symbol"WT/REG11/4"&amp;language=2&amp;ct=DDFFrench</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="2038">
      <article article_identifier="17152">AGREEMENT ON ACCESSION OF THE REPUBLIC OF SLOVENIA TO THE 

CENTRAL EUROPEAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT 


The Czech Republic, the Republic of Hungary, the Republic of Poland and the Slovak Republic on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side (hereinafter called the Parties), 

Reaffirming their commitment to the principles of a market economy, which constitutes the basis for their relations, 

Considering the positive development of the mutual economic cooperation between the Parties to the Central European Free Trade Agreement and the Republic of Slovenia, 

Wishing to contribute to the process of integration in Europe through the extension of the Central European Free Trade Agreement, 

Having in mind the Declarations of Prime Ministers, done on 25 November 1994 in Poznán, on 11 September 1995 in Brno, 

Recalling the official request of the Republic of Slovenia on 17 July 1995 to accede to the Central European Free Trade Agreement, 

Taking into account the Agreement Amending the Central European Free Trade Agreement, signed in Brno on 11 September 1995, 

In accordance with the provisions of Article 39 a of the Central European Free Trade Agreement, 

Have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="2039">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="17153">The Republic of Slovenia shall accede to the Central European Free Trade Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="17154">The Republic of Slovenia shall accept the Central European Free Trade Agreement with all its amendments signed before the signature of this Agreement and shall apply it in accordance with the provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="17155">References in the Central European Free Trade Agreement to its Parties and where all states are explicitly mentioned shall be understood to include the Republic of Slovenia.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="17156">1. In order to implement the provisions of paragraph 2 of Article 3 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement Protocols 8, 9, and 10 to the Central European Free Trade Agreement are hereby established and attached to this Agreement. 


2. 	Provisions for the abolition of customs duties on imports between: 
-the Czech Republic and the Slovak Republic on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 8, 

-the Republic of Hungary on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 9, 

-	the Republic of Poland on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 10, 

3. 	The Protocol 9 mentioned in this Article shall be replaced by 1 July 1996 at the latest by new one which will be in accordance with the rules on liberalisation applied within the provisions of the Central European Free Trade Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="17157">1. In order to implement the provisions of paragraph 1 of Article 12 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement Protocols 11, 12, and 13 to the Central European Free Trade Agreement are hereby established and attached to this Agreement. 


2. 	Provisions for granting mutual agricultural concessions between: 
-the Czech Republic and the Slovak Republic on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 11, 

-	the Republic of Hungary on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 12, 

-the Republic of Poland on the one side and the Republic of Slovenia on the other side are laid down in Protocol 13. 

3. The Protocols 11 and 12 mentioned in this Article shall be replaced by 1 July 1996 at the latest by new ones which will be in accordance with the rules on liberalisation applied within the provisions of the Central European Free Trade Agreement. 

The Protocol 13 mentioned in this Article shall be replaced, if possible, by 1 July 1996 at the latest by new one which will be in accordance with the rules on liberalisation applied within the provisions of the Central European Free Trade Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="17158">Quantitative restrictions on imports or measures having equivalent effect referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 8 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement and specified in Annexes III/a, III/b and III/c of the Central European Free Trade Agreement shall also apply to imports of products originating in the Republic of Slovenia, subject to the provisions in Annex to Article 6 to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="17159">Quantitative restrictions on exports or measures having equivalent effect referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 9 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement and specified in Annexes IV/a, IV/b and IV/c of the Central European Free Trade Agreement shall also apply to exports of products originating in the Republic of Slovenia, subject to the provisions in Annex to Article 7 to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="17160">1. For the purposes of this Agreement it is understood that Protocol 7 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement concerning the definition of the concept of "originating products" and methods of administrative cooperation shall also apply to the products originating in the Republic of Slovenia, subject to the provisions in Annex to Article 8 to this Agreement. 


2. The Protocol 7 mentioned in this Article shall be replaced by 1 July 1996 at the latest by new one which will be in accordance with the rules agreed with the European Union.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="17161">1. References to government procurement in Article 24 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement shall be understood, in relations between the Czech Republic and the Republic of Slovenia, as for public procurement and the period mentioned in paragraph 2 of Article 24 shall end by 31 December 1998 at the latest. 


2. References to government procurement in Article 24 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement shall be understood, in relations between the Slovak Republic and the Republic of Slovenia, as for public procurement and the period mentioned in paragraph 2 of Article 24 shall end by 1 January 1996. 


3. It is agreed that consultations shall be held in the Joint Committee under paragraph 3 of Article 24 of the Central European Free Trade Agreement concerning the extension of the treatment referred to in paragraph 1 and 2 to other Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="17162">This Agreement shall constitute an integral part of the Central European Free Trade Agreement. Article 11 


1. This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth day after receiving by the Depositary of the last notification of Parties to the Central European Free Trade Agreement and the Republic of Slovenia on the completion of procedures necessary for that purpose. 


2. The Depositary shall, without any delay, notify all Parties of the completion of procedures necessary for entry into force of this Agreement. 


3. If this Agreement shall not enter into force by 1 January 1996, it shall be applied provisionally from that date. 


4. As from the date of entry into force of this Agreement the free trade agreements concluded between: 
-the Czech Republic and the Republic of Slovenia signed at Ljubljana on 4 December 1993, 

-the Slovak Republic and the Republic of Slovenia signed at Bratislava on 22 December 1993, 

-the Republic of Hungary and the Republic of Slovenia signed at Ljubljana on 6 April 1994, 

-the Republic of Poland the Republic of Slovenia singed at Ljubljana on 17 July 1995, 

by mutual consent of the Parties concerned expressed in this Agreement shall cease to be in force or shall not enter into force. 

5. As from the date of provisional application of this Agreement the free trade agreements mentioned in paragraph 4 of this Article shall not apply between their Contracting Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="2040">
      <article article_identifier="17163">IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undesigned plenipotentiaries, being duly authorized thereto, have signed this Agreement. 

DONE at Ljubljana this 25th day of November 1995, in a single authentic copy in the English language, which shall be deposited with the Government of the Republic of Poland. The Depositary shall transmit certified copies to all Parties. 

For the Czech Republic For the Republic of Poland For the Republic of Hungary For the Republic of Slovenia</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
