<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EC - Romania Interim Agreement</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>269</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>232</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1993-02-01</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1993-05-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1994-12-23</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>1995-02-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">ROU</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=90080545&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="340">
      <article article_identifier="19274">TheEuropeanEconomicCommunityandtheEuropeanCoaland SteelCommunity, hereinafter 
referred to as "the Community", 


of the one part, 


and Romania, 


of the other part, 


Whereas theEuropeAgreement establishingan associationbetween the EuropeanCommunities 
and their Member States and Romania was signed in Brussels on 1February 1993; 


Whereas,theaimoftheEuropeAgreement istoprovideanappropriateframeworkforpolitical 
dialogue; whereas it is to govern commercial and economic relations between the Parties and includes 
provisions relating to financial cooperationandassistanceand thepromotionofcooperation incultural 
matters; 


Whereas the Europe Agreement is intended to establish close and lasting relations, based on 
reciprocity, which would allow Romania to take part in the process of European integration; 


Whereas it is necessary to ensure the development of trade links by strengthening and widening 
the relations established in the past, notably by the Agreement on trade and commercial and economic 
cooperation, signed on 22 October 1990; 


Whereastothisend itisnecessarytoimplementasspeedilyaspossible,bymeansofanInterim 
Agreement, provisions of the Europe Agreement on trade and trade-related matters; 


Whereas it is necessary to ensure that pending the entry into force of the Europe Agreement 
and the establishment of the Association Council, the Joint Committee set up by the Agreement on 
trade and commercial and economic cooperation can exercise the powers assigned by the Europe 
Agreement to the Association Council which are necessary in order to implement the Interim Agreement; 


Have decided to conclude this Agreement and to this end have designated as their 
plenipotentiaries, 


The European Economic Community: 


The European Coal and Steel Community: 


Romania: 


Who, having exchanged their full powers, formed in good and due form, 


Have agreed as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="General Principles" chapter_identifier="341">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="19275">Respect for the democratic principles and human rights established by the Helsinki Final Act 
andtheCharterofParisfora'newEurope', aswellastheprinciplesofmarketeconomyandthesupport 
by the Community through this Agreement, inspire the domestic and external policies of the Parties 
and constitute essential elements of this Agreement.


Free Movement of Goods</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="19276">1. The Community and Romania shall gradually establish a free-trade area based on reciprocal 
andbalanced obligations inatransitionalperiod lasting amaximum oftenyears startingfromtheentry 
into force of this Agreement (hereinafter called "the Agreement"), in accordance with the provisions 
ofthisAgreementand inconformitywiththoseoftheGeneralAgreementonTariffsandTrade(GATT). 


2 The combined nomenclature of goods shall be applied to the classification of goods in trade 
between the two parties. 


3. For each product the basic duty to which the successive reductions set out in this Agreement 


are to be applied shall be that actually applied erga omnes on the day preceding the entry into force 
of the Agreement. 



4. If, after the entry into force of the Agreement, any tariff reduction is applied on an erga omnes 
basis, such reduced duties shall replace the basic duties referred to in paragraph 3 as from that date 
when such reductions are applied. 



5. The Community and Romania shall communicate to each other their respective basic duties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER I" name="Industrial Products" chapter_identifier="342">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="19277">1. The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to products originating in the Community and in 
Romania listed in Chapters 25 to 97 of the combined nomenclature with the exception of the products 
listed in Annex I. 



2. The provisions of Articles 4 to 8 included do not apply to products mentioned in Articles 10 
and 11.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="19278">1. Customs duties on imports applicable in the Community to products originating in Romania 
other than those listed in Annexes II(a), II(b) and III shall be abolished on the entry into force of the 
Agreement. 



2. Customs duties on imports applicable in the Community to products originating in Romania 
whicharelistedinAnnexlIashallbeprogressivelyabolished inaccordancewiththefollowingtimetable: 

-

on the date of entry into force of the Agreement, each duty shall be reduced to 50 per cent of the basic duty, 
-

one year after the date of entry into force of the Agreement. the remaining duties shall be eliminated. 
Customs duties on imports applicable in the Community to products originating in Romania 
listed in Annex Ilb shall be progressively reduced, from the date of entry into force of the Agreement, 
by annual reductions of 20 per cent of the basic duty so as to arrive at total abolition by the end of 
the fourth year after the date of entry into force of the Agreement. 


3. TheproductsofRomanianoriginlistedinAnnexIIIshallbenefitfromasuspensionofcustoms 
dutiesonimportswithinthe limitsofannualCommunity tariffquotasorceilings increasingprogressively 
inaccordancewiththeconditionsdefined inthatAnnexsoastoarrive atacompleteabolitionofcustoms 
duties on imports of the products concerned at the and of the fifth year at the latest. 


At the same time, the customs duties on imports to be applied when the quotas have been 
exhausted orwhenthe levyingofcustoms duties hasbeen re-establishedwith respect to products covered 
by a tariff ceiling, shall be progressively dismantled, from the entry into force of the Agreement by 
annualreductionsof15percentofthebasicduty. Bytheendofthefifthyear,remainingdutiesshall 
be abolished. 


4. Quantitative restrictions and measures having an effect equivalent to quantitative restrictions 
on imports to the Community shall be abolished on the date of entry into force of the Agreement with 
regard to the products originating in Romania.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="19279">1. Customs duties on imports applicable in Romania to products originating in the Community 
which are listed in Annex IV shall be abolished on the date of entry into force of the Agreement. 



2. Customs duties on imports applicable in Romania to products originating in the Community 
which are listed in Annex V shall be progressively reduced in accordance with the following timetable: 

-on the date of entry into force of the Agreement, to 80 per cent of the basic duty, 


-threeyearsaftertheentryintoforceoftheAgreement,to40percentofthebasicduty, 


-five years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 0 per cent of the basic duty. 



3. Customs duties on imports applicable in Romania to products originating in the Community 
which are listed in Annex VI shall be abolished in accordance with the timetable mentioned in that 
Annex. 



4. Customs duties on imports applicable in Romania to products originating in the Community 
otherthanthoselisted inAnnexesIV,VandVIshallbeprogressivelyreducedaccordingtothefollowing 
timetable: 

-three years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 80 per cent of the basic duty, 


-five years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 60 per cent of the basic duty, 


-six years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 50 per cent of the basic duty, 


-seven years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 35 per cent of the basic 
duty, 


-eightyearsaftertheentryintoforceoftheAgreement,to20percentofthebasicduty, 


-nine years after the entry into force of the Agreement, to 0 per cent of the basic duty. 


5. TheproductsoriginatingintheCommunitylistedinAnnexVIIshallbenefitfromasuspension 


of customs duties on imports in Romania within the limits of annual quotas which will be increased 
progressively as foreseen in that Annex. Customs duties on imports applicable to quantities in excess 
oftheabove-mentioned quotas shallbeprogressivelydismantled according to thetimetablementioned 
in paragraph 4. 



6. Quantitative restrictions on imports into Romania of products originating in the Community 
shall be abolished upon entry into force of the Agreement. 



7. Measures having an effect equivalent to quantitative restrictions on imports into Romania of 

productsoriginating intheCommunity shallbeabolisheduponentryintoforceoftheAgreement,except 
for those listed in Annex VIII which shall be abolished according to the timetable in that Annex.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="19280">Theprovisionsconcerningtheabolitionofcustomsdutiesonimports shallalsoapplytocustoms 
duties of a fiscal nature.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="19281">1. The Community shall abolish in its imports from Romania any charges having an equivalent 
effect to customs duties on imports upon entry into force of the Agreement. 



2. Romania shall abolish in its imports from the Community any charges having an equivalent 
effect to customs duties on imports upon entry into force of the Agreement, except for the charges 
of0.5 per centadvaloremforthecustomsformalitieswhichwillbeabolishedaccording tothefollowing 
timetable: 

-reduction to 0.25 per cent ad valorem at the end of the third year, 


-elimination at the latest by the end of the fifth year upon entry into force of the 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="19282">1. The Community and Romania shall progressively abolish between then at the latest by the 
end of the fifth year after entry into force of the Agreement any customs duties on exports and charges 
having equivalent effect. 



2. Quantitative restrictions on exports to Romania and any measures having equivalent effect shall 
be abolished by the Community upon entry into force of the Agreement. 



3. Quantitative restrictions on exports to the Community and any measures having equivalent 
effect shall be abolished by Romania upon entry into force of the Agreement except for those listed 
in Annex IX which shall be progressively reduced and shall be eliminated at the latest by the end of 
the fifth year after the entry into force of the Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="19283">Each Party declares its readiness to reduce its customs duties in trade with the other Party more 
rapidly than is provided for in Articles 4 and 5 if its general economic situation and the situation of 
the economic sector concerned so permit. 


TheJoint Committee. referred to in Article 39 (hereinafter referred to as "theJoint Committee") 
may make recommendations to this effect.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="19284">Protocol 1 lays down the arrangements applicable to the textile products referred to therein.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="19285">Protocol 2 lays down the arrangements applicable to products covered by the Treaty establishing 
the European Coal and Steel Community.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="19286">1. The provisionsofthisChapterdonotprecludetheretentionbytheCommunityofanagricultural 
component in the duties applicable to products listed in Annex X in respect of products originating 
in Romania. 



2. The provisions of this Chapter do not preclude the introduction of an agricultural component 
byRomania inthedutiesapplicabletotheproductslistedinAnnexX inrespectofproductsoriginating 
in the Community.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER II" name="Agriculture" chapter_identifier="343">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="19287">1. TheprovisionsofthisChaptershallapplytoagriculturalproductsoriginatingintheCommunity 
and in Romania. 



2. The term "agricultural products" means the products listed in Chapters 1 to 24 of the combined 
nomenclatureandtheproductslistedinAnnex I,butexcludingfisheryproductsasdefinedbyRegulation 
(EEC) No. 3687/91.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="19288">Protocol 3 lays down the trade arrangements for processed agricultural products which are 
listed in such protocol.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="19289">1 The Community shall abolish at the date of entry into force of the Agreement the quantitative 
restrictionsonimportsofagricultural productsoriginating inRomaniamaintainedby virtueofCouncil 
Regulation (EEC) No. 3420/83 in the form exist ng on the date of signature hereof. 



2. TheagriculturalproductsoriginatinginRomanialistedinAnnexesXI(a)andXI(b)shallbenefit, 
upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement, from the reduction of levies within the limit of 
Community quotas or from the reduction of customs duties and upon the conditions provided in the 
same Annexes. 



3. Romania shall abolish quantitative restrictions on imports of agricultural products originating 
in the Community upon entry into force of the Agreement. 



4. The Community and Romania shall grant each other the concessions referred to in 
Annexes XII(a), XII(b) and XIII, on a harmonious and reciprocal basis, in accordance with the conditions 
laid down therein. 



5. Takingaccountofthevolumeoftradeinagriculturalproductsbetweenthem,oftheirparticular 
sensitivity,ofthe rulesofthecommonagriculturalpolicyoftheCommunity,oftheroleofagriculture 
inRomania'seconomy, andoftheconsequences ofthemultilateral tradenegotiationsundertheGeneral 
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the Community and Romania shall examine in the Joint Committee, 
productbyproductandonanorderlyandreciprocal basis, thepossibilitiesofgrantingeachotherfurther 
concessions. 



6. Taking account of the need for an increased harmony between the agricultural policies in the 
Community andRomania, aswellasRomania's objectiveofbecomingamemberoftheCommunity, 
both Parties will have regular consultations in the Joint Committee on the strategy and practical modalities 
of their respective policies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="19290">Notwithstanding other provisions of this Agreement, and in particular Article 25, if, given 
theparticularsensitivityoftheagriculturalmarkets, importsofproductsoriginatinginoneParty,which 
are the subject of concessions granted in Article 15, cause serious disturbance to the markets in the 
other Party, both Parties shall enter into consultations immediately to find an appropriate solution. 
Pending such a solution, the Party concerned may take the measures it deems necessary.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER III" name="Fisheries" chapter_identifier="2319">
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="19291">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to fishery products originating in the Community 
and in Romania, which are covered by Regulation (EEC) No. 3687/91 on the common organization 
of the market in fishery products.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" article_identifier="19292">1. TheCommunityandRomaniashallgranteachothertheconcessionsreferredtoinAnnexesXIV 
and XV on a harmonious and reciprocal basis. in accordance with the conditions laid down therein. 
The provisions of Article 15(5) shall apply mutatis mutandis to fishery products. 



2. TheJointCommitteewillexaminethepossibilityofconcludinganagreementonfisheryproducts 
between the Parties when the necessary conditions so permit.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER IV" name="Common Provisions" chapter_identifier="2320">
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="19293">The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to trade in all products, except where otherwise 
provided herein or in Protocols 1, 2 or 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" article_identifier="19294">1. No new customs duties on imports or exports or charges having equivalent effect shall be 
introduced, nor shall those already applied be increased, in the trade between the Community and 
Romania from the date of entry into force of the Agreement. 



2. No new quantitative restrictions on imports or exports or measures having equivalent effect 
shall be introduced, nor shallthose existing be made more restrictive, in the trade between the 
Community and Romania from the date of entry into force of the Agreement. 



3. Any new customs duties on imports or exports or charges having equivalent effect or increases 
thereof or any new quantitative restrictions or charges having equivalent effect or increases thereof 
introduced by Romania after the beginning of the negotiations shall be abolished at the latest at the 
entry into force of the Agreement. 



4. Without prejudice to the concessions granted pursuant to Article 15, the provisions of 
paragraphs Iand2ofthisArticleshallnotrestrictinanywaythepursuanceoftherespectiveagricultural 
policies of Romania and the Community or the taking of any measures under such policies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" article_identifier="19295">1. The two Parties shall refrain from any measure or practice of an internal fiscal nature 
establishing. whether directly or indirectly, discrimination between the products of one Party and like 
products originating in the territory of the other Party. 



2. Products exported to the territory of one of the two Parties may not benefit from repayment 
of internal taxation in excess of the amount of direct or indirect taxation imposed on them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" article_identifier="19296">1. This Agreement shall not preclude the maintenance or establishment of customs unions, free-
trade areas or arrangements for frontier trade except in so far as they alter the trade arrangements 
provided for in this Agreement. 



2. Consultations between the Parties shall take place within the Joint Committee concerning 
Agreements establishing such customs unions or free-trade areas and, where requested, on other major 
issues related to their respective trade policies with third countries. In particular in the event of a third 
country acceding to the Community, such consultations shall take place so as to ensure that account 
can be taken of the mutual interests of the Community and Romania stated in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" article_identifier="19297">Exceptional measures of limited duration which derogate from the provisions of 
Articles 5 and 20 (1) may be taken by Romania in the form of increased customs duties. 


These measures may only concern infant industries, or certain sectors undergoing restructuring 
or facing serious difficulties, particularly where these difficulties produce important social problems. 


Customs duties on imports applicable in Romania to products originating in the Community 
introduced by these measures may not exceed 25 per cent ad valorem and shall maintain an element 
of preference for products originating in the Community. The total value of imports of the products 


which are subject to these measures may not exceed 15 per cent of total imports from the Community 
of industrial products as defined in Chapter 1, during the last year for which statistics are available. 


These measures shall be applied for a period not exceeding five years, unless a longer duration 
is authorized by the Joint Committee. They shall cease to apply at the latest at the expiration of the 
transitional period. 


Nosuchmeasurescanbeintroducedinrespectofaproduct ifmorethanthreeyearshaveelapsed 
since the elimination of all duties and quantitative restrictions or charges or measures having an equivalent 
effect concerning that product. 


RomaniashallinformtheJointCommitteeofanyexceptionalmeasures itintendstotakeand, 
at the request of the Community. consultations shall be held in the Joint Committee on such measures 
and the sectors to which they apply before they are applied. When taking such measures, Romania 
shall provide the Joint Committee with a schedule for the elimination of the customs duties introduced 
under this Article. This schedule shall provide for a phasing out of these duties starting at the latest 
two years after their introduction at equal annual rates. TheJoint Committee may decide on a different 
schedule.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" article_identifier="19298">If one of the Parties finds that dumping is taking place in trade with the other Party within 
the meaning of Article VI of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, it may take appropriate 
measures againstthispractice inaccordancewiththeAgreement relatingtotheapplicationofArticle VI 
oftheGeneralAgreementon TariffsandTrade, with related internal legislationandwith theconditions 


and procedures laid down in Article 28.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" article_identifier="19299">Where any product is being imported in such increased quantities and under such conditions 
as to cause, or threaten to cause: 


-

serious injury to domestic producers of like or directly competitive products in the territory of one of the Parties, or 
-

serious disturbances in any sector of the economy or difficulties which could bring about serious deterioration in the economic situation of a region, 
the Community or Romania, whichever is concerned, may take appropriate measures under 
the conditions and in accordance with the procedures laid down in Article 28.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" article_identifier="19300">Where compliance with the provisions of Articles 8 and 20 leads to: 



(i) 	re-export towards a third country against which the exporting Party maintains, for the 
product concerned, quantitative export restrictions, export duties or measures having 
equivalent effect; or 



(ii) 	a serious shortage. or threat thereof, of a product essential to the exporting Party, 

and where the situations above referred to give rise, or are likely to give rise to major difficulties 
fortheexportingParty. thatPartymaytakeappropriatemeasuresundertheconditionsand inaccordance 
withtheprocedures laiddowninArticle28. Themeasuresshallbenon-discriminatoryandbeeliminated 
when conditions no longer justify their maintenance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" article_identifier="19301">The Member States and Romania shall progressively adjust any State monopolies ofa commercial 
character so as to ensure that. by the end of the fifth year following the entry into force of this 
Agreement. no discrimination regarding the conditions under which goods are procured and marketed 
existsbetweennationalsoftheMemberStatesandofRomania. TheJointCommittee willbeinformed 
about the measures adopted to implement this objective.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" article_identifier="19302">1. In the event of the Community or Romania subjecting imports of products liable to give rise 
to the difficulties referred to in Article 25 to an administrative procedure having as its purpose the 
rapid provision of information on the trend of trade flows, it shall inform the other Party. 



2. In the cases specified in Articles 24, 25 and 26, before taking the measures provided for therein 
or, in cases to which paragraph 3(d) applies, as soon as possible. the Community or Romallia, as the 
case may be, shall supply the Joint Committee with all relevant information, with a view to seeking 
a solution acceptable to the two Parties. 

Intheselectionofmeasures, prioritymustbegiventothosewhich leastdisturbthefunctioning 
of this Agreement. 


The safeguard measures shall be notified immediately to the Joint Committee and shall be the 
subject of periodic consultations within that body, particularly with a view to establishing a timetable 
for their abolition as soon as circumstances permit. 


3. 	For the implementation of paragraph 2, the following provisions shall apply: 


(a) 	as regards Article 25, the difficulties arising from the situation referred to in that Article 
shall be referred for examination to the Joint Committee, which may take any decision 
needed to put an end to such difficulties. 


If the Joint Committee or the exporting Party has not taken a decision putting an end 
to the difficulties or no other satisfactory solution has been reached within 30 days 
of the matter being referred, the importing Party may adopt the appropriate measures 
toremedytheproblem. Thesemeasuresmustnotexceedthescopeofwhat isnecessary 
to remedy the difficulties which have arisen; 



(b) 	as regards Article 24, the Joint Committee shall be informed of the dumping case as 
soon as the authorities of the importing Party have initiated an investigation. When 
no end has been put to the dumping or no other satisfactory solution has been reached 
within30daysofthematterbeingreferredtotheJointCommittee, theimportingParty 
may adopt the appropriate measures; 



(c) 	as regards Article 26. the difficulties arising from the situations referred to in that Article 
shall be referred for examination to the Joint Committee. 

The Joint Committee may take any decision needed to put an end to the difficulties. 
If it has not taken such a decision within 30 days of the matter being referred to it, 
the exporting Party may apply appropriate measures on the exportation of the product 
concerned: 


(d) 	where exceptional circumstances requiring immediate action make prior information 
orexamination, asthecasemay be, impossible, theCommunityorRomania,whichever 
is concerned, may, in the situations specified in Articles 24, 25 and 26, apply forthwith 
the precautionary and provisional measures strictly necessary to deal with the situation, 
and the Joint Committee will be informed immediately.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" article_identifier="19303">Protocol 4 lays down rules of origin for the application of tariff preferences foreseen in this 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" article_identifier="19304">This Agreement shall not preclude prohibitions or restrictions on imports, exports or goods 
in transit justified on grounds of public morality, public policy or public security; the protection of 
health and life of humans, animals or plants; the protection of natural resources; the protection of 
national treasures of artistic, historic or archaeological value or the protection of intellectual, industrial 
and commercial property or rules relating to gold and silver. Such prohibitions or restrictions shall 
not,however, constituteameansofarbitrarydiscriminationoradisguised restrictionontradebetween 
the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" article_identifier="19305">Protocol 5 lays down the specific provisions to apply to trade between Romania of the one 
part and Spain and Portugal of the other part.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE III" name="Payments, Competition And Other Economic Provisions" chapter_identifier="2321">
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" article_identifier="19306">The Parties undertake to authorize in freely convertible currency, any payments on the current 
account of balance of payments to the extent that the transactions underlying the payments concern 
movements of goods between the Parties which have been liberalized pursuant to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" article_identifier="19307">With reference to the provisionsofthisChapter, and notwithstanding theprovisionsofArticle 35, 
until a full convertibility of Romanian currency in the meaning of Article VIII of the International 
Monetary Fund (IMF) is introduced, Romania may in exceptional circumstances apply exchange 
restrictions connected with the granting or taking up of short-and medium-term credits to the extent 
that such restrictions are imposed on Romania for the granting ofsuch credits and are permitted according 
to Romania's status under the IMF. 


Romania shall apply these restrictions in a non-discriminatory manner. They shall be applied 
in such a manner as to cause the least possible disruption to this Agreement. Romania shall inform 
the Joint Committee promptly of the introduction of such measures and of any changes therein.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" article_identifier="19308">1. The following are incompatible with the proper functioning of this Agreement, in so far as 
they may affect trade between the Community and Romania: 



(i) 	all agreements between undertakings, decisions by associations of undertakings and 
concerted practices between undertakings which have as their object or effect the 
prevention, restriction or distortion of competition; 



(ii) 	abuse by one or more undertakings of a dominant position in the territories of the 
Community or of Romania as a whole or in a substantial part thereof; 

(iii) 	any public aid which distorts or threatens to distort competition by favouring certain 
undertakings or the production of certain goods. 



2. Any practices contrary to this Article shall be assessed on the basis of criteria arising from 
theapplicationofthe rulesofArticles85,86and92oftheTreatyestablishingtheEuropeanEconomic 
Community. 



3. The Joint Committee shall, within three years of the entry into force of the Agreement, adopt 
the necessary rules for the implementation of paragraphs 1 and 2. 



4. 	(a) For the purposes of applying the provisions of paragraph 1, point (iii), the Parties 
recognize that during the first five years after the entry into force of the Agreement, 
any public aid granted by Romania shall be assessed taking into account the fact that 
Romania shall be regarded as an area identical to those ar-as of the Community 
described in Article 92(3)(a) of the Treaty establishing the European Economic 
Community. The Joint Committee shall, taking into account the economic situation 
of Romania, decide whether that period should be extended by further periods of five 
years. 


(b) 	Each Party shall ensure transparency in the area of public aid, inter alia, by reporting 
annually to the other Party on the total amount and the distribution of the aid given 
and by providing, upon request. information on aid schemes. Upon request by one 
Party, theotherParty shallprovideinformationonparticularindividualcasesofpublic 
aid. 


5. 	With regard to products referred to in Chapters Il and III of Title Il: 

-	the provision of paragraph 1(iii) does not apply, 


-any practices contrary to paragraph 1(i) should assessed according to the criteria 
established by the Community on the basis of Articles 42 and 43 of the Treaty 
establishing theEuropeanEconomicCommunity and inparticularofthoseestablished 
in Council Regulation No. 26/1962. 


6. IftheCommunityorRomaniaconsidersthataparticularpracticeisincompatiblewiththeterms 
of paragraph 1. and: 


-is not adequately dealt with under the implementing rules referred to in paragraph 3, 
or 


-in the absence of such rules, and if such practice causes or threatens to cause serious 
prejudice to the interest of the other Party or material injury to its domestic industry, 
including its services industry, 


it may take appropriate measures after consultation within the Joint Committee or after 30 
working days following referral for such consultation. 


In the case of practices incompatible with paragraph 1(iii) of this Article, such appropriate 
measures may, where the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade applies thereto, only be adopted 
in conformity with the procedures and under the conditions laid down by the General Agreement on 
Tariffs and Trade and any other relevant instrument negotiated under its auspices which are applicable 
between the Parties. 



7. Notwithstanding any provisions to the contrary adopted in conformity with paragraph 3, the 
Parties shall exchange information taking into account the limitations imposed by the requirements 
of professional and business secrecy. 



8. This Article shall not apply to the products covered by the Treaty establishing the European 
Coal and Steel Community which are the subject of Protocol 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" article_identifier="19309">1. The Parties shall endeavour to avoid the imposition of restrictive measures including measures 
relating to imports for balance of payments purposes. In the event of their introduction, the Party 
having introduced the same shall present to the other Party a time schedule for their removal. 



2. Where one or more Member States or Romania is in serious balance of payments difficulties, 
or under imminent threat thereof, the Community or Romania, as the case may be, may, in accordance 
with the conditions established under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, adopt restrictive 
measures, including measures relating to. imports, which shall be of limited duration and may not go 
beyond what is necessary to remedy the balance of payrnents situation. The Community or Romania, 
as the case may be, shall inform the other Party forthwith.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" article_identifier="19310">With regard to public undertakings and undertakings to which special or exclusive rights have 
beengranted, theJointCommittee shallensurethat, asfromthethirdyearfromthedateofentry into 
force of the Agreement, the principles of the Treaty establishing the European Economic Community, 
notably Article 90, and the principles of the concluding document of the April 1990 Bonn meeting 
oftheConferenceonSecurityandCooperation inEurope(notablyentrepreneurs'freedomofdecision) 
are applied in the operation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" article_identifier="19311">Romania shall continue to improve the protection of intellectual, industrial and commercial 
property rights in order to provide, by the end of the fifth year after the entry into force of the 
Agreement, for a level of protection similar to that provided in the Community by Community acts, 
inparticular theones referred to inAnnexXVI, including comparablemeans ofenforcingsuch rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" article_identifier="19312">Mutual assistance between administrative authorities in customs matters of the Parties shall 
take place in accordance with the provisions of Protocol 6.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IV" name="Institutional, General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="2322">
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" article_identifier="19313">The Joint Committee set up by the Agreement on Trade and Commercial and Economic 


Cooperation signed between the European Economic Community and Romania on 20 October 1990 
shall perform the duties assigned to it by this Agreement until the Association Council provided for 
in Article 106 of the Europe Agreement is established.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" article_identifier="19314">The Joint Committee shall, for the purpose of attaining the objectives of the Agreement, have 
the power to take decisions in the cases provided for therein. The decisions taken shall be binding 
on the Parties which shall take the measures necessary to implement the decisions taken. The Joint 
Committee may also make appropriate recommendations. 


It shall draw up its decisions and recommendations by agreement between the two Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" article_identifier="19315">1. EachofthetwoPartiesmayrefertotheJointCommitteeanydisputerelatingtotheapplication 
or interpretation of this Agreement. 



2. 	TheJointCommitteemaysettlethedisputebymeansofadecision. 



3. Each Party shall be bound to take the measures involved in carrying out the decision referred 
to in paragraph 2. 



4. In the event of it not being possible to settle the dispute in accordance with paragraph 2, either 
Party may notify the other of the appointment of an arbitrator; the other Party must then appoint a 
second arbitrator within two months. 

The Joint Committee shall appoint a third arbitrator. 
The arbitrators' decisions shall be taken by majority vote. 
Each Party to the dispute must take the steps required to implement the decision of the arbitrators.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" article_identifier="19316">Within the scope of this Agreement, each Party undertakes to ensure that natural and legal 
persons of the other Party have access free of discrimination in relation to its own nationals to the 
competent courts and administrative organs of the Parties to defend their individual rights and their 
property rights, including those concerning intellectual, industrial and commercial property.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" article_identifier="19317">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a Contracting Party from taking any measures: 



(a) 	which it considers necessary to prevent the disclosure of information necessary to its 
essential security interests; 



(b) 	which relate to the production of, or trade in, arms, ammunition or war materials or 
to research, development or production indispensable for defence purposes, provided 
that such measures do not impair the conditions of competition in respect of products 
not intended for specifically military purposes; 



(c) 	which it considers essential to its own security in the event of serious internal 
disturbances affecting the maintenance of law and order, in time of war or serious 
international tension constituting threat of war or in order to carry out obligations it 
has accepted for the purpose of maintaining peace and international security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" article_identifier="19318">In the fields covered by this Agreement and without prejudice to any special provisions contained 
therein: 


-the arrangements applied by Romania in respect of the Community shall not give rise 
to any discrimination between the Member States, their nationals, or their companies 
or firms, 


-the arrangements applied by the Community in respect of Romania shall not give rise 
to any discrimination between Romanian nationals or its companies or firms.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" article_identifier="19319">Products originating in Romania shall not enjoy more favourable treatment when imported 
into the Community than that applied by Member States among themselves.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" article_identifier="19320">1. The Parties shall take any general or specific measures required to fulfil their obligations under 
the Agreement. They shall see to it that the objectives set out in the Agreement are attained. 



2. If either Party considers that the other Party has failed to fulfil an obligation under the 
Agreement, it may take appropriate measures. Before so doing, except in cases of special urgency, 
it shall supply the Joint Committee with all relevant information required for a thorough examination 
of the situation with a view to seeking a solution acceptable to the Parties. 

Intheselectionofmeasures, prioritymustbegiventothosewhichleastdisturbthefunctioning 
of the Agreement. These measures shall be notified immediately to the Joint Committee and shall 
be the subject of consultations within the Joint Committee if the other Party so requests.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" article_identifier="19321">Protocols 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7, and Annexes I to XVI shall form an integral part of this 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" article_identifier="19322">1 This Agreement shall be applicable until the entry into force of the Europe Agreement signed 
on 1 February 1993. 


2. Either Party may denounce this Agreement by notifying the other Party. This Agreement -hall 
cease to apply six months after the date of such notification.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" article_identifier="19323">ThisAgreementshallapply,ontheonehand, totheterritoriesinwhichtheTreatiesestablishing 
the European Economic Community and the European. Coal and Steel Community are applied and under 
the conditions laid down in those Treaties and, on the other hand, to the territory of Romania.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" article_identifier="19324">This Agreement is drawn up in duplicate in the Danish, Dutch, English, French, German, Italian, 
Spanish, Greek, Portuguese and Romanian languages, each of these texts being equally authentic.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" article_identifier="19325">This Agreement will be approved by the Parties in accordance with their own procedures. 


This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the second month following the date 
on which the Parties notify each other that the procedures referred to in the first paragraph have been 
completed. 


Upon its entry into force, Articles 2, 3(1) and 4 to 16 of the Agreement between the European 
Atomic Energy Comrunity and Romania on trade and economic and commercial cooperation signed 
in Luxembourg on 22 October 1990, shall be suspended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" article_identifier="19326">1. In the event that this Agreement enters into force afte. 1 January but before 30 June 1993 for 
the purpose of Titles Il and III of this Agreement and Protocols 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7 hereto, "date 
of entry into force of the Agreement" shall mean: 


-	the date of entry into force in relation to obligations taking effect on that date, and 


-	1January1993inrelationtoobligationstakingeffectafterthedateofentryintoforce 
by reference to the date of entry into force. 


2. 	In the case of entry into force after 1 January the provisions of Protocol 7 shall apply.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
