<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU - Papua New Guinea / Fiji</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>759</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>411</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>2009-07-30</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2009-12-20</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2011-10-18</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2023-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FJI</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">PNG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FJI</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">PNG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="30">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Europe; Oceania</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391908038&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/ES/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="fr" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/FR/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)&amp;from=EN</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391908038&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391908038&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399391908038&amp;uri=CELEX:22009A1016(01)</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="4098">
      <article article_identifier="35388">Interim Partnership Agreement

  between the European Community, of the one part, and the Pacific
  States, of the other part

  THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY, hereinafter referred to as "the EC
  Party",

  of the one part, and

  THE REPUBLIC OF THE FIJI ISLANDS,

  THE INDEPENDENT STATE OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA (hereinafter referred to as
  "Papua New Guinea"),

  hereinafter referred to as "the Pacific States",

  of the other part,

  HAVING REGARD TO the Partnership Agreement between the Members of the
  African, Caribbean and Pacific Group of States of the one part, and
  the European Community and its Member States of the other part, signed
  in Cotonou on 23 June 2000 and revised in 2005 (hereinafter referred
  to as the "Cotonou Agreement");

  HAVING REGARD TO the fact that the trade preferences granted under the
  Cotonou Agreement will expire on 31 December 2007;

  HAVING REGARD TO the negative impact on the exports from Pacific
  States to the European Community that may result from the expiration
  of the Cotonou trade preferences in case no WTO compatible successor
  trade arrangement is in place by 31 December 2007 and that it is
  therefore necessary to establish an Interim Partnership Agreement that
  would safeguard the trade and development interests of the Pacific
  States affected;

  HAVING REGARD TO the fact that the EC Party has offered improved
  market access within the framework of the negotiations on Economic
  Partnership Agreements (EPAs) and that Pacific States wish to start
  benefiting from this offer as from 1 January 2008;

  REAFFIRMING their continuing commitment to the ongoing negotiations
  aiming at the conclusion of a comprehensive EPA by 31 December 2008
  which will contain all relevant elements and include all interested
  Pacific Islands;

  REAFFIRMING that development cooperation will be a crucial element of
  the comprehensive EPA and an essential factor for the realisation of
  its objectives;

  REAFFIRMING their commitment to the objectives and the implementation
  of the Cotonou Agreement and desiring to build upon those commitments;

  REAFFIRMING their commitment to the respect for human rights,
  democratic principles, the rule of law and to good governance, which
  constitute essential and fundamental elements of the Cotonou
  Agreement, and to sustainable and equitable development, along with
  greater involvement of an active and organised civil society and the
  private sector, which, along with the market economy, are the main
  elements recognised in the Cotonou Agreement as contributing to
  achieving the objectives of the partnership;

  REAFFIRMING their commitment to work together towards the achievement
  of the objectives of the Cotonou Agreement of poverty eradication,
  sustainable development and the gradual integration of the Pacific
  States into the world economy, with due regard for their political
  choices and development priorities;

  REAFFIRMING their commitment to support the regional integration
  process within the Pacific region, and in particular to foster
  regional economic integration as a key instrument for their
  integration into the world economy and helping them face the
  challenges of globalisation and achieving the economic and social
  development to which they aim;

  DESIRING to cooperate closely at the national level within the
  framework of the existing structures as set out in the Cotonou
  Agreement to maximise the synergies between development cooperation
  and the objectives of this Agreement;

  DESIRING to progressively remove barriers to trade between them; while
  taking into account the principles of asymmetry and flexibility;

  DESIRING to establish a framework for improved arrangements for trade
  between the Pacific States and the European Community that are
  consistent with their obligations under the World Trade Organisation
  ("WTO");

  DESIRING to establish an institutional framework for their Interim
  Partnership Agreement and a mechanism to resolve any disputes that
  might arise in that relationship consistently with the objectives of
  this Agreement,

  HAVE DECIDED TO CONCLUDE THIS AGREEMENT:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART I" name="Trade Partnership For Sustainable Development" chapter_identifier="4099">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="35389">The objectives of this Agreement are to:

  (a) enable Pacific States to start benefiting from the improved market
  access offered by the EC Party within the framework of the EPA
  negotiations and, at the same time, avoid trade disruption between
  Pacific States and the European Community in view of the expiry of the
  trade preferences granted under the Cotonou Agreement on 31 December
  2007 and pending the conclusion of a comprehensive EPA between the
  Pacific States and the EC Party, and its Member States as the case may
  be;

  (b) promote sustainable development and the gradual integration of
  Pacific States into the world economy, in conformity with the their
  political choices and development priorities;

  (c) establish a free trade area between the Parties based on the
  common interest, and fulfil this objective by the progressive
  liberalisation of trade in a manner compliant with applicable WTO
  rules and the principle of asymmetry, commensurate to the specific
  needs and capacity constraints of the Pacific States, in terms of
  levels and timing for commitments under this Agreement;

  (d) set up the appropriate dispute settlement arrangements;

  (e) set up the appropriate institutional arrangements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Principles" article_identifier="35390">1. This Agreement is based on the Fundamental Principles as well as
  the Essential and Fundamental Elements set out in Articles 2 and 9 of
  the Cotonou Agreement. This Agreement shall build on the provisions of
  the Cotonou Agreement and the previous ACP-EC Partnership Agreements
  in the area of regional cooperation and integration as well as
  economic and trade cooperation.

  2. The Parties agree that the Cotonou Agreement and this Agreement
  shall be implemented in a complementary and mutually reinforcing
  manner.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Sustainable Development" article_identifier="35391">1. The Parties reaffirm that the objective of sustainable development
  shall be an integral part of the provisions of this Agreement,
  consistent with the overarching objectives and principles set out in
  Articles 1, 2 and 9 of the Cotonou Agreement, and especially the
  general commitment to reduce and eventually eradicate poverty in a way
  that is consistent with the objectives of sustainable development.

  2. The Parties understand this objective to apply in the case of the
  present Agreement as a commitment that:

  (a) the application of this Agreement shall fully take into account
  the human, cultural, economic, social, health and environmental best
  interests of their respective populations and of future generations;

  (b) decision-taking methods embrace the fundamental principles of
  ownership, participation and dialogue.

  3. As a result the Parties agree to work cooperatively towards the
  realisation of a sustainable development centred on the human person,
  who is the main beneficiary of development.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Regional Integration" article_identifier="35392">1. This Agreement builds upon and aims at deepening regional
  integration and the Parties undertake to cooperate to further develop
  it.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent any Party from entering
  into any Agreement for the establishment of a free trade area, customs
  union or other free trade Agreement with any third countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Cooperation In International Fora" article_identifier="35393">1. The Parties shall endeavour to cooperate in all international fora
  where issues relevant to this Agreement are discussed.

  2. The Parties recognise the valuable contribution that regional
  organisations can make to the achievement of the objectives of this
  Agreement. The Parties agree to work closely with existing Pacific
  regional organisations and programmes wherever useful and possible to
  support the implementation of this Agreement.

  TRADE IN GOODS</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Scope" article_identifier="35394">This Agreement shall apply to products originating in the European
  Community or in the Pacific States and falling within Chapters 01 to
  97 set out in the EC Party's and the Pacific States’ respective tariff
  nomenclatures in conformity with the rules of classification
  applicable to the Harmonised Commodity Description and Coding System
  (HS).</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Customs Duties" chapter_identifier="4100">
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Customs Duties And Other Charges" article_identifier="35395">1. A customs duty includes any duty or charge of any kind imposed on
  or in connection with the importation of goods, including any form of
  surtax or surcharge, but does not include:

  (a) internal taxes or other internal charges imposed consistently with
  Article 23;

  (b) any antidumping, countervailing or safeguard measure applied
  consistently with Chapter 2 of Part II;

  (c) fees or other charges imposed consistently with paragraph 2.

  2. Fees and charges referred to in paragraph 1(c) shall be limited in
  amount to the approximate cost of services rendered and shall not
  represent indirect protection for domestic products or a taxation of
  imports for fiscal purposes. Any such fees and charges shall not be
  applied on an ad valorem basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="35396">For the purposes of this Chapter, "originating" means
  qualifying under the rules of origin set out in Protocol II to this
  Agreement. In the period of the five years following the entry into
  force of this Agreement the Parties shall review the operation of
  these provisions, with a view to further simplifying the concepts and
  methods used for the purpose of determining origin in the light of the
  development needs of the Pacific States. In such review, full
  consideration shall be given to providing certainty for investors, the
  development of technologies and production processes and all other
  factors, including on-going reforms of rules of origin and the
  establishment of appropriate mechanisms for administrative cooperation
  between the Parties and the Pacific States as the case may be, which
  may require modifications to the provisions of this Protocol. Not
  later than one year before the end of this period, the Parties shall
  open negotiations on the Protocol with a view to modifying or
  replacing it. Any such modification or replacement shall be effected
  by a decision of the Trade Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="35397">The classification of goods in trade between the EC Party and the
  Pacific States shall be that set out in the respective tariff
  nomenclatures based on the Harmonised Commodity Description and Coding
  System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties On Exports" article_identifier="35398">Neither the EC Party nor the Pacific States may maintain or institute
  any duties, taxes or other fees and charges imposed on or in
  connection with the exportation of goods to the other Party, or any
  internal taxes, fees and charges on goods exported to the other Party
  that are in excess of those imposed on like products destined for
  internal sale, except:

  (a) when these measures are necessary, in conjunction with domestic
  measures, for ensuring fiscal solvency of a Pacific State or for the
  protection of the environment; and

  (b) in exceptional circumstances, where a Pacific State can justify
  specific protection to develop infant industries, that Pacific State
  may introduce temporary export taxes on a limited number of products
  destined for the EC market after mutual Agreement with the EC Party
  [1].</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The Pacific States" article_identifier="35399">Products originating in the Pacific States shall be imported in the EC
  Party free of customs duties, except for the products indicated, and
  under the conditions set out in Annex I.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Customs Duties On Products Originating In The Ec Party" article_identifier="35400">Customs duties on imports of products originating in the EC Party
  shall be reduced or eliminated in accordance with the provisions set
  out in Annex II.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Modification Of Tariff Commitments" article_identifier="35401">In the event of serious difficulties in respect of imports of a given
  product, the Pacific State facing such difficulty may request that the
  Trade Committee review the schedule of customs duty reductions and
  eliminations with a view to modify where necessary the time schedule
  for reduction or elimination by common accord.

  The Trade Committee by agreement may modify Annex II in any manner
  deemed appropriate.

  The Parties shall ensure that any such modifications do not result in
  an incompatibility of this Agreement with the requirements of Article
  XXIV of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Standstill" article_identifier="35402">No new customs duties shall be introduced in trade, nor shall those
  already applied be increased between the Parties as from the entry
  into force of the Agreement for all products subject to liberalising
  commitments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Circulation Of Goods" article_identifier="35403">1. Customs duties shall be levied only once for goods originating in
  the EC Party or in the Pacific States. Once customs duties have been
  levied, goods originating in any of the Parties shall circulate within
  the territory of the EC Party or of the Pacific States respectively
  without any further payment of customs duties.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 and for goods of tariff headings whose
  duties have not yet been eliminated in all of the Pacific States, any
  customs duty paid upon importation in a Pacific State shall be
  refunded fully and without delay when the goods leave the customs
  territory of first importation. Such product shall then pay the duty
  in the country of consumption.

  3. The Parties agree to cooperate with a view to facilitating the
  circulation of goods and simplifying customs procedures as provided
  for under Chapter 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Non-Discrimination Clause" article_identifier="35404">1. With respect to matters covered by this Chapter, the EC Party shall
  accord to Pacific States any more favourable treatment applicable as a
  result of the EC Party becoming party to a free trade agreement with
  third parties after the signature of this Agreement.

  2. With respect to the subject matter covered by this Chapter, the
  Pacific States shall accord to the EC Party any more favourable
  treatment applicable as a result of the Pacific States becoming party
  to a free trade agreement with any major trading economy after the
  signature of this Agreement.

  3. Where a Pacific State or the Pacific States can demonstrate that
  they have been offered by a third Party a substantially more
  favourable treatment in goods, including rules of origin, than that
  offered by the EC Party, the Parties will consult and may jointly
  decide how best to implement the provisions of paragraph 2.

  4. The provisions of this Chapter shall not be so construed as to
  oblige the EC Party or any Pacific State to extend reciprocally any
  preferential treatment applicable as a result of the EC Party or any
  Pacific State being party to a free trade agreement with third parties
  on the date of signature of this Agreement.

  5. For the purposes of this Article, "free trade agreement"
  means an agreement substantially liberalising trade and providing for
  the absence or elimination of substantially all discrimination between
  or among parties thereto through the elimination of existing
  discriminatory measures and/or the prohibition of new or more
  discriminatory measures, either at the entry into force of that
  agreement or on the basis of a reasonable time frame.

  6. For the purposes of this Article, "major trading economy"
  means any developed country, or any country accounting for a share of
  world merchandise exports above 1 percent in the year before the entry
  into force of the free trade agreement referred to in paragraph 2, or
  any group of countries acting individually, collectively or through a
  free trade agreement accounting collectively for a share of world
  merchandise exports above 1,5 percent in the year before the entry
  into force of the free trade agreement referred to in paragraph 2 [2].</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Special Provisions On Administrative Cooperation In Customs Matters" article_identifier="35405">1. The Parties agree that administrative cooperation is essential for
  the implementation and the control of the preferential treatment
  granted under this Part and underline their commitment to combat
  irregularities and fraud in customs and related matters.

  2. Where a Party or a Pacific State as the case may be has made a
  finding, on the basis of objective information, of a failure to
  provide administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities or fraud,
  the Party or Pacific State concerned may temporarily suspend the
  relevant preferential treatment of the product(s) concerned in
  accordance with this Article.

  3. For the purpose of this Article a failure to provide administrative
  cooperation shall mean, inter alia:

  (a) a repeated failure to respect the obligations to verify the
  originating status of the product(s) concerned;

  (b) a repeated refusal or undue delay in carrying out and/or
  communicating the results of subsequent verification of the proof of
  origin;

  (c) a repeated refusal or undue delay in obtaining authorisation to
  conduct administrative cooperation missions to verify the authenticity
  of documents or accuracy of information relevant to the granting of
  the preferential treatment in question.

  For the purpose of this Article, a finding of irregularities or fraud
  may be made, inter alia, where there is a rapid increase, without
  satisfactory explanation, in imports of goods exceeding the usual
  level of production and the export capacity of the other Party or
  Pacific State as the case may be, which is linked to objective
  information concerning irregularities or fraud.

  4. The application of a temporary suspension pursuant to paragraph 2
  shall be subject to the following conditions:

  (a) The Party or Pacific State as the case may be which has made a
  finding, on the basis of objective information, of a failure to
  provide administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities or fraud
  shall without undue delay notify the Trade Committee of its finding
  together with the objective information and enter into consultations
  within the Trade Committee, on the basis of all relevant information
  and objective findings, with a view to reaching a solution acceptable
  to both the EC Party and the Pacific States or State as the case may
  be.

  (b) Where the Parties have entered into consultations within the Trade
  Committee as above and have failed to agree on an acceptable solution
  within three months following the notification, the Party or Pacific
  State concerned may temporarily suspend the relevant preferential
  treatment of the product(s) concerned. A temporary suspension shall be
  notified to the Trade Committee without undue delay.

  (c) Temporary suspensions under this Article shall be limited to that
  necessary to protect the financial interests of the Party or Pacific
  State concerned. They shall not exceed a period of six months, which
  may be renewed. Temporary suspensions shall be notified immediately
  after their adoption to the affected Party or Pacific State and the
  Trade Committee. They shall be subject to periodic consultations
  within the Trade Committee in particular with a view to their
  termination as soon as the conditions for their application are no
  longer given.

  5. At the same time as the notification to the Trade Committee under
  paragraph 4(a) of this Article, the Party or Pacific State concerned
  should publish a notice to importers in its official gazette or
  journal. The notice to importers should indicate for the product
  concerned and for the specific origin concerned that there is a
  finding, on the basis of objective information, of a failure to
  provide administrative cooperation and/or of irregularities or fraud.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Management Of Administrative Errors" article_identifier="35406">The Parties recognise each others’ rights to correct errors during the
  implementation of this Agreement. Where errors are identified, either
  Party may request the Trade Committee to examine the possibilities of
  adopting appropriate measures with a view to resolving the situation.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade Defence Instruments" chapter_identifier="4101">
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Anti-Dumping And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="35407">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall prevent the EC Party or Pacific States, both WTO
  members and non-WTO members, whether individually or collectively,
  from adopting anti-dumping or countervailing measures in accordance
  with the relevant WTO agreements. For the purpose of this Article,
  origin shall be determined in accordance with the non-preferential
  rules of origin of the Parties.

  2. The EC Party may not impose definitive anti-dumping or
  countervailing duties in respect of products imported from Pacific
  States before considering the possibility of constructive remedies
  foreseen in the relevant WTO agreements, in accordance with EC law. In
  that respect, the EC Party shall provide appropriate assistance to the
  exporters from the Pacific States which are proposing such
  constructive remedies.

  3. Where an anti-dumping or countervailing measure has been imposed on
  behalf of two or more Pacific States by a regional or sub-regional
  authority, there shall be one single forum of judicial review,
  including the stage of appeals.

  4. Where anti-dumping or countervailing measures can be imposed on a
  regional or sub-regional basis and on a national basis the Parties or
  Pacific States as the case may be shall ensure that such measures are
  not applied simultaneously in respect of the same product by regional
  or sub-regional authorities on the one hand, and national authorities
  on the other.

  5. The EC Party shall notify the exporting Pacific States of the
  receipt of a properly documented complaint before initiating any
  investigation.

  6. The provisions of this Article shall be applicable to all
  investigations initiated after this Agreement enters into force.

  7. The provisions of this Article shall not be subject to the Dispute
  Settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Multilateral Safeguards" article_identifier="35408">1. Subject to the provisions of this Article, nothing in this
  Agreement shall prevent the Pacific States and the EC Party from
  adopting measures in accordance with Article XIX of the GATT 1994, the
  Agreement on Safeguards, and Article 5 of the Agreement on
  Agriculture. For the purpose of this Article, origin shall be
  determined in accordance with the non-preferential rules of origin of
  the Parties.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the EC Party may, in the light of the
  overall development objectives of this Agreement and the small size of
  the economies of the Pacific States, exclude imports from any Pacific
  State from any measures taken pursuant to Article XIX of the GATT
  1994, the WTO Agreement on Safeguards and Article 5 of the Agreement
  on Agriculture.

  3. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall apply for a period of five
  years, beginning with the date of entry into force of the Agreement.
  Not later than 120 days before the end of this period, the Parties
  shall review the operation of those provisions in the light of the
  development needs of the Pacific States, with a view to determining
  whether to extend their application for a further period.

  4. The provisions of paragraph 1 shall not be subject to the Dispute
  Settlement provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Bilateral Safeguards" article_identifier="35409">1. Notwithstanding Article 20, after having examined alternative
  solutions, the EC Party or a Pacific State may apply safeguard
  measures of limited duration which derogate from the provisions of
  Articles 11 and 12, under the conditions and in accordance with the
  procedures laid down in this Article.

  2. Safeguard measures referred to in paragraph 1 may be taken where a
  product originating in the EC Party or a Pacific State is being
  imported into the territory of the EC Party or a Pacific State in such
  increased quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten
  to cause:

  (a) serious injury to the domestic industry producing like or directly
  competitive products in the territory of the importing Parties or
  Pacific States, or

  (b) disturbances in a sector or industry of the economy, whether of an
  economic or social nature, or difficulties which could bring about
  serious deterioration in the economic situation of the importing
  Parties or Pacific States, or

  (c) disturbances in the markets of agricultural like or directly
  competitive products [3] or mechanisms regulating those markets.

  3. Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall not exceed
  what is necessary to remedy or prevent the serious injury or
  disturbances, as defined in paragraphs 2 and 5(b). Those safeguard
  measures of the importing Parties or Pacific States may only consist
  of one or more of the following:

  (a) suspension of the further reduction of the rate of import duty for
  the product concerned, as provided for under this Agreement;

  (b) increase in the customs duty on the product concerned up to a
  level which does not exceed the customs duty applied to imports
  originating in other WTO Members, and

  (c) introduction of tariff quotas on the product concerned.

  4. Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 above, where any product
  originating in one or more Pacific State(s) is being imported in such
  increased quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten
  to cause one of the situations referred to under subparagraphs 2(a),
  (b) and (c) above to one or several of the EC Party's Outermost
  Regions, the EC Party may take surveillance or safeguard measures
  limited to the region or regions concerned in accordance with the
  procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  5. (a) Without prejudice to paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 above, where any
  product originating in the EC Party is being imported in such
  increased quantities and under such conditions as to cause or threaten
  to cause one of the situations referred to under subparagraphs 2(a),
  (b) and (c) above to a Pacific State, the Pacific State concerned may
  take surveillance or safeguard measures limited to its territory in
  accordance with the procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9.

  (b) A Pacific State may take safeguard measures where a product
  originating in the EC Party as a result of the reduction of duties is
  being imported into its territory in such increased quantities and
  under such conditions as to cause or threaten to cause disturbances to
  an infant industry producing like or directly competitive products.
  These measures shall be taken in order to promote development of
  productive and sustainable industries with a view to raising the
  general standard of living of the people. This provision is only
  applicable for a period of twenty years from the date of entry into
  force of this Agreement. Measures must be taken in accordance with the
  procedures laid down in paragraphs 6 to 9 except that the initial
  duration of measures may be of seven years in the case of non-Least
  Developed Countries (non-LDCs) with a joint review for a possible
  extension for further three years and in the case of Small Islands
  States and Pacific LDC States for twelve years with joint review for a
  possible extension for a further three years. No Pacific State shall,
  at any time, raise tariffs under this provision on goods originating
  in the EC Party on more than 3 per cent of tariff lines or on more
  than 15 per cent of the total value of goods originating in the EC
  Party calculated as the average value of imports over the last three
  years.

  6. (a) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall only be
  maintained for such a time as may be necessary to prevent or remedy
  serious injury or disturbances as defined in paragraphs 2, 4 and 5
  above.

  (b) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article shall not be
  applied for a period exceeding two years. In exceptional
  circumstances, such measures may be extended for a further period of
  no more than two years. Where a Pacific State applies a safeguard
  measure, or where the EC Party applies a measure limited to the
  territory of one or more of its outermost regions, such measures may
  however be applied for a period not exceeding four years and, in
  exceptional circumstances, extended for a further period of four
  years.

  (c) Safeguard measures referred to in this Article that exceed one
  year shall contain clear elements progressively leading to their
  elimination at the end of the set period, at the latest.

  (d) No safeguard measure referred to in this Article shall be applied
  to the import of a product that has previously been subject to such a
  measure, for a period of at least one year from the expiry of the
  measure.

  7. For the implementation of the above paragraphs, the following
  provisions shall apply:

  (a) Where the EC Party or a Pacific State takes the view that one of
  the circumstances set out in paragraphs 2, 4 and/or 5 exists, it shall
  immediately refer the matter to the Trade Committee for examination.

  (b) The Trade Committee may make any recommendation needed to remedy
  the circumstances which have arisen. If no recommendation has been
  made by the Trade Committee aimed at remedying the circumstances, or
  no other satisfactory solution has been reached within 30 days of the
  matter being referred to the Trade Committee, the importing EC Party
  or the Pacific State may adopt the appropriate measures to remedy the
  circumstances in accordance with this Article.

  (c) Before taking any measure provided for in this Article or, in the
  cases to which paragraph 8 of this Article applies, as soon as
  possible, the EC Party or the Pacific State concerned shall supply the
  Trade Committee with all relevant information required for a thorough
  examination of the situation, with a view to seeking a solution
  acceptable to the parties concerned.

  (d) In the selection of safeguard measures pursuant to this Article,
  priority must be given to those which least disturb the operation of
  this Agreement.

  (e) Any safeguard measure taken pursuant to this Article shall be
  notified immediately to the Trade Committee and shall be the subject
  of periodic consultations within that body, particularly with a view
  to establishing a timetable for their abolition as soon as
  circumstances permit.

  8. Where exceptional circumstances require immediate action, the
  importing EC Party or Pacific State concerned may take the measures
  provided for in paragraph 3, 4 and/or 5 on a provisional basis without
  complying with the requirements of paragraph 7. Such action may be
  taken for a maximum period of 180 days where measures are taken by the
  EC Party and 200 days where measures are taken by the Pacific State,
  or where measures taken by the EC Party are limited to the territory
  of one or more of its outermost regions. The duration of any such
  provisional measure shall be counted as a part of the initial period
  and any extension referred to in paragraph 6. In the taking of such
  provisional measures, the interest of the Parties, and especially of
  Small Island States, shall be taken into account. The importing Party
  or Pacific State as the case may be shall inform the other party
  concerned and it shall immediately refer the matter to the Trade
  Committee for examination.

  9. If an importing Party or Pacific State as the case may be subjects
  imports of a product to an administrative procedure having as its
  purpose the rapid provision of information on the trend of trade flows
  liable to give rise to the problems referred to in this Article, it
  shall inform the Trade Committee without delay.

  10. Safeguard measures adopted under the provisions of this Article
  shall not be subject to WTO Dispute Settlement provisions.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Non-Tariff Measures" chapter_identifier="4102">
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Prohibition Of Quantitative Restrictions" article_identifier="35410">Unless otherwise specified in this Agreement, all prohibitions or
  restrictions applying to the import or export of goods between the EC
  Party and the Pacific States, other than customs duties and taxes, and
  fees and other charges, whether made effective through quotas, import
  or export licenses or other measures, shall be eliminated upon the
  entry into force of this Agreement. No such new measures shall be
  introduced. The provisions of this Article shall be without prejudice
  to the provisions of Chapter 2 of Part II.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="National Treatment On Internal Taxation And Regulation" article_identifier="35411">1. Imported products originating in the other Party shall not be
  subject, either directly or indirectly, to internal taxes or other
  internal charges of any kind in excess of those applied, directly or
  indirectly, to like national products. Moreover, the Parties shall not
  otherwise apply internal taxes or other internal charges so as to
  afford protection to national production.

  2. Imported products originating in the other Party shall be accorded
  treatment no less favourable than that accorded to like national
  products in respect of all laws, regulations and requirements
  affecting their internal sale, offering for sale, purchase,
  transportation, distribution or use. The provisions of this paragraph
  shall not prevent the application of differential internal
  transportation charges which are based exclusively on the economic
  operation of the means of transport and not on the nationality of the
  product.

  3. No Party shall establish or maintain any internal quantitative
  regulation relating to the mixture, processing or use of products in
  specified amounts or proportions which requires, directly or
  indirectly, that any specified amount or proportion of any product
  which is the subject of the regulation must be supplied from domestic
  sources. Moreover, no Party or Pacific State shall otherwise apply
  internal quantitative regulations so as to afford protection to
  national production.

  4. The provisions of this Article shall not prevent the payment of
  subsidies or the granting of tax incentives for the purpose of
  developing industries to national producers, including payments to
  national producers derived from the proceeds of internal taxes or
  charges applied consistently with the provisions of this Article and
  subsidies implemented through governmental purchases of national
  products.

  5. The provisions of this Article shall not apply to laws,
  regulations, procedures or practices governing public procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Agricultural Export Subsidies" article_identifier="35412">1. With regard to any product as defined in paragraph 3, for which the
  Pacific States have committed to the elimination of customs duties,
  the EC Party undertakes to phase out existing subsidies granted upon
  the exportation of that product to the territories of the Pacific
  States.

  2. Parties will consult each other no later than 18 December 2007 with
  a view to determining the modalities of the elimination of existing
  subsidies mentioned under paragraph 1.

  3. This Article applies to products as covered by Annex 1 of the WTO
  Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs And Trade Facilitation" chapter_identifier="4103">
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Objectives" article_identifier="35413">The objectives of this Chapter are to:

  (a) assist the integration of the Pacific States into the
  international economy, and in particular facilitate trade between the
  Parties;

  (b) reinforce cooperation on customs issues with a view to ensuring
  that the relevant legislation and procedures, as well as the
  administrative capacity of the relevant administrations, enable the
  effective and efficient administration of customs, and facilitate
  trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Relationship With Existing Programmes And Assistance" article_identifier="35414">The Parties shall endeavour to coordinate and integrate their
  cooperation on trade facilitation and trade promotion with the work of
  other actors, regional organisations, and national bodies and
  organisations with the objective of avoiding unnecessary duplication
  of existing programmes and maximising the benefits from the resources
  devoted to trade facilitation, in particular, where appropriate,
  through:

  (a) sharing of information between the Parties, actors, regional and
  international organisations and their members;

  (b) utilisation of the expertise and resources of other regional or
  international organisations;

  (c) cooperation between the Parties with and within other regional and
  international organisations;

  (d) cooperation with other regional and international organisations in
  the development, establishment and implementation of international
  agreements on harmonised standards and procedures, or the
  establishment of new regional organisations;

  (e) participation of other regional organisations, and their members,
  in the trade facilitation and trade promotion programme; and

  (f) any other form of cooperation, coordination or integration of
  activities the Parties decide is appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Customs And Administrative Cooperation" article_identifier="35415">1. The Parties agree to:

  (a) exchange information concerning customs legislation and
  procedures;

  (b) develop joint initiatives in mutually agreed areas;

  (c) establish, wherever possible, common positions on customs issues
  in international fora;

  (d) promote coordination between all related agencies, both internally
  and across borders.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the administrations of the Parties
  shall provide mutual administrative assistance in customs matters in
  accordance with the provisions of Protocol I.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Customs Procedures" article_identifier="35416">1. The EC Party and the Pacific States agree that their respective
  customs legislation, provisions and procedures shall draw upon the
  international instruments and standards applicable in the field of
  customs and trade, including the substantive elements of the revised
  Kyoto Convention on the Simplification and Harmonization of Customs
  Procedures, the WCO Framework of Standards to Secure and Facilitate
  Global Trade, the WCO data set and the Convention on the Harmonized
  Commodity Description and Coding System.

  2. The EC Party and the Pacific States agree that their respective
  trade and customs legislation, provisions and procedures shall be
  based upon:

  (a) the need to protect and facilitate legitimate trade through
  effective enforcement of and compliance with legislative requirements;

  (b) the need to avoid unnecessary or discriminatory burdens on
  economic operators, to provide safeguards against fraud, to provide
  simplified procedures for compliant traders and to encourage
  compliance, as well as the need to avoid applying excessive penalties
  for minor breaches of customs regulations or procedural requirements;

  (c) the application of modern customs techniques, including risk
  assessment, simplified procedures for entry and release of goods, post
  release controls, and company audit methods;

  (d) the progressive development of systems, including those based upon
  Information Technology, to facilitate the electronic exchange of data
  between traders, customs administrations and other related agencies;

  (e) the need to facilitate transit movements;

  (f) the need to avoid any requirement for the mandatory use of customs
  brokers. Transparent, non-discriminatory and proportionate rules in
  respect of the licensing of customs brokers shall apply;

  (g) the need to avoid, except in exceptional circumstances, any
  requirements for the mandatory use of pre-shipment inspections, as
  defined by the WTO Agreement on Pre-Shipment Inspections, or their
  equivalent.

  3. The implementation of paragraph 1 and paragraph 2 (c) and (d) of
  this Article by Small Island States shall be done as appropriate,
  taking into account the small size and capacity of their
  administrations.

  4. The Parties agree that:

  (a) a single administrative document or electronic equivalent should
  be applied in the EC Party and the Pacific States respectively. The
  Pacific States will continue efforts to this end, with a view to
  implementation at an early stage during the life of this Agreement. A
  joint review of the situation will be carried out five years after the
  entry into force of the Agreement;

  (b) a system of binding rulings on customs matters should be provided,
  notably on tariff classification and rules of origin, in accordance
  with rules laid down in their respective legislation.

  5. In order to improve working methods, as well as to ensure
  non-discrimination, transparency, efficiency, integrity and
  accountability of operations, the Parties or the Pacific States, as
  the case may be, shall:

  (a) provide effective, prompt and non-discriminatory procedures
  enabling the right of appeal against customs and other agency
  administrative actions, rulings and decisions affecting imports,
  exports or goods in transit. Procedures for appeal shall be easily
  accessible, including to small or medium enterprises and any costs
  shall be reasonable and commensurate with costs in providing for
  appeals;

  (b) ensure that measures are put in place in order to achieve high
  standards of integrity in the customs service, in line with the
  relevant international conventions and instruments in this field.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Relations Of Customs With The Business Community" article_identifier="35417">The EC Party and the Pacific States agree:

  (a) to foster cooperation between operators and relevant
  administrations;

  (b) to ensure that all legislation, procedures and fees and charges
  are made publicly available, wherever possible through electronic
  means, together, where appropriate and possible, with the
  justification for them;

  (c) to make publicly available relevant notices of an administrative
  nature, including agency requirements and entry procedures, hours of
  operation and operating procedures for customs offices at ports and
  border crossing points, and points of contact for information
  enquiries;

  (d) on the need, wherever possible, for timely and regular
  consultation with the business community on legislative proposals and
  procedures related to customs and trade issues. To this end,
  appropriate mechanisms for regular consultations between
  administrations and the business community, shall be established by
  each Party;

  (e) that new or amended legislation and procedures and their entry
  into force should be introduced in a way that provides traders with
  sufficient information in order to become well prepared for complying
  with them;

  (f) to work to ensure that their respective customs and related
  requirements and procedures continue to meet the needs of the trading
  community, follow best practices, and remain as little
  trade-restrictive as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="35418">1. The Parties agree to apply Article VII of the GATT 1994 and the
  Agreement on the Implementation of Article VII of the GATT 1994 to
  trade in goods covered by Part II of this Agreement.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the Pacific States which are not
  members of the WTO on the date of entry into force of this Agreement
  shall apply rules on customs valuation consistently with Article VII
  of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on the Implementation of Article
  VII of the GATT 1994 to trade in goods covered by Part II of this
  Agreement within five years of this Agreement coming into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Harmonisation Of Customs Standards At Regional Level" article_identifier="35419">1. The Parties shall promote regional integration in the field of
  customs and shall strive to develop common legislation, procedures and
  requirements, in line with the relevant international standards.

  2. A regular follow-up of the implementation of the provisions of this
  Article shall be carried out.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Review Clause" article_identifier="35420">The Parties agree to review the implementation of this Chapter no
  later than three years after the entry into force of this Agreement,
  with a view to determining further steps to be taken.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Technical Barriers To Trade And Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="4104">
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Scope And Definitions" article_identifier="35421">1. The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to technical
  regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures
  (hereinafter referred to as "TBT measures"), as defined in
  the WTO Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade (hereinafter referred
  to as "the TBT Agreement"), and to Sanitary and
  Phytosanitary Measures (hereinafter referred to as "SPS
  measures"), as defined in the WTO Agreement on the Application of
  Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures (hereinafter referred to as
  "the SPS Agreement"), in so far as they affect trade covered
  by Part II of this Agreement.

  2. For the purposes of this Chapter the definitions used by the TBT
  Agreement and the SPS Agreement shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Objectives" article_identifier="35422">1. The Parties agree to cooperate in order to facilitate and increase
  trade in goods between them, by identifying, preventing and
  eliminating obstacles to trade arising from TBT and SPS measures.

  2. The Parties agree to cooperate to strengthen regional trade in
  Pacific regional integration and cooperation on matters concerning TBT
  and SPS measures.

  3. The Parties shall cooperate to facilitate compliance with SPS
  measures applying to exports, whilst safeguarding human, animal and
  plant safety and health, in particular through building the capacity
  of the public and private sectors in the Pacific States and assisting
  the Pacific States to improve their regulatory frameworks and related
  institutions.

  4. The Parties shall cooperate with a view to reinforcing regional
  integration and promoting the capacity of private and public sectors
  to comply with TBT and SPS measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Priority Products" article_identifier="35423">To better achieve the objectives of this Chapter, the Parties agree to
  define a list of priority products for export from the Pacific States
  to the EC Party and a list of priority products for trade among the
  Pacific States. These lists shall be contained in Annex III. A and
  III. B respectively, which shall be reviewed and may be modified by a
  decision of the Trade Committee as and when appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="35424">1. The Parties agree to apply the SPS and TBT agreements to trade in
  goods covered by Part II of this Agreement.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the SPS and TBT-related measures of
  the Pacific States that are not WTO members on the date of entry into
  force of this Agreement shall be applied in accordance with the
  requirements of the SPS and TBT agreements.

  3. The EC Party will take full account of the capacity constraints in
  the short-term of non-WTO members to comply with the provisions of
  this Article.

  4. Where necessary and possible, the Parties agree that the provisions
  concerning special and differential treatment in the WTO SPS and TBT
  agreements are applicable to the trade between the Parties to this
  Agreement, including Pacific States that are not WTO members.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Equivalence" article_identifier="35425">1. The Parties recognise the importance of making operational the
  provisions of Article 4 of the SPS Agreement and enabling the Pacific
  States to have the equivalence of their SPS measures recognised by
  developed importing countries.

  2. The Parties reaffirm the Decision on the implementation of Article
  4 of the Agreement on the Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary
  Measures of 23 July 2004 of the WTO Committee on Sanitary and
  Phytosanitary Measures. The EC Party agrees to give due consideration
  to reasonable requests from one or more of the Pacific States to
  examine the equivalence of their SPS measures in areas of particular
  export interest to the Pacific States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Competent Authorities" article_identifier="35426">1. The respective SPS authorities of the Parties shall be the
  competent authorities in the Pacific States and in the EC Party for
  the implementation of the measures referred to in this Chapter.

  2. The Parties shall, in accordance with this Agreement, inform each
  other of their respective competent SPS authorities and of any changes
  thereto.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Resolution Of Sps And Tbt Problems" article_identifier="35427">1. The Parties shall provide the necessary information to facilitate
  access to information on TBT-related and SPS measures and their
  implementation and enforcement, and future developments in these
  areas, and to facilitate the avoidance and/or resolution of any
  difficulties that might arise between the EC Party and the Pacific
  States.

  2. The Parties shall inform and consult each other as early as
  possible with a view to finding a mutually agreed solution when a TBT
  or SPS measure results in a barrier to trade.

  3. Nothing in this Chapter shall impair the rights of the Parties
  under other international agreements, including the right to resort to
  the good offices or dispute settlement mechanisms of international
  organisations or those established under any international agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Transparency And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="35428">1. The Parties confirm their commitments to implement the transparency
  provisions set out in the SPS Agreement and the TBT Agreement to
  facilitate access to relevant information on TBT or SPS measures.

  2. The EC Party agrees to cooperate with initiatives of the Pacific
  States to establish a mechanism to permit efficient notifications of
  TBT and SPS measures at a regional level.

  3. The Parties shall endeavour to inform each other at an early stage
  of proposals to modify or introduce TBT or SPS measures that may
  affect trade between the Parties, where appropriate making use of
  existing systems.

  4. In particular with regard to TBT measures, the Parties agree, inter
  alia, to:

  (a) intensify their collaboration, with a view to facilitating access
  to their respective markets, by increasing the mutual knowledge and
  understanding of their respective systems in the field of technical
  regulations, standards, metrology, accreditation and conformity
  assessment;

  (b) exchange information, identify and implement appropriate
  mechanisms for particular issues or sectors, e.g., alignment to
  international standards and reliance on the supplier's declaration of
  conformity;

  (c) develop common views and approaches on technical regulatory
  practices, including transparency, consultation, proportionality, the
  use of international standards, conformity assessment, and market
  surveillance.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Implementation" article_identifier="35429">The Parties agree that the Trade Committee shall be competent under
  this Chapter to:

  (a) monitor and review its implementation;

  (b) provide coordination and consultation on TBT and SPS issues;

  (c) identify and review priority sectors and products and the
  resulting priority areas for cooperation; and

  (d) make recommendations for modifications to this Chapter.

  Exceptions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="General Exception Clause" article_identifier="35430">Subject to the requirement that such measures are not applied in a
  manner which would constitute a means of arbitrary or unjustifiable
  discrimination between the Parties where like conditions prevail, or a
  disguised restriction on trade in goods, services or establishment,
  nothing in this Agreement shall be construed to prevent the adoption
  or enforcement by the EC Party or Pacific States of measures which:

  (a) are necessary to protect public security and public morals or to
  maintain public order;

  (b) are necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health;

  (c) are necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations not
  inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement, including those
  relating to:

  (i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or to deal
  with the effects of a default on contracts;

  (ii) the protection of the privacy of individuals in relation to the
  processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of
  confidentiality of individual records and accounts;

  (iii) safety;

  (iv) customs enforcement; or

  (v) protection of intellectual property rights;

  (d) relate to the importation or exportation of gold or silver;

  (e) are necessary for the protection of national treasures of
  artistic, historic or archaeological value;

  (f) relate to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources if
  such measures are made effective in conjunction with restrictions on
  domestic production or consumption of goods, domestic supply or
  consumption of services and on domestic investors;

  (g) relate to the products of prison labour; or

  (h) are inconsistent with Article 23, provided that the difference in
  treatment is aimed at ensuring the effective or equitable imposition
  or collection of direct taxes in respect of economic activities,
  investors or service suppliers of the EC Party or a Pacific State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="35431">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed:

  (a) to require the EC Party or a Pacific State to furnish any
  information the disclosure of which it considers contrary to its
  essential security interests;

  (b) to prevent the EC Party or a Pacific State from taking any action
  which it considers necessary for the protection of its essential
  security interests:

  (i) relating to fissionable and fusionable materials or the materials
  from which they are derived;

  (ii) relating to economic activities carried out directly or
  indirectly for the purpose of supplying or provisioning a military
  establishment;

  (iii) connected with the production of or trade in arms, munitions and
  war materials;

  (iv) relating to government procurement indispensable for national
  security or for national defence purposes; or

  (v) taken in time of war or other emergency in international
  relations; or

  (c) to prevent the EC Party or a Pacific State from taking any action
  in order to carry out obligations it has accepted for the purpose of
  maintaining international peace and security.

  2. The Trade Committee shall be informed to the fullest extent
  possible of measures taken under paragraphs 1(b) and (c) and of their
  termination.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Taxation" article_identifier="35432">1. Nothing in this Agreement or in any arrangement adopted under this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the EC Party or a Pacific
  State from distinguishing, in the application of the relevant
  provisions of their fiscal legislation, between taxpayers who are not
  in the same situation, in particular with regard to their place of
  residence or with regard to the place where their capital is invested.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement or in any arrangement adopted under this
  Agreement shall be construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement of
  any measure aimed at preventing the avoidance or evasion of taxes
  pursuant to the tax provisions of agreements to avoid double taxation
  or other tax arrangements or domestic fiscal legislation.

  3. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations
  of the EC Party or a Pacific State under any tax convention. In the
  event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and any such
  convention, that convention shall prevail to the extent of the
  inconsistency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Balance Of Payments Difficulties" article_identifier="35433">1. Where a Pacific State or the EC Party is in serious balance of
  payments and external financial difficulties, or under threat thereof,
  and in particular where a Party or Pacific State determines that:

  (a) there is a serious decline or an imminent threat of serious
  decline in its monetary reserves, or in the case of a Pacific State
  with very low monetary reserves, its monetary reserves have failed to
  achieve a reasonable rate of increase;

  (b) there is a serious decline in its fiscal position due to a decline
  in government revenue from the collection of customs duties; or

  (c) there has been a natural disaster that has or is likely to cause a
  serious decline in government revenue or private sector revenue,

  that Party or Pacific State may impose or increase tariffs for the
  minimum period necessary and to the minimum extent necessary to arrest
  or prevent the serious decline in reserves, or to enable reserves to
  increase at a reasonable rate, or to arrest or prevent a serious
  decline in the fiscal position.

  2. The Pacific States and the EC Party shall endeavour to avoid the
  application of the restrictive measures referred to in paragraph 1.

  3. Parties or Pacific States applying restrictions under this Article
  may determine the incidence of the restrictions on imports of
  different products or classes of products in such a way as to give
  priority to the importation of those products which are more
  essential.

  4. Any restrictive measure adopted or maintained under this Article
  shall be consistent with any WTO and IMF obligations of the Party or
  Pacific State adopting or maintaining the restrictive measure. The
  Party or Pacific State adopting and maintaining the restrictive
  measure shall take all reasonable steps to ensure that the measure
  does not disproportionately impact on imports covered by this
  Agreement from another Party.

  5. Any restricted measure adopted or maintained under this Article
  shall be non-discriminatory, of limited duration, shall not go beyond
  what is necessary to remedy the balance of payments and external
  financial situation and shall:

  (a) avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial or economic interests
  of any other Party or Pacific State;

  (b) not prevent unreasonably the importing of any goods in minimum
  commercial quantities, the exclusion of which would impair regular
  channels of trade; and

  (c) not prevent the importing of commercial samples or prevent
  compliance with patent, trade mark, copyright, or similar procedures.

  6. Any Pacific State or the EC Party maintaining or having adopted
  restrictive measures, or any changes thereto, shall promptly notify
  them to the Party or Pacific States from which the affected imports
  originate and present, as soon as possible, a time schedule for their
  removal.

  7. Consultation shall be held promptly between the Party or Pacific
  State adopting and maintaining the restrictive measure and the Party
  or Pacific States from which the affected imports originate. Such
  consultations shall assess the balance of payments situation of the
  concerned Pacific State or the EC Party and the restrictions adopted
  or maintained under this Article, taking into account, inter alia,
  such factors as:

  (a) the nature and extent of the balance of payments and the external
  financial difficulties;

  (b) the external economic and trading environment;

  (c) alternative corrective measures which may be available.

  The consultations shall address the compliance of any restrictive
  measures with paragraphs 3 and 4. All findings of statistical and
  other facts presented by the International Monetary Fund relating to
  foreign exchange, monetary reserves and balance of payments shall be
  accepted and conclusions shall be based on the assessment by the Fund
  of the balance of payments and the external financial situation of the
  Pacific State concerned or the EC Party.

  8. If there is a persistent and widespread application of restrictions
  under this Article, indicating the existence of a general
  disequilibrium which is restricting international trade, the EC Party
  and the Pacific States shall review the Agreement to consider whether
  other measures might be taken to remove the underlying causes of the
  disequilibrium.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Food Security" article_identifier="35434">1. The Parties acknowledge that the removal of barriers to trade
  between the Parties, as envisaged in this Agreement, may pose
  significant challenges to producers in the agricultural and food
  sectors of a Party or a Pacific State, and agree to consult with each
  other on these issues.

  2. Where compliance with the provisions of this Agreement leads to
  problems with the availability of, or access to, foodstuffs or other
  products essential to ensure food security of a Party or Pacific State
  and where this situation gives rise or is likely to give rise to major
  difficulties for such a Party or Pacific State, that Party or Pacific
  State may take appropriate measures in accordance with the procedures
  laid down in Article 21, paragraph 2(c).

  DISPUTE AVOIDANCE AND SETTLEMENT</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Objective And Scope" chapter_identifier="4105">
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Objective" article_identifier="35435">The objective of this Part is to avoid and settle any dispute between
  the EC Party and the Pacific States with a view to arriving at a
  mutually agreed solution.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Scope" article_identifier="35436">1. This Part shall apply to any dispute concerning the interpretation
  and application of this Agreement except where otherwise expressly
  provided for in this Agreement.

  2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the procedure set out in Article 98 of
  the Cotonou Agreement shall be applicable in the event of a dispute
  concerning development finance cooperation as provided for by the
  Cotonou Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Consultations And Mediation" chapter_identifier="4106">
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Consultations" article_identifier="35437">1. The Parties shall endeavour to resolve any dispute referred to in
  Article 48 by entering into consultations in good faith with the aim
  of reaching an agreed solution.

  2. A Party shall seek consultations by means of a written request to
  the other Party, copied to the Trade Committee, identifying the
  measure at issue and the provisions of the Agreement that it considers
  the measure not to be in conformity with.

  3. Consultations shall be held within 40 days of the date of the
  submission of the request. The consultations shall be deemed concluded
  within 60 days of the date of the submission of the request, unless
  both Parties to the dispute agree to continue consultations. All
  information disclosed during the consultations shall remain
  confidential.

  4. Consultations on matters of urgency, including those regarding
  perishable or seasonal goods shall be held within 15 days of the date
  of the submission of the request, and shall be deemed concluded within
  30 days of the date of the submission of the request.

  5. If consultations are not held within the timeframes laid down in
  this Article, or if consultations have been concluded and no agreement
  has been reached on a mutually agreed solution, the complaining Party
  may request the establishment of an arbitration panel in accordance
  with Article 51.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Mediation" article_identifier="35438">1. If consultations fail to produce a mutually agreed solution, the
  Parties to the dispute may, by agreement, seek recourse to a mediator.
  Unless the Parties to the dispute agree otherwise, the terms of
  reference for the mediation shall be the matter referred to in the
  request for consultations.

  2. Unless the Parties to the dispute agree on a mediator within ten
  days of the date of the agreement to request mediation, the presiding
  co-chair of the Trade Committee, or his or her delegate, shall select
  by lot a mediator from the pool of individuals who are on the list
  referred to in Article 65 and are not nationals of either Party to the
  dispute. The selection shall be made within 20 days of the date of the
  submission of agreement to request mediation and in the presence of a
  representative of each Party to the dispute. The mediator will convene
  a meeting with the Parties to the dispute no later than 30 days after
  being selected. The mediator shall receive the submissions of each
  Party to the dispute no later than 15 days before the meeting and
  notify an opinion no later than 45 days after having been selected.

  3. The mediator's opinion may include a recommendation on how to
  resolve the dispute consistent with the provisions of this Agreement.
  The mediator's opinion is non-binding.

  4. The Parties to the dispute may agree to amend the time limits
  referred to in paragraph 2. The mediator may also decide to amend
  these time limits upon request of any of the Parties to the dispute or
  on his own initiative, given the particular difficulties experienced
  by the Party concerned or the complexities of the case.

  5. The proceedings involving mediation, in particular all information
  disclosed and positions taken by the Parties to the dispute during
  these proceedings shall remain confidential.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Dispute Settlement Procedures" chapter_identifier="4107">
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Initiation Of The Arbitration Procedure" article_identifier="35439">1. Where the Parties to the dispute have failed to resolve the dispute
  by recourse to consultations as provided for in Article 49, and, if
  applicable, by recourse to mediation as provided for in Article 50,
  the complaining Party may request the establishment of an arbitration
  panel.

  2. The request for the establishment of an arbitration panel shall be
  made in writing to the Party complained against and the Trade
  Committee. The complaining Party or Pacific State shall identify in
  its request the specific measures at issue, and it shall explain how
  such measures constitute a breach of the provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Establishment Of The Arbitration Panel" article_identifier="35440">1. An arbitration panel shall be composed of three arbitrators.

  2. Within ten days of the date of the submission of the request for
  the establishment of an arbitration panel to the Trade Committee, the
  Parties to the dispute shall consult each other in order to reach an
  agreement on the composition of the arbitration panel.

  3. In the event that the Parties to the dispute are unable to agree on
  its composition within the time frame laid down in paragraph 2, either
  Party may request the presiding co-chair of the Trade Committee, or
  her or his delegate, to select all three members by lot from the list
  established under Article 65, one among the individuals proposed by
  the complaining Party or Pacific State, one among the individuals
  proposed by the Party or Pacific State complained against and one
  among the individuals selected by the Parties to act as chairperson.
  Where the Parties agree on one or more of the members of the
  arbitration panel, any remaining members shall be selected by the same
  procedure.

  4. The presiding co-chair of the Trade Committee, or her or his
  delegate, shall select the arbitrators within five days of the request
  referred to in paragraph 3 by either Party and in the presence of a
  representative of each Party.

  5. The date of establishment of the arbitration panel shall be the
  date on which the three arbitrators are selected.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Interim Panel Report" article_identifier="35441">The arbitration panel shall notify to the Parties an interim report
  containing both the descriptive section and its findings and
  conclusions, as a general rule, not later than 120 days from the date
  of establishment of the arbitration panel. Any Party to the dispute
  may submit written comments to the arbitration panel on precise
  aspects of its interim report within 15 days of the notification of
  the report.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Arbitration Panel Ruling" article_identifier="35442">1. The arbitration panel shall notify its ruling to the Parties to the
  dispute and to the Trade Committee within 150 days from the date of
  the establishment of the arbitration panel. Where it considers that
  this deadline cannot be met, the chairperson of the arbitration panel
  must notify the Parties to the dispute and the Trade Committee in
  writing, stating the reasons for the delay and the date on which the
  panel plans to conclude its work. Under no circumstances should the
  ruling be notified later than 180 days from the date of the
  establishment of the arbitration panel.

  2. In cases of urgency, including those involving perishable and
  seasonal goods, the arbitration panel shall make every effort to
  notify its ruling within 75 days from the date of its establishment.
  Under no circumstance should it take longer than 90 days from its
  establishment. The arbitration panel may give a preliminary ruling
  within 10 days of its establishment on whether it deems the case to be
  urgent.

  Compliance</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Compliance With The Arbitration Panel Ruling" article_identifier="35443">Each Party to the dispute or as the case may be, the relevant Pacific
  State shall take any measure necessary to comply with the arbitration
  panel ruling, and the Parties to the dispute will endeavour to agree
  on the period of time to comply with the ruling.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="The Reasonable Period Of Time For Compliance" article_identifier="35444">1. No later than 30 days after the notification of the arbitration
  panel ruling to the Parties to the dispute, the Party complained
  against shall notify the complaining Party and the Trade Committee of
  the time it will require for compliance (reasonable period of time).

  2. If there is disagreement between the Parties to the dispute on the
  reasonable period of time to comply with the arbitration panel ruling,
  the complaining Party shall, within 20 days of the notification made
  under paragraph 1, request in writing the arbitration panel to
  determine the length of the reasonable period of time. Such request
  shall be notified simultaneously to the other Party to the dispute and
  to the Trade Committee. The arbitration panel shall notify its ruling
  to the Parties to the dispute and to the Trade Committee within 30
  days from the date of the submission of the request.

  3. The arbitration panel shall, in determining the length of the
  reasonable period of time, take into consideration the length of time
  that it will normally take the Party complained against or, as the
  case may be, the relevant Pacific State to adopt comparable
  legislative or administrative measures to those identified by such
  Party or as the case may be, the relevant Pacific State as being
  necessary to ensure compliance. The arbitration panel shall also take
  into consideration capacity constraints which may affect the defending
  Party's adoption of the necessary measures.

  4. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures set out in Article
  52 shall apply. The time limit for notifying the ruling shall be 45
  days from the date of the submission of the request referred to in
  paragraph 2.

  5. The reasonable period of time may be extended by agreement of the
  Parties to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Review Of Any Measure Taken To Comply With The Arbitration Panel" article_identifier="35445">ruling

  1. The Party complained against shall notify the other Party and the
  Trade Committee before the end of the reasonable period of time of any
  measure that it has taken to comply with the arbitration panel ruling.

  2. In the event that there is disagreement between the Parties to the
  dispute concerning the compatibility of any measure notified under
  paragraph 1, with the provisions of this Agreement, the complaining
  Party may request in writing the arbitration panel to rule on the
  matter. Such request shall identify the specific measure at issue and
  it shall explain how such measure is incompatible with the provisions
  of this Agreement. The arbitration panel shall notify its ruling
  within 90 days of the date of the submission of the request. In cases
  of urgency, including those involving perishable and seasonal goods,
  the arbitration panel shall notify its ruling within 45 days of the
  date of the submission of the request.

  3. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures set out in Article
  52 shall apply. The time limit for notifying the ruling shall be 105
  days from the date of the submission of the request referred to in
  paragraph 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Temporary Remedies In Case Of Non-Compliance" article_identifier="35446">1. If the Party or Pacific State concerned fails to notify any measure
  taken to comply with the arbitration panel ruling before the expiry of
  the reasonable period of time, or if the arbitration panel rules that
  the measure notified under Article 57, paragraph 1 is not compatible
  with the provisions of this Agreement, the Party complained against
  or, as the case may be, the relevant Pacific State shall, if so
  requested by the complaining Party or Pacific State, present an offer
  for compensation. Such compensation may include or consist of
  financial compensation although nothing in this Agreement shall oblige
  the Party complained against, or as the case may be, the relevant
  Pacific State, to offer such financial compensation.

  2. If no agreement on compensation is reached within 30 days of the
  end of the reasonable period of time or of the arbitration panel’s
  ruling under Article 57 that a measure taken to comply is not
  compatible with the provisions of this Agreement, the complaining
  Party or Pacific State shall be entitled, upon notification to the
  other Party, to adopt appropriate measures. Such measures may be
  adopted either by the complaining Party, or as the case may be, the
  relevant Pacific State.

  3. In adopting appropriate measures, the complaining Party, or as the
  case may be, the relevant Pacific State, shall select measures
  proportionate to the violation that least affect the attainment of the
  objectives of this Agreement and shall take into consideration their
  impact on the economy or development of the Party or individual
  Pacific States complained against.

  4. The EC Party shall exercise due restraint in adopting appropriate
  measures pursuant to paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, in
  particular, where the failure to comply with the Agreement stems from
  capacity constraints.

  5. Compensation or appropriate measures shall be temporary and shall
  be applied only until any measure found to violate the provisions of
  this Agreement has been withdrawn or amended so as to bring it into
  conformity with those provisions or until the Parties have agreed to
  settle the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Review Of Any Measure Taken To Comply After The Adoption Of Appropriate Measures" article_identifier="35447">1. The Party or Pacific State complained against shall notify the
  other Party or Pacific State to the dispute and the Trade Committee of
  any measure it has taken to comply with the ruling of the arbitration
  panel and of its request for an end to application of appropriate
  measures by the complaining Party or Pacific State.

  2. If the Parties to the dispute do not reach an agreement on the
  compatibility of the notified measure with the provisions of this
  Agreement within 30 days of the date of the submission of the
  notification, the complaining Party or Pacific State shall request in
  writing the arbitration panel to rule on the matter. Such request
  shall be notified to the other Party or Pacific State to the dispute
  and to the Trade Committee. The arbitration panel ruling shall be
  notified to the Parties to the dispute and to the Trade Committee
  within 45 days of the date of the submission of the request. If the
  arbitration panel rules that any measure taken to comply is not in
  conformity with the provisions referred to in this Agreement, the
  arbitration panel will determine whether the complaining Party or, as
  the case may be, the relevant Pacific State can continue to apply
  appropriate measures. If the arbitration panel rules that any measure
  taken to comply is in conformity with the provisions of this
  Agreement, the appropriate measures shall be terminated.

  3. In the event of the original arbitration panel, or some of its
  members, being unable to reconvene, the procedures laid down in
  Article 52 shall apply. The period for notifying the ruling shall be
  60 days from the date of the submission of the request referred to in
  paragraph 2.

  Common provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="Mutually Agreed Solution" article_identifier="35448">The Parties to the dispute may reach an agreed solution to a dispute
  under Part III at any time. They shall notify the Trade Committee of
  any such solution. Upon adoption of the mutually agreed solution, the
  procedure shall be terminated.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Rules Of Procedure And Code Of Conduct" article_identifier="35449">1. Dispute settlement procedures under Part III of this Agreement
  shall be governed by the Rules of Procedure and the Code of Conduct
  which shall be adopted by the Parties.

  2. The Parties may decide to modify the Rules of Procedure and the
  Code of Conduct.

  3. Any meeting of the arbitration panel shall be open to the public in
  accordance with the Rules of Procedure, unless the arbitration panel
  decides otherwise on its own motion or at the request of the Parties
  to the dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Information And Technical Advice" article_identifier="35450">At the request of a Party to the dispute, or upon its own initiative,
  the arbitration panel may obtain information from any source,
  including the Parties involved in the dispute, it deems appropriate
  for the arbitration panel proceeding. The arbitration shall also have
  the right to seek the relevant opinion of experts as it deems
  appropriate. Interested parties are authorised to submit amicus curiae
  briefs to the arbitration panels in accordance with the Rules of
  Procedure. Any information obtained in this manner must be disclosed
  to each of the Parties to the dispute and submitted for their
  comments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Languages Of The Submissions" article_identifier="35451">1. The written and oral submissions of the Parties to the dispute
  shall be made in any of the official languages of the Parties.

  2. The Parties shall endeavour to agree on a common working language
  for any specific proceedings under this Part. If the Parties are
  unable to agree on a common working language, each Party or Pacific
  State shall arrange for and bear the costs of the translation of its
  submitted documents and interpretation at the hearings into the
  language chosen by the Party or Pacific State complained against,
  unless such language is an official language of that Party or Pacific
  State [4].</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Arbitration Panel Rulings" article_identifier="35452">1. The arbitration panel shall make every effort to take any decision
  by consensus. Where, nevertheless, a decision cannot be arrived at by
  consensus, the matter at issue shall be decided by majority vote.

  2. The ruling shall set out the findings of fact, the applicability of
  the relevant provisions of this Agreement and the reasoning behind any
  findings and conclusions that it makes. The Trade Committee shall make
  the arbitration panel rulings publicly available unless it decides not
  to do so.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="4108">
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="List Of Arbitrators" article_identifier="35453">1. The Trade Committee shall, not later than three months after the
  provisional application of this Agreement, establish a list of 15
  individuals who are willing and able to serve as arbitrators. Each of
  the Parties shall select five individuals to serve as arbitrators. The
  two Parties shall also agree on five individuals who are not nationals
  of either Party and who shall act as chairpersons of the arbitration
  panel. The Trade Committee will ensure that the list is always
  maintained at this level.

  2. Arbitrators shall have specialised knowledge or experience of law
  and international trade. They shall be independent, serve in their
  individual capacities and not take instructions from any organisation
  or government, or be affiliated with the government of any of the
  Parties, and shall comply with the Code of Conduct annexed to the
  Rules of Procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Relation With Wto Obligations" article_identifier="35454">1. Arbitration bodies set up under this Agreement shall not arbitrate
  disputes on each Party's or, as the case may be the relevant Pacific
  State's rights and obligations under the Agreement establishing the
  WTO.

  2. Recourse to the dispute settlement provisions of this Agreement
  shall be without prejudice to any action in the WTO framework,
  including dispute settlement action. However, where a Party, or as the
  case may be, the relevant Pacific State has, with regard to a
  particular measure, instituted a dispute settlement proceeding, either
  under Article 51(1) of this Agreement or under the WTO Agreement, it
  may not institute a dispute settlement proceeding regarding the same
  measure in the other forum until the first proceeding has ended. For
  purposes of this paragraph, dispute settlement proceedings under the
  WTO Agreement are deemed to be initiated by a Party's or, as the case
  may be, Pacific State's request for the establishment of a panel under
  Article 6 of the Understanding on Rules and Procedures Governing the
  Settlement of Disputes of the WTO.

  3. Nothing in this Agreement shall preclude a Party or Pacific State
  from implementing the suspension of obligations authorised by the
  Dispute Settlement Body of the WTO. Nothing in the WTO Agreement shall
  preclude Parties from suspending benefits under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Time-Limits" article_identifier="35455">1. All time limits laid down in this Part, including the limits for
  the arbitration panels to notify their rulings, shall be counted in
  calendar days from the day following the act or fact to which they
  refer.

  2. Any time limit referred to in this Part may be extended by mutual
  agreement of the Parties to the dispute.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART IV" name="Institutional Provisions" chapter_identifier="4109">
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Trade Committee" article_identifier="35456">1. A Trade Committee is hereby established that is composed of
  representatives of the Parties.

  2. The Trade Committee shall establish its rules of procedure and be
  co-chaired by a representative of the EC Party and a representative
  from the Pacific States. The two co-chairs shall alternate in
  presiding the meetings. Whoever is presiding a meeting shall be
  considered "presiding co-chair" for the purposes of this
  Agreement until the moment in time when the next meeting commences and
  the role of a presiding co-chair shall be assumed by the other Party.

  3. The Trade Committee shall deal with all matters necessary for the
  implementation of this Agreement.

  4. In the performance of its functions, the Trade Committee may:

  (a) set up and oversee any special committees or bodies necessary for
  the implementation of this Agreement;

  (b) meet at any time agreed by the Parties;

  (c) consider any issues under this Agreement and take appropriate
  action in the exercise of its functions; and

  (d) take decisions or make recommendations in cases provided for in
  this Agreement.

  5. The Trade Committee will delegate specific implementing
  decision-making powers to the special committees as provided for in
  the relevant provisions of the Agreement, in particular the Special
  Committee on Customs Cooperation and Rules of Origin.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="PART V" name="General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="4110">
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Modalities For The Continuation Of Negotiations" article_identifier="35457">1. The EC Party and the Pacific States covered by this Agreement are
  committed to the continuation and successful conclusion of the
  currently ongoing negotiations for a comprehensive Economic
  Partnership Agreement (EPA) in line with the Cotonou Agreement and
  previous Ministerial Declarations and Conclusions, including all
  components and involving all interested countries in the Pacific
  region. They confirm their commitment to the objective of concluding
  those negotiations by 31 December 2008.

  2. The Parties recognise that development cooperation will be a
  crucial element of the comprehensive EPA and an essential factor for
  the realisation of its objectives. They reaffirm their commitment to
  supporting the objective that development cooperation for regional
  economic cooperation and integration as provided for in the Cotonou
  Agreement shall be carried out so as to maximise the expected benefits
  of the comprehensive EPA.

  3. The Parties note that this Interim Partnership Agreement does not
  predetermine the positions that the region will be taking in the
  negotiations for a comprehensive EPA on development cooperation. They
  agree that provisions on development cooperation will be finalised in
  the wider context of the Pacific ACP States as soon as possible. In
  the meantime, they further agree to cooperate closely at the national
  level within the framework of the existing structures as set out in
  the Cotonou Agreement to facilitate implementation and the realisation
  of benefits and maximise the synergies between development cooperation
  and the objectives of this Agreement.

  4. The full Economic Partnership Agreement shall, upon its entry into
  force, replace this Agreement which will then cease to exist.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Definitions And Fulfilment Of Obligations" article_identifier="35458">1. For the purposes of this Agreement the "Contracting
  Parties" shall be the European Community, referred to as the
  "EC Party", on the one part, and Papua New Guinea and the
  Republic of the Fiji Islands, referred to as the "Pacific
  States", on the other part.

  2. For the purposes of this Agreement:

  (a) the term "Parties" shall refer to the Pacific States
  listed in paragraph 1 acting collectively and the EC Party. The term
  "Party" shall refer to the Pacific States listed in
  paragraph 1 acting collectively or the EC Party, as the case may be;

  (b) the term "Pacific States" shall refer to the Pacific
  States listed in paragraph 1 acting individually.

  3. For the purposes of this Agreement, where applicable "Small
  Island States" means the Cook Islands, Kiribati, Nauru, Niue,
  Palau, Republic of Marshall Islands and Tuvalu.

  4. For the purposes of this Agreement, "least developed
  country" means any Pacific State designated by the United Nations
  as a least developed country on the entry into force of this
  Agreement.

  5. The Pacific States and the EC Party shall adopt any general or
  specific measures required for them to fulfil their obligations under
  this Agreement and shall ensure that they comply with the objectives
  laid down in this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Coordinators And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="35459">1. In order to facilitate communication and to ensure the effective
  implementation of the Agreement the Parties shall designate a
  coordinator within a reasonable period of time after the provisional
  application of this Agreement. The designation of coordinators is
  without prejudice to the specific designation of competent authorities
  under specific Titles or Chapters of this Agreement.

  2. On the request of the Parties, the coordinators shall indicate the
  office or official responsible for any matter pertaining to the
  implementation of this Agreement and provide the required support to
  facilitate communication with the requesting Party.

  3. On request of the other Party, and to the extent legally possible,
  the Parties through their coordinators shall provide information and
  reply promptly to any question relating to an actual or proposed
  measure that might affect trade between the Parties.

  4. The EC Party and the Pacific States shall ensure that their laws,
  regulations, procedures and administrative rulings of general
  application relating to any trade matter covered by this Agreement are
  promptly published or made publicly available, which may include
  making the information available on the official, publicly and
  fee-free accessible websites of the EC Party or Pacific States
  concerned. Such measures shall also be brought to the attention of the
  other Party.

  5. Without prejudice to specific transparency provisions in this
  Agreement, the information referred to in paragraph 4 shall be
  considered to have been brought to the attention of the other Party
  when the information has been made available by appropriate
  notification to the WTO and to the coordinator of the Pacific States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Regional Preference" article_identifier="35460">1. Nothing in this Agreement shall oblige the EC Party or a Pacific
  State to extend to another Party to this Agreement any more favourable
  treatment applied by the EC Party or a Pacific State as part of its
  respective regional integration process.

  2. Any more favourable treatment and advantage that may be granted
  under this Agreement by any Pacific State to the EC Party shall also
  be provided to all other Pacific States which are a Party to this
  Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Relations With The Cotonou Agreement" article_identifier="35461">1. With the exception of development cooperation provisions provided
  for in Title II of Part 3 of the Cotonou Agreement, in case of any
  inconsistency between the provisions of this Agreement and the
  provisions of Title II of Part 3 of the Cotonou Agreement, the
  provisions of this Agreement shall prevail.

  2. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed so as to prevent the
  application of all provisions of the Cotonou Agreement outside Title
  II of Part 3 and according to the procedures set by the said
  Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Relations With The Wto Agreement" article_identifier="35462">The EC Party and the Pacific States agree that nothing in this
  Agreement requires the EC Party or the Pacific States, where
  applicable, to act in a manner inconsistent with their existing WTO
  obligations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Relationship With Other International Agreements" article_identifier="35463">Nothing in this Agreement shall be regarded as exempting any Party
  from its existing obligations, or abrogating the rights of any Party,
  under any existing international agreement, unless a contrary
  intention is expressly stated.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Entry Into Force And Duration" article_identifier="35464">1. This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the month
  following the date on which the Contracting Parties have notified each
  other in writing that their respective internal procedures necessary
  for its entry into force have been completed.

  2. Pending entry into force of the Agreement, the EC Party and Pacific
  States agree to provisionally apply the Agreement. Such application
  may be undertaken by provisional application pursuant to the laws of
  the EC Party and of the Pacific States or by ratification of the
  Agreement. The Agreement shall be applied provisionally 10 days after
  the Contracting Parties have notified each other in writing of the
  completion of the procedures necessary for this purpose.

  3. Where a Pacific State accedes to this Agreement, the Agreement
  shall be applied provisionally in the same manner as foreseen in
  paragraph 2, once the EC Party and that Pacific State have given
  notice accordingly.

  4. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, the EC Party and the Pacific States
  may take steps to apply the Agreement, before provisional application,
  to the extent feasible.

  5. Any Party may give written notice to the other of its intention to
  denounce this Agreement.

  6. Denunciation shall take effect twelve months after notification to
  the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Territorial Application" article_identifier="35465">This Agreement shall apply, on the one hand, to the territories in
  which the Treaty establishing the European Community applies and under
  the conditions laid down in that Treaty, and, on the other hand, to
  the territories of the Pacific States. References in this Agreement to
  "territory" shall be understood in this sense.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Revision Clause" article_identifier="35466">The Trade Committee may review this Agreement, its implementation,
  operation and performance where necessary and make appropriate
  suggestions to the Parties for its amendment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Outermost Regions And The European Community" article_identifier="35467">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent the EC Party from applying
  existing measures aimed at addressing the structural, social and
  economic situation of the outermost region pursuant to Article 299(2)
  of the Treaty establishing the European Community.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Accession Of The Pacific Islands" article_identifier="35468">1. This Agreement shall remain open for accession of all Pacific
  Island States party to the Cotonou Agreement and Pacific Islands whose
  structural characteristics and economic and social situation are
  comparable to those of the countries which are Parties to the Cotonou
  Agreement on the basis of the submission of a GATT 1994 Article XXIV
  compliant market access offer. Any request for accession shall be
  presented to the Parties of this Agreement which will take a decision.

  2. If the request is approved, the Pacific Island concerned shall
  accede to this Agreement by depositing an act of accession which shall
  be transmitted to the Contracting Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Authentic Texts" article_identifier="35469">This Agreement is drawn up in duplicate in the Bulgarian, Czech,
  Danish, Dutch, English, Estonian, Finnish, French, German, Greek,
  Hungarian, Italian, Latvian, Lithuanian, Maltese, Polish, Portuguese,
  Romanian, Slovak, Slovenian, Spanish and Swedish languages, each of
  these texts being equally authentic.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Annexes" article_identifier="35470">The Annexes and Protocols to this Agreement shall form an integral
  part thereof.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="4111">
      <article article_identifier="35471">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have affixed
  their signatures below this Agreement.

  Съставено в Лондон на тридесети юли две хиляди и девета година

  Hecho en Londres, el treinta de julio de dos mil nueve.

  V Londýně dne třicátého července dva tisíce devět.

  Udfærdiget i London den tredivte juli to tusind og ni.

  Geschehen zu London am dreißigsten Juli zweitausendneun.

  Kahe tuhande üheksanda aasta juulikuu kolmekümnendal päeval Londonis.

  Έγινε στο Λονδίνο, στις τριάντα Ιουλίου δύο χιλιάδες εννιά.

  Done at London on the thirtieth day of July in the year two thousand
  and nine.

  Fait à Londres, le trente juillet deux mille neuf.

  Fatto a Londra, addì trenta luglio duemilanove.

  Londonā, divi tūkstoši devītā gada trīsdesmitajā jūlijā.

  Priimta du tūkstančiai devintų metų liepos trisdešimtą dieną Londone.

  Kelt Londonban, a kétezer-kilencedik év július harmincadik napján.

  Magħmul f’Londra, fit-tletin jum ta’ Lulju tas-sena elfejn u disgħa.

  Gedaan te Londen, de dertigste juli tweeduizend negen.

  Sporządzono w Londynie dnia trzydziestego lipca roku dwa tysiące
  dziewiątego.

  Feito em Londres, em trinta de Julho de dois mil e nove.

  Încheiat la Londra, la treizeci iulie două mii nouă.

  V Londýne dňa tridsiateho júla dvetisícdeväť.

  V Londonu, dne tridesetega julija leta dva tisoč devet.

  Tehty Lontoossa kolmantenakymmenentenä päivänä heinäkuuta vuonna
  kaksituhattayhdeksän.

  Som skedde i London den trettionde juli tjugohundranio.

  За Европейската общност

  Por la Comunidad Europea

  Za Evropské společenství

  For Det Europæiske Fællesskab

  Für die Europäische Gemeinschaft

  Euroopa Ühenduse nimel

  Για την Ευρωπαϊκή Κοινότητα

  For the European Community

  Pour la Communauté européenne

  Per la Comunità europea

  Eiropas Kopienas vārdā

  Europos bendrijos vardu

  Az Európai Közösség részéről

  Għall-Komunità Ewropea

  Voor de Europese Gemeenschap

  W imieniu Wspólnoty Europejskiej

  Pela Comunidade Europeia

  Pentru Comunitatea Europeană

  Za Európske spoločenstvo

  Za Evropsko skupnost

  Euroopan yhteisön puolesta

  För Europeiska gemenskapen

  For the Republic of the Fiji Islands

  For the Independent State of Papua New Guinea

  [1] The Parties recognise that any such measure shall be applied on a
  Most Favoured Nation (MFN) basis.

  [2] For this calculation official data by the WTO on leading exporters
  in world merchandise trade (excluding intra-EU trade) shall be used.

  [3] For the purpose of this Article agricultural products are those
  covered by Annex I of the WTO Agreement on Agriculture.

  [4] The official language of the Pacific States is English and the
  official languages of the EC Party are those indicated in Article 81.

  --------------------------------------------------</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
