<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Viet Nam</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>170</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>148</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2008-12-25</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2009-10-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2009-10-01</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2026-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">VNM</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/vietnam/epa0812/agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/asia-paci/vietnam/epa0812/index.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="1608">
      <article article_identifier="13211">Preamble 

Japan and the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam (hereinafterreferred to in this Agreement as “Viet Nam”), 

Recognizing that a dynamic and rapidly changing globalenvironment brought about by globalization and technologicalprogress presents various economic and strategic challenges and opportunities to the Parties; 

Conscious of their longstanding friendship and strongeconomic and political ties that have developed through manyyears of fruitful and mutually beneficial cooperation betweenthe Parties; 

Believing that such a bilateral relationship will beenhanced by forging a mutually beneficial economic partnership through trade liberalization, trade facilitation, andcooperation; 

Recognizing the development gap between the Parties; 

Reaffirming that the economic partnership will provide auseful framework for enhanced cooperation and serve the commoninterests of the Parties in various fields as agreed in thisAgreement and lead to the improvement of economic efficiencyand the development of trade, investment, and human resources; 

Recognizing that such a partnership will create a largerand new market, and enhance the attractiveness and vibrancy oftheir markets; 

Recalling Article XXIV of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General Agreement on Tradein Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B, respectively, to theMarrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994; 

Convinced that this Agreement would open a new era for therelationship between the Parties; and 

Determined to establish a legal framework for an economicpartnership between the Parties; 

HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="1609">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="13212">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 


(a) liberalize and facilitate trade in goods and servicesbetween the Parties; 


(b) ensure protection of intellectual property andpromote cooperation in the field thereof; 


(c) promote cooperation and coordination for theeffective enforcement of competition laws in eachParty; 


(d) facilitate the movement of natural persons between the Parties; 


(e) improve business environment in each Party; 


(f) establish a framework to enhance closer cooperationin the fields agreed in this Agreement; and 


(g) create effective procedures for the implementation of this Agreement and for the settlement of disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="13213">For the purposes of this Agreement, the term: 


(a) “Area” means with respect to a Party, (i) the territory of the Party, including its territorial sea; and (ii)the exclusive economic zone and the continental shelf with respect to which the Party exercises sovereignrights or jurisdiction in accordance withinternational law; 

Note: 	Nothing in this subparagraph shall affect the rights and obligations of the Parties underinternational law, including those under the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. 

(b) “customs authority” means the competent authoritythat is responsible for the administration andenforcement of customs laws and regulations; 


(c) “GATS” means the General Agreement on Trade inServices in Annex 1B to the WTO Agreement; 


(d) “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. For the purposes of this Agreement, references to articles inthe GATT 1994 include the interpretative notes; 


(e) “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the HarmonizedCommodity Description and Coding System set out in the Annex to the International Convention on the Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding System,and adopted and implemented by the Parties in theirrespective laws; 


(f) “Parties” means Japan and Viet Nam, and “Party” meanseither Japan or Viet Nam; and 


(g) “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh AgreementEstablishing the World Trade Organization, done atMarrakesh, April 15, 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13214">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, promptly publish, or otherwise make publiclyavailable, its laws, regulations, administrative procedures,and administrative rulings and judicial decisions of generalapplication as well as international agreements to which theParty is a party, with respect to any matter covered by thisAgreement. 


2. Each Party shall make available to the public the names and addresses of the competent authorities responsible for laws, regulations, administrative procedures, and administrativerulings, referred to in paragraph 1. 


3. Each Party shall, upon request by the other Party, withina reasonable period of time, respond to specific questions from, and provide information to, the other Party with respect tomatters referred to in paragraph 1. 


4. When introducing or changing its laws, regulations, oradministrative procedures that significantly affect theimplementation and operation of this Agreement, each Partyshall, in accordance with its laws and regulations, endeavorto provide, except in emergency situations, a reasonable interval between the time when such laws, regulations, oradministrative procedures as introduced or changed arepublished or made publicly available and the time when theyenter into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Public Comment Procedures" article_identifier="13215">The Government of each Party shall, in accordance with thelaws and regulations of the Party, endeavor to adopt or maintain public comment procedures, in order to: 


(a) make public in advance regulations of generalapplication that affect any matter covered by thisAgreement, when the Government adopts, amends, orrepeals them; and 


(b) provide a reasonable opportunity for comments by thepublic and give consideration to those comments before adoption, amendment, or repeal of such regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="13216">1. Where administrative decisions which pertain to or affectthe implementation and operation of this Agreement are takenby the competent authorities of a Party, the competentauthorities shall, in accordance with the laws and regulationsof the Party: 


(a) inform the applicant of the decision within areasonable period of time after the submission of theapplication considered complete under the laws andregulations of the Party, taking into account theestablished standard periods of time referred to inparagraph 3; and 


(b) provide, within a reasonable period of time,information concerning the status of the application, at the request of the applicant. 
2. The competent authorities of a Party shall, in accordancewith the laws and regulations of the Party, endeavor toestablish standards for taking administrative decisions inresponse to submitted applications. The competent authoritiesshall endeavor to: 


(a) make such standards as specific as possible; and 


(b) make such standards publicly available except when itwould extraordinarily raise administrativedifficulties for the Government of the Party. 
3. The competent authorities of a Party shall, in accordancewith the laws and regulations of the Party, endeavor to: 


(a) establish standard periods of time between the receipt of applications by the competent authorities and theadministrative decisions taken in response to thesubmitted applications; and 


(b) make publicly available such periods of time, ifestablished.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="13217">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, maintain the confidentiality of informationprovided in confidence by the other Party pursuant to thisAgreement. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, the information providedpursuant to this Agreement may be transmitted to a third partysubject to prior consent of the Party which provided theinformation. 


3. Nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party to provideconfidential information, the disclosure of which would impede the enforcement of its laws and regulations, or otherwise becontrary to the public interest, or which would prejudice thelegitimate commercial interests of particular enterprises,public or private.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Taxation" article_identifier="13218">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, theprovisions of this Agreement shall not apply to any taxationmeasures. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights andobligations of either Party under any tax convention. In theevent of any inconsistency between this Agreement and any suchconvention, that convention shall prevail to the extent of theinconsistency. 


3. Articles 3 and 6 shall apply to taxation measures, to the extent that the provisions of this Agreement are applicable tosuch taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="General And Security Exceptions" article_identifier="13219">1. For the purposes of Chapters 2, 3, and 4, Articles XX andXXI of the GATT 1994 are incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 


2. For the purposes of Chapters 7 and 8, Articles XIV and XIVbis of the GATS are incorporated into and form part of thisAgreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="13220">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations under the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which both Partiesare parties. 


2. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreementand the WTO Agreement, the WTO Agreement shall prevail to theextent of the inconsistency. 


3. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreementand any agreement other than the WTO Agreement to which both Parties are parties, the Parties shall immediately consult with each other with a view to finding a mutually satisfactorysolution, taking into consideration general principles ofinternational law. 


4. The provisions of the Agreement between Japan and theSocialist Republic of Viet Nam for the Liberalization,Promotion and Protection of Investment, signed at Tokyo onNovember 14, 2003 (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“BIT”), except its Article 20, as may be amended, areincorporated into and form part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 


5. Nothing in this Agreement shall be construed so as toderogate from any of obligations of a Party under the BIT, ifsuch an obligation entitles the other Party to treatment morefavorable than that accorded by this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="13221">The Governments of the Parties shall conclude a separateagreement setting forth the details and procedures for theimplementation of this Agreement (hereinafter referred to inthis Agreement as “the Implementing Agreement”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="13222">1. A Joint Committee shall be established under this Agreement. 


2. The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation andoperation of this Agreement; 


(b) considering and recommending to the Parties anyamendments to this Agreement; 


(c) supervising and coordinating the work of allSub-Committees established under this Agreement; 


(d) adopting: 


(i) the Implementing Regulations referred to in Part2 of Annex 1 and Rule 11 of Annex 3; and 


(ii) any necessary decisions; and 


(e) carrying out other functions as the Parties may agree. 

3. 	The Joint Committee: 


(a) shall be composed of representatives of theGovernments of the Parties; and 


(b) may establish, and delegate its responsibilities to,Sub-Committees. 

4. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules and procedures. 


5. The Joint Committee shall meet at such time and venue as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Communications" article_identifier="13223">Each Party shall designate a contact point to facilitatecommunications between the Parties on any matter relating tothis Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="1610">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13224">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “bilateral safeguard measure” means a bilateralsafeguard measure provided for in paragraph 4 ofArticle 20; 


(b) 	“customs duty” means any customs or import duty anda charge of any kind imposed in connection with theimportation of a good, but does not include any: 


(i) 	charge equivalent to an internal tax imposedconsistently with the provisions of paragraph2 of Article III of the GATT 1994, in respect of the like goods or, directly competitive orsubstitutable goods of the Party or in respectof goods from which the imported goods have been manufactured or produced in whole or in part; 


(ii) 	anti-dumping or countervailing duty appliedpursuant to a Party’s law and appliedconsistently with the provisions of Article VIof the GATT 1994, the Agreement onImplementation of Article VI of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1Ato the WTO Agreement, and the Agreement onSubsidies and Countervailing Measures in Annex1A to the WTO Agreement; or 
 (iii) 	fees or other charges commensurate with the cost of services rendered; 


(c) “customs value of goods” means the value of goods forthe purposes of levying ad valorem customs duties onimported goods; 


(d) “domestic industry” means the producers as a whole ofthe like or directly competitive goods operating ina Party, or those whose collective output of the likeor directly competitive goods constitutes a majorproportion of the total domestic production of thosegoods; 


(e) “originating good” means a good that qualifies asoriginating in accordance with the provisions ofChapter 3; 


(f) “provisional bilateral safeguard measure” means aprovisional bilateral safeguard measure provided forin subparagraph 11(a) of Article 20; 


(g) “serious injury” means a significant overallimpairment in the position of a domestic industry; and 


(h) “threat of serious injury” means serious injury that,on the basis of facts and not merely on allegation,conjecture, or remote possibility, is clearlyimminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="13225">The classification of goods in trade between the Partiesshall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13226">Each Party shall accord national treatment to the goodsof the other Party in accordance with Article III of the GATT1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Elimination Or Reduction Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="13227">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement, each Party shall, in accordance with its Schedule in Annex 1,eliminate or reduce its customs duties on originating goods ofthe other Party. 


2. The Parties shall negotiate on issues such as improvingmarket access conditions on originating goods designated fornegotiation in the Schedules in Annex 1, in accordance with theterms and conditions set out in such Schedules. 


3. In cases where its most-favored-nation applied rate ofcustoms duty on a particular good is lower than the rate ofcustoms duty to be applied in accordance with paragraph 1 onthe originating good which is classified under the same tariffline as that particular good, each Party shall apply the lowerrate with respect to that originating good in accordance withits laws, regulations, and procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="13228">For the purposes of determining the customs value of goodstraded between the Parties, provisions of Part I of theAgreement on Implementation of Article VII of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTOAgreement (hereinafter referred to in this Agreement as “theAgreement on Customs Valuation”) shall apply mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Export Subsidies" article_identifier="13229">Neither Party shall, in accordance with its obligationsunder the WTO Agreement, introduce or maintain any exportsubsidies.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Non-Tariff Measures" article_identifier="13230">1. Each Party shall not introduce or maintain any non-tariffmeasures on the importation of any good of the other Party oron the exportation or sale for export of any good destined forthe other Party which are inconsistent with its obligationsunder the WTO Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall ensure transparency of its non-tariffmeasures permitted under paragraph 1, including quantitativerestrictions. Each Party shall ensure full compliance with the obligations under the WTO Agreement with a view to minimizingpossible distortions to trade to the maximum extent possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="13231">1. Each Party may apply a safeguard measure to an originatinggood of the other Party in accordance with Article XIX of theGATT 1994 and the Agreement on Safeguards in Annex 1A to theWTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theAgreement on Safeguards”), or Article 5 of the Agreement onAgriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement (hereinafterreferred to in this Article as “Agreement on Agriculture”).  Anyaction taken pursuant to Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and theAgreement on Safeguards, or Article 5 of the Agreement onAgriculture shall not be subject to Chapter 13 of thisAgreement. 


2. Each Party shall be free to apply a bilateral safeguardmeasure, to the minimum extent necessary to prevent or remedythe serious injury to a domestic industry of that Party and tofacilitate adjustment, if as an effect of the obligationsincurred by that Party under this Agreement, including tariffconcessions, or if as a result of unforeseen developments andof the effects of the obligations incurred by that Party underthis Agreement, an originating good of the other Party is beingimported in such increased quantities, in absolute terms orrelative to domestic production, and under such conditions asto cause or threaten to cause serious injury to the domesticindustry of the former Party that produces like or directlycompetitive goods in the former Party. 


3. A Party shall not apply a bilateral safeguard measure toan originating good imported up to the limit of quota quantities granted under tariff rate quotas applied in accordance with its Schedule in Annex 1. 


4. A Party applying a bilateral safeguard measure may: 


(a) suspend the further reduction of any customs duty onthe originating good of the other Party provided forunder this Chapter; or 


(b) increase the customs duty on the originating good ofthe other Party to a level not to exceed the lesserof: 


(i) the most-favored-nation applied rate on the goodin effect on the day when the bilateral safeguardmeasure is applied; and 


(ii) the most-favored-nation applied rate on the goodin effect on the day immediately preceding thedate of entry into force of this Agreement. 

5. 	(a) A Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure only after an investigation has been carried out by thecompetent authorities of that Party in accordance with the same procedures as those provided for in Article3 and paragraph 2 of Article 4 of the Agreement onSafeguards. 

(b) The investigation referred to in subparagraph (a)shall be completed within one year following its dateof initiation. 

6. The following conditions and limitations shall apply withregard to a bilateral safeguard measure: 


(a) A Party shall immediately give a written notice to theother Party upon: 


(i) initiating an investigation referred to insubparagraph 5(a) relating to serious injury, orthreat of serious injury, and the reasons for it; 


(ii) making a finding of serious injury or threat ofserious injury caused by increased imports; and 
(iii) taking a decision to apply or extend a bilateralsafeguard measure. 


(b) The Party giving the written notice referred to insubparagraph (a) shall provide the other Party withall pertinent information, which shall include: 


(i) in the written notice referred to in subparagraph (a)(i), the reason for the initiation of theinvestigation, a precise description of anoriginating good subject to the investigation and its heading or subheading of the HarmonizedSystem, on which the Schedules in Annex 1 arebased, the period subject to the investigation,and the date of initiation of the investigation;and 


(ii) in the written notice referred to in subparagraphs (a)(ii) and (iii), the evidence of serious injury or threat of serious injury caused by theincreased imports of the originating good, aprecise description of the originating goodsubject to the proposed safeguard measure and its heading or subheading of the Harmonized System, on which the Schedules in Annex 1 are based, aprecise description of the bilateral safeguardmeasure, the proposed date of its introduction,and its expected duration. 


(c) A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateralsafeguard measure shall provide adequate opportunityfor prior consultations with the other Party with aview to reviewing the information arising from theinvestigation referred to in subparagraph 5(a),exchanging views on the bilateral safeguard measureand reaching an agreement on compensation set out inparagraph 7. 


(d) No bilateral safeguard measure shall be maintainedexcept to the extent and for such time as may benecessary to prevent or remedy serious injury and tofacilitate adjustment, provided that such time shallnot exceed a period of three years. A bilateral safeguard measure may be extended, provided that theconditions set out in this Article are met. The total duration of the bilateral safeguard measure,including any extensions thereof, shall not exceedfour years. In order to facilitate adjustment in asituation where the expected duration of a bilateralsafeguard measure is over one year, the Partymaintaining the bilateral safeguard measure shallprogressively liberalize the bilateral safeguardmeasure at regular intervals during the period ofapplication. 


(e) No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied againto the import of a particular originating good whichhas been subject to such a bilateral safeguard measure, for a period of time equal to the duration of theprevious safeguard measure or one year, whichever islonger. 


(f) Upon the termination of a bilateral safeguard measureon a good, the rate of the customs duty for that goodshall be the rate which, in accordance with theSchedule of the Party applying the bilateral safeguard measure set out in Annex 1, would have been in effecthad the bilateral safeguard measure not been applied. 

7. 	(a) A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral safeguard measure shall provide to the other Partymutually agreed adequate means of trade compensationin the form of substantially equivalent level ofconcessions or other obligations to that existingunder this Agreement. 


(b) In seeking compensation provided for in subparagraph(a), the Parties shall hold consultations in the Joint Committee. Any proceedings arising from suchconsultations shall be completed within 30 days fromthe date on which the bilateral safeguard measure wasapplied. 


(c) If no agreement on the compensation is reached withinthe time frame specified in subparagraph (b), theParty against whose originating good the bilateralsafeguard measure is taken shall be free to suspendconcessions of customs duties under this Agreement,which is substantially equivalent to the bilateralsafeguard measure. That Party may suspend the concessions only for the minimum period necessary toachieve the substantially equivalent effects and only while the bilateral safeguard measure is maintained.The right of suspension provided for in thissubparagraph shall not be exercised for the first twoyears that a bilateral safeguard measure is in effect, provided that the bilateral safeguard measure has been applied as a result of an absolute increase in imports and that such a bilateral safeguard measure conformsto the provisions of this Article. 

8. 	(a) A Party applying a safeguard measure in connection with an importation of an originating good of the other Party in accordance with Article XIX of the GATT 1994and the Agreement on Safeguards, or Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture, shall not apply thebilateral safeguard measure to that importation. 

(b) The period of application of the bilateral safeguardmeasure referred to in subparagraph 6(d) shall not beinterrupted by the Party’s non-application of thebilateral safeguard measure in accordance withsubparagraph (a). 

9. Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial, andreasonable administration of its laws and regulations relating to bilateral safeguard measures. 


10. Each Party shall adopt or maintain equitable, timely,transparent, and effective procedures relating to bilateralsafeguard measures. 


11. (a) In critical circumstances, where delay would cause damage which it would be difficult to repair, a Partymay apply a provisional bilateral safeguard measure,which shall take the form of the measure set out in subparagraph 4(a) or 4(b), pursuant to a preliminarydetermination that there is clear evidence that increased imports of an originating good have causedor are threatening to cause serious injury to adomestic industry. 


(b) A Party shall give a written notice to the other Partyprior to applying a provisional bilateral safeguardmeasure. Consultations by the Parties in the JointCommittee on the application of the provisionalbilateral safeguard measure shall be initiatedimmediately after the provisional bilateral safeguard measure is applied. 


(c) The duration of a provisional bilateral safeguardmeasure shall not exceed 200 days. During that period, the pertinent requirements of paragraph 5 shall be met.  The duration of the provisional bilateral safeguardmeasure shall be counted as a part of the periodreferred to in subparagraph 6(d). 


(d) Subparagraph 6(f) shall apply, mutatis mutandis, to the provisional bilateral safeguard measure. 


(e) The customs duty imposed as a result of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall be refunded if thesubsequent investigation referred to in subparagraph5(a) does not determine that increased imports of theoriginating good have caused or threatened to causeserious injury to a domestic industry. 

12. All official communications and documentations exchangedbetween the Parties relating to a bilateral safeguard measureshall be in writing and shall be in the English language. 


13. (a) Within 10 years after the entry into force of this Agreement, the Parties shall review this Article witha view to determining whether there is a need tomaintain the bilateral safeguard mechanism. 
(b) If the Parties do not agree to remove the bilateralsafeguard mechanism during the review pursuant tosubparagraph (a), the Parties shall thereafterconduct reviews to determine the necessity of thebilateral safeguard mechanism in the Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Measures To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="13232">Where a Party is in serious balance of payments and external financial difficulties or threat thereof, the Party may, inaccordance with the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on theBalance-of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement onTariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, adoptrestrictive import measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Relation To The Agreement On Comprehensive Economic Partnership Among Japan And Member States Of The Association Of Southeast Asian Nations" article_identifier="13233">The Parties reaffirm that, as is provided for in Article9 of this Agreement, any commitments of the Parties under thisChapter shall not affect the commitments of the Parties underthe Agreement on Comprehensive Economic Partnership among Japan and Member States of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="1611">
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13234">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “exporter” means a natural or juridical personlocated in an exporting Party who exports a good from the exporting Party; 


(b) “factory ships of the Party” or “vessels of the Party” respectively means factory ships or vessels: 


(i) which are registered in the Party; 


(ii) 	which sail under the flag of the Party; 
(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 50 percent by nationals of the Parties, or by ajuridical person with its head office in either Party, of which the representatives, chairmanof the board of directors, and the majority ofthe members of such board are nationals of the Parties, and of which at least 50 percent of the equity interest is owned by nationals orjuridical persons of the Parties; and 


(iv) 	of which at least 75 percent of the total of themaster, officers, and crew are nationals of the Parties or non-Parties which are Member States of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (hereinafter referred to in this Agreement as“ASEAN”); 


(c) “generally accepted accounting principles” meansthe recognized consensus or substantialauthoritative support in a Party, with respect to the recording of revenues, expenses, costs, assets, andliabilities; the disclosure of information; and thepreparation of financial statements. These standards may encompass broad guidelines of generalapplication as well as detailed standards, practices, and procedures; 


(d) “good” means any merchandise, product, article, ormaterial; 


(e) “identical and interchangeable materials” meansmaterials being of the same kind and commercialquality, possessing the same technical and physicalcharacteristics, and which once they areincorporated into the good cannot be distinguishedfrom one another for origin purposes by virtue of anymarkings; 


(f) “importer” means a natural or juridical person whoimports a good into the importing Party; 


(g) “materials” means any matter or substance used orconsumed in the production of a good, physicallyincorporated into a good, or used in the productionof another good; 


(h) “originating good” or “originating material” meansa good or material that qualifies as originating inaccordance with the provisions of this Chapter; 


(i) “packing materials and containers fortransportation and shipment” means the goods used to protect a good during its transportation and shipment, different from those containers or materials used for its retail sale; 


(j) “preferential tariff treatment” means the rate ofcustoms duties applicable to an originating good ofthe exporting Party in accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 16; and 


(k) “production” means methods of obtaining a goodincluding growing, mining, harvesting, raising,breeding, extracting, gathering, collecting,capturing, fishing, trapping, hunting,manufacturing, processing, or assembling.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="13235">For the purposes of this Agreement, a good shall qualifyas an originating good of a Party if it: 


(a) is wholly obtained or produced entirely in the Partyas provided for in Article 25; 


(b) satisfies the requirements of Article 26 when usingnon-originating materials; or 


(c) is produced entirely in the Party exclusively fromoriginating materials of the Party, 
and meets all other applicable requirements of this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Goods Wholly Obtained Or Produced" article_identifier="13236">For the purposes of paragraph (a) of Article 24, the

following shall be considered as wholly obtained or produced

entirely in a Party: 


(a) plant and plant products grown and harvested, picked, or gathered in the Party; 

Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, the term “plant” refers to all plant life, includingfruit, flowers, vegetables, trees, seaweed,fungi, and live plants. 

(b) live animals born and raised in the Party; 

 Note: For the purposes of paragraphs (b) and (c), the term “animals” covers all animal life,including mammals, birds, fish, crustaceans,molluscs, reptiles, bacteria, and viruses. 

(c) goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 


(d) goods obtained from hunting, trapping, fishing,gathering, or capturing conducted in the Party; 


(e) minerals and other naturally occurring substances,not included in paragraphs (a) through (d), extracted or taken from soil, waters, seabed or beneath theseabed of the Party; 


(f) goods taken from the waters, seabed or beneath theseabed outside the territorial waters of the Party,provided that the Party has the rights to exploit such waters, seabed and beneath the seabed in accordancewith its laws and regulations and international law; 

Note: Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations of the Parties underinternational law, including those under theUnited Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea. 

(g) goods of sea-fishing and other marine products taken by vessels of the Party from outside the territorialseas of the Parties; 


(h) goods processed and/or made on board factory shipsof the Party exclusively from products referred toin paragraph (g); 


(i) articles collected in the Party which can no longerperform their original purpose or be restored orrepaired, and are fit only for disposal, for therecovery of parts or raw materials, or for recyclingpurposes; 


(j) parts or raw materials recovered in the Party fromarticles which can no longer perform their originalpurpose nor are capable of being restored orrepaired; 


(k) scrap and waste derived from manufacturing orprocessing operations, including mining,agriculture, construction, refining, incinerationand sewage treatment operations, or from consumption, in the Party, and fit only for disposal or for therecovery of raw materials; and 


(l) goods obtained or produced in the Party exclusivelyfrom goods referred to in paragraphs (a) through (k).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Goods Not Wholly Obtained Or Produced" article_identifier="13237">1. For the purposes of paragraph (b) of Article 24, a goodshall qualify as an originating good of a Party if: 


(a) the good has a local value content (hereinafterreferred to in this Agreement as “LVC”), calculatedusing the formula set out in Article 27, of not lessthan 40 percent, and the final process of productionhas been performed in the Party; or 


(b) 	all non-originating materials used in the production of the good have undergone in the Party a change intariff classification (hereinafter referred to inthis Agreement as “CTC”) at the 4-digit level (i.e.a change in tariff heading) of Harmonized System. 
Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, “Harmonized System” is that on which theproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2 arebased. 

Each Party shall permit the exporter of the good to decidewhether to use subparagraph (a) or (b) when determining whether the good qualifies as an originating good of the Party. 

2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, a good subject to productspecific rules shall qualify as an originating good if itsatisfies the applicable product specific rules set out in Annex 


2. Where a product specific rule provides a choice of rulesfrom an LVC-based rule of origin, a CTC-based rule of origin,a specific manufacturing or processing operation, or acombination of any of these, each Party shall permit theexporter of the good to decide which rule to use in determiningwhether the good qualifies as an originating good of the Party. 


3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a) and the relevantproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2 which specify a certain LVC, it is required that the LVC of a good, calculated usingthe formula set out in Article 27, is not less than the percentage specified by the rule for the good. 


4. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(b) and the relevantproduct specific rules set out in Annex 2, the rules requiringthat the materials used have undergone CTC, or a specificmanufacturing or processing operation, shall apply only tonon-originating materials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Calculation Of Local Value Content" article_identifier="13238">1. For the purposes of calculating the LVC of a good, thefollowing formula shall be used: 

FOB -VNM

LVC = 	x 100 %

FOB 

2. 	For the purposes of this Article: 


(a) “FOB” is, except as provided for in paragraph 3, thefree-on-board value of a good, inclusive of the costof transport from the producer to the port or site of final shipment abroad; 


(b) 	“LVC” is the LVC of a good, expressed as a percentage;and 


(c) 	“VNM” is the value of non-originating materials used in the production of a good. 
3. 	FOB referred to in subparagraph 2(a) shall be the value: 


(a) adjusted to the first ascertainable price paid fora good from the buyer to the producer of the good,if there is free-on-board value of the good, but itis unknown and cannot be ascertained; or 


(b) determined in accordance with Articles 1 through 8of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if there isno free-on-board value of a good. 
4. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the value ofnon-originating materials used in the production of a good ina Party: 


(a) 	shall be determined in accordance with the Agreement on Customs Valuation and shall include freight,insurance, and where appropriate, packing and allother costs incurred in transporting the materialsto the importation port in the Party where theproducer of the good is located; or 


(b) if such value is unknown and cannot be ascertained,shall be the first ascertainable price paid for thematerials in the Party, but may exclude all the costs incurred in the Party in transporting the materialsfrom the warehouse of the supplier of the materialsto the place where the producer is located such as freight, insurance and packing as well as any otherknown and ascertainable costs incurred in the Party. 

5. For the purposes of paragraph 1, the VNM of a good shallnot include the value of non-originating materials used in theproduction of originating materials of the Party which are used in the production of the good. 


6. For the purposes of subparagraph 3(b) or 4(a), in applying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to determine the value ofa good or non-originating materials, the Agreement on CustomsValuation shall apply, mutatis mutandis, to domestic transactions or to the cases where there is no domestic transaction of the good or non-originating material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="13239">1. A good that does not satisfy the requirements ofsubparagraph 1(b) of Article 26 or an applicable CTC-based rule of origin set out in Annex 2 shall be considered as an originating good of a Party if: 


(a) in the case of a good classified under Chapters 16,19, 20, 22, 23, 28 through 49, and 64 through 97 ofthe Harmonized System, the total value ofnon-originating materials used in the production ofthe good that have not undergone the required CTC does not exceed 10 percent of the FOB; 


(b) in the case of a particular good classified underChapters 9, 18, and 21 of the Harmonized System, thetotal value of non-originating materials used in the production of the good that have not undergone therequired CTC does not exceed 10 percent or sevenpercent of the FOB, as specified in Annex 2; or 


(c) in the case of a good classified under Chapters 50through 63 of the Harmonized System, the weight ofall non-originating materials used in the production of the good that have not undergone the required CTCdoes not exceed 10 percent of the total weight of thegood, 
provided that it meets all other applicable criteria set outin this Chapter for qualifying as an originating good. 

Note: For the purposes of this paragraph, subparagraph 2(a) ofArticle 27 shall apply. 

2. The value of non-originating materials referred to inparagraph 1 shall, however, be included in the value ofnon-originating materials for any applicable LVC-based rule oforigin for the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="13240">Originating materials of a Party used in the productionof a good in the other Party shall be considered as originatingmaterials of that other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="13241">A good shall not be considered to satisfy the requirements of CTC or specific manufacturing or processing operation merely by reason of: 


(a) operations to ensure the preservation of products in good condition during transport and storage (such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine) and other similar operations; 


(b) changes of packaging and breaking up and assembly ofpackages; 


(c) disassembly; 


(d) placing in bottles, cases, and boxes and other simple packaging operations; 


(e) collection of parts and components classified as agood pursuant to Rule 2(a) of the General Rules forthe Interpretation of the Harmonized System; 


(f) mere making-up of sets of articles; or 


(g) any combination of operations referred to insubparagraphs (a) through (f).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Direct Consignment" article_identifier="13242">1. Preferential tariff treatment shall be accorded to an originating good satisfying the requirements of this Chapterand which is consigned directly from the exporting Party to theimporting Party. 


2. The following shall be considered as consigned directlyfrom the exporting Party to the importing Party: 


(a) 	a good transported directly from the exporting Party to the importing Party; or 


(b) a good transported through one or more non-Parties,provided that the good does not undergo operationsother than transit or temporary storage in warehouses, unloading, reloading, and any other operation topreserve it in good condition.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Packing Materials And Containers" article_identifier="13243">1. Packing materials and containers for transportation andshipment of a good shall not be taken into account in determining the origin of any good. 


2. Packing materials and containers in which a good ispackaged for retail sale, when classified together with the good, shall not be taken into account in determining whether all ofthe non-originating materials used in the production of the good have met the applicable CTC-based rule of origin for the good. 


3. If a good is subject to an LVC-based rule of origin, thevalue of the packing materials and containers in which the goodis packaged for retail sale shall be taken into account asoriginating or non-originating materials, as the case may be,in calculating the LVC of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Accessories, Spare Parts, Tools, And Instructional Or Other Information Materials" article_identifier="13244">1. If a good is subject to the requirements of CTC or specific manufacturing or processing operation, the accessories, spare parts, tools, and instructional or other information materials presented with the good shall not be taken into account indetermining whether the good qualifies as an originating good,provided that: 


(a) the accessories, spare parts, tools, andinstructional or other information materials are not invoiced separately from the good; and 


(b) the quantities and value of the accessories, spareparts, tools, and instructional or other information materials are customary for the good. 
2. If a good is subject to an LVC-based rule of origin, thevalue of the accessories, spare parts, tools, and instructional or other information materials shall be taken into account as the value of the originating or non-originating materials, asthe case may be, in calculating the LVC of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="13245">1. Indirect materials shall be treated as originatingmaterials regardless of where they are produced. 


2. For the purposes of this Article, the term “indirectmaterials” means goods used in the production, testing, orinspection of a good but not physically incorporated into thegood, or goods used in the maintenance of buildings or theoperation of equipment associated with the production of a good, including: 


(a) fuel and energy; 


(b) tools, dies, and moulds; 


(c) spare parts and materials used in the maintenance ofequipment and buildings; 


(d) lubricants, greases, compounding materials, andother materials used in production or used to operate equipment and buildings; 


(e) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safetyequipment, and supplies; 


(f) equipment, devices, and supplies used for testing or inspecting the good; 


(g) catalysts and solvents; and 


(h) any other goods that are not incorporated into thegood but whose use in the production of the good canreasonably be demonstrated to be a part of thatproduction.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Identical And Interchangeable Materials" article_identifier="13246">The determination of whether identical and interchangeable materials are originating materials shall bemade by the use of generally accepted accounting principles ofstock control applicable, or those of inventory managementpracticed, in the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Operational Certification Procedures" article_identifier="13247">The operational certification procedures, as set out inAnnex 3, shall apply with respect to procedures regardingcertificate of origin and related matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="13248">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on: 


(i) 	the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 


(ii) 	any amendments to Annex 2 and Attachment to Annex 3, proposed by either Party; and 
(iii) 	the Implementing Regulations referred to inRule 11 of Annex 3; 


(b) considering any other matter related to this Chapter, as the Parties may agree; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-committee shall be composed of representatives of the Governments of the Parties, and may invite representativesof relevant entities other than the Governments of the Parties with necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be discussed, upon agreement of the Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="1612">
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Scope" article_identifier="13249">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures required for the clearance of goods traded between the Parties, topromote the following aspects of the customs procedures: 


(a) transparency; 


(b) simplification and harmonization; and 


(c) cooperation and exchange of information. 
2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties inaccordance with the laws and regulations of each Party andwithin the available resources of their respective customsauthorities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13250">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “customs laws”means such laws and regulations administered and enforced bythe customs authority of each Party concerning the importation, exportation, and transit of goods, as they relate to customsduties, charges, and other taxes, or to prohibitions,restrictions, and other similar controls with respect to themovement of controlled items across the boundary of the customs territory of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13251">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant information ofgeneral application pertaining to its customs laws is readilyavailable to any interested person. 


2. When information that has been made available must be revised due to changes in its customs laws, each Party shallmake the revised information readily available sufficiently in advance of the entry into force of the changes to enableinterested persons to take account of them, unless such anadvance notice is precluded. 


3. At the request of any interested person of the Parties,each Party shall, wherever appropriate, provide, as quickly and as accurately as possible, information relating to the specific customs matters raised by the interested person and pertainingto its customs laws. Each Party shall supply not only theinformation specifically requested but also any other pertinent information which it considers the interested person should bemade aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="13252">1. The Parties shall apply their respective customsprocedures in a predictable, consistent, and transparentmanner. 


2. For prompt customs clearance of goods traded between theParties, each Party shall: 


(a) endeavor to make use of information and communications technology; 


(b) simplify its customs procedures; 


(c) harmonize its customs procedures, as far as possible,with relevant international standards and recommended practices such as those made under the auspices of theCustoms Co-operation Council; and 


(d) promote cooperation, wherever appropriate, betweenits customs authority and: 


(i) other national authorities of the Party; 


(ii) the trading communities of the Party; and 
(iii) the customs authorities of non-Parties. 

3. Each Party shall provide affected parties with easilyaccessible processes of administrative and judicial review ofits administrative actions relating to customs matters.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Goods In Transit" article_identifier="13253">Each Party shall continue to facilitate customs clearanceof goods in transit from or to the other Party in accordancewith paragraph 3 of Article V of the GATT 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Cooperation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="13254">1. The Parties shall cooperate and exchange information witheach other in the field of customs procedures, including theirenforcement against the trafficking of prohibited goods and the importation and exportation of goods suspected of infringingintellectual property rights. 


2. Such cooperation and exchange of information shall beimplemented as provided for in the Implementing Agreement. 


3. Paragraph 3 of Article 6 shall not apply to the exchangeof information under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Sub-Committee On Customs Procedures" article_identifier="13255">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on CustomsProcedures (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established in accordance with Article 

11. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 


(b) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; 


(c) identifying areas, relating to this Chapter, to beimproved for facilitating trade between the Parties;and 


(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties. 


4. The composition of the Sub-Committee shall be specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="1613">
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Scope" article_identifier="13256">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary and phytosanitary (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as "SPS") measures ofthe Parties under the Agreement on the Application of Sanitaryand Phytosanitary Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement(hereinafter referred to in this Agreement as “SPS Agreement”), that may, directly or indirectly, affect trade in goods between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="13257">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations relating to SPS measures under the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="13258">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which is ableto answer all reasonable enquiries from the other Partyregarding SPS measures and, if appropriate, to provide therelevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Sub-Committee On Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="13259">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Sanitary andPhytosanitary Measures (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchange of information on such matters as occurrences of SPS incidents in the Parties and non-Parties, andchange or introduction of SPS-related regulations and standards of the Parties, which may, directly orindirectly, affect trade in goods between the Parties; 


(b) science-based consultations to identify and addressspecific issues that may arise from the applicationof SPS measures with the objective of achievingmutually acceptable solutions; 


(c) consulting on cooperative efforts between the Parties in international fora in relation to SPS measures; 


(d) discussing technical cooperation between the Partieson SPS measures with a view to strengthening it; 


(e) reviewing the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 


(f) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; and 


(g) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of governmentofficials of the Parties with responsibility for SPS measures. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties. 


5. The Sub-Committee may, if necessary, establish ad hoctechnical working groups as its subsidiary bodies relating toa specific area of SPS measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="13260">Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Technical Regulations, Standards, And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="1614">
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Objectives" article_identifier="13261">The objectives of this Chapter are to promote trade between the Parties by: 


(a) ensuring that technical regulations, standards, andconformity assessment procedures do not createunnecessary obstacles to trade; 


(b) promoting mutual understanding of the technicalregulations, standards, and conformity assessmentprocedures in each Party; 


(c) strengthening information exchange and cooperationbetween the Parties in relation to the preparation,adoption, and application of technical regulations,standards, and conformity assessment procedures; 


(d) strengthening cooperation between the Parties atinternational and regional fora on the work relatedto standardization and conformity assessments; and 


(e) providing a framework to realize these objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="Scope" article_identifier="13262">1. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations,standards, and conformity assessment procedures as defined inthe Agreement on Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A to theWTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “TBTAgreement”). 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to purchasing specificationsprepared by governmental bodies for production or consumptionrequirements of governmental bodies and sanitary andphytosanitary measures as defined in Annex A of the SPSAgreement. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall limit the right of a Partyto prepare, adopt, and apply technical regulations andstandards, to the extent necessary, to fulfill a legitimateobjective. Such legitimate objectives are, inter alia, national security requirements; the prevention of deceptive practices;and protection of human health or safety, animal or plant lifeor health, or the environment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="13263">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations relating to technical regulations, standards, and conformity assessment procedures under the TBT Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="13264">1. For the purposes of ensuring that technical regulations,standards, and conformity assessment procedures do not createunnecessary obstacles to trade in goods between the Parties,the Parties shall, where possible, cooperate in the field oftechnical regulations, standards, and conformity assessmentprocedures. 


2. The forms of cooperation pursuant to paragraph 1 mayinclude the following: 


(a) conducting joint studies and holding seminars, inorder to enhance mutual understanding of technicalregulations, standards, and conformity assessmentprocedures in each Party; 


(b) exchanging government officials of the Parties fortraining purposes; 


(c) exchanging information on technical regulations,standards, and conformity assessment procedures; 


(d) contributing, where appropriate, jointly to theactivities related to technical regulations,standards, and conformity assessment procedures ininternational and regional fora; 


(e) encouraging the bodies responsible for technicalregulations, standards, and conformity assessmentprocedures in each Party to cooperate on matters ofmutual interest; and 


(f) enhancing participation in the existing framework for mutual recognition established under internationalagreements or developed by relevant international and regional bodies. 

3. The implementation of this Article shall be subject to theavailability of appropriated funds and the applicable laws andregulations of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="13265">1. Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which shallhave the responsibility to coordinate the implementation ofthis Chapter. 


2. Each Party shall provide the other Party with the name ofits designated enquiry point and the contact details of relevant officials in that organization including information ontelephone, facsimile, e-mail, and other relevant details. 


3. Each Party shall notify the other Party promptly of anychange of its enquiry point or any amendments to the information of the relevant officials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards, And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="13266">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on TechnicalRegulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment Procedures(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) coordinating cooperation pursuant to Article 53; 


(b) identifying mutually agreed priority sectors forenhanced cooperation, including giving favorableconsideration to any proposal made by either Party; 


(c) establishing work programs in mutually agreedpriority areas to facilitate the acceptance ofconformity assessment results of the other Party andequivalence of technical regulations; 


(d) monitoring the progress of work programs; 


(e) reviewing the implementation and operation of thisChapter; 


(f) facilitating technical consultations; 


(g) reporting, where appropriate, its findings to theJoint Committee; and 


(h) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of representatives of the Governments of theParties; and 


(b) co-chaired by officials of the Governments of theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="13267">Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="1615">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Scope" article_identifier="13268">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures by a Party affectingtrade in services. 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to: 


(a) in respect of air transport services, measuresaffecting traffic rights, however granted; or tomeasures affecting services directly related to theexercise of traffic rights, other than measuresaffecting: 


(i) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 


(ii) the selling and marketing of air transportservices; and 
(iii) computer reservation system services; 


(b) cabotage in maritime transport services; 


(c) measures pursuant to immigration laws and
regulations; 



(d) measures affecting natural persons of a Party seekingaccess to employment market of the other Party, normeasures regarding nationality, or residence oremployment on a permanent basis; and 


(e) government procurement. 

3. Annex 4 provides supplementary provisions to this Chapteron financial services, including scope and definitions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13269">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “aircraft repair and maintenance services” means such activities when undertaken on an aircraft or a partthereof while it is withdrawn from service and does not include so-called line maintenance; 


(b) “commercial presence” means any type of business orprofessional establishment, including through: 


(i) the constitution, acquisition, or maintenance of a juridical person; or 


(ii) the creation or maintenance of a branch or a representative office, 
  within the Area of a Party for the purposes of supplying a service; 


(c) “computer reservation system services” means services provided by computerized systems that containinformation about air carriers’ schedules,availability, fares and fare rules, through whichreservations can be made or tickets may be issued; 


(d) “juridical person” means any legal entity dulyconstituted or otherwise organized under applicablelaw, whether for profit or otherwise, and whetherprivately-owned or governmentally-owned, includingany corporation, trust, partnership, joint venture,sole proprietorship, or association; 


(e) “juridical person of the other Party” means ajuridical person which is either: 


(i) constituted or otherwise organized under the lawof the other Party and is engaged in substantivebusiness operations in the Area of the otherParty; or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service throughcommercial presence, owned or controlled by: 


(A) natural persons of the other Party; or 


(B) juridical persons of the other Partyidentified under subparagraph (i); 

(f) a juridical person is: 


(i) “owned” by persons of a Party or persons of anon-Party if more than 50 percent of the equityinterest in it is beneficially owned either bythe former persons or by the latter persons; 


(ii) “controlled” by persons of a Party or persons ofa non-Party if either the former persons or thelatter persons have the power to name a majorityof its directors or otherwise to legally directits actions; and 
(iii) “affiliated” with another person when it controls, or is controlled by, that other person; or whenit and the other person are both controlled bythe same person; 


(g) “measure” means any measure, whether in the form ofa law, regulation, rule, procedure, decision,administrative action or any other form; 

  Note: “measure” shall include taxation measures to the extent covered by the GATS. 

(h) “measures by a Party” means any measures taken by: 


(i) the central or local governments or authoritiesof a Party; and 


(ii) non-governmental bodies in the exercise of powers delegated by the central or local governments orauthorities of a Party; 


(i) “measures by a Party affecting trade in services”includes measures in respect of: 


(i) the purchase, payment, or use of a service; 


(ii) the access to and use of, in connection with the supply of a service, services which are requiredby the Party to be offered to the public generally; and 
(iii) the presence, including commercial presence, ofpersons of the other Party for the supply of aservice in the Area of the former Party; 


(j) “monopoly supplier of a service” means any person,public or private, which in the relevant market of theArea of a Party is authorized or established formallyor in effect by that Party as the sole supplier of that service; 


(k) “natural person of the other Party” means a naturalperson who resides in the other Party or elsewhere,and who is a national of the other Party under the lawof the other Party; 


(l) "person" means either a natural person or a juridicalperson; 


(m) “sector” of a service means: 


(i) with reference to a specific commitment,one or more, or all, sub-sectors of that service,as specified in a Party’s Schedule of SpecificCommitments in Annex 5; or 


(ii) otherwise, the whole of that service sector,including all of its sub-sectors; 


(n) “service” includes any service in any sector excepta service supplied in the exercise of governmentalauthority; 


(o) “service consumer” means any person that receives oruses a service; 


(p) “service of the other Party” means a service which issupplied: 


(i) from or in the Area of the other Party, or in thecase of maritime transport, by a vessel registered under the laws of the other Party, or by a personof the other Party which supplies the servicethrough the operation of a vessel or its use inwhole or in part; or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service throughcommercial presence or through the presence ofnatural persons, by a service supplier of theother Party; 


(q) “service supplied in the exercise of governmentalauthority” means any service which is supplied neither on a commercial basis nor in competition with one or more service suppliers; 


(r) “service supplier” means any person that supplies aservice; 
Note: Where the service is not supplied directly by a juridical person but through other forms ofcommercial presence such as a branch or arepresentative office, the service supplier

(i.e. the juridical person) shall, nonetheless, through such presence be accorded the treatment provided for service suppliers under thisChapter. Such treatment shall be extended to the presence through which the service is suppliedand need not be extended to any other parts ofthe supplier located outside the Area of a Party where the service is supplied. 


(s) “supply of a service” includes the production,distribution, marketing, sale, and delivery of aservice; 


(t) “the selling and marketing of air transport services”means opportunities for the air carrier concerned tosell and market freely its air transport servicesincluding all aspects of marketing such as marketresearch, advertising, and distribution. These activities do not include the pricing of air transport services nor the applicable conditions; 


(u) “trade in services” means the supply of services: 


(i) from the Area of a Party into the Area of the other Party (“cross-border supply mode”); 


(ii) in the Area of a Party to the service consumerof the other Party (“consumption abroad mode”); 
(iii) by a service supplier of a Party, throughcommercial presence in the Area of the other Party (“commercial presence mode”); and 


(iv) by a service supplier of a Party, through presence of natural persons of that Party in the Area ofthe other Party (“presence of natural personsmode”); and 


(v) “traffic rights” means the rights for scheduled andnon-scheduled services to operate and/or to carrypassengers, cargo and mail for remuneration or hirefrom, to, within, or over a Party, including pointsto be served, routes to be operated, types of trafficto be carried, capacity to be provided, tariffs to becharged and their conditions, and criteria fordesignation of airlines, including such criteria asnumber, ownership, and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Market Access" article_identifier="13270">1. With respect to market access through the modes of supplydefined in paragraph (u) of Article 58, each Party shall accordservices and service suppliers of the other Party treatment noless favorable than that provided for under the terms,limitations and conditions agreed and specified in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 5. 

 Note: If a Party undertakes a market-access commitment in relation to the supply of a service through the modeof supply referred to in subparagraph (u)(i) ofArticle 58 and if the cross-border movement of capital is an essential part of the service itself,that Party is thereby committed to allow suchmovement of capital. If a Party undertakes a market-access commitment in relation to the supplyof a service through the mode of supply referred toin subparagraph (u)(iii) of Article 58, it is thereby committed to allow related transfers of capital into its Area. 

2. In sectors where market-access commitments are undertaken, the measures which a Party shall not maintain or adopt eitheron the basis of a regional subdivision or on the basis of itsentire Area, unless otherwise specified in its Schedule ofSpecific Commitments in Annex 5, are defined as: 


(a) limitations on the number of service suppliers whether in the form of numerical quotas, monopolies, exclusive service suppliers, or the requirements of an economicneeds test; 


(b) limitations on the total value of service transactions or assets in the form of numerical quotas or therequirement of an economic needs test; 


(c) limitations on the total number of service operationsor on the total quantity of service output expressedin terms of designated numerical units in the form ofquotas or the requirement of an economic needs test; 

  Note: This subparagraph does not cover measures of a Party which limit inputs for the supply ofservices. 

(d) limitations on the total number of natural personsthat may be employed in a particular service sectoror that a service supplier may employ and who arenecessary for, and directly related to, the supply ofa specific service in the form of numerical quotas orthe requirement of an economic needs test; 


(e) measures which restrict or require specific types oflegal entity or joint venture through which a servicesupplier may supply a service; and 


(f) limitations on the participation of foreign capitalin terms of maximum percentage limit on foreignshareholding or the total value of individual oraggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13271">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of SpecificCommitments in Annex 5, and subject to any conditions andqualifications set out therein, each Party shall accord toservices and service suppliers of the other Party, in respectof all measures affecting the supply of services, treatment noless favorable than that it accords to its own like services and service suppliers. 

Note: Specific commitments assumed under this Article shall not be construed to require either Party to compensate for anyinherent competitive disadvantages which result from theforeign character of the relevant services or servicesuppliers. 

2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 by according to services and service suppliers of the other Party, eitherformally identical treatment or formally different treatmentto that it accords to its own like services and service suppliers. 


3. Formally identical or formally different treatment shallbe considered to be less favorable if it modifies the conditions of competition in favor of services or service suppliers of theParty compared to like services or service suppliers of theother Party. 


4. A Party shall not invoke the preceding paragraphs underChapter 13 with respect to a measure of the other Party thatfalls within the scope of an international agreement betweenthe Parties relating to the avoidance of double taxation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Additional Commitments" article_identifier="13272">The Parties may negotiate commitments with respect tomeasures affecting trade in services not subject to schedulingunder Articles 59 and 60, including those regardingqualifications, standards, or licensing matters. Suchcommitments shall be inscribed in a Party’s Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Schedule Of Specific Commitments" article_identifier="13273">1. Each Party shall set out in its Schedule the specificcommitments it undertakes under Articles 59, 60, and 61. With respect to sectors or sub-sectors where such specificcommitments are undertaken, the Party’s Schedule of SpecificCommitments in Annex 5 shall specify: 


(a) terms, limitations and conditions on market access; 


(b) conditions and qualifications on national treatment; 


(c) undertakings relating to additional commitments; and 


(d) where appropriate, the time-frame for implementationof such commitments. 
2. Measures inconsistent with both Articles 59 and 60 shall be inscribed in the column relating to Article 59.  In this case the inscription will be considered to provide a condition orqualification to Article 60 as well.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="13274">1. Unless otherwise specified in Annex 6, each Party shallaccord to services and service suppliers of the other Partytreatment no less favorable than that it accords to like services and service suppliers of any non-Party. 


2. Treatment granted under other agreements concluded by aParty and notified under Article V or Article V bis of the GATS shall not be subject to paragraph 1. 


3. If, after this Agreement enters into force, a Partyconcludes or amends an agreement of the type referred to inparagraph 2 with a non-Party, it shall provide the other Partyan opportunity to consult on the possibility of accordingtreatment no less favorable than that granted to services andservice suppliers of the non-Party under that agreement to like services and service suppliers of that other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Modification Of Schedules" article_identifier="13275">1. Any modification or withdrawal of specific commitments ontrade in services shall be made in accordance with paragraph1 of Article 127. In the negotiations for such modification orwithdrawal, the Parties shall endeavor, in line withsubparagraph 2(a) of Article XXI of the GATS, to maintain ageneral level of mutually advantageous commitments not lessfavorable to trade than that provided for in their Schedulesof Specific Commitments in Annex 5 prior to such negotiations. 


2. With regard to the same commitment that appears in a Party’sSchedule of Specific Commitments under both the GATS and thisAgreement, if modification or withdrawal has been made to suchcommitment with regard to its Schedule of Specific Commitmentsunder the GATS and compensatory adjustment has been made to theother Party as an “affected Member” in accordance with ArticleXXI of the GATS, the Parties shall agree to amend this Agreement to incorporate such modification or withdrawal into it withoutfurther negotiation, subject to their applicable domesticprocedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Qualifications, Technical Standards, And Licensing" article_identifier="13276">With a view to ensuring that measures by a Party relatingto qualification requirements and procedures, technicalstandards, and licensing requirements of service suppliers ofthe other Party do not constitute unnecessary barriers to trade in services, each Party shall endeavor to ensure that suchmeasures: 


(a) are based on objective and transparent criteria, suchas competence and the ability to supply the service; 


(b) are not more burdensome than necessary to ensure thequality of the service; and 


(c) in the case of licensing procedures, are not inthemselves a restriction on the supply of the service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Recognition" article_identifier="13277">1. A Party may recognize the education or experience obtained, requirements met, or licenses or certifications granted in theother Party for the purposes of the fulfillment, in whole orin part, of its standards or criteria for the authorization,licensing, or certification of service suppliers of the otherParty. 


2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1, which may beachieved through harmonization or otherwise, may be based uponan agreement or arrangement between the Parties or may beaccorded unilaterally. 


3. Where a Party recognizes, by agreement or arrangementbetween the Party and a non-Party or unilaterally, the education or experience obtained, requirements met, or licenses orcertifications granted in the non-Party: 


(a) nothing in Article 63 shall be construed to requirethe Party to accord such recognition to the educationor experience obtained, requirements met, or licenses or certifications granted in the other Party; 


(b) the Party shall accord the other Party an adequateopportunity to negotiate the accession of that otherParty to such an agreement or arrangement or tonegotiate comparable ones with it between the Parties; and 


(c) where the Party accords such recognitionunilaterally, the Party shall accord the other Partyan adequate opportunity to demonstrate that theeducation or experience obtained, requirements met,or licenses or certifications granted in the otherParty should also be recognized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="13278">1. Each Party shall ensure that any monopoly supplier of aservice in its Area does not, in the supply of the monopolyservice in the relevant market, act in a manner inconsistentwith the Party’s commitments under this Chapter. 


2. Where a Party’s monopoly supplier competes, eitherdirectly or through an affiliated juridical person, in thesupply of a service outside the scope of its monopoly rightsand which is subject to that Party’s specific commitments, theParty shall ensure that such a supplier does not abuse itsmonopoly position to act in the Area of the Party in a mannerinconsistent with such commitments. 


3. If a Party has a reason to believe that a monopoly supplierof a service of the other Party is acting in a manner inconsistent with paragraph 1 or 2, it may request the other Party to provide specific information concerning the relevant operations. 


4. The provisions of this Article shall also apply to casesof exclusive service suppliers, where a Party, formally or ineffect: 


(a) authorizes or establishes a small number of service suppliers; and 


(b) substantially prevents competition among thosesuppliers in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="13279">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article 69, a Party shall not apply restrictions on international transfers and payments for current transactions relating to its specificcommitments. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights andobligations of the Parties as members of the InternationalMonetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of theInternational Monetary Fund, including the use of exchangeactions which are in conformity with the Articles of Agreementof the International Monetary Fund, provided that a Party shall not impose restrictions on any capital transactionsinconsistently with its specific commitments under this Chapter regarding such transactions, except under Article 69, or at the request of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="13280">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and externalfinancial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party may adopt ormaintain restrictions on trade in services on which it has undertaken specific commitments, including on payments ortransfers for transactions related to such commitments. It is recognized that particular pressure on the balance of paymentsof a Party in the process of economic development or economictransition may necessitate the use of restrictions to ensure,inter alia, the maintenance of a level of financial reservesadequate for the implementation of its program of economicdevelopment or economic transition. 


2. The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1: 


(a) shall ensure that the other Party is treated asfavorably as any non-Party; 


(b) shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement ofthe International Monetary Fund; 


(c) shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,economic, and financial interests of the other Party; 


(d) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with thecircumstances described in paragraph 1; and 


(e) shall be temporary and be phased out progressively asthe situation specified in paragraph 1 improves. 

3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a Party may give priority to the supply of services which are moreessential to its economic or development programs. However,such restrictions shall not be adopted or maintained for thepurpose of protecting a particular service sector. 


4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under paragraph 1,or any changes therein, shall be promptly notified to the otherParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="13281">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a servicesupplier that is a juridical person, where the denying Partyestablishes that the juridical person is owned or controlledby persons of a non-Party, and that denying Party: 


(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with thatnon-Party; or 


(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to thatnon-Party that prohibit transactions with thejuridical person or that would be violated orcircumvented if the benefits of this Chapter wereaccorded to the juridical person. 
2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, a Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a service supplier that is a juridical person, if the denying Party establishes thatthe juridical person is not a service supplier of the otherParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Services" article_identifier="13282">1. For the purposes of effective implementation and operation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Trade in Services(hereinafter referred to in this Article as "theSub-Committee") shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing commitments, with respect to measuresaffecting trade in services in this Chapter, with aview to achieving further liberalization on a mutuallyadvantageous basis and securing an overall balance ofrights and obligations; 


(b) reviewing and monitoring the implementation andoperation of this Chapter; 


(c) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; and 


(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of representatives of the Governments of theParties and may invite representatives of relevantentities other than the Governments of the Parties with necessary expertise relevant to the issues to bediscussed; and 


(b) co-chaired by officials of the Governments of theParties. 

4. The working group on financial services (hereinafterreferred to in this Article as “the Working Group”) shall beestablished under the Sub-Committee. The details and procedures of the Working Group shall be specified in Annex 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Review Of Commitments" article_identifier="13283">1. The Parties shall review commitments on trade in services within five years from the date of entry into force of thisAgreement, with the aim of improving the overall level ofcommitments undertaken by the Parties under this Chapter. 


2. In reviewing their commitments pursuant to paragraph 1, the Parties shall take into account the principles in paragraph 1 of Article IV and paragraph 2 of Article XIX of the GATS.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Emergency Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="13284">In the event that the implementation of this Agreementcauses substantial adverse impact to a Party in a specificservice sector, the Party may request consultations with theother Party for the purposes of taking appropriate measures toaddress such adverse impact. In such consultations, the Parties shall take into account the circumstances of the particular case and the result of the multilateral negotiations pursuant toArticle X of the GATS if the said negotiations have beenconcluded at the time of such consultations.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="1616">
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Scope" article_identifier="13285">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting themovement of natural persons of a Party who enter the other Party and fall under one of the categories referred to in Annex 7. 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting natural persons of a Party seeking access to employment market of theother Party, nor measures regarding nationality, or residenceor employment on a permanent basis. 


3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applyingmeasures to regulate the entry of natural persons of the otherParty into, or their temporary stay in, the former Party,including those measures necessary to protect the integrity of, and to ensure the orderly movement of natural persons across,its borders, provided that such measures are not applied in such a manner as to nullify or impair the benefits accruing to theother Party under the terms of specific commitments underArticle 76. 
 Note: The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural persons of the other Party and not for those of certainnon-Parties shall not be regarded as nullifying orimpairing benefits under specific commitments under Article 76.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13286">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “natural person of a Party” means a natural person who resides in a Party orelsewhere and who under the law of the Party is a national of the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Specific Commitments" article_identifier="13287">1. Each Party shall grant entry and temporary stay to natural persons of the other Party in accordance with this Chapterincluding the terms of the categories in Annex 7, provided thatthe natural persons comply with the laws and regulations of theformer Party related to movement of natural persons applicableto entry and temporary stay which are not inconsistent with theprovisions of this Chapter. 


2. Neither Party shall impose or maintain any limitations onthe number of granting entry and temporary stay under paragraph 1, unless otherwise specified in Annex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Requirements And Procedures" article_identifier="13288">1. Each Party shall publish or otherwise make available tothe other Party on the date of entry into force of this Agreement, with respect to natural persons covered by that Party’s specific commitments under Article 76, information on requirements andprocedures necessary for an effective application by naturalpersons of the other Party for the grant of entry into, initialtemporary stay in or renewal thereof, and, where applicable,permission to work in, and a change of status of temporary stayin, the former Party. 


2. Each Party shall endeavor to provide, upon request by anatural person of the other Party, information on requirementsand procedures referred to in paragraph 1. 


3. Each Party shall endeavor to promptly inform the otherParty of the introduction of any new requirements and procedures, or changes in any existing requirements and procedures referred to in paragraph 1 that affect the effective application bynatural persons of the other Party for the grant of entry into,initial temporary stay in or renewal thereof, and, whereapplicable, permission to work in, and a change of status oftemporary stay in, the former Party. 


4. Each Party shall ensure that fees charged by its competent authorities on application referred to in paragraph 1 do notin themselves represent an unjustifiable impediment to movement of natural persons of the other Party under this Chapter. 


5. Each Party shall endeavor, to the maximum extent possible, to take measures to simplify the requirements and to facilitate and expedite the procedures relating to the movement of natural persons of the other Party within the framework of its laws andregulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Sub-Committee On Movement Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="13289">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Movement ofNatural Persons (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

11. 

2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation andoperation of this Chapter; 


(b) discussing any issues related to this Chapter,including the subjects of further negotiationsreferred to in Annex 7; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to theJoint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee in accordance with Article 11.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="13290">The Parties shall, after the date of the entry into forceof this Agreement, enter into negotiations in accordance withAnnex 7.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="1617">
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="13291">1. The Parties shall grant and ensure adequate, effective, and non-discriminatory protection of intellectual property,promote efficiency and transparency in the administration ofintellectual property protection system, and provide formeasures for adequate and effective enforcement of intellectual property rights against infringement, counterfeiting, andpiracy, in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter andthe international agreements to which both Parties are parties. 


2. The Parties, recognizing the growing importance ofprotection of intellectual property in further promoting trade and investment between the Parties, in accordance with theirrespective laws and regulations and subject to their availableresources, shall cooperate in the field of intellectualproperty. 


3. Intellectual property referred to in this Chapter shallmean all categories of intellectual property: 


(a) that are subject of Articles 86 through 92; and/or 


(b) that are under the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspectsof Intellectual Property Rights in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as“the TRIPS Agreement”) and/or the relevantinternational agreements referred to in the TRIPSAgreement. 

4. The Parties reaffirm their commitment to comply with theobligations set out in the international agreements relatingto intellectual property to which both Parties are parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="13292">Each Party shall accord to nationals of the other Partytreatment no less favorable than the treatment it accords to its own nationals with regard to the protection of intellectual property in accordance with Articles 3 and 5 of the TRIPSAgreement. 

Note: For the purposes of Articles 81 and 82, “nationals” shall have the same meaning as in the TRIPS Agreement, and "protection" shall include matters affectingthe availability, acquisition, scope, maintenance,and enforcement of intellectual property rights aswell as those matters affecting the use ofintellectual property rights specificallyaddressed in this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="13293">Each Party shall accord to nationals of the other Partytreatment no less favorable than the treatment it accords to the nationals of a non-Party with regard to the protection ofintellectual property in accordance with Articles 4 and 5 ofthe TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Streamlining And Harmonization Of Procedural Matters" article_identifier="13294">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administration ofintellectual property protection system, each Party shall take appropriate measures to streamline its administrativeprocedures concerning intellectual property. 


2. Neither Party may require the authentication of signatures or other means of self-identification on documents to be submitted to the competent authority of the Party, includingapplications, translations into a language accepted by suchauthority of any earlier application whose priority is claimed, powers of attorney, and certifications of assignment, in thecourse of application procedure or other administrativeprocedures on patents, utility models, industrial designs, ortrademarks. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, a Party may require: 


(a) the authentication of signatures or other means ofself-identification, if the law of the Party soprovides, where the signatures or other means ofself-identification concern the change in ownershipof a patent or a registration of utility models,industrial designs, or trademarks; and 


(b) the submission of evidence if there is a reasonable doubt as to the authenticity of the signature or othermeans of self-identification on documents submitted to the competent authority of the Party. Where thecompetent authority notifies the person that thesubmission of evidence is required, the notificationshall state the reason for doubting the authenticityof the signature or other means ofself-identification. 

4. Neither Party may require the certification, by any partyother than the applicant or his or her representatives, of theaccuracy of a translation of an earlier application whosepriority is claimed. 


5. Each Party shall introduce and implement a system in whicha power of attorney for application procedures or otheradministrative procedures on patents, utility models,industrial designs, or trademarks before the competentauthority of the Party may relate to one or more applicationsand/or grants or registrations identified in the power ofattorney or, subject to any exception indicated by theappointing person, to all existing and future applicationsand/or grants or registrations of that person. 


6. The applications for and grants of patents and publications thereof shall be classified in accordance with the international patent classification system established underthe Strasbourg Agreement Concerning the International PatentClassification of March 24, 1971, as amended. The applicationsfor registrations of, and registrations of, trademarks forgoods and services and publication thereof shall be classifiedin accordance with the international classification system ofgoods and services established under the Nice AgreementConcerning the International Classification of Goods andServices for the Purposes of the Registration of Marks, of June15, 1957, as revised and amended. 


7. Each Party shall endeavor to improve patent attorney system with a view to further facilitating acquisition and utilization of rights to patents, utility models, industrial designs andtrademarks.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Transparency" article_identifier="13295">For the purposes of further promoting transparency inadministration of intellectual property protection system,each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and regulations: 


(a) take appropriate measures to publish information atleast on applications for and grants of patents,registrations of utility models and industrialdesigns, registrations of trademarks and applicationtherefor, and registration of new varieties of plantsand application therefor; 


(b) endeavor to make available to the interested partiesofficial information contained in the dossiers in connection with matters provided for in paragraph (a); 


(c) endeavor to make easily available to the publicinformation on intellectual property protectionsystem, including information on its efforts toprovide effective enforcement of intellectualproperty rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="13296">The Parties shall take appropriate measures to enhancepublic awareness of protection of intellectual propertyincluding educational and dissemination projects on the use ofintellectual property as well as on the enforcement ofintellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Patents" article_identifier="13297">1. Each Party shall ensure that any application for a patentis not rejected solely on the ground that the subject matterclaimed in the application is related to a computer program. 


2. The provisions of paragraph 1 shall not prejudice thepatentability of computer programs as such which shall bedetermined in accordance with the laws and regulations of eachParty. 


3. Each Party shall ensure that, if an invention claimed inthe application for a patent is being worked by any person other than the applicant for the patent in that person’s businessafter the publication of the application, that person or theapplicant for the patent may file a request to the competentauthority of the Party that the application be examined inadvance of other applications, in accordance with its laws andregulations. In this case, the competent authority of the Party may require the applicant for the patent or the person who filed the request to furnish a proof that the invention is being worked, a result of prior art search in relation to the application,or a copy of the final decision by the administrative authorityfor patents of the other Party or of a non-Party on an application, which the applicant has filed in the other Party or in thenon-Party, of an invention that is the same or substantially the same with the invention claimed in the application at issue. Where such a request has been filed, the competent authorityof the Party shall take the request into consideration andendeavor to examine the application in advance of otherapplications, where appropriate. 


4. Each Party shall ensure that a patent owner may file arequest for correction of the description, the scope of theclaims, or the drawings, that are attached to the application,to the administrative authority for patents for the purpose ofrestricting the scope of the claims.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="13298">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective protectionof industrial designs in accordance with Articles 25 and 26 ofthe TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="13299">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective protectionof trademarks in accordance with Articles 15 through 21 of theTRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Copyright And Related Rights" article_identifier="13300">1. Each Party shall ensure effective protection of copyrightand related rights in accordance with its laws and regulationsand international agreements to which it is a party. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that its laws and regulations beimplemented with appropriate legal remedies in order to protect copyright and related rights in the digital environment. 


3. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, take appropriate measures to promote thedevelopment of the collective management organizations forcopyright and related rights in that Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="New Varieties Of Plants" article_identifier="13301">Each Party recognizes the importance of providing a system of protection of new varieties of plants and shall endeavor toprovide for the protection of all plant genera and species asearly as practicable in accordance with the 1991 Act of theInternational Convention for the Protection of New Varieties of Plants.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Geographical Indications" article_identifier="13302">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective protectionof geographical indications in accordance with its laws andregulations and with the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="13303">1. Each Party shall provide for effective protection againstacts of unfair competition. 


2. Any act of competition contrary to honest practices inindustrial or commercial matters constitutes an act of unfair competition. 


3. The following acts, in particular, shall be prohibited asacts of unfair competition: 


(a) all acts of such a nature as to create confusion byany means whatever with the establishment, the goods,or the industrial or commercial activities, of acompetitor; 


(b) false allegations in the course of trade of such anature as to discredit the establishment, the goods,or the industrial or commercial activities, of acompetitor; 


(c) indications or allegations the use of which in thecourse of trade is liable to mislead the public as tothe nature, the characteristics, the suitability fortheir purpose, or the quantity, of the goods or theservices, or the manufacturing process of the goods; 


(d) acts of acquiring or holding the right to use or usinga domain name identical with or confusingly similarto a protected trade name and trademark of anotherperson, for the purposes specified in the laws andregulations of each Party, such as with the intentionto gain an unfair profit or the intention to causedamage to that other person. 

4. Each Party shall ensure in its laws and regulationsadequate and effective protection of undisclosed informationin accordance with Article 39 of the TRIPS Agreement. 


5. Each Party shall establish appropriate remedies to prevent or punish acts of unfair competition. In particular, each Party shall ensure that any person that considers its businessinterests to be affected by an act of unfair competition maybring legal action and request suspension or prevention of theact, destruction of the goods which constitute the act, removal of materials and implements used for the act, or damages tocompensate for the injury which result from the act, unlessotherwise provided for in the laws and regulations of the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Enforcement – Border Measures" article_identifier="13304">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective enforcement of border measures in accordance with Articles 51 through 60of the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="Enforcement – Civil Remedies" article_identifier="13305">1. Each Party shall ensure that the right holder ofintellectual property has the right to claim against theinfringer damages adequate to compensate for the injury theright holder has suffered because of an infringement of thatperson’s intellectual property right by an infringer whoknowingly, or with reasonable grounds to know, engaged ininfringing activity. 


2. In cases where it is extremely difficult for the rightholder of intellectual property to prove the actual economicharm due to the nature of facts concerned, each Party shallensure, to the extent possible in accordance with its laws andregulations, that its judicial authorities have the authorityto determine the amount of damages based on the totality of theevidence presented to them. 


3. Each Party shall endeavor, as necessary, to take necessary measures to improve its judicial system with a view to providing effective civil remedies against infringement of intellectualproperty rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Enforcement – Criminal Remedies" article_identifier="13306">Each Party shall ensure that criminal procedures andpenalties be applied in accordance with Article 61 of the TRIPSAgreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="13307">1. The Parties shall cooperate in the field of intellectualproperty in accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 80. 


2. Areas and forms of cooperation under this Article shallbe set forth in the Implementing Agreement. 


3. Costs of cooperation under this Article shall be borne inas equitable a manner as possible. 


4. Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Sub-Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="13308">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on IntellectualProperty (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation andoperation of this Chapter; 


(b) discussing any issues related to intellectualproperty with a view to enhancing protection ofintellectual property and enforcement of intellectual property rights and to promoting efficient andtransparent administration of intellectual propertyprotection system, such as: 


(i) issues on patents; 


(ii) issues on industrial designs; 
(iii) issues on trademarks; 


(iv) issues on liability of internet serviceproviders; 


(v) issues on unfair competition; 


(vi) issues on border measures; 
(vii) issues on geographical indications; and 

(viii) issues on administrative remedies; 


(c) reporting the findings and the outcome of discussionsof the Sub-Committee to the Joint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated bythe Joint Committee in accordance with Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) composed of representatives of the Governments of theParties; and 


(b) co-chaired by officials of the Governments.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="13309">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article 73 of the TRIPSAgreement is incorporated into and forms part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="1618">
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Promotion Of Competition By Addressing Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="13310">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, promote competition by addressinganti-competitive activities in order to facilitate theefficient functioning of its market. Any measure taken for such purposes shall be taken in conformity with the principles oftransparency, non-discrimination, and procedural fairness.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Definitions" article_identifier="13311">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term: 


(a) “anti-competitive activities” means any conduct ortransaction that may be subject to penalties or reliefunder the competition law of either Party; and 


(b) “competition law” means: 


(i) for Japan, the Law Concerning Prohibition ofPrivate Monopoly and Maintenance of Fair Trade(Law No. 54, 1947) and its implementingregulations as well as any amendments thereto; and 


(ii) for Viet Nam, the Competition Law (Law No.27/2004/QH11) and its implementing regulations as well as any amendments thereto.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Cooperation On Promoting Competition By Addressing Anti-Competitive Activities" article_identifier="13312">The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective laws and regulations, cooperate in the field of promotingcompetition by addressing anti-competitive activities subjectto their respective available resources, with a view tocontributing to the effective enforcement of the competitionlaw of each Party and to avoiding or lessening the possibilityof conflicts between the Governments of the Parties in all matters pertaining to the application of the competition lawof each Party. Such cooperation may take the form of exchangeof information, notification and coordination of enforcementactivities, and consultation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Technical Cooperation" article_identifier="13313">The Parties agree that it is in their common interest forthe competition authorities of the Parties to work together intechnical cooperation activities related to strengthening ofcompetition policy and implementation of the competition lawof each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Non-Application Of Paragraph 3 Of Article 6 And Chapter 13" article_identifier="13314">Paragraph 3 of Article 6 and Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="13315">1. Detailed arrangements to implement this Chapter may be made between the competition authorities of the Parties. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prevent the Parties fromseeking or providing assistance to one another pursuant to other bilateral or multilateral agreements or arrangements. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prejudicethe policy or legal position of either Party regarding anyissues related to jurisdiction. 


4. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to affect therights and obligations of either Party under otherinternational agreements or arrangements or under its laws.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Improvement Of The Business Environment" chapter_identifier="1619">
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="13316">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations, take appropriate measures to further improve thebusiness environment for the persons of the other Partyconducting their business activities in the former Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Government Procurement" article_identifier="13317">Recognizing the importance of enhancing efficiency of itsgovernment procurement in improving the business environmentin the Party, each Party, subject to its laws and regulations,policies, and practices on government procurement shallendeavor to: 


(a) enhance transparency of the measures regardinggovernment procurement; and 


(b) implement in a fair and effective manner the measuresregarding government procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Sub-Committee On Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="13318">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Improvement ofthe Business Environment (hereinafter referred to in thisChapter as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuantto Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing findings reported by a Liaison Office onImprovement of the Business Environment (hereinafterreferred to in this Chapter as the “Liaison Office”)to be designated by each Party under Article 109; 


(b) addressing and seeking ways to resolve issues relatedto the business environment on its own initiative or based on the findings reported by the Liaison Office; 


(c) reporting its findings and making recommendations,including those on measures that should be taken bythe Parties, to the Parties; 


(d) reviewing, where appropriate, the measures taken bythe Parties in relation to such recommendations referred to in subparagraph (c); 


(e) making available to the public, in an appropriatemanner, the recommendations referred to insubparagraph (c) and the results of the reviewreferred to in subparagraph (d); 


(f) reporting promptly the recommendations referred to in subparagraph (c) and other findings in relation to the implementation and operation of this Chapter to theJoint Committee; 


(g) cooperating, in an appropriate manner, with otherSub-Committees established under this Agreement, with a view to avoiding unnecessary duplication of works.The forms of such cooperation may include: 


(i) informing the results of consideration to suchother Sub-Committees; 


(ii) seeking opinions from such other Sub-Committees; 
(iii) inviting to the Sub-Committee the members of such other Sub-Committees; and 

(iv) where appropriate, transferring the relevantissues to such other Sub-Committees. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives ofthe Governments of the Parties. The Sub-Committee may inviterepresentatives of relevant entities other than the Governments of the Parties with the necessary expertise relevant to theissues to be addressed. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Consulting Fora" article_identifier="13319">Where appropriate, the Parties may make use of existingconsulting fora between the Parties for improvement of thebusiness environment in the Parties in connection with the matters covered by this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Liaison Office" article_identifier="13320">1. Each Party shall designate and maintain the Liaison Office in the Party. The designation of the Liaison Office by each Party shall be notified to the other Party. 


2. The functions of the Liaison Office in each Party shallbe: 


(a) receiving complaints, inquiries, and/or requests forconsultations from the persons of the other Party with regard to the laws, regulations, and other measuresof the former Party which may adversely affect thebusiness activities of such persons of the otherParty; 


(b) transmitting the complaints, inquiries, and/orrequests for consultations referred to insubparagraph (a) to relevant authorities of the former Party; 


(c) transmitting responses from the relevant authoritiesof the former Party to the persons that filed thecomplaints, made inquiries, and/or made request forconsultations; 


(d) providing the persons referred to in subparagraph (a)with necessary information and advice incollaboration with relevant authorities of the former Party; and 


(e) reporting its findings, with regard to the exerciseof its functions referred to in subparagraphs (a)through (d), to the Joint Committee, relevantSub-Committees, and/or the existing consulting forareferred to in Article 108. 

3. The Liaison Office in each Party shall endeavor to respondwithin a reasonable period of time to the persons that filedcomplaints, made inquiries, and/or made requests forconsultations. 


4. Communications between the Liaison Office in a Party andthe persons of the other Party referred to in paragraph 2 maybe conducted through an authority or an organization designated by the Government of the latter Party. 


5. Paragraphs 2 through 4 shall not be construed as to prevent or restrict any contacts made by the persons of a Party directly to relevant authorities of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="13321">Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Cooperation" chapter_identifier="1620">
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="13322">The Parties shall, in accordance with their respectiveapplicable laws and regulations, promote cooperation under this Agreement for their mutual benefits in order to liberalize andfacilitate trade and investment between the Parties and to promote the well-being of the peoples of the Parties. For thispurpose, the Parties shall cooperate between the Governmentsof the Parties and, where necessary and appropriate, encourageand facilitate cooperation between the parties, one or both ofwhom are entities other than the Governments of the Parties,in the following fields: 


(a) agriculture, forestry, and fisheries; 


(b) trade and investment promotion; 


(c) small and medium enterprises; 


(d) human resource management and development; 


(e) tourism; 


(f) information and communications technology; 


(g) environment; 


(h) transportation; and 


(i) other fields to be mutually agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Areas And Forms Of Cooperation" article_identifier="13323">Areas and forms of cooperation under this Chapter shallbe set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="Implementation" article_identifier="13324">1. The implementation of cooperation under this Chapter shall be subject to the availability of appropriated funds and otherresources, and the applicable laws and regulations of eachParty. 


2. Costs of cooperation under this Chapter shall be borne inas equitable a manner as possible between the Parties throughefficient and effective utilization of resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Sub-Committee On Cooperation" article_identifier="13325">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, the Sub-Committee on Cooperation(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 11. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchanging views and information on cooperation ineach of the fields of cooperation referred to inArticle 111 and identifying ways of furthercooperation between the Parties; 


(b) monitoring, reviewing, and discussing issuesconcerning the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter; 


(c) reporting the findings and actions taken by theSub-Committee to the Joint Committee regardingissues relating to the implementation and operationof this Chapter; 


(d) supervising the functions and activities of theworking groups to be established pursuant toparagraph 6; 


(e) establishing its own rules and procedures; 


(f) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; and 


(g) performing other functions as may be delegated by the Joint Committee pursuant to Article 11. 

3. The Sub-Committee shall respect existing consultationmechanisms between the Parties for Official DevelopmentAssistance and other existing cooperation schemes and, asappropriate, share information with such mechanisms to ensureeffective and efficient implementation of cooperativeactivities. 


4. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives of the Governments of the Parties. The Sub-Committee may inviterepresentatives of relevant entities other than the Governments of the Parties as resource persons with the necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be addressed. 


5. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such time and venue as maybe agreed by the Parties. 


6. The Sub-Committee may establish a working group under theSub-Committee for each of the fields of cooperation referredto in Article 111. The functions, composition, and otherdetails of the working groups may be set forth in theImplementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 13" article_identifier="13326">Chapter 13 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="1621">
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Scope" article_identifier="13327">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, thisChapter shall apply with respect to the settlement of disputesbetween the Parties concerning the interpretation orapplication of this Agreement. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights of theParties to have recourse to dispute settlement proceduresavailable under any other international agreement to which both Parties are parties. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, once a dispute settlementprocedure has been initiated under this Chapter or under anyother international agreement to which both Parties are partieswith respect to a particular dispute, that procedure shall beused to the exclusion of any other procedure for that particular dispute. However, this shall not apply if substantially separate and distinct rights or obligations under differentinternational agreements are in dispute. 


4. For the purposes of paragraphs 2 and 3, a disputesettlement procedure shall be deemed to have been initiated when a Party has requested the establishment of, or referred adispute to, an arbitral tribunal or a dispute settlement panel, in accordance with this Chapter or any other internationalagreement to which the Parties are parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Consultations" article_identifier="13328">1. Either Party may make a request in writing forconsultations to the other Party concerning any matter on theinterpretation or application of this Agreement. 


2. Any request for consultations shall be submitted inwriting, containing the identification of the specific measures at issue and indication of the factual and legal basis(including, if applicable, the provisions of this Agreementalleged to have been breached and any other relevant provisions) of the complaint. 


3. When a Party makes a request for consultations pursuantto paragraph 1, the other Party shall reply to the request andenter into consultations in good faith within 30 days after thedate of receipt of the request, with a view to reaching a prompt and mutually satisfactory resolution of the matter.  In case of consultations regarding perishable goods, the other Partyshall enter into consultations within 15 days after the dateof receipt of the request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Good Offices, Conciliation, Or Mediation" article_identifier="13329">1. Good offices, conciliation, or mediation may be requested at any time by either Party. They may begin at any time by agreement of the Parties and be terminated at any time upon therequest of either Party. 


2. If the Parties agree, good offices, conciliation, ormediation may continue while the proceedings of the arbitraltribunal provided for in this Chapter are in progress.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13330">1. The complaining Party that made a request forconsultations under Article 117 may request in writing theestablishment of an arbitral tribunal to the Party complainedagainst: 


(a) if the Party complained against does not enter intosuch consultations within 30 days, or within 15 daysin case of consultations regarding perishable goods, after the date of receipt of the request for suchconsultations; or 


(b) if the Parties fail to resolve the dispute throughsuch consultations within 60 days, or within 30 daysin case of consultations regarding perishable goods, after the date of receipt of the request for suchconsultations, 
provided that the complaining Party considers that any benefitaccruing to it under this Agreement is being nullified orimpaired as a result of the failure of the Party complainedagainst to carry out its obligations under this Agreement, oras a result of the application by the Party complained againstof measures which are in conflict with its obligations underthis Agreement. 

2. Any request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunalpursuant to this Article shall identify: 


(a) the legal basis of the complaint including theprovisions of this Agreement alleged to have been breached and any other relevant provisions; and 


(b) the factual basis for the complaint. 

3. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date of receiptof the request for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,appoint one arbitrator who may be its national and propose upto three candidates to serve as the third arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either Party, nor have his or herusual place of residence in either Party, nor be employed byeither Party, nor have dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 


4. The Parties shall agree on and appoint the third arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of the request for theestablishment of an arbitral tribunal, taking into account thecandidates proposed pursuant to paragraph 3. 


5. If either Party has not appointed an arbitrator pursuantto paragraph 3, or if the Parties fail to agree on and appointthe third arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 4, theDirector-General of the World Trade Organization shallimmediately be requested to make the necessary appointments.In the event that the Director-General is a national of either Party, the Deputy Director-General or the officer next inseniority who is not a national of either Party shall berequested to make the necessary appointments. 


6. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal shall be the date on which the chair is appointed. 


7. An arbitral tribunal should be composed of arbitratorswith relevant technical or legal expertise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13331">1. 	The arbitral tribunal established pursuant to Article 119: 


(a) should consult with the Parties as appropriate andprovide adequate opportunities for the developmentof a mutually satisfactory resolution; 


(b) 	shall make its award in accordance with this Agreement and applicable rules of international law; 


(c) shall set out, in its award, its findings of law andfact, together with the reasons therefor; and 


(d) may, apart from giving its findings, include in itsaward suggested implementation options for theParties to consider in conjunction with Article 123.  

2. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Parties, suchrelevant information as it considers necessary and appropriate.  The Parties shall respond promptly and fully to any request bythe arbitral tribunal for such information. 


3. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from anyrelevant source and may consult experts to obtain their opinion on certain aspects of the matter. With respect to factual issues concerning a scientific or other technical matter raised by a Party, the arbitral tribunal may request advisory reportsin writing from experts. The arbitral tribunal may, at the request of a Party or on its own initiative, select, inconsultation with the Parties, no fewer than two scientific ortechnical experts who shall assist the arbitral tribunalthroughout its proceedings, but who shall not have the right to vote in respect of any decision to be made by the arbitraltribunal, including its award.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="13332">1. The rules and procedures as set out in this Article shallapply to the proceedings of an arbitral tribunal. 


2. The Parties, in consultation with the arbitral tribunal,may agree to adopt additional rules and procedures notinconsistent with the provisions of this Article. 


3. After consulting the Parties, the arbitral tribunal shall as soon as practicable and whenever possible within seven daysafter the establishment of the arbitral tribunal, fix thetimetable for the arbitral tribunal process. The timetable fixed for the arbitral tribunal shall include precise deadlines for written submissions by the Parties. Modifications to such timetable may be made by the agreement of the Parties inconsultation with the arbitral tribunal. 


4. The venue for the arbitral tribunal proceedings shall bedecided by mutual agreement between the Parties. If there is no agreement, the venue shall alternate between the capitalsof the Parties with the first meeting of the arbitral tribunalproceedings to be held in the capital of the Party complainedagainst. 


5. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. The Parties shall be present at the meetings only when invited bythe arbitral tribunal to appear before it. 


6. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend anyof the presentations, statements or rebuttals in theproceedings. Any information provided or written submissions made by a Party to the arbitral tribunal, including any comments on the descriptive part of the draft award and responses toquestions put by the arbitral tribunal, shall be made available to the other Party. 


7. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 


8. Notwithstanding paragraph 7, either Party may make public statements as to its views regarding the dispute, but shalltreat as confidential, information provided and writtensubmissions made by the other Party to the arbitral tribunalwhich that other Party has designated as confidential. Where a Party has provided information or made written submissionsdesignated to be confidential, that Party shall, upon requestof the other Party, provide a non-confidential summary of theinformation or written submissions which may be disclosedpublicly. 


9. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted without the presence of the Parties, and in the light of the information provided and the statements made. 


10. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 90 days after the date of its establishment, submit to the Parties its draft award,including both the descriptive part and its findings andconclusions, for the purposes of enabling the Parties to review it. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit its draft award within the aforementioned 90 day period, it mayextend that period with the consent of the Parties. A Party may submit comments in writing to the arbitral tribunal on thedraft award within 15 days after the date of submission of thedraft award. 


11. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award within 30 days after the date of submission of the draft award. 


12. The arbitral tribunal shall attempt to make its decisions, including its award, by consensus but may also make itsdecisions, including its award, by majority vote. 


13. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Termination Of Proceedings" article_identifier="13333">The Parties may agree to terminate the proceedings of thearbitral tribunal by jointly so notifying the chair of thearbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of the awardto the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="13334">1. The Party complained against shall promptly comply withthe award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant to Article

121. 


2. The Party complained against shall, within 20 days afterthe date of issuance of the award, notify the complaining Partyof the period of time in which to implement the award. If the complaining Party considers the period of time notified to beunacceptable, it may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunalwhich then determines the reasonable implementation period. 


3. If the Party complained against considers it impracticable to comply with the award within the implementation period asdetermined pursuant to paragraph 2, the Party complainedagainst shall, no later than the expiry of that implementationperiod, enter into consultations with the complaining Party,with a view to developing mutually satisfactory compensation.If no satisfactory compensation has been agreed within 20 daysafter the date of expiry of that implementation period, thecomplaining Party may notify the Party complained against thatit intends to suspend the application to the Party complainedagainst of concessions or other obligations under thisAgreement. 


4. If the complaining Party considers that the Partycomplained against has failed to comply with the award withinthe implementation period as determined pursuant to paragraph2, it may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal to confirmthe failure. 


5. If the arbitral tribunal to which the matter is referred pursuant to paragraph 4 confirms that the Party complainedagainst has failed to comply with the award within theimplementation period as determined pursuant to paragraph 2,the complaining Party may, within 30 days after the date of such confirmation by the arbitral tribunal, notify the Partycomplained against that it intends to suspend the applicationto the Party complained against of concessions or otherobligations under this Agreement. 


6. The suspension of the application of concessions or otherobligations under this Agreement pursuant to paragraphs 3 and5 may only be implemented at least 30 days after the date of the notification in accordance with those paragraphs. Such suspension shall: 


(a) 	not be effected if, in respect of the dispute to which the suspension relates, consultations orproceedings before the arbitral tribunal are inprogress; 


(b) be temporary, and be discontinued when the Partiesreach a mutually satisfactory resolution or wherecompliance with the award is effected; 


(c) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification or impairment that is attributable to the failure tocomply with the award; and 


(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to which the nullification or impairment relates, unless itis not practicable or effective to suspend theapplication of concessions or other obligationsunder this Agreement in such sector or sectors. 

7. If the Party complained against considers that therequirements for the suspension of the application to it ofconcessions or other obligations under this Agreement by thecomplaining Party set out in paragraph 6 have not been met, itmay request consultations with the complaining Party. The complaining Party shall enter into consultations within 10 days after the date of receipt of the request. If the Parties fail to resolve the matter within 30 days after the date of receiptof the request for consultations pursuant to this paragraph,the Party complained against may refer the matter to an arbitral tribunal. 


8. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes of this Article shall, wherever possible, have, as itsarbitrators, the arbitrators of the original arbitral tribunal.  If this is not possible, then the arbitrators to the arbitraltribunal that is established for the purposes of this Articleshall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 3 through 5 of Article 
119. Unless the Parties agree to a different period, thearbitral tribunal established for the purposes of this Articleshall issue its award within 60 days after the date when thematter is referred to it. Such award shall be binding on theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Expenses" article_identifier="13335">Each Party shall bear the costs of the arbitrator appointed by it and its representation in the proceedings of the arbitraltribunal. The other costs of the arbitral tribunal shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares, unless otherwise agreedby the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="1622">
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="13336">The table of contents and headings of the Chapters and theArticles of this Agreement are inserted for convenience ofreference only and shall not affect the interpretation of thisAgreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="13337">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall form anintegral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Amendment" article_identifier="13338">1. This Agreement may be amended by agreement between theParties. Such amendment shall be approved by the Parties inaccordance with their respective legal procedures, and shallenter into force on the date to be agreed by the Parties. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, amendments relating only tothe following may be made by diplomatic notes exchanged between the Governments of the Parties: 


(a) Annex 1, provided that the amendments are made inaccordance with the amendment of the Harmonized System, and include no change on the rates of customsduty to be applied by a Party to the originating goods of the other Party in accordance with Annex 1; 


(b) Annex 2; or 


(c) Attachment to Annex 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="13339">This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day ofthe second month following the month in which the Governmentsof the Parties exchange diplomatic notes informing each otherthat their respective legal procedures necessary for entry into force of this Agreement have been completed. It shall remain in force unless terminated pursuant to Article 129.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Termination" article_identifier="13340">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving oneyear’s advance notice in writing to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="1623">
      <article article_identifier="13341">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement. 

DONE at Tokyo on this twenty-fifth day of December in theyear 2008 in duplicate in the English language. 

For Japan:  	For the Socialist Republic  of Viet Nam: 

中曽根弘文	                         Vu Huy Hoang</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
