<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Mexico</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>38</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>34</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2004-09-17</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2005-04-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2005-03-31</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2015-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MEX</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MEX</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia; North America</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/latin/mexico/agreement/agreement.pdf</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/latin/mexico/agreement/index.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="513">
      <article article_identifier="4456">AGREEMENT BETWEEN JAPAN AND THE UNITED MEXICAN STATES 
FOR THE STRENGTHENING OF THE ECONOMIC PARTNERSHIP 


Preamble 

Japan and the United Mexican States, 

Conscious of their longstanding friendship and strongeconomic and political ties that have developed throughgrowing trade and investment and mutually beneficialcooperation between the Parties; 

Realizing that a dynamic and rapidly changing globalenvironment brought about by globalization and closerintegration among economies in the world presents many neweconomic challenges and opportunities to the Parties; 

Recognizing that the economies of the Parties are endowed with conditions to complement each other and thatthis complementarity should contribute to further promotingthe economic development in the Parties, by making use oftheir respective economic strengths through bilateral tradeand investment activities; 

Recognizing that creating a clearly established andsecured trade and investment framework through mutuallyadvantageous rules to govern trade and investment betweenthe Parties would enhance the competitiveness of theeconomies of the Parties, make their markets more efficientand vibrant and ensure predictable commercial environmentfor further expansion of trade and investment between them; 

Noting that such a framework would promote theeconomic relations between the Parties; 

Recalling Article XXIV of the General Agreement onTariffs and Trade 1994 and Article V of the General Agreement on Trade in Services in Annex 1A and Annex 1B,respectively, to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing theWorld Trade Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15,1994; 

Realizing that enhancing economic ties between theParties would contribute to increasing trade and investmentflows across the Pacific; 

Convinced that this Agreement would open a new era forthe relationship between the Parties; and 

Determined to establish a legal framework forstrengthening the economic partnership between the Parties; 

HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Objectives" chapter_identifier="514">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Objectives" article_identifier="4457">The objectives of this Agreement are to: 


(a) liberalize and facilitate trade in goods andservices between the Parties; 


(b) increase investment opportunities and strengthenprotection for investments and investmentactivities in the Parties; 


(c) enhance opportunities for suppliers toparticipate in government procurement in theParties; 


(d) promote cooperation and coordination for theeffective enforcement of competition laws in eachParty; 


(e) create effective procedures for theimplementation and operation of this Agreementand for the resolution of disputes; and 


(f) 	establish a framework for further bilateral cooperation and improvement of businessenvironment.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="General Definitions" chapter_identifier="515">
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="4458">1. For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwisespecified: 

(a) 	the term “Area” means: 

with respect to the United Mexican States (hereinafterreferred to as “Mexico”): 


(i) 	the States of the Federation and the Federal District; 


(ii) the islands, including the reefs and keys,in adjacent seas; 
(iii) the islands of Guadalupe and Revillagigedosituated in the Pacific Ocean; 


(iv) 	the continental shelf and the submarine shelf of such islands, keys and reefs; 


(v) the waters of the territorial seas, inaccordance with international law, and itsinterior maritime waters; 


(vi) the space located above the nationalterritory, in accordance with internationallaw; and 
(vii) any areas beyond the territorial seas ofMexico within which, in accordance withinternational law, including the UnitedNations Convention on the Law of the Sea, asmay be amended, and its domestic law, Mexicomay exercise rights with respect to theseabed and subsoil and their natural resources; and 

with respect to Japan: 

(viii) the territory of Japan which means the landareas, internal waters, and territorial seasand the airspace above such areas, watersand seas, under the sovereignty of Japan inaccordance with international law; and 

(ix) any areas beyond the territorial seas ofJapan within which, in accordance withinternational law, including the UnitedNations Convention on the Law of the Sea, asmay be amended, and its domestic law, Japanmay exercise rights with respect to theseabed and subsoil and their natural resources. 

Nothing in this subparagraph shall affect the rightsand obligations of the Parties under the UnitedNations Convention on the Law of the Sea, as may beamended; 


(b) the term “days” means calendar days, includingweekends and holidays; 


(c) the term “enterprise” means any entityconstituted or organized under applicable law,whether or not for profit, and whether privately-owned or governmentally-owned, including anycorporation, trust, partnership, joint venture,or other association or sole proprietorship; 


(d) the term “enterprise of a Party” means anenterprise constituted or organized under the lawof a Party; 


(e) the term “existing” means in effect on the dateof entry into force of this Agreement; 


(f) the term “GATS” means the General Agreement onTrade in Services in Annex 1B to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994,as may be amended; 


(g) the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreementon Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994,as may be amended. For the purposes of this Agreement, references to Articles in the GATT1994 include the interpretative notes; 


(h) the term “goods of a Party” means domesticproducts as these are understood in the GATT1994, and includes originating goods of thatParty; 


(i) the term “Harmonized System (HS)” means theHarmonized Commodity Description and CodingSystem set out in the Annex to the InternationalConvention on the Harmonized CommodityDescription and Coding System, as may be amended,and adopted and implemented by the Parties intheir respective domestic laws; 


(j) 	the term “Joint Committee” means the Joint Committee established under Article 165; 


(k) the term “measure” means any measure by a Party,whether in the form of a law, regulation, rule,procedure, decision, administrative action or anyother form; 


(l) the term “national” means a natural personpossessing the nationality of a Party under itsdomestic laws; 


(m) the term “originating goods” means goodsqualifying as originating under the provisions ofChapter 4; 


(n) the term “originating materials” means materialsqualifying as originating under the provisions ofChapter 4; 


(o) the term “person” means a natural person orenterprise; 


(p) the term “person of a Party” means a national oran enterprise of a Party; 


(q) the term “state enterprise” means an enterpriseowned or controlled through ownership interestsby a Party; and 


(r) the term “WTO Agreement” means the MarrakeshAgreement Establishing the World TradeOrganization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994,as may be amended. 
2. For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwisespecified: 


(a) in the case of Mexico, a reference to a stateincludes local governments of that state; and 


(b) in the case of Japan, a reference to a localgovernment means a prefecture or any other localauthority.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="516">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="4459">1. Each Party shall accord national treatment to thegoods of the other Party in accordance with Article III ofthe GATT 1994 and to this end Article III of the GATT 1994 is incorporated into and made part of this Agreement. 


2. The provisions of paragraph 1 above regarding nationaltreatment shall mean, with respect to a local government inthe case of Japan, and with respect to a state in the caseof Mexico, treatment no less favorable than the mostfavorable treatment accorded by that local government orstate to any like goods or, directly competitive orsubstitutable goods, as the case may be, of the Party ofwhich it forms a part.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="4460">The classification of goods in trade between the
Parties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Elimination Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="4461">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,each Party shall eliminate or reduce its Customs Duties onoriginating goods designated for such purposes in itsSchedule in Annex 1, in accordance with the terms andconditions set out therein. 


2. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,neither Party shall increase any Customs Duty onoriginating goods from the level provided for in itsSchedule in Annex 1. 
Note: 	The term “level” means the level of Customs Duty that shall be implemented by each Party in

accordance with its Schedule and does not mean 

the Base Rate specified in such Schedule. 

3. 	(a) On the request of either Party, the Parties shall consult to consider: 


(i) issues such as improving market accessconditions on originating goods designatedfor consultation in the Schedule in Annex 1,in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in such Schedule; or 


(ii) further steps in the process ofliberalization of trade between the Parties in respect of goods after 4 years of the date of entry into force of this Agreement. 
(b) Subparagraph (a)(ii) above shall not apply to theoriginating goods referred to in subparagraph(a)(i) above while the consultation on theoriginating goods is held under the terms andconditions referred to in subparagraph (a)(i)above. 


4. The Parties shall consult to consider further steps inthe process of liberalization of trade between the Partiesin respect of originating goods set out in the Schedule inAnnex 1, in light of the result of the multilateral tradenegotiations under the World Trade Organization (WTO). 


5. Any amendment to the Schedules as a result of theconsultations referred to in paragraph 3 or 4 above shallbe approved by both Parties in accordance with theirrespective legal procedures, and shall supersede anycorresponding concession provided for in their respectiveSchedules.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="Export Duties" article_identifier="4462">Neither Party shall adopt or maintain any duties ongoods exported from a Party into the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="4463">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,each Party shall not institute or maintain any prohibitionor restriction other than Customs Duties on the importationof any good of the other Party or on the exportation orsale for export of any good destined to the other Party,which is inconsistent with its obligations under Article XIof the GATT 1994 and its relevant provisions under the WTOAgreement. 


2. The measures specified in Annex 2 may be maintained,provided that such measures are consistent with the rightsand obligations of the Party taking such measures under theWTO Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Protection Of Geographical Indications For Spirits" article_identifier="4464">1. The Parties agree that indications for spirits listedin Annex 3 are geographical indications referred to inparagraph 1 of Article 22 of the Agreement on Trade-RelatedAspects of Intellectual Property Rights in Annex 1C to theWTO Agreement, as may be amended, and shall abide by theobligations under the relevant provisions of the saidAgreement with respect to the protection of geographicalindications, and for this purpose, they shall takeappropriate measures to prohibit the use of anygeographical indications listed in Annex 3 for spirits notoriginating in the place indicated by the respectivegeographical indication. 


2. Modifications to Annex 3 proposed by both Parties maybe adopted by the Joint Committee pursuant to subparagraph2(e)(i) of Article 165. The adopted modifications shall be confirmed by an exchange of diplomatic notes and shallenter into force on the date specified in the said notes.The modified part of Annex 3 shall supersede thecorresponding part provided for in Annex 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Goods" article_identifier="4465">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Section, a Sub-Committee on Trade inGoods (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 165. 


2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation of this Section; 


(b) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(c) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165. 

4. 	(a) For the purposes of the effective implementation and operation of this Section, the Sub-Committeeshall establish a Special Sub-Committee on SteelProducts. If necessary, the Sub-Committee mayestablish any other Special Sub-Committees. 


(b) The Special Sub-Committees shall be held at suchvenue and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


(c) The functions of the Special Sub-Committees shallbe: 


(i) analyzing relevant matters on the relevantproducts and its sector, including trade insuch products; and 


(ii) reporting the findings of the Special Sub-Committees, through the Sub-Committee, tothe Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="Uniform Regulations" article_identifier="4466">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement,the Joint Committee shall adopt the Uniform Regulationsthat provide detailed regulations pursuant to which thecustoms authorities, the competent governmental authoritiesdefined in Article 49 and the relevant authorities of the Parties shall implement their functions under this Section,Chapter 4 and Chapter 5, except Section 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Definition" article_identifier="4467">For the purposes of this Section, the term “CustomsDuty” means any customs or import duty and a charge of anykind, imposed in connection with the importation of a good,but does not include any: 


(a) charge equivalent to an internal tax imposedconsistently with the provisions of paragraph 2of Article III of the GATT 1994, in respect ofthe like goods or, directly competitive orsubstitutable goods of the Party or in respect ofgoods from which the imported goods have beenmanufactured or produced in whole or in part; 


(b) anti-dumping or countervailing duty appliedpursuant to a Party’s domestic law and appliedconsistently with the provisions of Article VI ofthe GATT 1994, the Agreement on Implementation ofArticle VI of the General Agreement on Tariffsand Trade 1994, as may be amended, and theAgreement on Subsidies and CountervailingMeasures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as maybe amended; or 


(c) fees or other charges commensurate with the costof services rendered. 
Sanitary and Phytosanitary Measures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="4468">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligationsrelating to sanitary and phytosanitary (hereinafterreferred to in this Chapter as “SPS”) measures under theAgreement on the Application of Sanitary and PhytosanitaryMeasures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as may beamended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="4469">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which isable to answer all reasonable enquiries from the otherParty regarding SPS measures referred to in Article 12 and,if appropriate, to provide their relevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="Sub-Committee On Sps Measures" article_identifier="4470">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Section, a Sub-Committee on SPS Measures(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 165. 


2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchange of information on such matters asoccurrences of SPS incidents in the Parties and non-Parties, and change or introduction of SPS-related regulations and standards of the Parties,which may, directly or indirectly, affect tradein goods between the Parties; 


(b) notification to either Party of information onpotential SPS risks recognized by the otherParty; 


(c) science-based consultation to identify andaddress specific issues that may arise from theapplication of SPS measures with the objective ofobtaining mutually acceptable solutions; 


(d) discussing technical cooperation in relation toSPS measures; 


(e) consulting cooperative efforts between theParties in international fora in relation to SPS measures; 


(f) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(g) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165. 

4. The Sub-Committee may, if necessary, establish ad hoc technical advisory groups as its subsidiary bodies. The groups shall provide the Sub-Committee with technicalinformation and advice at the request of the Sub-Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="4471">The dispute settlement procedure provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Section.
Technical Regulations, Standards and
Conformity Assessment Procedures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="4472">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligationsrelating to technical regulations, standards and conformityassessment procedures under the Agreement on TechnicalBarriers to Trade in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as maybe amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="4473">1. The Parties shall develop cooperation between theGovernments of the Parties in the field of technical regulations, standards and conformity assessment procedures(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theCooperation”) with a view to facilitating trade in goodsbetween them. 


2. The forms of the Cooperation may include thefollowing: 


(a) conducting joint studies and holding seminars andsymposia, in order to enhance mutualunderstanding of their domestic technicalregulations, standards and conformity assessmentprocedures; 


(b) exchanging government officials for trainingpurpose; 


(c) contributing jointly to activities related totechnical regulations, standards and conformityassessment procedures in international andregional fora; and 


(d) encouraging entities related to technicalregulations, standards and conformity assessmentprocedures other than the Governments of theParties to participate in the Cooperation and toimplement cooperation between such entities. 

3. The implementation of this Article shall be subject tothe availability of appropriated funds and the applicablelaws and regulations of each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Enquiry Points" article_identifier="4474">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point which isable to answer all reasonable enquiries from the otherParty regarding technical regulations, standards andconformity assessment procedures and, if appropriate, toprovide their relevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="4475">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Section, a Sub-Committee on TechnicalRegulations, Standards and Conformity Assessment Procedures(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 165. 


2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue as may beagreed by the Parties and shall make efforts to meet once ayear. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) exchanging information on technical regulations,standards and conformity assessment procedures; 


(b) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Section; 


(c) discussing any issues related to this Section; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(e) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="4476">The dispute settlement procedure provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Section.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="Relation To Section 2" article_identifier="4477">This Section shall not apply to SPS measures referredto in Section 2.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="517">
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="4478">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Chapter, agood shall be an originating good where: 


(a) the good is wholly obtained or produced entirelyin the Area of one or both Parties, as defined inArticle 38; 


(b) the good is produced entirely in the Area of oneor both Parties exclusively from originatingmaterials; 


(c) the good satisfies the requirements set out inAnnex 4, as well as all other applicablerequirements of this Chapter, when the good isproduced entirely in the Area of one or bothParties using non-originating materials; or 


(d) except for a good provided for in Chapters 61through 63 of the Harmonized System, the good isproduced entirely in the Area of one or bothParties, but one or more of the non-originatingmaterials that are used in the production of thegood does not undergo an applicable change intariff classification because: 


(i) the good was imported into a Party in anunassembled or a disassembled form but was classified as an assembled good pursuant toRule 2(a) of the General Rules for theInterpretation of the Harmonized System; or 


(ii) the heading for the good provides for andspecifically describes both the good itselfand its parts and is not further subdividedinto subheadings, or the subheading for thegood provides for and specifically describesboth the good itself and its parts; 
provided that the regional value content of thegood, determined in accordance with Article 23,is not less than 50 percent, unless otherwiseprovided for in Annex 4, and that the goodsatisfies all other applicable requirements ofthis Chapter. 

2. For the purposes of this Chapter, the production of agood using non-originating materials that undergo anapplicable change in tariff classification and satisfyingother requirements, as set out in Annex 4, shall occurentirely in the Area of one or both Parties and everyregional value content of a good shall be entirelysatisfied in the Area of one or both Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Regional Value Content" article_identifier="4479">1. Except as provided for in paragraph 4 below andArticle 26, the regional value content of a good shall becalculated on the basis of the transaction value method set out in paragraph 2 below. 


2. For the purposes of calculating the regional valuecontent of a good on the basis of the transaction valuemethod, the following formula shall be applied: 
TV - VNM 
RVC= -------------- x 100 
TV 


where: 

RVC: 	the regional value content, expressed as apercentage; 

TV: transaction value of the good adjusted to a

F.O.B. basis, except as provided for in paragraph3 below; and 

VNM: 	value of non-originating materials used by theproducer in the production of the gooddetermined pursuant to Article 24. 


3. For the purposes of paragraph 2 above, when theproducer of the good does not export it directly, thetransaction value of the good shall be adjusted to thepoint where the buyer receives the good from the producerin the Area of a Party where the producer is located. 


4. In the event that there is no transaction value or the transaction value of the good is unacceptable under Article1 of the Customs Valuation Code, the value of the goodshall be determined in accordance with Articles 2 through 7of the Customs Valuation Code. 


5. A producer may average the regional value content forone or more goods classified in the same subheading underthe Harmonized System that he produces in the same plant orin more than one plant in the Area of one Party, on thebasis of either all the goods produced by the producer oronly those goods exported to the other Party: 


(a) in its fiscal year or period; or 


(b) in any period of 1, 2, 3, 4 or 6 months.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Value Of Materials" article_identifier="4480">1. 	The value of a material: 


(a) shall be the transaction value of the material; or 


(b) 	in the event that there is no transaction value or the transaction value of the material is unacceptable under Article 1 of the CustomsValuation Code, shall be determined in accordancewith Articles 2 through 7 of the CustomsValuation Code. 
2. Where not included under subparagraph 1(a) or 1(b)above, the value of a material: 


(a) shall include freight, insurance, packing and allother costs incurred in transporting the materialto the importation port in the Party where theproducer of the good is located, except asprovided for in paragraph 3 below; and 


(b) may include the cost of waste and spoilageresulting from the use of the material in theproduction of the good, less the value ofreusable scrap or by-product. 

3. The value of a non-originating material shall notinclude, where the producer acquires the material in theArea of the Party where the producer is located, freight,insurance, packing and all other costs incurred intransporting the material from the warehouse of thesupplier of the material to the place where the producer islocated; as well as any other known and ascertainable costincurred in the Area of the producer of the good. 


4. The value of non-originating materials used by theproducer in the production of the good shall not includethe value of the non-originating materials used by: 


(a) another producer in the production of anoriginating material which is acquired and usedby the producer of the good in the production ofsuch good; or 


(b) the producer of the good in the production of aself-produced originating material, which isdesignated by the producer as an intermediatematerial under Article 26.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="4481">1. A good shall be considered to be an originating goodif the value of all non-originating materials used in theproduction of the good that do not undergo an applicablechange in tariff classification set out in Annex 4 is notmore than 10 percent of the transaction value of the good,adjusted to the basis set out in paragraph 2 or 3, as thecase may be, of Article 23, and the good satisfies allother applicable requirements of this Chapter. 


2. Where the good referred to in paragraph 1 above isalso subject to a regional value content, the value of suchnon-originating materials shall be taken into account indetermining the regional value of the good and the goodshall be required to satisfy all other applicablerequirements of this Chapter. 


3. A good that is subject to a regional value contentrequirement pursuant to Annex 4 shall not be required tosatisfy such requirement if the value of all non-originating materials is not more than 10 percent of thetransaction value of the good, adjusted to the basis setout in paragraph 2 or 3, as the case may be, of Article 23. 


4. Paragraph 1 above shall not apply to: 


(a) a good provided for in Chapters 50 through 63 ofthe Harmonized System; or 


(b) a good provided for in Chapters 1 through 27 ofthe Harmonized System, except where the non-originating material used in the production ofthe good is provided for in a differentsubheading to the good classified in Chapter 1, 4through 15, or 17 through 27 of the HarmonizedSystem for which the origin is being determinedunder this Article. 

5. A good provided for in Chapters 50 through 63 of theHarmonized System that does not originate because certainfibers or yarns used in the production of the material thatdetermines the tariff classification of the good do notundergo an applicable change in tariff classification setout in Annex 4, shall nonetheless be considered tooriginate if the total weight of all such fibers or yarnsin that material is not more than 7 percent of the totalweight of such material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Intermediate Materials" article_identifier="4482">1. For the purposes of determining the regional valuecontent of a good under Article 23, the producer of thegood may designate as an intermediate material, any self-produced material used in the production of the good. 


2. Where an intermediate material is subject to aregional value content requirement under subparagraph 1(d)of Article 22 or Annex 4, the value of the intermediatematerial shall be: 


(a) the total cost incurred with respect to all goodsproduced by the producer of the good which may bereasonably allocated to such intermediatematerial, in accordance with the UniformRegulations referred to in Article 10; or 


(b) the sum of each cost which are part of the totalcost incurred with respect to such intermediatematerial, in accordance with the UniformRegulations referred to in Article 10. 
In this case, the regional value content of suchmaterial shall be not less than the percentage set out inAnnex 4 minus 5 percent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="4483">For the purposes of determining whether a good is anoriginating good, a producer of the good may accumulate hisproduction with the production of one or more producers inthe Area of one or both Parties, of materials incorporatedin the good, in a manner that the production of thematerials is considered to have been performed by thatproducer, provided that the provisions of Article 22 aresatisfied.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="4484">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good is anoriginating good, where originating and non-originatingfungible materials that are commingled in an inventory, areused in the production of a good, the origin of thematerials may be determined pursuant to an inventorymanagement method set out in paragraph 3 below. 


2. Where originating and non-originating fungible goodsare commingled in an inventory and, prior to exportation donot undergo any production process or any operation in theArea of the Party where they were commingled other thanunloading, loading or any other operation necessary topreserve it in good condition or to transport the good tothe other Party, the origin of the good may be determinedpursuant to an inventory management method set out inparagraph 3 below. 


3. The inventory management methods for fungible goods ormaterials shall be the following: 


(a) “FIFO method” (first in-first out) is theinventory management method by which the originof the number of fungible goods or materialsfirst received in the inventory is considered tobe the origin of the same number of fungiblegoods or materials first withdrawn from theinventory; 


(b) “LIFO method” (last in-first out) is theinventory management method by which the originof the number of fungible goods or materials lastreceived in the inventory is considered to be theorigin of the same number of fungible goods ormaterials first withdrawn from the inventory; or 


(c) “average method” is the inventory managementmethod by which, except as provided for inparagraph 4 below, the origin of fungible goodsor materials withdrawn from an inventory is basedon the ratio, calculated under the followingformula: 
TOM 
ROM= --------------- x 100 
TONM 


where: 

ROM: 	ratio of originating fungible goods ormaterials; 

TOM: 	total units of originating fungiblegoods or materials in the inventoryprior to the shipment; and 

TONM: 	total sum of units of originating andnon-originating fungible goods ormaterials in the inventory prior tothe shipment. 

4. Where a good is subject to a regional value contentrequirement, the determination of value of non-originatingfungible materials shall be made through the followingformula: 

TNM 
RNM= --------------- x 100 
TONM 


where: 

RNM: 	ratio of value of non-originating fungiblematerials; 

TNM: 	total value of fungible non-originatingmaterials in the inventory prior to theshipment; and 

TONM: 	total value of originating and non-originatingfungible materials in the inventory prior tothe shipment. 

5. Once an inventory management method set out inparagraph 3 above has been chosen, it shall be used throughall the fiscal year or period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Sets, Kits Or Composite Goods" article_identifier="4485">1. Sets, kits and composite goods classified pursuant toRule 3 of the General Rules for the Interpretation of theHarmonized System, and the goods specifically described assets, kits or composite goods in the nomenclature of theHarmonized System, shall qualify as originating, whereevery good contained in the sets, kits or composite goodssatisfies the applicable rule of origin for each of themunder this Chapter. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 above, a set, kit orcomposite good shall be considered as originating, if thevalue of all non-originating goods used in the collectionof the set, kit or composite good does not exceed 10percent of the transaction value of the set, kit orcomposite good, adjusted to the basis set out in paragraph2 or 3, as the case may be, of Article 23, and such set,kit or composite good satisfies all other applicablerequirements of this Chapter. 


3. The provisions of this Article shall prevail over thespecific rules of origin set out in Annex 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="4486">Indirect materials shall be considered to be originating without regard to where they are produced andthe value of such materials shall be their cost as reportedin the accounting records of the producer of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Accessories, Spare Parts And Tools" article_identifier="4487">1. Accessories, spare parts or tools delivered with thegood that form part of the good’s standard accessories,spare parts or tools, shall be disregarded in determiningwhether all the non-originating materials used in theproduction of the good undergo the applicable change intariff classification set out in Annex 4, provided that: 


(a) the accessories, spare parts or tools are notinvoiced separately from the good, without regardof whether they are separately detached in thecommercial invoice; and 


(b) the quantities and value of the accessories,spare parts or tools are customary for the good. 
2. If the good is subject to a regional value contentrequirement, the value of the accessories, spare parts ortools shall be taken into account as the value of originating or non-originating materials, as the case maybe, in calculating the regional value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Packaging Materials And Containers For Retail Sale" article_identifier="4488">1. Packaging materials and containers in which a good ispackaged for retail sale shall, if classified with the goodpursuant to Rule 5 of the General Rules for theInterpretation of the Harmonized System, be disregarded indetermining whether all the non-originating materials usedin the production of the good undergo the applicable changein tariff classification set out in Annex 4. 


2. If the good is subject to a regional value contentrequirement, the value of such packaging materials andcontainers for retail sale shall be taken into account as the value of originating or non-originating materials, asthe case may be, in calculating the regional value contentof the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Packing Materials And Containers For Shipment" article_identifier="4489">Packing materials and containers in which a good ispacked for shipment shall be disregarded in determiningwhether: 


(a) all non-originating materials used in theproduction of the good undergo an applicablechange in tariff classification set out in Annex4; and 


(b) the good satisfies a regional value contentrequirement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="4490">1. A good shall not be considered to be an originatinggood merely by reason of: 


(a) 	dilution with water or another substance that does not materially alter the characteristics ofthe good; 


(b) simple operations for the maintenance of the goodduring transportation or storing, such asventilation, refrigeration, removal of damagedparts, drying or addition of substances; 


(c) sieving, classification, selection; 


(d) packing, repacking or packaging for retail sale; 


(e) collection of goods to form sets, kits orcomposite goods; 


(f) application of stamps, labels or similardistinctive signs; 


(g) washing, including removal of dust, oxide, oil,paint or other coverings; 


(h) mere collection of parts and componentsclassified as a good, according to Rule 2(a) ofthe General Rules for the Interpretation of theHarmonized System. Mere collection does not include the collection of parts and components ofdisassembled originating goods that werepreviously disassembled for consideration ofpackaging, handling or transportation; or 


(i) mere disassembly of the good into parts orcomponents. Disassembling originating goods that were previously assembled, for consideration ofpackaging, handling or transportation, shall notbe considered as mere disassembly. 
2. The provisions of this Article shall prevail over thespecific rules of origin set out in Annex 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Transshipment" article_identifier="4491">1. An originating good shall be considered as non-originating, even if it has undergone production thatsatisfies the requirements of Article 22 if, subsequent tothat production, outside the Areas of the Parties, thegood: 


(a) undergoes further production, or operations otherthan unloading, reloading or any other operationnecessary to preserve it in good condition or totransport it to the other Party; or 


(b) 	does not remain under surveillance of the customs authorities in one or more non-Parties where it undergoes transshipment or temporary storage inthose non-Parties. 
2. Evidence that an originating good has not lost itsoriginating condition by means of paragraph 1 above shallbe provided to the customs authority of the importingParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Application And Interpretation" article_identifier="4492">1. For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) 	the basis for tariff classification is the Harmonized System; 


(b) the determination of transaction value of a goodor of a material shall be made in accordance with the Customs Valuation Code; and 


(c) all costs referred to in this Chapter shall berecorded and maintained in accordance with the Generally Accepted Accounting Principlesapplicable in the Party in which the good isproduced. 
2. For the purposes of this Chapter, in applying theCustoms Valuation Code to determine the transaction value of a good or a material: 


(a) the principles of the Customs Valuation Codeshall apply to domestic transactions, with suchmodifications as may be required by thecircumstances, as would apply to internationaltransactions; and 


(b) the provisions of this Chapter shall prevail overthe Customs Valuation Code to the extent of anydifference.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Sub-Committee, Consultation And Modifications" article_identifier="4493">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter and Chapter 5, a Sub-Committee onRules of Origin, Certificate of Origin and CustomsProcedures (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “theSub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article

165. 


2. The Sub-Committee shall meet at such venue and times as may be agreed by the Parties. 


3. 	The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on theimplementation and operation of this Chapter andChapter 5; 


(b) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on the: 


(i) 	tariff classification and customs valuation matters relating to determinations oforigin; 


(ii) certificate of origin referred to in Article39; 

(c) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on anymodification to Annex 4, proposed by eitherParty, duly based on issues related with thedetermination of origin; 


(d) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,as needed, to the Joint Committee on the UniformRegulations referred to in Article 10; 


(e) considering any other matter as the Parties mayagree related to this Chapter and Chapter 5; 


(f) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(g) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165. 

4. The recommendation of the Sub-Committee shall be sent to the Joint Committee for necessary action under Article
165. 


5. The Parties shall consult and cooperate to ensure thatthis Chapter and Chapter 5 are applied in an effective anduniform manner in accordance with the provisions, thespirit and the objectives of this Agreement. 


6. Modifications to Annex 4 recommended by the Sub-Committee pursuant to subparagraph 3(c) above and proposedby both Parties may be adopted by the Joint Committeepursuant to subparagraph 2(e)(i) of Article 165. The adopted modifications shall be confirmed by an exchange ofdiplomatic notes and shall enter into force on the datespecified in the said notes. The modified part of Annex 4 shall supersede the corresponding part provided for inAnnex 4.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4494">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) 	the term “Customs Valuation Code” means the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended,including its interpretative notes; 


(b) 	the term “direct overhead” means overhead incurred during a period, directly related to thegood, other than direct material costs and directlabor costs; 


(c) the term “factory ships of a Party” and “vesselsof a Party” respectively means factory ships andvessels: 


(i) which are registered in the Party; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of that Party; 
(iii) 	which are owned to an extent of at least 50 percent by nationals of that Party, or by anenterprise with its head office in thatParty, of which the managers orrepresentatives, chairman of the board ofdirectors or the supervisory board, and themajority of the members of such boards arenationals of that Party, and of which, inaddition, in the case of partnerships orlimited companies, at least half the capitalbelongs to that Party or to public bodies ornationals or enterprises of that Party; 


(iv) 	of which the master and officers are all nationals of that Party; and 


(v) of which at least 75 percent of the crew arenationals of that Party; 

(d) the term “F.O.B.” means free on board, regardlessof the mode of transportation, at the point ofdirect shipment by the seller to the buyer; 


(e) the term “fungible goods” means goods that areinterchangeable for commercial purposes, whoseproperties are essentially identical, notpractical to distinguish by the naked eye; 


(f) the term “fungible materials” means materialsthat are interchangeable for commercial purposesand whose properties are essentially identical,not practical to distinguish by the naked eye; 


(g) the term “Generally Accepted AccountingPrinciples” means the recognized consensus orsubstantial authoritative support in a Party withrespect to the recording of revenues, expenses,costs, assets and liabilities, the disclosure ofinformation and the preparation of financialstatements. These standards may be broadguidelines of general application as well asdetailed standards, practices and procedures; 


(h) the term “goods wholly obtained or producedentirely in the Area of one or both Parties”means: 


(i) mineral goods extracted in the Area of oneor both Parties; 


(ii) vegetable goods harvested in the Area of oneor both Parties; 
(iii) 	live animals born and raised in the Area of one or both Parties; 


(iv) goods obtained from hunting or fishing inthe Area of one or both Parties; 


(v) fish, shellfish and other marine speciestaken by vessels of a Party from the seaoutside the territorial seas of the Party; 


(vi) goods produced on board factory ships of aParty from the goods referred to insubparagraph (v); 
(vii) goods taken by a Party or a person of aParty from the seabed or beneath the seabedoutside territorial seas of the Party,provided that the Party has rights toexploit such seabed; 

(viii) waste and scrap derived from: 

(AA) production in the Area of one or bothParties; or 

(BB) used goods collected in the Area of oneor both Parties, provided such goodsare fit only for the recovery of rawmaterials; or 

(ix) goods produced in the Area of one or bothParties exclusively from goods referred toin subparagraphs (i) through (viii), or fromtheir derivatives, at any stage ofproduction; 


(i) the term “indirect material” means a good used inthe production, testing or inspection of a goodbut not physically incorporated into the good, ora good used in the maintenance of buildings orthe operation of equipment associated with theproduction of a good, including: 


(i) fuel and energy; 


(ii) tools, dies and molds; 
(iii) spare parts and materials used in themaintenance of equipment and buildings; 


(iv) lubricants, greases, compounding materialsand other materials used in production orused to operate equipment and buildings; 


(v) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safetyequipment and supplies; 


(vi) equipment, devices and supplies used fortesting or inspecting the goods; 
(vii) catalysts and solvents; and 

(viii) any other goods that are not incorporatedinto the good but whose use in theproduction of the good can reasonably bedemonstrated to be a part of thatproduction; 

(j) 	the term “indirect overhead” means overhead incurred during a period, other than directoverhead, direct labor costs and direct materialcosts; 


(k) 	the term “intermediate material” means a material that is self-produced and used in the productionof a good, and designated pursuant to Article 26; 


(l) the term “material” means a good that is used inthe production of another good; 


(m) the term “packing materials and containers forshipment” means goods that are used to protect agood during transportation, other than packagingmaterials and containers for retail sale; 


(n) the term “place where the producer is located”means in relation to a good, the production plantof that good; 


(o) the term “producer” means a person who conducts aproduction of a good or material; 


(p) the term “production” means methods of obtaininggoods including manufacturing, assembling,processing, growing, mining, harvesting, fishing,and hunting; 


(q) the term “self-produced material” means amaterial that is produced by the producer of agood and used in the production of that good; 


(r) 	the term “total cost” means the sum of the following elements, calculated in accordance withthe Generally Accepted Accounting Principles ofthe Party and the Uniform Regulations referred toin Article 10: 


(i) 	the direct materials cost used in the production of the good; 


(ii) the direct labor cost used in the productionof the good; and 
(iii) 	the amount of direct and indirect overhead of the good, reasonably allocated to thegood, except for those not to be included inthe cost of the good; 

(s) the term “transaction value of a good” means theprice actually paid or payable for a good withrespect to a transaction of the producer of thegood, pursuant to the principles of Article 1 ofthe Customs Valuation Code, adjusted inaccordance with the principles of paragraphs 1, 3and 4 of Article 8 of the Customs Valuation Code,regardless of whether the good is sold forexport. For the purposes of this definition, the seller referred to in the Customs Valuation Code shall be the producer of the good; 


(t) 	the term “transaction value of a material” means the price actually paid or payable for a materialwith respect to a transaction of the producer ofthe good, pursuant to the principles of Article 1of the Customs Valuation Code, adjusted inaccordance with the principles of paragraphs 1, 3and 4 of Article 8 of the Customs Valuation Code,regardless of whether the material is sold forexport. For the purposes of this definition, the seller referred to in the Customs Valuation Code shall be the supplier of the material, and thebuyer referred to in the Customs Valuation Codeshall be the producer of the good; and 


(u) 	the term “used” means used or consumed in the production of goods.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Certificate Of Origin And Customs Procedures" chapter_identifier="518">
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="4495">1. For the purposes of this Section and Section 2, uponthe date of entry into force of this Agreement, the Partiesshall establish a format for the certificate of origin inthe Uniform Regulations referred to in Article 10. 


2. The certificate of origin referred to in paragraph 1above will have the purpose of certifying that a good beingexported from one Party into the other Party qualifies asan originating good. 


3. The certificate of origin referred to in paragraph 1above shall be issued by the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party on request having beenmade in writing by the exporter or, under the exporter’sresponsibility, by his authorized representative, inaccordance with paragraph 4 below. The certificate of origin must be stamped and signed by the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party or itsdesignees at the time of issue. 
For the purposes of this Article, the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party may designateother entities or bodies to be responsible for the issuanceof the certificate of origin, prior authorization givenunder its applicable laws and regulations. 

Where the competent governmental authority of theexporting Party designates other entities or bodies tocarry out the issuance of the certificate of origin, theexporting Party shall notify in writing the other Party ofits designees. 

The exporting Party shall revoke the designation,where the issuance of certificates of origin by a designeeis not in conformity with the provisions provided for inthis Section and the situation warrants the revocation. For this purpose, the exporting Party shall consider viewsexpressed by the importing Party in deciding on revokingthe designation. 


4. Prior to the issuance of a certificate of origin, anexporter that requests a certificate of origin must proveto the competent governmental authority of the exportingParty or its designees, that the good to be exportedqualifies as an originating good. 

Where an exporter is not the producer of the good, theexporter may request a certificate of origin on the basisof a declaration voluntarily provided by the producer ofthe good that demonstrates that such producer has proved tothe competent governmental authority or its designees, thatthe good concerned qualifies as an originating good.Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to oblige theproducer of the good to certificate that the good qualifiesas an originating good. If the producer decides not to provide the declaration concerned, the exporter shall berequired to prove to the competent governmental authorityor its designees that the good to be exported qualifies asan originating good. 

5. The competent governmental authority or its designeesshall issue a certificate of origin after the exportationof a good when it is requested by the exporter inaccordance with paragraph 4 above. The certificate of origin issued retrospectively must be endorsed with thephrase set out in the Uniform Regulations referred to inArticle 10.    


6. In the event of theft, loss or destruction of acertificate of origin, the exporter may request to thecompetent governmental authority or its designees whichissued it a duplicate made out on the basis of the exportdocuments in their possession. The duplicate issued in this way must be endorsed with the phrase set out in theUniform Regulations referred to in Article 10. 


7. The certificate of origin for a good imported into theimporting Party shall be completed in the English language.If the certificate of origin is not completed in theEnglish language, a translation into the official languageof the importing Party shall be attached thereto. If the certificate of origin is completed in the English language,a translation into the Spanish or the Japanese languageshall not be required. 


8. Each Party shall provide that a valid certificate oforigin that fulfills the requirements of this Section thatis applicable to a single importation of a good into theother Party, shall be accepted by the customs authority ofthe importing Party for 1 year or another period that theParties may agree, after the date on which the certificatewas issued. 


9. The competent governmental authority of the exportingParty shall: 


(a) 	determine the administrative mechanisms for the issuing of the certificate of origin; 


(b) provide, at the request of the importing Party inaccordance with Article 44 information relatingto the origin of the goods for which preferentialtariff treatment was claimed; and 


(c) provide the other Party with specimen impressionsof stamps used in the offices of the competentgovernmental authority or its designees for theissue of the certificate of origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Obligations Regarding Importations" article_identifier="4496">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Section, eachParty shall require an importer that claims preferentialtariff treatment for a good imported from the other Partyto: 


(a) make a written declaration, based on a validcertificate of origin, that the good qualifies asan originating good; 


(b) have the certificate in its possession at thetime the declaration is made; 


(c) provide the certificate on the request of thecustoms authority; and 


(d) promptly make a corrected declaration and pay anyduties owing where the importer has reason tobelieve that a certificate on which a declaration was based contains information that is not correct. 

2. Where an importer claims preferential tariff treatmentfor a good imported into a Party from the other Party, thecustoms authority of the importing Party may denypreferential tariff treatment to the good if the importerfails to comply with any requirement under this Article. 


3. Each Party shall ensure that, in the case that theimporter at the time of importation does not have in hispossession a certificate of origin, the importer of thegood may, in accordance with the domestic laws andregulations of the importing Party, provide the certificateof origin and if required such other documentation relatingto the importation of the good at a later stage, within aperiod not exceeding 1 year after the time of importation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Obligations Regarding Exportations" article_identifier="4497">1. Each Party shall ensure that an exporter or a producerthat has completed and signed a certificate of origin, andthat has reasons to believe that the certificate contains incorrect information, shall promptly notify in writing, ofany change that could affect the accuracy or validity ofthe certificate of origin to all persons to whom he gavethe certificate, as well as to its competent governmentalauthority or its designees and to the customs authority ofthe importing Party. The notification shall be sent by one of the methods stipulated in paragraph 4 of Article 44. If this is done prior to the commencement of a verificationreferred to in Article 44 and if the exporter or producerdemonstrates that at time of issuance of the certificate of origin he possessed facts upon which he could reasonablyrely to the effect that the good qualified as anoriginating good, the exporter or producer shall not besubject to penalties for having submitted an incorrectcertificate. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that providing falsedeclarations or documents to its competent governmentalauthority or its designees by its exporters or producersstating that the good qualifies as an originating goodshall be subject to penalties or other appropriatesanctions as provided for in Article 46. 


3. Each Party shall ensure that the exporter referred toin paragraph 3 of Article 39 or the producer referred to inparagraph 4 of Article 39, as the case may be, shall beprepared to submit at any time, at the request of thecompetent governmental authority or its designees of theexporting Party, all appropriate documents proving theoriginating status of the goods concerned as well as thefulfillment of other requirements under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="4498">Each Party shall ensure that a certificate of originshall not be required for: 


(a) a commercial importation of a good whose valuedoes not exceed 1,000 United States dollars orits equivalent amount in the Party’s currency, orsuch higher amount as it may establish, providedthat it may require that the invoice accompanyingthe importation includes a statement indicatingthat the good qualifies as an originating good; 


(b) a non-commercial importation of a good whosevalue does not exceed 1,000 United States dollarsor its equivalent amount in the Party’s currency,or such higher amount as it may establish; or 


(c) an importation of a good for which the importingParty has waived the requirement for acertificate of origin, 
provided that the importation does not form part of aseries of importations that may reasonably beconsidered to have been undertaken or arranged for thepurposes of avoiding the certification requirements ofArticles 39 and 40.
Administration and Enforcement</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="Records" article_identifier="4499">1. Each Party shall ensure that: 


(a) an exporter referred to in paragraph 3 of Article39 or a producer referred to in paragraph 4 ofArticle 39, that has the documentation thatproves that the good qualifies as an originatinggood for the purposes of requesting a certificateof origin shall maintain in that Party, for 5years after the date on which the certificate wasissued or for such longer period as the Party mayspecify, the records relating to the origin of agood for which preferential tariff treatment wasclaimed in the other Party, including recordsassociated with: 


(i) the purchase of, cost of, value of, andpayment for, the good that is exported; 


(ii) the purchase of, cost of, value of, andpayment for, all materials, includingindirect materials, used in the productionof the good that is exported; and 
(iii) the production of the good in the form inwhich the good is exported; and 

(b) an importer claiming preferential tarifftreatment for an imported good shall maintain for5 years after the date of importation of the goodor for such longer period as the Party mayspecify, such documentation as the Party mayrequire relating to the importation of the good. 
2. Each Party shall ensure that the competentgovernmental authority or its designees shall keep a recordof the certificate of origin issued for a minimum period of5 years after the date on which the certificate was issued.Such record will include all antecedents, which werepresented to prove the qualification as an originatinggood.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" name="Origin Verifications" article_identifier="4500">1. For the purposes of determining whether a goodimported from the other Party under preferential tarifftreatment qualifies as an originating good, the importingParty may conduct a verification through its customsauthority, by means of: 


(a) request of information relating to the origin ofa good to the competent governmental authority ofthe exporting Party on the basis of a certificateof origin; 


(b) written questionnaires to an exporter or aproducer of the good in the other Party; 


(c) request to the exporting Party to collectinformation, including that contained in thedocuments maintained pursuant to Article 43, thatdemonstrate the compliance with Chapter 4 and tocheck, for that purpose, the facilities used inthe production of the good, through a visit byits competent governmental authority along withthe customs authority of the importing Party tothe premises of an exporter or a producer of thegood in the exporting Party, and to provide thecollected information in the English language tothe customs authority of the importing Party; or 


(d) such other procedure as the Parties may agree. 

2. Where the customs authority of the importing Party hasinitiated a verification in accordance with this Article,the provisions of Annex 5 shall be applied as appropriate. 


3. For the purposes of subparagraph 1(a), the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party shall providethe information requested, in a period not exceeding 4months, after the date of the request. 
If the customs authority of the importing Partyconsiders necessary, it may require additional informationrelating to the origin of the good. If additional information is requested by the customs authority of theimporting Party, the competent governmental authority ofthe exporting Party shall provide the information requestedin a period not exceeding 2 months after the date of therequest. 

If the competent governmental authority of theexporting Party fails to respond to the request within theperiod specified therein, the customs authority of theimporting Party shall determine that the good subject tothe verification does not qualify as an originating good,therefore considering the certificate of origin as notvalid, and shall deny it preferential tariff treatment. 

4. The customs authority of the importing Party shallsend the questionnaires referred to in subparagraph 1(b),to the exporters or producers in the exporting Party, byany of the following means: 


(a) certified or registered mail with confirmation ofreceipt; 


(b) any other method that produces a confirmation ofreceipt by the exporter or producer; or 


(c) such other method that the Parties may agree. 
The customs authority of the importing Party shallimmediately communicate to the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party whenever it sends aquestionnaire referred to in subparagraph 1(b). 


5. The provisions of paragraph 1 above shall not preventthe customs authority or the competent governmentalauthority, as the case may be, of the importing Party fromexercising its powers to take action in that Party, inrelation with the compliance with its domestic laws andregulations by its own importers, exporters or producers. 


6. The exporter or producer who receives a questionnairepursuant to subparagraph 1(b) shall have 30 days from thedate of its receipt to answer such questionnaire and returnit. 


7. Where the importing Party has received the answer tothe questionnaire referred to in subparagraph 1(b) withinthe period specified in paragraph 6 above, and considersthat it requires more information to determine whether thegood subject to the verification qualifies as anoriginating good, it may, through its customs authority,request additional information from the exporter orproducer, by means of a subsequent questionnaire, in whichcase, the exporter or producer shall have 30 days from thedate of its receipt to answer and return it. 


8. 	(a) If the response by the exporter or producer to any of the questionnaires referred to inparagraph 6 or 7 above does not containsufficient information to determine that the goodis originating, the customs authority of theimporting Party may determine that the goodsubject to the verification does not qualify asan originating good and may deny it preferentialtariff treatment, upon written determinationunder paragraph 22 below. 

(b) If the response to the questionnaire referred toin paragraph 6 above is not returned within theperiod specified therein, the customs authorityof the importing Party shall determine that thegood subject to the verification does not qualifyas an originating good, therefore considering thecertificate of origin as not valid, and shalldeny it preferential tariff treatment. 

9. The conducting of a verification in accordance withone of the methods set forth in paragraph 1 above shall notpreclude the use of another verification method providedfor in paragraph 1 above. 


10. When requesting the exporting Party to conduct a visitpursuant to subparagraph 1(c), the importing Party shalldeliver a written communication with such request to theexporting Party, the receipt of which is to be confirmed bythe latter Party, at least 30 days in advance of theproposed date of the visit. The competent governmental authority of the exporting Party shall request the writtenconsent of the exporter or producer whose premises are tobe visited. 


11. The communication referred to in paragraph 10 aboveshall include: 


(a) the identity of the customs authority issuing thecommunication; 


(b) the name of the exporter or producer whosepremises are requested to be visited; 


(c) the proposed date and place of the visit; 


(d) the object and scope of the proposed visit,including specific reference to the good or goodssubject of the verification referred to in thecertificate of origin; and 


(e) 	the names and titles of the officials of the customs authority of the importing Party to bepresent during the visit. 

12. Any modification to the information referred to inparagraph 11 above shall be notified in writing, prior tothe proposed date of the visit referred to in subparagraph11(c). 

If the proposed date referred to in subparagraph 11(c)is to be modified, this shall be notified in writing atleast 10 days prior to the date of the visit. 

13. The exporting Party shall respond in writing to theimporting Party, within 20 days of the receipt of thecommunication referred to in paragraph 10 above, if itaccepts or refuses to conduct a visit requested pursuant tosubparagraph 1(c). 


14. Where the exporting Party refuses to conduct a visit,or that Party fails to respond to the communicationreferred to in paragraph 10 above within the periodreferred to in paragraph 13 above, the customs authority ofthe importing Party shall determine that the good or goodsthat would have been the subject of the visit do notqualify as originating goods, therefore considering thecertificate of origin as not valid, and shall deny thempreferential tariff treatment. 


15. The competent governmental authority of the exportingParty shall provide, within 45 days, or any other mutuallyagreed period, from the last day of the visit, to thecustoms authority of the importing Party the informationobtained through the visit. 


16. It is confirmed by both Parties that during the courseof a verification referred to in paragraph 1 above, thecustoms authority of the importing Party may requestinformation necessary for determining the origin of amaterial used in the production of the good. 


17. For the purposes of obtaining information on theorigin of the material used in the production of the good,the exporter or producer of the good referred to inparagraph 1 above may request a producer of the material toprovide voluntarily the former with information relating tothe origin of such material. In case the producer of such material desires, such information may be sent to thecompetent governmental authority of the exporting Party forthe provision to the customs authority of the importingParty, without the involvement of the exporter or producerof the good. 


18. Where the customs authority of the importing Partyrequests information relating to the origin of a materialpursuant to paragraph 16 above, during the course of averification in accordance with the method set forth in subparagraph 1(a), the information shall be provided by thecompetent governmental authority of the exporting Party inaccordance with paragraph 3 above. 
Where the customs authority of the importing Partyrequests information relating to the origin of a materialpursuant to paragraph 16 above, during the course of averification in accordance with the method set forth in subparagraph 1(b), the information shall be provided by theexporter or producer of the good or the competentgovernmental authority of the exporting Party, as the casemay be, in accordance with paragraph 6 or 7 above, asappropriate and mutatis mutandis, provided that in case theinformation is provided by the competent governmentalauthority, the 30 day period referred to in paragraph 6 or7 above shall mean the period beginning on the date of thereceipt of the questionnaire by that exporter or producer. 

Where the customs authority of the importing Partyrequests information relating to the origin of a materialpursuant to paragraph 16 above, during the course of averification in accordance with the method set forth in subparagraph 1(c), the information shall be provided by thecompetent governmental authority of the exporting Party inaccordance with paragraph 15 above. 


19. The requesting of information relating to the originof a material pursuant to paragraph 16 above during thecourse of a verification in accordance with one of the methods set forth in paragraph 1 above shall not precludethe requesting of information relating to the origin of amaterial during the course of a verification in accordancewith another verification method provided for in paragraph1 above. 


20. The customs authority of the importing Party shalldetermine that a material used in the production of thegood is a non-originating material where the exporter orproducer of the good or the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party, as the case may be, doesnot provide the information that demonstrates that thematerial in question qualifies as originating, or where theinformation provided is not sufficient to determine whetherthat material is originating. Such a determination shall not necessarily lead to a decision that the good itself isnot originating. 


21. Each Party shall, through its customs authority,conduct a verification of a regional value contentrequirement in accordance with the Generally AcceptedAccounting Principles applied in the Party from which thegood was exported. 


22. After carrying out the verification proceduresoutlined in paragraph 1 above, the customs authority of theimporting Party shall in the manner specified in paragraph4 above, provide the exporter or producer whose good issubject to the verification, a written determination ofwhether or not the good qualifies as an originating goodunder Chapter 4, including findings of fact and the legalbasis for the determination. 


23. Where the customs authority of the importing Partydenies preferential tariff treatment to the good inquestion in the cases of paragraph 3, 8(b) or 14 above, awritten determination thereof shall be sent to the exporteror producer, in the manner specified in paragraph 4 above. 


24. When the Party conducting a verification referred toin paragraph 1 above determines, based on the informationobtained during the verification, that a good does notqualify as an originating good, and provides the exporteror producer with a written determination pursuant toparagraph 22 above, it shall grant the exporter or producerwhose good was the subject of the verification, 30 daysfrom the date of receipt of the written determination, toprovide any comments or additional information beforedenying preferential tariff treatment to the good, andshall issue a final determination after taking intoconsideration any comments or additional informationreceived from the exporter or producer during the above-mentioned period, and shall send it to the exporter orproducer in the manner specified in paragraph 4 above. 


25. Where the verification completed by the customsauthority of the importing Party indicates that an exporteror a producer has repeatedly made false representationsthat a good imported into the Party qualifies as anoriginating good, the customs authority of the importingParty may withhold preferential tariff treatment toidentical goods exported or produced by such person untilthat person establishes compliance with Chapter 4 to thatauthority. In taking such an action, the customs authority of the importing Party shall notify the person whocompleted and signed the certificate of origin and thecompetent governmental authority of the exporting Party. 


26. Communications from the importing Party to an exporteror producer in the exporting Party as well as the responseto the questionnaire referred to in subparagraph 1(b) tothe importing Party shall be conducted in the Englishlanguage.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="4501">1. Each Party shall maintain, in accordance with itsdomestic laws and regulations, the confidentiality ofinformation provided to it as confidential pursuant toSection 1 and this Section and shall protect thatinformation from disclosure that could prejudice thecompetitive position of the persons providing theinformation. 


2. Information obtained pursuant to Section 1 and thisSection may only be disclosed, for the purposes of Section1 and this Section, to those competent authorities of theParties responsible for the administration and enforcementof determinations of origin and of customs duties and otherindirect taxes on imports, and shall not be used by a Partyin any criminal proceedings carried out by a court or ajudge, unless the information is requested to the otherParty and provided to the former Party, in accordance withthe applicable laws of the requested Party or appropriateinternational cooperation agreements to which both Partiesare parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Penalties" article_identifier="4502">Each Party shall ensure that criminal, civil oradministrative penalties or other appropriate sanctionsagainst its importers, exporters and producers forproviding false declaration or documents relating toSection 1 and this Section to its customs authority,competent governmental authority or its designees, shall beestablished or maintained.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="4503">Each Party shall ensure that its importers have accessto: 


(a) 	at least one level of administrative review of a decision by its customs authority, provided thatsuch review is done by an official or officedifferent from the official or office making thedecision subject to review; and 


(b) judicial or quasi-judicial review of the decisionreferred to in subparagraph (a), 
in accordance with its domestic laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" name="Goods In Transit Or Storage" article_identifier="4504">The provisions of this Agreement may be applied togoods which comply with the provisions of Chapter 4 andSection 1, and which on the date of entry into force ofthis Agreement are in transit, in Japan or Mexico, or intemporary storage in bonded area, subject to the submissionto the customs authority of the importing Party inaccordance with the domestic laws and regulations of thatParty, within 4 months of that date, of a certificate oforigin issued retrospectively, in accordance with paragraph5 of Article 39, by the competent governmental authority orits designees of the exporting Party together with thedocuments showing that the goods have been transporteddirectly.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4505">1. For the purposes of Section 1 and this Section: 


(a) the term “authorized representative“ means theperson designated in accordance with its domesticlaws and regulations by the exporter to beresponsible for completing and signing thecertificate of origin on his behalf; 


(b) the term “commercial importation“ means theimportation of a good into a Party for thepurposes of sale, or any commercial, industrialor other like use; 


(c) the term “competent governmental authority“ meansthe authority that, according to the legislationof each Party, is responsible for the issuing ofthe certificate of origin or for the designationof the certification entities or bodies. In the case of Japan, the Minister of Economy, Trade andIndustry or his authorized representative, and inthe case of Mexico, the Ministry of Economy; 


(d) the term “customs authority“ means the authoritythat, according to the legislation of each Party,is responsible for the administration of itscustoms laws and regulations. In the case of Japan, the Minister of Finance or his authorizedrepresentative, and in the case of Mexico, theMinistry of Finance and Public Credit; 


(e) the term “determination of origin“ means adetermination whether a good qualifies as anoriginating good in accordance with Chapter 4; 


(f) the term “exporter“ means a person located in anexporting Party who exports a good from theexporting Party; 


(g) the term “identical goods“ means goods that arethe same in all respects, including physicalcharacteristics, quality and reputation,irrespective of minor differences in appearancethat are not relevant to a determination of origin; 


(h) the term “importer“ means a person located in animporting Party who imports a good into theimporting Party; 


(i) the term “preferential tariff treatment“ meansthe duty rate applicable to an originating goodin accordance with this Agreement; 


(j) the term “producer“ means “producer”, as definedin Article 38, located in a Party; 


(k) the term “valid certificate of origin“ means acertificate of origin in the format referred toin paragraph 1 of Article 39, completed andsigned by the exporter or the producer andstamped and signed by the competent governmentalauthority of the exporting Party or itsdesignees, in accordance with the provisions ofSection 1 and with the instructions indicated in the format; and 


(l) the term “value“ means the value of a good ormaterial for the purposes of applying Chapter 4. 
2. Except as otherwise defined in this Article, thedefinitions of Chapter 4 shall apply.
Customs Cooperation for Trade Facilitation</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" name="Customs Cooperation For Trade Facilitation" article_identifier="4506">For prompt customs clearance of goods traded betweenthe Parties, each Party, recognizing the significant roleof customs authorities and the importance of customsprocedures in promoting trade facilitation, shall makecooperative efforts to: 


(a) 	make use of information and communications technology; 


(b) simplify its customs procedures; and 


(c) make its customs procedures conform, as far aspossible, to relevant international standards andrecommended practices such as those made underthe auspices of the Customs Cooperation Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures" chapter_identifier="519">
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" name="General Provision" article_identifier="4507">1. This Chapter establishes rules for the application ofbilateral safeguard measures to originating goods, whichshall be applied only between the Parties (hereinafterreferred to as “bilateral safeguard measures”). 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a Party fromapplying safeguard measures in accordance with Article XIXof the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on Safeguards in Annex1A to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended. Except for the bilateral safeguard measures provided for in this Chapter,no Party shall apply safeguard measures to originatinggoods which are accorded the preferential tariff treatmentin accordance with Article 5, outside the scope of ArticleXIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on Safeguards inAnnex 1A to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" name="Consistency" article_identifier="4508">Each Party shall ensure the consistent, impartial andreasonable administration of its laws, regulations,decisions and rulings governing proceedings of bilateralsafeguard measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" name="Conditions" article_identifier="4509">1. Subject to the provisions of this Chapter, each Partymay apply a bilateral safeguard measure, to the minimumextent necessary to prevent or remedy the serious injuryand to facilitate adjustment if an originating goodimported from the other Party, which is accorded thepreferential tariff treatment in accordance with Article 5,as a result of the elimination or reduction of a customs duty, is being imported into the former Party in suchincreased quantities, in absolute terms, and under suchconditions that the imports of that originating goodconstitute a substantial cause of serious injury, or threatthereof, to a domestic industry of the former Party. 


2. A Party proposing to apply a bilateral safeguardmeasure may (a) suspend the further reduction of any rateof customs duty on the originating good referred to inparagraph 1 above in accordance with Article 5; or (b)increase the rate of customs duty on the originating goodto a level not to exceed the lesser of: 


(i) the most-favored-nation applied rate ofcustoms duty in effect at the time when thebilateral safeguard measure is taken; and 


(ii) the most-favored-nation applied rate ofcustoms duty in effect on the dayimmediately preceding the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement. 

3. A bilateral safeguard measure shall consist of tariffmeasures, including application of tariff rate quotas. 


4. Each Party shall not apply bilateral safeguardmeasures on an originating good imported up to the limit ofquota quantities granted under tariff rate quotas appliedin accordance with Schedule in Annex 1. 


5. No bilateral safeguard measure shall be maintained fora period exceeding 3 years. However, in very exceptional circumstances, after the prior consultations referred to inparagraph 9 below, a bilateral safeguard measure may bemaintained for up to a total maximum period of 4 years. A Party taking such measure shall present to the other Partya schedule leading to its progressive elimination. 


6. No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied againto the imports of the same originating good which has beensubject to a bilateral safeguard measure, for a period oftime equal to the duration of the previous measure or 1year, whichever is longer. 


7. A Party shall deliver a written notice in English tothe other Party immediately upon initiation of aninvestigation referred to in Article 55. Such written notice shall include the reason for the initiation of the investigation, a precise description of the originatinggood involved and its subheading or a more detailed levelof the Harmonized System. 


8. A Party shall deliver a written notice in English tothe other Party prior to applying a bilateral safeguardmeasure. Such written notice shall include a descriptionof evidence of the serious injury or threat thereof causedby the increased imports, a precise description of theoriginating good involved and its subheading or a moredetailed level of the Harmonized System, a precisedescription of the proposed bilateral safeguard measure,its date of entry into force, and its expected duration. 


9. A Party proposing to apply a bilateral safeguardmeasure shall provide adequate opportunity for priorconsultations with the other Party on such measure with aview to, inter alia, reaching an agreement on compensationset out in paragraph 10 below. 


10. A Party proposing to apply a bilateral safeguardmeasure shall offer the other Party adequate means of tradecompensation in the form of additional concessions ofcustoms duties whose levels are substantially equivalent tothe value of the additional customs duties expected toresult from such measure, and, in the case that room forsuch sufficient additional concessions of customs duties is already exhausted through overall reduction of customsduties, other concessions which the Parties may agree upon. 


11. If the Parties are unable to agree on compensationwithin 60 days after the date when a Party initiates theapplication of the bilateral safeguard measure, the otherParty shall be free to suspend, to the trade of the Partyapplying such measure, the application of concessions ofcustoms duties under Article 5, which are substantiallyequivalent to such measure applied. For this purpose, the Party exercising the right of suspension may suspend theapplication of concessions of customs duties only for theminimum period necessary. 


12. Upon termination of a bilateral safeguard measure, therate of customs duty shall be the rate which would havebeen in effect but for such measure. 


13. The Parties shall review the provisions of thisChapter, if necessary, after 10 years of the date of entryinto force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" name="Provisional Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="4510">1. In critical circumstances, where delay would causedamage which it would be difficult to repair, a Party maytake a provisional bilateral safeguard measure pursuant toa preliminary determination that there is clear evidencethat increased imports have caused or are threatening tocause serious injury to a domestic industry. 


2. A Party shall deliver a written notice in English tothe other Party prior to applying a provisional bilateralsafeguard measure. Consultations on such measure shall take place promptly after such measure is taken. 


3. The duration of the provisional bilateral safeguardmeasure shall not exceed 200 days. During that period, the pertinent requirements of Articles 52 and 55 shall be met.The duration of such measure shall be counted as a part ofthe period referred to in paragraph 5 of Article 53. 


4. Paragraphs 2 through 4 and 12 of Article 53 shall beapplied mutatis mutandis to the provisional bilateralsafeguard measure. The customs duty imposed as a result of such measure shall be refunded within 60 days if thesubsequent investigation referred to in Article 55 does notdetermine that increased imports have caused or threatenedto cause serious injury to a domestic industry.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" name="Bilateral Safeguard Measures Proceedings" article_identifier="4511">1. Each Party shall adopt or maintain equitable, timely,transparent and effective proceedings relating to bilateralsafeguard measures. 


2. A Party shall apply a bilateral safeguard measure onlyfollowing an investigation by its investigating authoritypursuant to the provisions of this Chapter. 


3. The investigating authority of a Party shall examineand ensure the existence of sufficient evidence that the increased imports of an originating good are causingserious injury or threat thereof to the domestic industryconcerned, to justify the initiation of an investigation. 


4. An investigation shall, except in specialcircumstances, be completed within 1 year, and in no casemore than 18 months, following its date of initiation. 


5. Upon initiation of an investigation, the investigatingauthority of a Party shall give a public notice of theinitiation of the investigation through the officialjournal of that Party. The public notice shall identify the originating good subject to the investigation and itssubheading or a more detailed level of the HarmonizedSystem, the period of investigation, the date of initiationof the investigation, deadlines for filing statements andother documents, and the place at which documents filedduring the investigation may be inspected. 


6. Each Party shall establish procedure to allow aninterested party to have access to information submitted byother interested parties to the investigating authority ofthat Party after submission of such information. The investigating authority shall, upon request of aninterested party, provide timely access to the information,including documents, items of evidence, and non-confidential written summaries referred to in paragraph 7below, which were submitted by other interested partiesduring the investigation. In particular, the investigating authority shall grant access to the interested parties tothe following information related to the investigation: 


(a) production processes for the good concerned; 


(b) production costs of the good concerned andspecifications of its components; 


(c) distribution costs of the good concerned; 


(d) terms and conditions of sale of the goodconcerned; 


(e) selling prices of the good concerned; 


(f) description of the category of individualcustomers, distributors, suppliers, and any otherenterprises related to the good concerned; 


(g) data considered for the injury analysis such asthe level of sales, production, productivity,capacity utilization, profits and losses, andemployment related to the domestic industryconcerned; and 


(h) any other information about the enterpriserelated to the good concerned. 

7. Notwithstanding paragraph 6 above, each Party shalladopt or maintain procedures for the treatment ofconfidential information as specified by that Party inaccordance with its domestic laws and regulations and whichis provided in the course of an investigation. When the interested parties provide such information, they shall berequired to furnish non-confidential written summariesthereof, or if they indicate that the information cannot besummarized, the reasons why a summary cannot be provided. 


8. During the course of each investigation, theinvestigating authority of a Party shall endeavor to hold apublic hearing after providing reasonable notice, so thatopposite views may be presented and rebuttal argumentsoffered. Such public hearing should allow interestedparties to defend their interest and to question the otherparties. 


9. In the investigation to determine whether increasedimports have caused serious injury or are threatening tocause serious injury to a domestic industry, theinvestigating authority of a Party shall evaluate allrelevant factors of an objective and quantifiable naturehaving a bearing on the situation of that domesticindustry, in particular, the rate and amount of theincrease in imports of the originating good, in absoluteterms, the share of the domestic market taken by increasedimports, and changes in the level of sales, production,productivity, capacity utilization, profits and losses,employment, and prices. 


10. The determination that increased imports have causedserious injury or are threatening to cause serious injuryto a domestic industry shall not be made unless thisinvestigation demonstrates, on the basis of objectiveevidence, the existence of the causal link betweenincreased imports of the originating good and seriousinjury or threat thereof. When factors other than increased imports are causing injury to the domesticindustry at the same time, such injury shall not beattributed to increased imports. 


11. With regard to determination on whether increasedimports have caused serious injury or are threatening tocause serious injury to a domestic industry, theinvestigating authority of a Party shall not arbitrarilymodify a negative injury determination. 


12. Upon decision to apply a bilateral safeguard measure,the investigating authority of a Party shall give a publicnotice through the official journal of that Party. The public notice shall identify the originating good subjectto such measure and its subheading or a more detailed levelof the Harmonized System, the duration of such measure, andthe findings and reasoned conclusions reached on allpertinent issues of law and fact. 


13. In the public notice the investigating authority of aParty shall not disclose any confidential informationreferred to in paragraph 7 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4512">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “domestic industry” means the producersas a whole of the like or directly competitivegoods operating in the Area of a Party, or thosewhose collective output of the like or directlycompetitive goods constitutes a major proportionof the total domestic production of those goods; 


(b) the term “serious injury” means a significantoverall impairment in the position of a domesticindustry; and 


(c) the term “threat of serious injury” means seriousinjury that is clearly imminent, based on factsand not merely on allegation, conjecture orremote possibility.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="520">
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4513">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted ormaintained by a Party relating to: 


(a) investors of the other Party; 


(b) investments of investors of the other Party inthe Area of the former Party; and 


(c) with respect to Articles 65 and 74, allinvestments in the Area of the former Party. 

2. A Party has the right to perform exclusively theeconomic activities set out in Annex 8 and to refuse to permit the establishment of investment in such activities. 


3. This Chapter shall not apply to measures adopted ormaintained by a Party to the extent that they are coveredby Chapter 9. 


4. Nothing in this Chapter shall impose any obligation oneither Party regarding measures pursuant to immigrationlaws and regulations. 
Note: 	Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed toprevent a Party from providing a service orperforming a function such as law enforcement,correctional services, income security or insurance,social security or insurance, social welfare, publiceducation, public training, health, and child care,in a manner that is not inconsistent with this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="4514">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the otherParty and to their investments treatment no less favorablethan the treatment it accords, in like circumstances, toits own investors and to their investments with respect tothe establishment, acquisition, expansion, management,conduct, operation, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale orother disposition of investments (hereinafter referred toin this Chapter as “investment activities”). 


2. The treatment accorded by a Party under paragraph 1above means, with respect to a local government in the caseof Japan, and with respect to a state in the case ofMexico, treatment no less favorable than the most favorabletreatment accorded, in like circumstances, by that localgovernment or state to investors, and to investments ofinvestors, of the Party of which it forms a part.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="4515">Each Party shall accord to investors of the other


Party and to their investments, treatment no less favorable

than the treatment it accords, in like circumstances, to

investors of a non-Party and to their investments with

respect to investment activities. 

Note 1: 	Each Party shall accord to investors of the otherParty and to their investments the better of thetreatment required by Articles 58 and 59. 

Note 2: 	For greater certainty, it is confirmed by bothParties that in the application of Articles 58 and59 a Party: 


(a) may not impose on an investor of the other Partya requirement that a minimum level of equity inan enterprise in the Area of the former Party beheld by its nationals; or 


(b) may not require an investor of the other Party,by reason of its nationality, to sell orotherwise dispose of an investment in the Area ofthe former Party. 
Note 3: 	Each Party shall in its Area accord to investorsof the other Party treatment no less favorablethan the treatment which it accords, in likecircumstances, to its own investors or investorsof a non-Party with respect to access to thecourts of justice and administrative tribunals andagencies in all degrees of jurisdiction, both inpursuit and in defense of such investor’s rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="4516">Each Party shall accord to investments of investors of

the other Party treatment in accordance with international

law, including fair and equitable treatment and full

protection and security. 

Note: 	This Article prescribes the customary internationallaw minimum standard of treatment of aliens as the minimum standard of treatment to be afforded to investments of investors of the other Party. The concepts of “fair and equitable treatment” and “fullprotection and security” do not require treatment inaddition to or beyond that which is required by thecustomary international law minimum standard oftreatment of aliens. A determination that there has been a breach of another provision of thisAgreement, or of a separate international agreement,does not establish that there has been a breach of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="4517">1. Neither Party shall expropriate or nationalize aninvestment of an investor of the other Party in its Areaeither directly or indirectly through measures tantamountto expropriation or nationalization (hereinafter referredto as “expropriation”) except: (a) for a public purpose; 

(b) on a non-discriminatory basis; (c) in accordance withdue process of law and Article 60; and (d) on payment ofcompensation pursuant to paragraphs 2 through 5 below. 


2. Compensation shall be equivalent to the fair marketvalue of the expropriated investment immediately before theexpropriation occurred. The fair market value shall not reflect any change in value occurring because theexpropriatory action had become known earlier. Valuation criteria to determine the fair market value may includedeclared tax value of tangible property. The compensation shall be paid without delay and be fully realizable. 


3. If payment is made in a freely usable currency,compensation shall include interest at a commerciallyreasonable rate for that currency from the date ofexpropriation until the date of actual payment. 


4. If a Party elects to pay in a currency other than afreely usable currency, the compensation paid, convertedinto the currency of payment at the market rate of exchangeprevailing on the date of payment, shall be no less than: 


(a) 	the fair market value on the date of expropriation, converted into a freely usablecurrency at the market rate of exchangeprevailing on that date, plus 


(b) interest, at a commercially reasonable rate forthat freely usable currency, accrued from thedate of expropriation until the actual date ofpayment. 

5. On payment, compensation shall be freely transferableas provided in Article 63.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="4518">Without prejudice to Article 60 and notwithstandingArticle 66, each Party shall accord to investors of theother Party and to their investments treatment no lessfavorable than the treatment it accords to its own investors or investors of a non-Party and to theirinvestments, whichever is more favorable to the investor ofthe other Party or its investments, with respect tomeasures, such as restitution, indemnification,compensation or any other settlement, it adopts ormaintains relating to losses suffered by investments in itsArea owing to armed conflict, civil strife or any othersimilar event.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" name="Transfers" article_identifier="4519">1. Each Party shall allow all transfers relating to aninvestment in its Area of an investor of the other Party tobe made freely and without delay. Such transfers shall include: 


(a) the initial capital and additional amounts tomaintain or increase the investment; 


(b) profits, dividends, interest, capital gains,royalty payments, management fees, technicalassistance fees and other fees; 


(c) proceeds from the sale or liquidation of all orany part of the investment; 


(d) payments made under a contract including paymentsmade pursuant to a loan agreement; 


(e) payments made in accordance with Article 61; and 


(f) payments arising out of the settlement of adispute under Section 2. 

2. Each Party shall allow transfers to be made withoutdelay in a freely usable currency at the market rate ofexchange prevailing on the date of the transfer withrespect to spot transactions in the currency to betransferred. 


3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2 above, a Party maydelay or prevent a transfer through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good faith application of its lawsrelating to: 


(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of therights of creditors; 


(b) issuing, trading or dealing in securities; 


(c) criminal or penal offenses; 


(d) reports of transfers of currency or othermonetary instruments; or 


(e) ensuring compliance with orders or judgments inadjudicatory proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" name="Senior Management And Boards Of Directors" article_identifier="4520">1. Neither Party may require that an enterprise of thatParty that is an investment of an investor of the otherParty appoint to senior management positions individuals ofany particular nationality. 


2. A Party may require that a majority of the board ofdirectors, or any committee thereof, of an enterprise ofthat Party that is an investment of an investor of theother Party, be of a particular nationality, or resident ofthe Party, provided that the requirement does notmaterially impair the ability of the investor to exercisecontrol over its investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 65" name="Performance Requirements" article_identifier="4521">1. Neither Party may impose or enforce any of thefollowing requirements, or enforce any commitment orundertaking, in connection with the establishment,acquisition, expansion, management, conduct or operation ofan investment of an investor of a Party or of a non-Partyin its Area: 


(a) to export a given level or percentage of goods orservices; 


(b) to achieve a given level or percentage ofdomestic content; 


(c) to purchase, use or accord a preference to goodsproduced or services provided in its Area, or topurchase goods or services from persons in itsArea; 


(d) to relate in any way the volume or value ofimports to the volume or value of exports or tothe amount of foreign exchange inflows associatedwith such investment; 


(e) to restrict sales of goods or services in itsArea that such investment produces or provides byrelating such sales in any way to the volume orvalue of its exports or foreign exchangeearnings; 


(f) to transfer technology, a production process orother proprietary knowledge to a person in itsArea, except when the requirement is imposed orthe commitment or undertaking is enforced by acourt, administrative tribunal or competitionauthority to remedy an alleged violation ofcompetition laws or to act in a manner notinconsistent with multilateral agreements inrespect of protection of intellectual propertyrights. A measure that requires an investment to use a technology to meet generally applicablehealth, safety or environmental requirementsshall not be construed to be inconsistent with this paragraph. For greater certainty, Articles 58 and 59 shall apply to the measure; or 


(g) to act as the exclusive supplier of the goods itproduces or services it provides to a specificregion or world market. 
2. Neither Party may condition the receipt or continuedreceipt of an advantage, in connection with an investmentin its Area of an investor of a Party or of a non-Party, oncompliance with any of the following requirements: 


(a) to achieve a given level or percentage ofdomestic content; 


(b) to purchase, use or accord a preference to goodsproduced in its Area, or to purchase goods fromproducers in its Area; 


(c) to relate in any way the volume or value ofimports to the volume or value of exports or tothe amount of foreign exchange inflows associatedwith such investment; or 


(d) to restrict sales of goods or services in itsArea that such investment produces or provides byrelating such sales in any way to the volume orvalue of its exports or foreign exchangeearnings. 
3. Nothing in paragraph 2 above shall be construed toprevent a Party from conditioning the receipt or continuedreceipt of an advantage, in connection with an investmentin its Area of an investor of a Party or of a non-Party, oncompliance with a requirement to: 


(a) locate production; 


(b) provide a service; 


(c) train or employ workers; 


(d) construct or expand particular facilities; or 


(e) carry out research and development 
in its Area. 


4. Paragraphs 1 and 2 above shall not apply to anyrequirement other than the requirements set out in thoseparagraphs. 


5. Provided that such measures are not applied in anarbitrary or unjustifiable manner, or do not constitute adisguised restriction on international trade or investmentactivities, nothing in subparagraph 1(b) or (c) or 2(a) or
(b) above shall be construed to prevent any Party fromadopting or maintaining measures: 


(a) necessary to secure compliance with laws andregulations that are not inconsistent with theprovisions of this Agreement; 


(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant lifeor health; or 


(c) necessary for the conservation of living or nonliving exhaustible natural resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 66" name="Reservations And Exceptions" article_identifier="4522">1. Articles 58, 59, 64 and 65 shall not apply to: 


(a) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by a Party at the federal or centralgovernment level, as set out in its Schedule toAnnex 6 or Annex 8; or 


(b) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by: 
(i) with respect to Mexico: 

(AA) a state, for 6 months after the date ofentry into force of this Agreement, andthereafter as to be set out by Mexicoin its Schedule to Annex 6 in accordance with paragraph 2 below; or 

(BB) a local government; and 

(ii) with respect to Japan: 

(AA) a prefecture, for 6 months after thedate of entry into force of thisAgreement, and thereafter as to be setout by Japan in its Schedule to Annex 6in accordance with paragraph 2 below;or 

(BB) a local authority other thanprefectures; 


(c) the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs

(a) and (b) above; or 

(d) an amendment or a modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs
(a) and (b) above provided that the amendment ormodification does not decrease the conformity ofthe measure, as it existed immediately before theamendment or modification, with Articles 58, 59,64 and 65. 


2. Each Party shall set out in its Schedule to Annex 6,within 6 months of the date of entry into force of thisAgreement, any existing non-conforming measure maintainedby a state or a prefecture as referred to in subparagraphs1(b)(i)(AA) and 1(b)(ii)(AA) above, and shall notifythereof the other Party by a diplomatic note. 


3. Articles 58, 59, 64 and 65 shall not apply to anymeasure that a Party adopts or maintains with respect tosectors, subsectors or activities, as set out in itsSchedule to Annex 7. 


4. Neither Party may, under any measure adopted after thedate of entry into force of this Agreement and covered byAnnex 7, require an investor of the other Party, by reasonof its nationality, to sell or otherwise dispose of aninvestment that exists at the time the measure becomes effective. 


5. Article 59 shall not apply to treatment accorded by aParty pursuant to agreements, or with respect to sectors,set out in its Schedule to Annex 9. 


6. Articles 58, 59 and 64 shall not apply to any measureadopted or maintained with respect to procurement by aParty or a state enterprise. 


7. The provisions of: 


(a) subparagraphs 1(a), (b) and (c), and 2(a) and (b)of Article 65 shall not apply to qualificationrequirements for goods or services with respectto export promotion and foreign aid programs; 


(b) subparagraphs 1(b), (c), (f) and (g), and 2(a)and (b) of Article 65 shall not apply toprocurement by a Party or a state enterprise; and 


(c) subparagraphs 2(a) and (b) of Article 65 shallnot apply to requirements imposed by an importingParty relating to the content of goods necessaryto qualify for preferential tariffs orpreferential quotas.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 67" name="Notification" article_identifier="4523">To the maximum extent possible, each Party shallnotify the other Party of any new measure that the formerParty considers might materially affect the implementationand operation of this Chapter and of Annexes 6 to 9.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 68" name="Special Formalities And Information Requirements" article_identifier="4524">1. Nothing in Article 58 shall be construed to prevent aParty from adopting or maintaining a measure thatprescribes special formalities in connection with theestablishment of investments by investors of the otherParty, such as the compliance with registrationrequirements or that investments be legally constitutedunder the laws or regulations of the Party, provided thatsuch formalities do not materially impair the protectionafforded by a Party to investors of the other Party andinvestments of investors of the other Party pursuant tothis Chapter. 


2. Notwithstanding Article 58 or 59, a Party may requirean investor of the other Party, or its investment in itsArea, to provide routine information concerning thatinvestment solely for information or statistical purposes.The Party shall protect such business information that isconfidential from any disclosure that would prejudice thecompetitive position of the investor or the investment.Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to prevent aParty from otherwise obtaining or disclosing information inconnection with the equitable and good faith application ofits law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 69" name="Relation To Other Chapters" article_identifier="4525">In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapterand another Chapter, the other Chapter shall prevail to theextent of the inconsistency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 70" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="4526">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to aninvestor of the other Party that is an enterprise of suchParty and to an investment of such investor if investors ofa non-Party own or control the enterprise and the denyingParty: 


(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with thenon-Party; or 


(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to thenon-Party that prohibit transactions with theenterprise or that would be violated orcircumvented if the benefits of this Chapter wereaccorded to the enterprise or to its investments. 
2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, aParty may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an investorof the other Party that is an enterprise of such Party andto investments of such investor if investors of a non-Partyown or control the enterprise and the enterprise has nosubstantial business activities in the Area of the Partyunder whose law it is constituted or organized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 71" name="Investment Support" article_identifier="4527">1. An issuer may provide to investors of any Party,investment support in connection with projects oractivities in the Area of the other Party. Investors and investments of investors of a Party in the Area of theother Party may enter into agreements for investmentsupport with the issuer. The issuer will undertake investment support only in respect of projects andactivities allowed by this Agreement. 


2. If the issuer makes a payment to any person or entity,or exercises its rights as a creditor or subrogee, inconnection with any investment support, the other Partyshall recognize the transfer to, or acquisition by, theissuer of any cash, accounts, credits, instruments or otherassets in connection with such payment or the exercise ofsuch rights, as well as the succession of the issuer to anyright, title, claim, privilege or cause of action,existing, or which may arise, in connection therewith. 


3. With respect to any interests transferred to oracquired by the issuer or any interests to which the issuersucceeds, under this Article, in its own right or otherwiseby contract or operation of law, the issuer shall assert nogreater rights than those of the person or entity from whomsuch interests were received. 


4. To the extent that the laws of a Party partially orwholly restrict ownership or acquisition by, or transfer orsuccession to, the issuer of any interests as described inparagraph 3 above, the Party shall permit the issuer tomake appropriate arrangements to transfer such assets,interests or rights to a person or entity permitted to ownthem under the laws of that Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 72" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="4528">1. A Party may adopt or maintain measures not conformingwith its obligations under Article 58 relating to cross-border capital transactions and Article 63: 


(a) in the event of serious balance-of-payments andexternal financial difficulties or imminent threat thereof; or 


(b) in cases where, in exceptional circumstances,movements of capital cause or threaten to causeserious difficulties for macroeconomic management, in particular, monetary and exchangerate policies. 
2. 	Measures referred to in paragraph 1 above: 


(a) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, asmay be amended; 


(b) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with thecircumstances set out in paragraph 1 above; 


(c) shall be temporary and shall be eliminated assoon as conditions permit; and 


(d) shall be promptly notified to the other Party. 
3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be regarded as alteringthe rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party asa party to the Articles of Agreement of the InternationalMonetary Fund, as may be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 73" name="Intellectual Property Rights" article_identifier="4529">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed so as toderogate from the rights and obligations under multilateralagreements in respect of protection of intellectualproperty rights to which the Parties are parties. 


2. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed so as tooblige either Party to extend to investors of the otherParty and their investments treatment accorded to investorsof a non-Party and their investments by virtue ofmultilateral agreements in respect of protection ofintellectual property rights, to which the former Party isa party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 74" name="Environmental Measures" article_identifier="4530">The Parties recognize that it is inappropriate toencourage investment by relaxing domestic health, safety orenvironmental measures. Accordingly, a Party should notwaive or otherwise derogate from, or offer to waive orotherwise derogate from, such measures as an encouragementfor the establishment, acquisition, expansion or retentionin its Area of an investment of an investor. If a Partyconsiders that the other Party has offered such anencouragement, it may request consultations with the otherParty and the Parties shall consult with a view to avoidingany such encouragement.
Settlement of Investment Disputes
between a Party and an Investor of the Other Party</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 75" name="Purpose" article_identifier="4531">Without prejudice to the rights and obligations of theParties under Chapter 15, this Section establishes amechanism for the settlement of investment disputes thatassures both equal treatment among investors of the Partiesand due process before an impartial tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 76" name="Claim By An Investor" article_identifier="4532">1. An investor of a Party: 


(a) on its own behalf, may submit to arbitrationunder this Section a claim that the other Partyhas breached an obligation under Section 1 andthat the investor has incurred loss or damage byreason of, or arising out of, that breach; and 


(b) on behalf of an enterprise of the other Partythat is a legal person that the investor owns orcontrols directly or indirectly, may submit toarbitration under this Section a claim that the other Party has breached an obligation underSection 1 and that the enterprise has incurredloss or damages by reason of, or arising out of,that breach. 
2. An investment may not make a claim under this Section.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 77" name="Consultation And Negotiation" article_identifier="4533">The disputing parties should first attempt to settle aclaim through consultation or negotiation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 78" name="Written Request" article_identifier="4534">1. The disputing investor shall submit to the disputingParty a written request for consultations with a view tosettling the claim amicably at least 180 days before theclaim may be submitted to arbitration. Such a request shall specify: 


(a) the name and address of the disputing investorand, where a claim is submitted by an investor ofa Party on behalf of an enterprise, the name andaddress of the enterprise; 


(b) the provisions of this Agreement alleged to havebeen breached and any other relevant provisions; 


(c) the issues and the factual and legal basis forthe claim, including specific measures adopted bythe disputing Party; and 


(d) the relief sought and the approximate amount ofdamages claimed. 
2. The disputing investor may not submit its writtenrequest referred to in paragraph 1 above before the eventsgiving rise to a claim have occurred.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 79" name="Submission Of A Claim To Arbitration" article_identifier="4535">1. Subject to the compliance of the requirementsestablished under Article 78 the disputing investor maysubmit the claim to: 


(a) arbitration under the ICSID Convention providedthat both the disputing Party and the Party ofthe investor are parties to the ICSID Convention; 


(b) arbitration under the ICSID Additional FacilityRules, as may be amended, provided that eitherthe disputing Party or the Party of the investor,but not both, is a party to the ICSID Convention; 


(c) arbitration under the UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules; or 


(d) if agreed by the disputing parties, anyarbitration in accordance with other arbitration rules. 
2. The applicable arbitration rules shall govern thearbitration under this Section except to the extentmodified by this Section.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 80" name="Consent To Arbitration" article_identifier="4536">1. Each Party consents to the submission of a claim toarbitration in accordance with the procedures set out inthis Section. 


2. The consent given by paragraph 1 above and thesubmission by a disputing investor of a claim toarbitration shall satisfy the requirement of: 


(a) Chapter II of the ICSID Convention (Jurisdictionof the Centre) and the Additional Facility Rulesfor written consent of the parties; and 


(b) 	Article II of the New York Convention for an agreement in writing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 81" name="Conditions And Limitations On Consent Of Each Party" article_identifier="4537">1. No claim may be submitted to arbitration under thisSection if more than 3 years have elapsed from the date onwhich the investor (for claims brought under subparagraph 1

(a) of Article 76) or the enterprise (for claims broughtunder subparagraph 1(b) of Article 76) first acquired, orshould have first acquired knowledge of the breach allegedunder Article 76 and knowledge that the investor (forclaims brought under subparagraph 1(a) of Article 76), orthe enterprise (for claims brought under subparagraph 1(b)of Article 76) had incurred loss or damage. 

2. No claim may be submitted to arbitration under thisSection unless: 


(a) (i) 	for claims submitted to arbitration under subparagraph 1(a) of Article 76, theinvestor consents in writing to arbitrationin accordance with the procedures set out inthis Section; 

(ii) 	for claims submitted to arbitration under subparagraph 1(b) of Article 76, theinvestor and the enterprise agree upon thesubmission of a claim on behalf of the enterprise by the investor with respect tothe claim and both of them consent in writing to arbitration in accordance withthe procedures set out in this Section; 

(b) 	for claims submitted to arbitration under subparagraph 1(a) of Article 76, the investorand, where the claim is for loss or damage to aninterest in an enterprise of the other Party thatis a legal person that the investor owns orcontrols directly or indirectly, the enterprise,waive in writing their right to initiate orcontinue before any administrative tribunal orcourt under the law of either Party, or otherdispute settlement procedures, any proceedingswith respect to any measure alleged to constitutea breach referred to in paragraph 1 of Article76; 


(c) 	for claims submitted to arbitration under subparagraph 1(b) of Article 76, both theinvestor and the enterprise waive in writingtheir right to initiate or continue before anyadministrative tribunal or court under the law of either Party, or other dispute settlementprocedures, any proceedings with respect to anymeasure alleged to constitute a breach referredto in paragraph 1 of Article 76; and 


(d) where the investor (for claims brought undersubparagraph 1(a) of Article 76) or theenterprise (for claims brought under subparagraph1(b) of Article 76) has initiated any proceedingsbefore any administrative tribunal or courtreferred to in subparagraphs (b) and (c) above,those proceedings are withdrawn in accordancewith the laws of that Party. 

3. Notwithstanding subparagraphs (b) and (c) above, theinvestor (for claims submitted to arbitration undersubparagraph 1(a) of Article 76) and both the investor andthe enterprise (for claims submitted to arbitration undersubparagraph 1(b) of Article 76), may initiate or continuean action that seeks interim injunctive relief or otherextraordinary relief that does not involve the payment ofdamages before an administrative tribunal or court underthe law of the disputing Party. 


4. With respect to the submission of a claim toarbitration: 


(a) an investor of a Party may not allege that theother Party has breached an obligation underSection 1, both in an arbitration under thisSection and in proceedings before anadministrative tribunal or court under the law of either Party; and 


(b) where an enterprise of a Party that is a legalperson that an investor of the other Party ownsor controls directly or indirectly alleges inproceedings before an administrative tribunal orcourt under the law of either Party that such aParty has breached an obligation under Section 1,the investor may not allege the breach in anarbitration under this Section.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 82" name="Constitution Of A Tribunal" article_identifier="4538">1. Except in respect of a Tribunal established underArticle 83, and unless the disputing parties otherwiseagree, the Tribunal shall comprise 3 arbitrators, onearbitrator appointed by each of the disputing parties andthe third, who shall be the presiding arbitrator, appointedby agreement of the disputing parties. 


2. The Secretary-General shall serve as appointingauthority for an arbitration under this Section. 


3. If the Tribunal, other than the Tribunal establishedunder Article 83, has not been constituted within 90 daysfrom the date on which a claim was submitted to arbitration, the Secretary-General, on the request ofeither disputing party, shall appoint, in his discretion,the arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed except thatthe presiding arbitrator shall be appointed in accordancewith paragraph 4 below. 


4. The Secretary-General shall appoint the presidingarbitrator from the roster of presiding arbitratorsreferred to in paragraph 5 below or, if not available, fromthe ICSID Panel of Arbitrators, provided that in both casesthe presiding arbitrator shall not be a national of thedisputing Party or a national of the Party of the disputinginvestor. 


5. The Parties may establish, and thereafter maintain, aroster of 20 presiding arbitrators experienced ininternational law and investment matters. The roster members shall be appointed by agreement of the Parties andwithout regard to nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 83" name="Consolidation Of Multiple Claims" article_identifier="4539">1. When a disputing party considers that two or moreclaims submitted to arbitration under Article 76 have a question of law or fact in common, the disputing party mayseek a consolidation order in accordance with the terms of paragraphs 2 through 9 below. 


2. A disputing party that seeks a consolidation orderunder this Article shall deliver, in writing, a request tothe Secretary-General to establish a Tribunal under thisArticle. The request shall: 


(a) specify the nature of the order sought and thegrounds on which the order is sought; and 


(b) be accompanied by a request for arbitration madeunder paragraph 1 of Article 36 of the ICSIDConvention or a notice of arbitration submitted under Article 2 of Schedule C of the ICSID Additional Facility Rules, as may be amended. 

3. Within 60 days of receipt of the request, theSecretary-General shall establish a Tribunal comprising 3arbitrators. One arbitrator shall be a national of the disputing Party, the second arbitrator shall be a nationalof the Party of the disputing investor, and the presidingarbitrator shall not be a national of any of the Parties. 


4. A Tribunal established under this Article shall be established under the ICSID Convention or the ICSID Additional Facility Rules as may be amended, asappropriate, and shall conduct its proceedings inaccordance with the provisions thereof, except as modifiedby this Section. 


5. Any disputing investor that has submitted a claim toarbitration and considers that such a claim raises questions of law or fact which are common to those uponwhich the consolidation under paragraph 2 above has beenrequested, but has not been named in a request made underparagraph 2 above, may request to the Tribunal establishedunder this Article to consider the consolidation of his claim. The request shall comply with the requirementsestablished in paragraph 2 above. 


6. The disputing investor referred to in paragraph 5above shall deliver to the disputing Party or disputinginvestors with respect to whom the order is sought, a copyof the request made under paragraph 5 above. 


7. On application of a disputing party, a Tribunalestablished under this Article may order the adjourning ofthe proceedings related to claims referred to in paragraphs1 and 5 above. 


8. A Tribunal established under this Article may, in theinterests of fair and efficient resolution of the dispute,and after hearing the disputing parties, by order: 


(a) assume jurisdiction over, and hear and determinetogether, all or part of the claims referred toin paragraphs 1 and 5 above; or 


(b) assume jurisdiction over, and hear and determineone or more of the claims referred to in paragraphs 1 and 5 above, the determination ofwhich it believes would assist in the resolution of the others. 

9. A Tribunal established under Article 79 shall not have jurisdiction to decide a claim, or a part of a claim, overwhich a Tribunal established under this Article has assumed jurisdiction in the terms of paragraph 8 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 84" name="Governing Law" article_identifier="4540">1. A Tribunal established under this Section shall decide the issues in dispute in accordance with this Agreement andapplicable rules of international law. 


2. An interpretation of a provision of this Agreementadopted by the Joint Committee shall be binding on aTribunal established under this Section. Such interpretation shall be made publicly available through themeans that each Party considers appropriate.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 85" name="Notice" article_identifier="4541">A disputing Party shall deliver to the other Party: 


(a) 	written notice of a claim that has been submitted to arbitration no later than 30 days after thedate on which the claim was submitted; and 


(b) copies of all pleadings filed in the arbitration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 86" name="Participation By A Party" article_identifier="4542">On written notice to the disputing parties, the Partyother than the disputing Party may make submissions to aTribunal on a question of interpretation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 87" name="Documents" article_identifier="4543">1. The Party other than the disputing Party shall beentitled to receive from the disputing Party, at the costof the requesting Party a copy of: 


(a) 	the evidence that has been tendered to the Tribunal; and 


(b) the written argument of the disputing parties. 
2. The Party receiving information pursuant to paragraph1 above shall treat the information as if it were a disputing Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 88" name="Place Of Arbitration" article_identifier="4544">Unless the disputing parties agree otherwise, aTribunal shall hold an arbitration in a country that is aparty to the New York Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 89" name="Interpretation Of Annexes" article_identifier="4545">1. Where a disputing Party asserts as a defense that themeasure alleged to be a breach is within the scope of areservation or exception set out in Annex 6, Annex 7, Annex8 or Annex 9, on request of the disputing Party, theTribunal shall request the Joint Committee to adopt aninterpretation on the issue. The Joint Committee, within 60 days of delivery of the request, shall adopt aninterpretation and submit in writing its interpretation tothe Tribunal. 


2. Further to Article 84, an interpretation adopted andsubmitted under paragraph 1 above shall be binding on theTribunal. If the Joint Committee fails to submit an interpretation within 60 days, the Tribunal shall decidethe issue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 90" name="Expert Reports" article_identifier="4546">Without prejudice to the appointment of other kinds ofexperts where authorized by the applicable arbitrationrules, a Tribunal, at the request of a disputing party or,unless the disputing parties disapprove, on its owninitiative, may appoint one or more experts in the fieldsof environmental, health, safety or other scientificmatters to report to it in writing on any factual issueconcerning matters of their expertise raised by a disputingparty in a proceeding, subject to such terms and conditionsas the disputing parties may agree.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 91" name="Interim Measures Of Protection" article_identifier="4547">A Tribunal may order an interim measure of protectionto preserve the rights of a disputing party, or tofacilitate the conduct of arbitral proceedings, includingan order to preserve evidence in the possession or controlof a disputing party. A Tribunal may not order attachment or enjoin the application of the measure alleged toconstitute a breach referred to in paragraph 1 of Article

76.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 92" name="Final Award" article_identifier="4548">1. Where a Tribunal makes a final award against adisputing Party, the Tribunal may award, separately or incombination, only: 


(a) monetary damages and any applicable interest; or 


(b) restitution of property, in which case the awardshall provide that the disputing Party may paymonetary damages and any applicable interest inlieu of restitution. 
A Tribunal may also award costs in accordance with theapplicable arbitration rules. 

2. Subject to paragraph 1 above, where a claim is madeunder subparagraph 1 (b) of Article 76: 


(a) an award of monetary damages and any applicableinterest shall provide that the sum be paid tothe enterprise; and 


(b) an award of restitution of property shall providethat restitution be made to the enterprise. 
3. A Tribunal may not order a Party to pay punitivedamages.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 93" name="Finality And Enforcement Of An Award" article_identifier="4549">1. Any arbitral award rendered pursuant to Article 92shall be final, and binding on the disputing parties inrespect of the particular case. 


2. Subject to the applicable revision, annulment or setaside procedures, a disputing party shall abide by andcomply with an award without delay. 


3. If a disputing Party fails to abide by or comply witha final award, the Party whose investor was a party to thearbitration may have recourse to the dispute settlementprocedure under Chapter 15. In this event, the requesting Party may seek: 


(a) a determination that the failure to abide by orcomply with the final award is inconsistent withthe obligations of this Agreement; and 


(b) a recommendation that the Party abide by orcomply with the final award.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 94" name="General" article_identifier="4550">1. A claim is submitted to arbitration under this Section when: 


(a) the request for arbitration under paragraph (1)of Article 36 of the ICSID Convention has been received by the Secretary-General; 


(b) 	the notice of arbitration under Article 2 of Schedule C of the ICSID Additional FacilityRules, as may be amended, has been received bythe Secretary-General; or 


(c) the notice of arbitration given under theUNCITRAL Arbitration Rules is received by thedisputing Party. 
The disputing parties shall otherwise agree inrelation to subparagraph 1 (d) of Article 79. 

2. Delivery of notice and other documents on a Partyshall be made: 


(a) 	in the case of Mexico: through the DirectorateGeneral of Foreign Investment of the Ministry ofEconomy; and 


(b) in the case of Japan: through the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. 

3. In an arbitration under this Section, a Party shallnot assert, as a defense, counterclaim, right of setoff orotherwise, that the disputing investor has received or willreceive, pursuant to an insurance or guarantee contract,indemnification or other compensation for all or part ofits alleged damages. 


4. Either disputing party may make available to thepublic in a timely manner all documents, including anaward, submitted to, or issued by, a Tribunal establishedunder this Section, subject to redaction of: 


(a) confidential business information; 


(b) information which is privileged or otherwiseprotected from disclosure under the applicablelaw of either Party; and 


(c) information which the Party must withholdpursuant to the relevant arbitral rules, asapplied. 
Note: 	For greater certainty, it is confirmed by bothParties that a Party may share with officialsof its central or local government in the caseof Japan, and its federal or state governmentin the case of Mexico, all relevant documentsin the course of dispute settlement under thisSection, including confidential information andthat the disputing parties may disclose toother persons in connection with the arbitralproceedings the documents submitted to, orissued by, a Tribunal established under thisSection, as they consider necessary for thepreparation of their cases; provided that theyshall ensure that those persons protect theconfidential information in such documents.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 95" name="Exceptions From Dispute Settlement Procedure" article_identifier="4551">1. Without prejudice to the applicability or non-applicability of the dispute settlement provisions of thisSection or of Chapter 15 to other actions taken by a Partypursuant to Article 169, a decision by a Party to prohibitor restrict the acquisition of an investment in its Area byan investor of the other Party, or its investment, pursuantto that Article shall not be subject to such provisions. 


2. In the case of Mexico, the dispute settlementprovisions of this Section and of Chapter 15 shall notapply to a decision by the National Commission on ForeignInvestment (“Comisión Nacional de Inversiones Extranjeras”)following a review pursuant to Annex 6, reservation 3 setout in the Schedule of Mexico, with respect to whether ornot to permit an acquisition that is subject to review. 
Definitions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 96" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4552">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) the term “disputing investor” means an investorthat makes a claim under Section 2; 


(b) the term “disputing parties” means the disputinginvestor and the disputing Party; 


(c) the term “disputing party” means the disputinginvestor or the disputing Party; 


(d) the term “disputing Party” means a Party againstwhich a claim is made under Section 2; 


(e) the term “equity or debt securities” includesvoting and non-voting shares, bonds, convertibledebentures, stock options and warrants; 


(f) the term “freely usable currency” means anycurrency designated as such by the InternationalMonetary Fund from time to time; 


(g) 	the term “ICSID” means the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes; 


(h) 	the term “ICSID Convention” means the Convention on the Settlement of Investment Disputes betweenStates and Nationals of other States done at Washington, March 18, 1965, as may be amended; 


(i) 	the term “investment” means: 
(AA) an enterprise; 

(BB) an equity security of an enterprise; 

(CC) a debt security of an enterprise: 

(aa) where the enterprise is an affiliate of the investor, or 

(bb) where the original maturity of the debt security is at least 3 years, 

but does not include a debt security,regardless of original maturity, of a Partyor a state enterprise; 

(DD) a loan to an enterprise: 

(aa) where the enterprise is an affiliate of the investor, or 

(bb) where the original maturity of the loan is at least 3 years, 

but does not include a loan, regardless oforiginal maturity, to a Party or a stateenterprise; 

(EE) an interest in an enterprise that entitles the owner to share in income or profits ofthe enterprise; 

(FF) an interest in an enterprise that entitles the owner to share in the assets of that enterprise on dissolution, other than adebt security or a loan excluded fromsubparagraph (CC) or (DD) above; 

(GG) real estate or other property, tangible or intangible, and any related property rightssuch as lease, liens and pledges, acquiredin the expectation or used for the purposeof economic benefit or other business purposes; and 

(HH) interests arising from the commitment of capital or other resources in the Area of aParty to economic activity in such Area,such as under: 

(aa) 	contracts involving the presence ofan investor’s property in the Area ofthe Party, including turnkey orconstruction contracts, orconcessions, or 

(bb) 	contracts where remuneration dependssubstantially on the production,revenues or profits of an enterprise; 

but investment does not mean, 

(II) claims to money that arise solely from: 

(aa) 	commercial contracts for the sale of goods or services by a national orenterprise in the Area of a Party toan enterprise in the Area of theother Party, or 

(bb) 	the extension of credit in connection with a commercial transaction, suchas trade financing, other than a loancovered by subparagraph (DD) above;or 

(JJ) any other claims to money, 

that do not involve the kinds of interests set out in subparagraphs (AA) through (HH)above; 


(j) the term “investment of an investor of a Party”means an investment owned or controlled directlyor indirectly by an investor of such Party; 


(k) the term “investor of a Party” means a Party orstate enterprise thereof, or a national or anenterprise of such Party, that seeks to make, ismaking or has made an investment; 


(l) the term “investment support” means any debt orequity investment, any investment guaranty andany investment insurance or reinsurance providedby the issuer in connection with projects oractivities in the Area of a Party; 


(m) the term “issuer” means a designated agency of aParty, or any successor agency, and any agent ofeither, which provides investment support, butdoes not refer to the Government of any of theParties; 


(n) 	the term “New York Convention” means the Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement ofForeign Arbitral Awards, done at New York, June10, 1958, as may be amended; 


(o) the term “Secretary-General” means the Secretary-General of ICSID; 


(p) 	the term “transfers” means transfers and international payments; 


(q) 	the term “Tribunal” means an arbitration tribunal established under Article 79 or 83; and 


(r) 	the term “UNCITRAL Arbitration Rules” means the arbitration rules of the United Nations Commission on International Trade Law, approvedby the United Nations General Assembly onDecember 15, 1976, as may be amended.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Cross-Border Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="521">
      <article number="ARTICLE 97" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4553">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted ormaintained by a Party affecting cross-border trade inservices by service suppliers of the other Party, includingmeasures respecting: 


(a) the supply of a service; 

Note: 	The measures respecting the supply of aservice include those respecting theprovision of any financial security as acondition for the supply of a service. 

(b) the purchase or use of, or payment for, aservice; 


(c) the access to services offered to the publicgenerally and the use of them, in connection withthe supply of a service; and 


(d) the presence in its Area of a service supplier ofthe other Party. 
2. This Chapter shall not apply to: 


(a) financial services, as defined in Chapter 9; 


(b) cabotage in maritime transport services,including navigation in inland waters; 


(c) with respect to air transport services, measuresaffecting traffic rights, however granted; ormeasures affecting services directly related tothe exercise of traffic rights, other thanmeasures affecting: 


(i) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 


(ii) the selling and marketing of air transportservices; and 
(iii) computer reservation system (CRS) services; 

Note: 	The term “traffic rights” means the rightsfor scheduled and non-scheduled services to operate and/or to carry passengers,cargo and mail for remuneration or hirefrom, to, within, or over a Party,including points to be served, routes tobe operated, types of traffic to becarried, capacity to be provided, tariffsto be charged and their conditions, andcriteria for designation of air lines,including such criteria as number,ownership, and control. 


(d) procurement by a Party or a state enterprise; 


(e) subsidies provided by a Party or a stateenterprise thereof, including grants, government-supported loans, guarantees and insurance; 


(f) measures pursuant to immigration laws andregulations; 


(g) services supplied in the exercise of governmentalauthority; and 

Note: 	For the purposes of this Chapter, servicessupplied in the exercise of governmentalauthority means any service which issupplied neither on a commercial basis norin competition with one or more servicesuppliers. 

(h) measures of a Party with respect to a national ofthe other Party seeking access to its employmentmarket, or employed on a permanent basis in thatParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 98" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="4554">1. Each Party shall accord to services and servicesuppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorablethan that it accords, in like circumstances, to its ownservices and service suppliers. 

Note: 	Nothing in this Article shall be construed torequire either Party to compensate for anyinherent competitive disadvantages which resultfrom the foreign character of the relevantservices or service suppliers. 

2. The treatment accorded by a Party under paragraph 1above means, with respect to a local government in the caseof Japan, and with respect to a state in the case ofMexico, treatment no less favorable than the most favorabletreatment accorded, in like circumstances, by that localgovernment or state to services and service suppliers ofthe Party of which it forms a part.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 99" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="4555">Each Party shall accord to services and servicesuppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorablethan that it accords, in like circumstances, to servicesand service suppliers of any non-Party. 

Note: 	Each Party shall accord to services and servicesuppliers of the other Party the better of thetreatment required by Articles 98 and 99.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 100" name="Local Presence" article_identifier="4556">Neither Party shall require a service supplier of theother Party to establish or maintain a representativeoffice or any form of enterprise, or to be resident, in itsArea as a condition for the cross-border supply of aservice.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 101" name="Reservations" article_identifier="4557">1. Articles 98, 99 and 100 shall not apply to: 


(a) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by a Party at the federal or centralgovernment level, as set out in its Schedule toAnnex 6; 


(b) any existing non-conforming measure that ismaintained by: 
(i) with respect to Mexico: 

(AA) a state, for 6 months after the date of entry into force of this Agreement, andthereafter as to be set out by Mexicoin its Schedule to Annex 6 in accordance with paragraph 2 below; or 

(BB) a local government; and 

(ii) with respect to Japan: 

(AA) a prefecture, for 6 months after the date of entry into force of thisAgreement, and thereafter as to be setout by Japan in its Schedule to Annex 6in accordance with paragraph 2 below;or 

(BB) a local authority other than prefectures; 


(c) the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs

(a) and (b) above; or 

(d) an amendment or a modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs
(a) and (b) above provided that the amendment ormodification does not decrease the conformity ofthe measure, as it existed immediately before theamendment or modification, with Articles 98, 99and 100. 


2. Each Party shall set out in its Schedule to Annex 6,within 6 months of the date of entry into force of thisAgreement, any existing non-conforming measure maintainedby a state or prefecture referred to in subparagraphs1(b)(i)(AA) and 1(b)(ii)(AA) above, and shall notifythereof the other Party by a diplomatic note. 


3. Articles 98, 99 and 100 shall not apply to any measurethat a Party adopts or maintains with respect to sectors,subsectors or activities, as set out in its Schedule toAnnex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 102" name="Notification" article_identifier="4558">To the maximum extent possible, each Party shallnotify the other Party of any new measure that the Partyconsiders might materially affect the implementation andoperation of this Chapter and of Annexes 6 and 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 103" name="Sub-Committee On Cross-Border Trade In Services" article_identifier="4559">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Article, a Sub-Committee on Cross-BorderTrade in Services (hereinafter referred to in this Articleas “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 165. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter; 


(b) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee andmaking recommendations to the Joint Committee;and 


(d) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 104" name="Licensing And Certification" article_identifier="4560">1. With a view to ensuring that any measure adopted ormaintained by a Party relating to the licensing,certification, or technical standards of service suppliersof the other Party does not constitute an unnecessarybarrier to cross-border trade in services, each Party shallendeavor to ensure that such measure: 


(a) is based on objective and transparent criteria,such as competence and the ability to supply theservices; 


(b) is not more burdensome than necessary to ensurethe quality of the services; and 


(c) does not constitute a disguised restriction onthe cross-border supply of the services. 
2. Where a Party recognizes, unilaterally or byagreement, education, experience, licenses orcertifications obtained in a non-Party, nothing in Article 99 shall be construed to require the Party to accord suchrecognition to education, experience, licenses orcertifications obtained in the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 105" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="4561">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to aservice supplier of the other Party where the Partyestablishes that the service is being supplied by anenterprise that is owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party, and that the denying Party: 


(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with thenon-Party; or 


(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to thenon-Party that prohibit transactions with theenterprise or that would be violated orcircumvented if the benefits of this Chapter wereaccorded to the enterprise. 
Note: 	An enterprise is “owned” by persons of a non-Party if more than 50 percent of the equityinterests in it is beneficially owned bypersons of that non-Party. An enterprise is “controlled” by persons of a non-Party if suchpersons have the power to name a majority ofits directors or otherwise to legally directits actions. 

2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, aParty may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a servicesupplier of the other Party where the Party establishesthat the service is being supplied by an enterprise that isowned or controlled by persons of a non-Party and that hasno substantial business activities in the Area of that other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 106" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4562">For the purposes of this Chapter: 

(a) 	the term “cross-border trade in services” means the supply of a service: 


(i) from the Area of a Party into the Area ofthe other Party; 


(ii) in the Area of a Party by a person of thatParty to a person of the other Party; or 
(iii) by a national of a Party in the Area of theother Party; 

but does not include the supply of a service byan investment of an investor of a Party, asdefined in Article 96 in the Area of the other Party; 


(b) the term “measures by a Party” means measurestaken by: 


(i) federal or central government, state, orprefecture or any other local authority; and 


(ii) non-governmental bodies in the exercise ofpowers delegated by federal or centralgovernment, state, or prefecture or anyother local authority; 

(c) the term “service supplier of a Party” means aperson of a Party that seeks to supply orsupplies a service; and 


(d) the term “supply of a service” includes theproduction, distribution, marketing, sale anddelivery of a service.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Financial Services" chapter_identifier="522">
      <article number="ARTICLE 107" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4563">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted ormaintained by a Party affecting: 


(a) cross-border trade in financial services; 


(b) financial institutions of the other Party; and 


(c) investors of the other Party, and investments ofsuch investors, in financial institutions in theParty. 

2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures pursuant toimmigration laws and regulations. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to preventa Party, including its public entities, from exclusivelyconducting or providing in its Area: 


(a) activities or services forming part of a publicretirement plan or statutory system of socialsecurity; or 


(b) 	activities or services for the account or with the guarantee or using the financial resources ofthe Party, including its public entities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 108" name="Commitments Under International Agreements" article_identifier="4564">The Parties shall be bound by the terms and conditionsthat each Party is committed to under the Organisation forEconomic Cooperation and Development Code of Liberalisationof Capital Movements, as may be amended, and the GATS,including the Understanding on Commitments in FinancialServices, and under other international agreements to whichboth Parties are parties. 

Note: Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to affect

the terms and conditions committed to by either

Party under the respective agreements referred to in

this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 109" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="4565">The dispute settlement procedure provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 110" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="4566">Notwithstanding the provisions of this Chapter,Chapter 7 and Chapter 8, a Party shall not be preventedfrom adopting or maintaining measures for prudentialreasons with respect to financial services, including forthe protection of investors, depositors, policy holders,policy claimants or persons to whom a fiduciary duty isowed by a financial institution or a cross-border financialservice supplier, or to ensure the soundness, integrity andstability of a Party’s financial system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 111" name="Relation To Other Chapters" article_identifier="4567">The provisions of Chapters 7 and 8 shall not apply tomeasures referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 107.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 112" name="Definitions" article_identifier="4568">For the purposes of this Chapter: 


(a) 	the term “cross-border financial service supplier” means a person of a Party that isengaged in the business of supplying financialservices within the Area of the Party and thatseeks to supply or supplies financial servicesthrough the cross-border supply of such services; 


(b) 	the term “cross-border trade in financial services” means the supply of a financialservice: 


(i) from the Area of a Party into the Area ofthe other Party; 


(ii) in the Area of a Party by a person of thatParty to a person of the other Party; or 
(iii) by a national of a Party in the Area of theother Party; 

but does not include the supply of a service byan investment of an investor of a Party, in theArea of that other Party; 


(c) the term “financial institution” means anyenterprise that is authorized to do business andregulated or supervised as a financialinstitution under the law of the Party in whichit is located; 


(d) 	the term “financial institution of the other Party” means a financial institution located in aParty that is owned or controlled by persons ofthe other Party; 


(e) 	the term “financial service” means a service of a financial nature, including insurance, and aservice incidental or auxiliary to a service of afinancial nature; 


(f) 	the term “investment” means "investment" as defined in Article 96, except that, with respectto “loan” and “debt security” referred to in that Article: 

(i) a loan to or debt security issued by afinancial institution is an investment onlywhere it is treated as regulatory capital bythe Party in which the financial institutionis located; and 


(ii) a loan granted by or debt security owned bya financial institution, other than a loanto or debt security of a financialinstitution referred to in subparagraph (i)above, is not an investment; 
  for greater certainty, 

(iii) a loan to, or debt security issued by, aParty or a state enterprise thereof is notan investment; and 

(iv) a loan granted by or debt security owned bya cross-border financial service supplier,other than a loan to or debt security issuedby a financial institution referred to insubparagraph (i) above, is an investmentunder Chapter 7 if such loan or debtsecurity meets the criteria for investmentsset out in Article 96; 


(g) the term “investor of a Party” means a Party orstate enterprise thereof, or a person of thatParty, that seeks to make, makes, or has made aninvestment; and 


(h) the term “public entity” means a central bank ora monetary authority of a Party, or any financialinstitution owned or controlled by a Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Entry And Temporary Stay Of Nationals For Business Purposes" chapter_identifier="523">
      <article number="ARTICLE 113" name="General Principles" article_identifier="4569">1. This Chapter reflects the preferential tradingrelationship between the Parties, the desirability offacilitating entry and temporary stay on a reciprocal basisand of establishing transparent criteria and procedures forentry and temporary stay, and the need to ensure bordersecurity and to protect the domestic labor force andpermanent employment in either Party. 


2. Each Party shall apply its measures relating to theprovisions of this Chapter in accordance with paragraph 1above, and in particular, shall apply expeditiously thosemeasures so as to avoid unduly impairing or delaying tradein goods or services or conduct of investment activitiesunder this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 114" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4570">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting theentry and temporary stay of nationals of a Party who enterinto the other Party for business purposes. 


2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affectingnationals seeking access to the employment market of theParties, nor shall it apply to measures regardingnationality or citizenship, or residence or employment on apermanent basis. 


3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applyingmeasures to regulate the entry of nationals of the otherParty into, or their temporary stay in, the former Party,including those measures necessary to protect the integrityof, and to ensure the orderly movement of natural personsacross, its borders, provided that such measures are notapplied in such a manner as to nullify or impair thebenefits accruing to the other Party under the terms of thecategories in Annex 10. 
Note: 	The sole fact of requiring a visa for naturalpersons of a certain nationality and not forthose of others shall not be regarded asnullifying or impairing benefits under aspecific category.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 115" name="Grant Of Entry And Temporary Stay" article_identifier="4571">1. Each Party shall grant entry and temporary stay tonationals of the other Party in accordance with thisChapter including the terms of the categories in Annex 10. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that fees charged by itscompetent authorities for processing applications for entryand temporary stay of nationals of the other Party forbusiness purposes have regard to the administrative costsinvolved.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 116" name="Provision Of Information" article_identifier="4572">1. Further to Article 160, each Party shall: 


(a) provide to the other Party such materials as willenable that other Party to become acquainted withits measures relating to this Chapter; and 


(b) prepare, publish and make publicly available inthe Parties, explanatory material in aconsolidated document regarding the requirementsfor entry and temporary stay under this Chapter,no later than one year after the date of entryinto force of this Agreement. 
2. From the entry into force of this Agreement, eachParty shall, to the extent possible, collect, maintain andmake available to the other Party, data respecting thegranting of entry and temporary stay under this Chapter tonationals of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 117" name="Sub-Committee On Entry And Temporary Stay" article_identifier="4573">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on Entry andTemporary Stay (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 165. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Chapter;   


(b) considering the development of measures tofurther facilitate entry and temporary stay ofnationals on a reciprocal basis; 


(c) enhancing mutual understanding between theParties on credentials and other qualificationsrelevant to entry and temporary stay of nationalsunder this Chapter; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee andmaking recommendations to the Joint Committee;and 


(e) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165. Such functions may includereporting to the Joint Committee on options forpossible modifications or additions to thisChapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 118" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="4574">1. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 152, a Partymay not request consultations with the other Partyregarding refusal to grant entry and temporary stay underthis Chapter unless: 


(a) the matter involves a pattern of practice; and 


(b) 	the nationals concerned have exhausted the administrative remedies, where available,regarding the particular matter. 
2. The remedies referred to in subparagraph 1(b) aboveshall be deemed to be exhausted if a final determination in the matter has not been issued by the competent authorityof a Party within one year after the date of theinstitution of an administrative remedy, and the failure toissue a determination is not attributable to delay causedby the nationals concerned.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="524">
      <article number="ARTICLE 119" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4575">1. This Chapter shall apply to any measures adopted ormaintained by a Party relating to government procurement: 


(a) by entities specified in Annex 11; 


(b) of goods specified in Annex 12, servicesspecified in Annex 13, or construction servicesspecified in Annex 14; and 


(c) 	where the value of the contracts to be awarded is estimated to be not less than the thresholds specified in Annex 15 at the time of publicationof an invitation to participate for procurement. 

2. Paragraph 1 above is subject to the General Notes setout in Annex 16. 


3. This Chapter shall apply to government procurement byany contractual means, including through such methods aspurchase or as lease, rental or hire purchase, with orwithout an option to buy, including any combination ofgoods and services. 


4. Subject to paragraph 5 below, where a contract to beawarded by an entity is not covered by this Chapter, thisChapter shall not be construed to cover any good or servicecomponent of that contract. 


5. Neither Party shall prepare, design or otherwisestructure any government procurement contract in order toavoid the obligations of this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 120" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="4576">1. With respect to any measures regarding governmentprocurement covered by this Chapter, each Party shallprovide immediately and unconditionally to the goods,services and suppliers of the other Party offering goods orservices of the other Party, treatment no less favorablethan that accorded to domestic goods, services andsuppliers. 


2. With respect to any measures regarding governmentprocurement covered by this Chapter, each Party shallensure: 


(a) that its entities shall not treat a locally-established supplier less favorably than anotherlocally-established supplier on the basis of thedegree of affiliation to, or ownership by, aperson of the other Party; and 


(b) that its entities shall not discriminate againstlocally-established suppliers on the basis of thecountry of production of the goods or servicebeing supplied, provided that the country ofproduction is the other Party in accordance withthe provisions of Article 121. 

3. The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 above shall notapply to customs duties and charges of any kind imposed onor in connection with importation, the method of levyingsuch duties and charges, other import regulations andformalities, and measures affecting trade in services otherthan measures regarding government procurement covered bythis Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 121" name="Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="4577">1. A Party shall not apply rules of origin to goods orservices imported or supplied for purposes of governmentprocurement covered by this Chapter from the other Partywhich are different from the rules of origin applied by theformer Party in the normal course of trade. 

Note: 	Rules of origin to services applied in thenormal course of trade shall be understood in accordance with paragraph (f) “service ofanother Member” and (g) “service supplier” ofArticle XXVIII “Definitions” of the GATS. 

2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, aParty may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a servicesupplier of the other Party where the denying Partyestablishes that the service is being provided by anenterprise that is owned or controlled by persons of a non-Party and that has no substantial business activities inthe Area of any Party. 


3. A Party may deny to an enterprise of the other Partythe benefits of this Chapter if nationals of a non-Partyown or control the enterprise and: 


(a) the denying Party does not maintain diplomaticrelations with the non-Party; or 


(b) the denying Party adopts or maintains measureswith respect to the non-Party that prohibittransactions with the enterprise or that would beviolated or circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were accorded to the enterprise.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 122" name="Procurement Procedures And Other Provisions" article_identifier="4578">1. Each Party shall apply the respective rules andprocedures set up in accordance with the provisions, as maybe amended, specified in Annex 18. 


2. Where a Party considers that a modification to rulesand procedures of the other Party corresponding to anamendment of the provisions specified in Annex 18affects access to the other Party’s government procurementmarket considerably, the former Party can requestconsultations in order to maintain equivalence between thetreatments under the rules and procedures of the Parties.If no satisfactory solution can be found, the former Partymay have recourse to the dispute settlement procedure underChapter 15, with a view to maintaining an equivalent levelof access to the other Party’s government procurementmarket. 


3. The Party concerned shall notify the other Party ofany modification to the rules and procedures referred to inparagraph 1 above no later than 30 days prior to the dateof entry into force of such modification. 


4. If, in tendering procedures, an entity allows tendersto be submitted in several languages, one of thoselanguages shall be English. 


5. No entity of either Party shall make it a conditionfor the qualification of suppliers and for the awarding ofa contract that the supplier has previously been awardedone or more contracts by an entity of that Party or thatthe supplier has prior work experience in the Area of thatParty.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 123" name="Offsets" article_identifier="4579">Each Party shall ensure that its entities do not, inthe qualification and selection of suppliers, goods orservices, in the evaluation of bids or the award ofcontracts, consider, seek or impose offsets, except as setout in the General Notes of Annex 16. For the purpose ofthis Article, offsets means conditions considered, soughtor imposed by an entity prior to or in the course of itsprocurement process that encourage local development orimprove its Party’s balance of payments accounts, by meansof requirements of local content, licensing of technology,investment, counter-trade or similar requirements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 124" name="Provision Of Information" article_identifier="4580">1. Each Party shall promptly publish any law, regulation,judicial decision, administrative ruling of generalapplication, and any procedure (including standard contractclauses) regarding government procurement covered by thisChapter, in the appropriate publications listed in Annex 17and in such a manner as to enable the other Party andsuppliers to become acquainted with them. 


2. The Party of an unsuccessful tenderer may seek,without prejudice to the provisions under Chapter 15, suchadditional information on the contract award as may benecessary to ensure that the procurement was made fairlyand impartially. To this end, the Party of the procuring entity shall provide information on both thecharacteristics and relative advantages of the winningtender and the contract price. Normally this latter information may be disclosed by the former Party providedit exercises this right with discretion. In cases where release of this information would prejudice competition infuture tenders, this information shall be confidential andnot be disclosed except after consultation with andagreement of the latter Party which gave the information tothe former Party. 


3. Available information concerning procurement bycovered entities and their individual contract awards shall be provided, upon request, to the Party requesting theinformation. 


4. Confidential information provided to a Party whichwould impede law enforcement or otherwise be contrary tothe public interest or would prejudice the legitimatecommercial interest of particular enterprises, public orprivate, or might prejudice fair competition betweensuppliers shall not be revealed without formalauthorization from the other Party. 


5. With a view to ensuring effective monitoring ofgovernment procurement covered by this Chapter, each Partyshall collect statistics and provide to the other Party ona reciprocal basis an annual report which shall contain thefollowing information to the extent that such informationis available: 


(a) 	statistics on the number and total value of contracts above and below the applicablethreshold values broken down by entities; 


(b) 	statistics on the number and total value of contracts above the applicable threshold values,broken down by entities, by categories of goodsand services and by the country of origin of thegoods and services procured; and 


(c) 	statistics on the number and total value of contracts awarded under limited tenderingprocedures, broken down by entities, and bycountry of origin of the goods and servicesprocured.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 125" name="Challenge Procedures" article_identifier="4581">1. In the event of a complaint by a supplier that therehas been a breach of this Chapter in the context of agovernment procurement, each Party shall encourage thesupplier to seek resolution of its complaint inconsultation with the procuring entity. In such instances the procuring entity shall accord impartial and timelyconsideration to any such complaint, in a manner that isnot prejudicial to obtaining corrective measures under thechallenge system. 


2. Each Party shall provide non-discriminatory, timely,transparent and effective procedures enabling suppliers tochallenge alleged breaches of this Chapter arising in thecontext of government procurements in which they have, orhave had, an interest. 


3. Each Party shall provide its challenge procedures inwriting and make them generally available. 


4. Each Party shall ensure that documentation relating toall aspects of the process concerning governmentprocurements covered by this Chapter shall be retained for3 years. 


5. The interested supplier may be required to initiate achallenge procedure and notify the procuring entity withinspecified time-limits from the time when the basis of thecomplaint is known or reasonably should have been known,but in no case within a period of less than 10 days. 


6. A Party may require that a challenge procedure beinitiated only after the notice of procurement has beenpublished or, where a notice is not published, after tenderdocumentation has been made available. Where a Partyimposes such a requirement, the 10 day period described inparagraph 5 above shall begin no earlier than the date thatthe notice is published or the tender documentation is madeavailable. 


7. Challenges shall be heard by an impartial andindependent reviewing authority with no interest in theoutcome of the government procurement and the members ofwhich are secure from external influence during the term ofappointment. A reviewing authority which is not a court shall either be subject to judicial review or shall haveprocedures which provide that: 


(a) participants can be heard before an opinion isgiven or a decision is reached; 


(b) participants can be represented and accompanied; 


(c) participants shall have access to all
proceedings; 



(d) proceedings can take place in public; 


(e) opinions or decisions are given in writing with astatement describing the basis for the opinionsor decisions; 


(f) witnesses can be presented; and 


(g) documents are disclosed to the reviewingauthority. 

8. Challenge procedures shall provide for: 


(a) rapid interim measures to correct breaches ofthis Chapter and to preserve commercialopportunities. Such action may result in suspension of the procurement process. However, procedures may provide that overriding adverseconsequences for the interests concerned,including the public interest, may be taken intoaccount in deciding whether such measures shouldbe applied. In such circumstances, just cause for not acting shall be provided in writing; 


(b) an assessment and a possibility for a decision onthe justification of the challenge; and 


(c) where appropriate, correction of the breach ofthis Chapter or compensation for the loss ordamages suffered, which may be limited to costsfor tender preparation or protest. 

9. With a view to the preservation of the commercial andother interests involved, the challenge procedure shallnormally be completed in a timely fashion.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 126" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="4582">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to preventa Party from taking any action or not disclosing anyinformation which it considers necessary for the protectionof its essential security interests relating to theprocurement of arms, ammunition or war materials, or toprocurement indispensable for national security or fornational defence purposes. 


2. Provided that such measures are not applied in amanner that would constitute a means of arbitrary orunjustifiable discrimination between the Parties where thesame conditions prevail, or a disguised restriction ontrade between the Parties, nothing in this Chapter shall beconstrued to prevent a Party from imposing, enforcing ormaintaining measures: 


(a) necessary to protect public morals, order orsafety; 


(b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant lifeor health; 


(c) necessary to protect intellectual property; or 


(d) relating to goods or services of handicappedpersons, of philanthropic institutions or ofprison labor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 127" name="Sub-Committee On Government Procurement" article_identifier="4583">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Chapter, a Sub-Committee on GovernmentProcurement (hereinafter referred to in this Article as“the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant toArticle 165. 


2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) analyzing available information on each Party’sgovernment procurement market including thestatistical information provided under paragraph5 of Article 124; 


(b) evaluating the effective access of suppliers of aParty to government procurement market of theother Party covered by this Chapter; 


(c) monitoring the application of the provisions ofthis Chapter and providing a forum to identifyand address any problems or other issues that mayarise; 


(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(e) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165. 

3. The Parties shall cooperate, on mutually agreed terms,to increase understanding of their respective governmentprocurement systems, with a view to maximizing for thesuppliers of both Parties the access to their respectivegovernment procurement market. For this purpose, each Party shall develop and implement, within one year afterthe entry into force of this Agreement, concrete measuresfor the cooperation, which may include training andorientation programs for government personnel or interestedsuppliers regarding such aspects as how to identifygovernment procurement opportunities and how to participatein the respective government procurement markets. In developing such measures, special attention should be givento small businesses in each Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 128" name="Rectifications Or Modifications" article_identifier="4584">1. A Party shall notify the other Party of itsrectifications, or in exceptional cases, othermodifications relating to Annexes 11, 12, 13, 14, 16 and 17along with the information as to the likely consequences ofthe change for the mutually agreed coverage provided inthis Chapter. If the rectifications or other modifications are of a purely formal or minor nature, notwithstandingparagraph 1 of Article 174, they shall become effectiveprovided that no objection from the other Party has beenraised within 30 days. In other cases, both Parties shall consult the proposal and any claim for compensatoryadjustments with a view to maintaining a balance of rightsand obligations and a comparable level of mutually agreedcoverage provided in this Chapter prior to suchrectification or other modification. In the event of an agreement between the Parties not being reached, the Partywhich has received such notification may have recourse tothe dispute settlement procedure under Chapter 15. 


2. Notwithstanding any other provision of this Chapter, aParty may undertake reorganizations of its entities coveredby this Chapter, including programs through which theprocurement of such entities is decentralized or thecorresponding government functions cease to be performed byany government entity, whether or not subject to thisChapter. In cases of reorganizations, compensation need not be proposed. Neither Party shall undertake such reorganizations or programs to avoid the obligations ofthis Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 129" name="Privatization Of Entities" article_identifier="4585">When government control at the federal or centralgovernment level over an entity specified in Annex 11 hasbeen effectively eliminated, notwithstanding that thegovernment may possess holding thereof or appoint member ofthe board of directors thereto, this Chapter shall nolonger apply to that entity. A Party shall notify the other Party of the name of such entity before eliminationof government control or as soon thereafter as possible.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 130" name="Miscellaneous Provisions" article_identifier="4586">1. The Joint Committee may make recommendations to theParties to adopt appropriate measures to enhance theconditions for effective access to a Party’s coveredgovernment procurement or, as the case may be, to adjust aParty’s coverage so that such conditions for effectiveaccess are maintained on an equitable basis. 


2. In the event that after the entry into force of thisAgreement a Party offers a non-Party specified in paragraph3 below additional advantages of access to its governmentprocurement market beyond what the other Party has beenprovided with under this Chapter, the former Party shallconsent to enter into negotiations with the other Partywith a view to extending these advantages to the otherParty on a reciprocal basis. 


3. A non-Party referred to in paragraph 2 above shall be,in the case of Japan, a Party to the Agreement onGovernment Procurement in Annex 4 to the WTO Agreement, asmay be amended, (hereinafter referred to as “the GPA”) or aparty to an existing Economic Partnership Agreement withJapan and in the case of Mexico, a party to the NorthAmerican Free Trade Agreement, as may be amended,(hereinafter referred to as “the NAFTA”) or the EuropeanCommunities.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="525">
      <article number="ARTICLE 131" name="Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="4587">Each Party shall, in accordance with its applicablelaws and regulations, take measures which it considersappropriate against anticompetitive activities, in order tofacilitate trade and investment flows between the Parties and the efficient functioning of its market.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 132" name="Cooperation On Controlling Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="4588">1. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respectivelaws and regulations, cooperate in the field of controllinganticompetitive activities. 


2. The details and procedures of cooperation under thisArticle shall be specified in an implementing agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 133" name="Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="4589">Each Party shall apply its competition laws andregulations in a manner which does not discriminate betweenpersons in like circumstances on the basis of theirnationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 134" name="Procedural Fairness" article_identifier="4590">Each Party shall implement administrative and judicialprocedures in a fair manner to control anticompetitiveactivities, pursuant to its relevant laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 135" name="Non-Application Of Article 164 And Chapter 15" article_identifier="4591">Article 164 and the dispute settlement procedureprovided for in Chapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Improvement Of The Business Environment" chapter_identifier="526">
      <article number="ARTICLE 136" name="Consultations For The Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="4592">The Parties, confirming their interest in creating amore favorable business environment with a view to promoting trade and investment activities by their privateenterprises, shall from time to time have consultations inorder to address issues concerning the improvement of thebusiness environment in the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 137" name="Committee For The Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="4593">1. For the purposes of addressing issues concerning theimprovement of the business environment, a Committee forthe Improvement of the Business Environment (hereinafterreferred to in this Article as “the Committee”) shall beestablished. 


2. The Committee: 


(a) shall discuss ways and means to improve thebusiness environment in the Parties; 


(b) may, as needed, make recommendations onappropriate measures to be taken by the Parties.Such recommendations should be taken into consideration by the Parties; 


(c) shall be provided with information on theimplementation of such recommendations; 


(d) may make public such recommendations in anappropriate manner; and 


(e) may give the Joint Committee advisory opinions,where appropriate. 

3. The Committee: 


(a) shall be composed of representatives of theGovernments of the Parties; 


(b) may invite representatives of relevant entitiesother than the Governments of the Parties with the necessary expertise relevant to the issues tobe discussed; and 


(c) shall establish its rules and procedures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 138" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="4594">The dispute settlement procedure provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Bilateral Cooperation" chapter_identifier="527">
      <article number="ARTICLE 139" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Trade And Investment Promotion" article_identifier="4595">1. The Parties shall cooperate in promoting trade andinvestment activities by private enterprises of theParties, recognizing that the joint efforts of the Partiesto facilitate exchange and collaboration between privateenterprises will act as a catalyst to further promote tradeand investment between the Parties. Such cooperationbetween the Parties includes: 


(a) encouraging the exchange of trade, investment andmarketing experts and trainees to foster businessopportunities; 


(b) exchanging information concerning laws,regulations and practices in relation tobilateral trade and investment; 


(c) encouraging the joint organization of trade andinvestment missions, seminars, fairs andexhibitions; 


(d) encouraging the sharing, through electroniclinkages, of online databases of privateenterprises of the Parties keen to establishbusiness ties; and 


(e) encouraging the exchange of information, for theidentification of investment opportunities andthe promotion of business alliances, for theestablishment of joint ventures between privateenterprises of both Parties. 

2. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Article, a Sub-Committee on Cooperationin the Field of Trade and Investment Promotion (hereinafterreferred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shallbe established pursuant to Article 165. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Article; 


(b) discussing any issues related to this Article; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 140" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Supporting Industries" article_identifier="4596">The Parties shall cooperate in promoting thedevelopment of supporting industries of both Parties with aview to improving the business environment and to promotingbilateral trade and investment. Such cooperation includesencouraging appropriate entities to: 


(a) assist private enterprises of either Party toenter supporting industries’ market of the otherParty through direct investment or jointventures; 


(b) assist private enterprises of supportingindustries to establish their business ties with other private enterprises of supportingindustries, as well as final goods suppliers; 


(c) assist actual or potential private enterprises ofsupporting industries through financial andtechnological support; and 


(d) exchange experts and information on bestpractices and methodologies for the developmentof supporting industries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 141" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Small And Medium Enterprises" article_identifier="4597">The Parties shall cooperate in promoting thedevelopment of small and medium enterprises of both Parties(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “SMEs”) inorder to maintain the dynamism of their respectiveeconomies and promote favorable environment for bilateraltrade and investment. Such cooperation may include: 


(a) exchange of information on SMEs policies for: 


(i) strengthening competitiveness of SMEs; 


(ii) assisting SMEs to start up businesses; and 
(iii) promoting entrepreneurial networks of SMEs; 

(b) encouragement of establishment of networks amongappropriate entities of both Parties that provideassistance to SMEs; and 


(c) encouragement of the exchange of experts on thedevelopment of SMEs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 142" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Science And Technology" article_identifier="4598">1. The Parties, recognizing that science and technologywill contribute to the continued expansion of theirrespective economies in the medium and long term, shalldevelop and promote cooperative activities between theGovernments of the Parties for peaceful purposes in thefield of science and technology on the basis of equalityand mutual benefit. 


2. Forms of the cooperative activities under this Articlemay include: 


(a) exchange of information regarding science andtechnology policies and programs and data; 


(b) joint seminars, workshops and meetings; 


(c) visits and exchanges of scientists, technicalpersonnel or other experts; 


(d) implementation of joint projects and programs; 


(e) encouragement of cooperation for research anddevelopment related to industrial technologies;and 


(f) encouragement of cooperation between educationaland research institutions. 

3. Scientific and technological information of a non-proprietary nature arising from the cooperative activitiesunder this Article may be made available to the public bythe Government of either Party. 


4. In accordance with the applicable laws and regulationsof the Parties and with relevant international agreementsto which the Parties are parties, the Parties shall ensurethe adequate and effective protection, and give dueconsideration to the distribution, of intellectual propertyrights or other rights of a proprietary nature resultingfrom the cooperative activities under this Article. The Parties shall consult for this purpose as necessary. 


5. The implementation of this Article shall be subject tothe availability of appropriated funds and the applicablelaws and regulations of each Party. 


6. Costs of the cooperative activities under this Articleshall be borne in such manner as may be mutually agreed. 


7. Implementing arrangements setting forth the detailsand procedures of the cooperative activities under thisArticle may be made between the government agencies of theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 143" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Technical And Vocational Education And Training" article_identifier="4599">The Parties, recognizing that sustainable economicgrowth and prosperity largely depend on people’s knowledgeand skills, in order to raise the productivity andcompetitiveness of private enterprises of either Party,shall develop cooperation between the Governments of theParties in the field of technical and vocational education and training. Such cooperation may include: 


(a) exchange of information related to best practiceson technical and vocational education and training including labor policy; 


(b) encouragement of technical and vocationaleducation and training, including training ofrelated instructors and development of trainingprograms, particularly for the development ofhigher technological education and distanceeducation; and 


(c) encouragement of exchange of scholars, teachers,instructors and students.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 144" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="4600">The Parties, recognizing the growing importance ofintellectual property (hereinafter referred to in thisArticle as “IP”) as a factor of economic competitiveness inthe knowledge-based economy, and of IP protection in thisnew environment, shall develop their cooperation in thefield of IP. Such cooperation may include the exchange ofinformation on: 


(a) public awareness activities of the importance ofIP protection and the function of IP protectionsystems to their respective nationals; 


(b) improvement of IP protection systems and theiroperation; 


(c) policy measures conducive to ensuring adequateenforcement of IP rights; and 


(d) automation of administrative processes of IPauthority in order to enhance its efficiency. 
Note: 	Information provided from a Party to the other Partypursuant to this Article shall not includeinformation regarding individual cases ofinfringement of intellectual property rights so asnot to be used by the receiving Party in criminalproceedings carried out by a court or a judge.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 145" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Agriculture" article_identifier="4601">1. The Parties, recognizing that the development in thefield of agriculture in both Parties is of mutual interestand of economic and social importance for the rational andsustainable use of natural resources, shall cooperate inthe field of agriculture. Such cooperation may include: 


(a) exchange of information and data regardingexperience of rural development, know-how offinancial assistance to farmers and the agricultural cooperatives system; 


(b) encouragement of dialogues and exchange ofinformation between entities other than the Governments of the Parties concerningagriculture; and 


(c) encouragement of joint scientific andtechnological research in agriculture includingnew technologies. 

2. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Article, a Sub-Committee on Cooperationin the Field of Agriculture (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be establishedpursuant to Article 165. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Article; 


(b) discussing any issues related to this Article; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee tothe Joint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 146" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Tourism" article_identifier="4602">1. The Parties, recognizing that tourism will contributeto the enhancement of mutual understanding between them andthat tourism is an important industry for their economies,shall cooperate to promote and develop tourism in theParties. Such cooperation may include: 


(a) exchange of information on: 


(i) activities and policies, including bestpractices, concerning market research,sustainable development of tourism and thestrengthening of the competitiveness of thetourism industry; and 


(ii) laws, regulations and statistics on tourism; 

(b) provision of appropriate assistance for tourismpromotion campaigns; 


(c) encouragement of cooperation between entitiesother than the Governments of the Parties concerning the promotion and development oftourism; and 


(d) encouragement of training of persons engaged inthe tourism industry. 

2. For the purposes of the effective implementation andoperation of this Article, a Sub-Committee on Cooperationin the Field of Tourism (hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”) shall be established pursuant to Article 165. 


3. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Article; 


(b) discussing any issues related to this Article; 


(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to the Joint Committee; and 


(d) carrying out other functions which may bedelegated by the Joint Committee pursuant toArticle 165.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 147" name="Cooperation In The Field Of Environment" article_identifier="4603">1. The Parties, recognizing the need for environmentalpreservation and improvement to promote sound andsustainable development, shall cooperate in the field ofenvironment. Cooperative activities under this Article mayinclude: 


(a) exchange of information on policies, laws,regulations and technology related to thepreservation and improvement of the environment,and the implementation of sustainabledevelopment; 


(b) promotion of capacity and institutional buildingto foster activities related with the Clean Development Mechanism under the Kyoto Protocol tothe United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, as may be amended, by means ofworkshops and dispatch of experts, andexploration of appropriate ways to encourage theimplementation of the Clean Development Mechanismprojects; 


(c) encouragement of trade and dissemination ofenvironmentally sound goods and services; and 


(d) encouraging the exchange of information for theidentification of investment opportunities andthe promotion and development of businessalliances in the field of environment. 
2. Implementing arrangements setting forth the detailsand procedures of cooperative activities under this Articlemay be made between the government agencies of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 148" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 15" article_identifier="4604">The dispute settlement procedure provided for inChapter 15 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 149" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="4605">1. The Agreement between the Government of Japan and theGovernment of the United Mexican States concerningCooperation in the Field of Tourism signed in Tokyo, onNovember 1, 1978 shall expire upon the date of entry intoforce of this Agreement. 


2. It is confirmed by both Parties that nothing in thisChapter prejudices the rights and obligations of theParties under the Agreement on Technical Cooperationbetween the Government of Japan and the Government of theUnited Mexican States signed in Tokyo, on December 2, 1986,as may be amended.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="528">
      <article number="ARTICLE 150" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="4606">Except as otherwise provided for in this Agreement,this Chapter shall apply with respect to the settlement ofall disputes between the Parties regarding theinterpretation or application of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 151" name="Choice Of Dispute Settlement Procedure" article_identifier="4607">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights ofthe Parties to have recourse to dispute settlementprocedures available under any other internationalagreement to which both Parties are parties. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 above, once a disputesettlement procedure has been initiated under this Chapteror under any other international agreement to which bothParties are parties with respect to a particular dispute,that procedure shall be used to the exclusion of any otherprocedure for that particular dispute. However, this does not apply if substantially separate and distinct rights orobligations under different international agreements are indispute. 


3. For the purposes of paragraph 2 above, a disputesettlement procedure under this Chapter shall be deemed tobe initiated by a Party’s request for the establishment ofan arbitral tribunal pursuant to paragraph 1 of Article
153. 

4. For the purposes of paragraph 2 above, a disputesettlement procedure under the WTO Agreement shall bedeemed to be initiated by a Party’s request for theestablishment of a panel pursuant to Article 6 of theUnderstanding on Rules and Procedures Governing theSettlement of Disputes in Annex 2 to the WTO Agreement, asmay be amended.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 152" name="Consultations" article_identifier="4608">1. Each Party may request in writing consultations withthe other Party regarding any matter on the interpretationor application of this Agreement. 


2. When a Party requests consultations pursuant toparagraph 1 above, the other Party shall reply to therequest and enter into consultations in good faith within30 days after the date of receipt of the request, with aview to a prompt and satisfactory resolution of the matter.In a case of consultations regarding perishable goods, therequested Party shall enter into consultations within 15days after the date of receipt of the request.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 153" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="4609">1. The complaining Party that requested consultationsunder Article 152 above may request in writing theestablishment of an arbitral tribunal to the Partycomplained against: 


(a) if the Party complained against does not enterinto such consultations within 30 days after thedate of its receipt of the request forconsultations under that Article; or 


(b) if the Parties fail to resolve the disputethrough such consultations under that Articlewithin 60 days after the date of receipt of therequest for such consultations, 
provided that the complaining Party considers that anybenefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under thisAgreement is being nullified or impaired as a result of thefailure of the Party complained against to carry out itsobligations, or as a result of the application by the Partycomplained against of measures which are in conflict withthe obligations of that Party, under this Agreement. 

2. Any request for the establishment of an arbitraltribunal pursuant to this Article shall identify: 


(a) the legal basis of the complaint, including theprovisions of this Agreement alleged to have beenbreached and any other relevant provisions; and 


(b) the factual basis for the complaint. 

3. The arbitral tribunal shall comprise 3 arbitrators. 


4. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date ofreceipt of the request for the establishment of an arbitraltribunal, appoint one arbitrator who may be its nationaland propose up to 3 candidates to serve as the thirdarbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either Party, nor have his or her usual place of residence ineither Party, nor be employed by either Party. 


5. The Parties shall agree on and appoint the thirdarbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt of therequest for the establishment of an arbitral tribunal,taking into account the candidates proposed pursuant toparagraph 4 above. 


6. If a Party has not appointed one arbitrator pursuantto paragraph 4 above or if the Parties fail to agree on andappoint the third arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 5 above,such arbitrator or such third arbitrator shall be chosen bylot within further 7 days from the candidates proposedpursuant to paragraph 4 above. 


7. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal shall be the date on which the chair is appointed. 


8. Unless the Parties otherwise agree within 20 days fromthe date of receipt of the request for the establishment ofthe arbitral tribunal, the terms of reference of sucharbitral tribunal shall be: 

“To examine, in the light of the relevant provisionsof this Agreement, the matter referred to in therequest for the establishment of an arbitral tribunalpursuant to this Article, to rule on the consistencyof the measures at issue with this Agreement, and,where the arbitral tribunal reaches the conclusion that the measure is inconsistent with this Agreement,to make recommendations that the Party complainedagainst bring the measure into conformity with thisAgreement. When making recommendations, the arbitral tribunal may not suggest specific ways in which theParty complained against could implement therecommendations.” 

9. The Parties shall promptly deliver the terms ofreference pursuant to paragraph 8 above to the arbitraltribunal. 


10. If an arbitrator dies, withdraws or is removed, areplacement shall be appointed within 30 days in accordancewith the appointment procedure provided for in paragraphs 4to 6 above, which shall be applied, respectively, mutatis mutandis. In such a case, any time period applicable tothe arbitral tribunal proceeding shall be suspended for aperiod beginning on the date the arbitrator dies, withdrawsor is removed and ending on the date the replacement isappointed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 154" name="Award Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="4610">1. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 


2. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal, thedocuments submitted to it and the draft award referred to in paragraph 4 below shall be kept confidential. 


3. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude a Party fromdisclosing statements of its own position to the public.Each Party shall treat as confidential, informationsubmitted by the other Party to the arbitral tribunal whichthat other Party has designated as confidential. A Party shall also, upon request of the other Party, provide a non-confidential summary of the information contained in itswritten submissions that could be disclosed to the public. 


4. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 90 days after thedate of its establishment, submit to the Parties its draftaward, including both descriptive part and its findings andconclusions, for the purposes of enabling the Parties toreview precise aspects of the draft award. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it cannot submit to the Parties its draft award within the aforementioned 90 dayperiod, it may extend that period with the consent of theParties. However, in no case should the period from theestablishment of the arbitral tribunal to the submission of the draft award to the Parties exceed 150 days. A Party may submit comments in writing to the arbitral tribunal onthe draft award within 15 days after the date of thesubmission of the draft award. 


5. The arbitral tribunal shall issue its award within 30 days after the date of the submission of the draft award. 


6. In the case that the matters referred to the arbitral tribunal are those concerning perishable goods, thearbitral tribunal shall make every effort to issue itsaward to the Parties within 90 days after the date of itsestablishment. In no case should it do so later than 120 days. 


7. The arbitral tribunal shall take its decisions including its award by majority vote. 


8. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 155" name="Termination Of Proceedings Of The Arbitral Tribunal" article_identifier="4611">While the proceedings of the arbitral tribunal are inprogress, the Parties may agree to terminate theproceedings at any time by jointly so notifying the chairof the arbitral tribunal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 156" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="4612">1. The Party complained against shall promptly complywith the award of the arbitral tribunal issued pursuant toArticle 154. 


2. The Party complained against shall, within 20 daysafter the date of issuance of the award, notify thecomplaining Party of the period of time for implementingthe award. If the complaining Party considers the periodof time notified to be unacceptable, it may refer thematter to an arbitral tribunal. 


3. If the Party complained against fails to comply withthe award within the implementation period as determinedpursuant to paragraph 2 above, the Party complained againstshall no later than the expiry of that implementationperiod enter into consultations with the complaining Party,with a view to developing mutually acceptable compensation.If no satisfactory compensation has been agreed within 20days after the date of expiry of that implementationperiod, the complaining Party may notify the Partycomplained against that it intends to suspend theapplication to the Party complained against of concessionsor other obligations under this Agreement. 


4. If the complaining Party considers that measures takenby the Party complained against for implementing the awarddo not comply with the award within the implementationperiod as determined pursuant to paragraph 2 above, it mayrefer the matter to an arbitral tribunal. 


5. If the arbitral tribunal to which the matter is referred pursuant to paragraph 4 above confirms that theParty complained against has failed to comply with theaward within the implementation period as determinedpursuant to paragraph 2 above, the complaining Party may,within 30 days after the date of such confirmation by thearbitral tribunal, notify the Party complained against thatit intends to suspend the application to the Partycomplained against of concessions or other obligationsunder this Agreement. 


6. Suspension of the application of concessions or otherobligations under paragraphs 3 and 5 above may only beimplemented at least 30 days after the date of thenotification in accordance with those paragraphs. Such suspension shall: 


(a) not be effected if, in respect of the dispute towhich the suspension relates, consultations, orproceedings before an arbitral tribunal are inprogress; 


(b) be temporary, and be discontinued when theParties reach a mutually satisfactory resolutionor where compliance with the award is effected; 


(c) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification or impairment that is attributable to the failureto comply with the award; and 


(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to which the nullification or impairment relates,unless it is not practicable or effective tosuspend the application of concessions or otherobligations in such sector or sectors. 

7. If the Party complained against considers that therequirements for the suspension of the application to it ofconcessions or other obligations under this Agreement bythe complaining Party set out in paragraph 3, 5 or 6 abovehave not been met, it may refer the matter to an arbitraltribunal. 


8. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes of this Article shall, wherever possible, have asits arbitrators, the arbitrators to the original arbitraltribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators tothe arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposesof this Article shall be appointed pursuant to paragraphs 4to 6 of Article 153. Unless the Parties agree to adifferent period, such arbitral tribunal shall issue itsaward within 30 days after the date when the matter isreferred to it. The award of the arbitral tribunal established under this Article shall be binding on theParties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 157" name="Modification Of Time Periods" article_identifier="4613">Any time period provided for in this Chapter may bemodified by mutual consent of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 158" name="Expenses" article_identifier="4614">Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the expenses ofthe arbitral tribunal, including the remuneration of itsarbitrators, shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 159" name="Rules Of Procedure" article_identifier="4615">Unless the Parties agree otherwise, the details andprocedures for the arbitral tribunal provided for in thisChapter shall be in accordance with the Rules of Procedureto be adopted by the Joint Committee within the first yearof the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 16" name="Implementation And Operation Of The Agreement" chapter_identifier="529">
      <article number="ARTICLE 160" name="Transparency" article_identifier="4616">1. Each Party shall promptly publish, or otherwise makepublicly available, its laws, regulations, administrativeprocedures and administrative rulings and judicialdecisions of general application as well as internationalagreements to which the Party is a party, respecting anymatter covered by this Agreement. 


2. Each Party shall, upon request by the other Party,promptly respond to specific questions from, and provideinformation to, the other Party with respect to mattersreferred to in paragraph 1 above. 


3. Nothing in this Article shall prejudice as to whethera measure adopted by a Party is consistent with thisAgreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 161" name="Public Comment Procedures" article_identifier="4617">The Government of each Party shall, in accordance withthe domestic laws and regulations of the Party, endeavor tomaintain public comment procedures, except in cases ofemergency, inter alia, a real or imminent danger to thehealth, safety, or welfare of persons, to the preservationof the environment or to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources, in order to: 


(a) make public in advance regulations of generalapplication that affect any matter covered bythis Agreement, accompanied by an explanation oftheir rationale and potential effects, when theGovernment adopts, amends or repeals them; 


(b) provide a reasonable opportunity for comments bythe public and give consideration to thosecomments before the adoption of such regulations;and 


(c) make public those comments. Where appropriate, those comments should be compiled and accompaniedby the views of the Government on them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 162" name="Administrative Proceedings" article_identifier="4618">1. Where measures are to be adopted which pertain to oraffect the implementation and operation of this Agreement,the competent authorities of a Party shall, in accordancewith the domestic laws and regulations of the Party: 


(a) inform the applicant of the decision concerningthe application within a reasonable period oftime after the submission of an applicationconsidered complete under the domestic laws andregulations of the Party; and 


(b) provide, without undue delay, informationconcerning the status of the application, at therequest of the applicant. 
2. Where measures are to be adopted by the competentauthorities of a Party which pertain to or affect theimplementation and operation of this Agreement and whichimpose obligations on or restrict rights of a person, suchcompetent authorities shall, prior to any final decision,when time, the nature of the measures and public interestpermit and in accordance with the domestic laws andregulations of the Party, provide that person with: 


(a) a reasonable notice, including a description ofthe nature of the measure, specific provisionsupon which such measure will be based, and thefacts which may be a cause of taking suchmeasure; and 


(b) a reasonable opportunity to present facts andarguments in support of the position of suchperson.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 163" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="4619">1. Each Party shall maintain judicial or administrativetribunals or procedures for the purpose of prompt reviewand, where warranted, correction of administrative actionsregarding matters covered by this Agreement. Such tribunals or procedures shall be impartial and independentof the authorities entrusted with the administrative enforcement. 


2. Each Party shall ensure that, in any such tribunals orprocedures, the parties to the proceeding are provided withthe right to: 


(a) a reasonable opportunity to support or defendtheir respective positions; and 


(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions of record. 

3. Each Party shall ensure, subject to appeal or furtherreview as provided in its domestic laws and regulations,that such decisions are implemented by the competentauthorities of the Party with respect to the administrativeaction at issue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 164" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="4620">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement,neither Party shall be required by this Agreement toprovide confidential information, the disclosure of whichwould impede the enforcement of its domestic laws andregulations, including the law protecting the informationrelating to personal privacy or the financial affairs oraccounts of individual customers of financial institutions,or otherwise be contrary to the public interest, or whichwould prejudice legitimate commercial interests ofparticular enterprises, public or private. 


2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its domestic lawsand regulations, maintain the confidentiality ofinformation provided in confidence by the other Partypursuant to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 165" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="4621">1. The Joint Committee composed of representatives of theGovernments of the Parties shall be established under this Agreement. 


2. 	The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 


(a) reviewing the implementation and operation ofthis Agreement and, when necessary, makingappropriate recommendations to the Parties; 


(b) considering and recommending to the Parties anyamendments to this Agreement; 


(c) by mutual consent of the Parties, serving as aforum for consultations referred to in Article 152; 


(d) supervising the work of all Sub-Committeesestablished under this Agreement; 


 (e) adopting: 


(i) 	modifications to Annexes referred to in Articles 8 and 37; 


(ii) 	the Uniform Regulations referred to in Article 10; 
(iii) an interpretation of a provision of thisAgreement referred to in Articles 84 and 89; 


(iv) 	the Rules of Procedure referred to in Article 159; and 


(v) any necessary decisions; and 

(f) carrying out other functions as the Parties mayagree. 

3. 	The Joint Committee may: 


(a) establish and delegate its responsibilities toSub-Committees for the purposes of the effectiveimplementation and operation of this Agreement;and 


(b) 	take such other action in the exercise of its functions as the Parties may agree. 

4. The following Sub-Committees shall be established onthe date of entry into force of this Agreement: 


(a) 	Sub-Committee on Trade in Goods. 


(b) Sub-Committee on Sanitary and PhytosanitaryMeasures. 


(c) Sub-Committee on Technical Regulations, Standardsand Conformity Assessment Procedures. 


(d) Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin, Certificate ofOrigin and Customs Procedures. 


(e) 	Sub-Committee on Cross-Border Trade in Services. 


(f) Sub-Committee on Entry and Temporary Stay. 


(g) 	Sub-Committee on Government Procurement. 


(h) Sub-Committee on Cooperation in the Field ofTrade and Investment Promotion. 


(i) Sub-Committee on Cooperation in the Field ofAgriculture. 


(j) Sub-Committee on Cooperation in the Field ofTourism. 
Other Sub-Committees may be established as the Partiesmay agree. 


5. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules and procedures. 


6. The Joint Committee shall meet alternately in Japanand Mexico at the request of either Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 166" name="Communications" article_identifier="4622">Each Party shall designate a contact point tofacilitate communications between the Parties on any matterrelating to this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 167" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="4623">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligationsunder the WTO Agreement. 


2. Nothing in Chapters 3, 7 and 8 shall be construed toprevent either Party from taking any necessary action asmay be authorized by Article 22 of the Understanding onRules and Procedures Governing the Settlement of Disputesin Annex 2 to the WTO Agreement, as may be amended. 


3. The Convention on Commerce between Japan and theUnited Mexican States signed at Tokyo on January 30, 1969shall expire upon the date of entry into force of thisAgreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 17" name="Exceptions" chapter_identifier="530">
      <article number="ARTICLE 168" name="General Exceptions" article_identifier="4624">1. For the purposes of Chapters 3, 4, 5, and 6, ArticleXX of the GATT 1994 is incorporated into and made part ofthis Agreement, mutatis mutandis. 


2. For the purposes of Chapters 8 and 10, paragraphs (a),
(b) and (c) of Article XIV of the GATS are incorporatedinto and made part of this Agreement, mutatis mutandis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 169" name="National Security" article_identifier="4625">For the purposes of Chapters 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10 and16, nothing in this Agreement shall be construed: 


(a) to require a Party to furnish or allow access toany information the disclosure of which itconsiders contrary to its essential securityinterests; 


(b) to prevent a Party from taking any action that itconsiders necessary for the protection of itsessential security interests: 


(i) relating to the traffic in arms, ammunitionand implements of war and to such trafficand transactions in other goods, materialsor services undertaken directly orindirectly for the purpose of supplying amilitary or other security establishment, 


(ii) taken in time of war or other emergency ininternational relations, or 
(iii) relating to the implementation of nationalpolicies or international agreementsrespecting the non-proliferation of nuclearweapons or other nuclear explosive devices,or relating to fissionable and fusionablematerials or the materials from which theyare derived; or 

(c) to prevent a Party from taking any action inpursuance of its obligations under the UnitedNations Charter, as may be amended, for themaintenance of international peace and security.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 170" name="Taxation" article_identifier="4626">1. Except as otherwise provided for in this Article,nothing in this Agreement shall apply to taxation measures. 


2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights andobligations of either Party under any tax convention. In the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement andany such convention, that convention shall prevail to theextent of the inconsistency. 

Note: 	The term “tax convention” means a convention for the avoidance of double taxation or other international taxation agreement orarrangement. 

3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 above: 


(a) Article 3 shall apply to taxation measures to thesame extent as does Article III of the GATT 1994;and 


(b) Article 6 shall apply to taxation measures. 

4. 	(a) Article 61 shall apply to taxation measures except that no investor may invoke that Articleas the basis for a claim under Article 76, whereit has been determined pursuant to subparagraph
(b) below that the measure is not an expropriation. 


(b) The investor shall refer the issue, at the timethat it gives a written request under Article 78,to the competent authorities of both Parties todetermine whether such measure is not an expropriation. If the competent authorities of both Parties do not consider the issue or, havingconsidered it, fail to determine that the measureis not an expropriation within a period of 180days of such referral, the investor may submitits claim to arbitration under Article 79. 


(c) For the purposes of subparagraph (b) above, theterm “competent authorities” means: 


(i) in the case of Mexico, the Ministry ofFinance and Public Credit; and 


(ii) in the case of Japan, the Minister ofFinance or his authorized representative.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 171" name="Payments And Transfers And Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="4627">1. For the purposes of Chapter 3: 


(a) nothing in this Agreement shall be construed toprevent a Party from taking any measure forbalance-of-payments purposes; 


(b) a Party taking such measure shall do so inaccordance with the conditions established under Article XII of the GATT 1994, and theUnderstanding on the Balance-of-PaymentsProvisions of the General Agreement on Tariffsand Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement,as may be amended; and 


(c) nothing in this Agreement shall preclude the useby a Party of exchange controls or exchangerestrictions in accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund, asmay be amended. 
2. For the purposes of Chapter 8: 


(a) except under the circumstances envisaged insubparagraph (d) below, a Party shall not applyrestrictions on international transfers and payments for current transactions relating tocross-border trade in services under Chapter 8; 


(b) nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rightsand obligations of the Parties as members of theInternational Monetary Fund under the Articles ofAgreement of the International Monetary Fund, asmay be amended, including the use of exchangeactions which are in conformity with the Articlesof Agreement of the International Monetary Fund,as may be amended; 


(c) notwithstanding subparagraph (b) above, a Partyshall not impose restrictions on any capitaltransactions inconsistently with its obligationsregarding such transactions under Chapter 8except under subparagraph (d) below or at therequest of the International Monetary Fund; 


(d) in the event of serious balance-of-payments andexternal financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party may adopt or maintainrestrictions on trade in services, including onpayments or transfers for transactions; 


(e) the restrictions referred to in subparagraph (d)above: 


(i) shall ensure that the other Party is treatedas favorably as any non-Party; 


(ii) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the International MonetaryFund, as may be amended; 
(iii) shall avoid unnecessary damage to thecommercial, economic and financial interestsof the other Party; 


(iv) shall not exceed those necessary to dealwith the circumstances described in subparagraph (d) above; and 


(v) shall be temporary and be phased outprogressively as the situation specified insubparagraph (d) above improves; 

(f) in determining the incidence of such restrictionsreferred to in subparagraph (d) above, a Partymay give priority to the supply of services whichare more essential to their economic or development programs. However, such restrictions shall not be adopted or maintained for thepurpose of protecting a particular servicesector; and 


(g) any restrictions adopted or maintained undersubparagraph (d) above, or any changes therein,shall be promptly notified to the other Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 18" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="531">
      <article number="ARTICLE 172" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="4628">The table of contents and the headings of theChapters, Sections and Articles of this Agreement areinserted for convenience of reference only and shall notaffect the interpretation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 173" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="4629">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shallconstitute an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 174" name="Amendment" article_identifier="4630">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, thisAgreement may be amended by agreement between the Parties.Such amendment shall be approved by the Parties inaccordance with their respective legal procedures. Such amendment shall enter into force on the thirtieth day afterthe date of exchange of diplomatic notes indicating suchapproval. 


2. Any amendment to this Agreement shall constitute anintegral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 175" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="4631">This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtiethday after the date on which the Government of Japan and theGovernment of Mexico exchange diplomatic notes informingeach other that their respective legal procedures necessaryfor entry into force of this Agreement have been completed.It shall remain in force unless terminated as provided forin Article 176 below.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 176" name="Termination" article_identifier="4632">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by givingone year’s advance notice in writing to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 177" name="Authentic Texts" article_identifier="4633">1. The texts of this Agreement in the Japanese, Spanishand English languages shall be equally authentic. In case of differences of interpretation, the English text shallprevail. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1 above: 


(a) Section 2 of Annex 1 is written in the Japaneseand English languages, such texts being equallyauthentic; and 


(b) Section 3 of Annex 1 is written in the Spanishand English languages, such texts being equallyauthentic.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="532">
      <article article_identifier="4634">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being dulyauthorized by their respective Governments, have signedthis Agreement. 

DONE at Mexico City, on this seventeenth day ofSeptember, 2004, in duplicate. 

For Japan:         For the United Mexican States:      Junichiro Koizumi  Vicente Fox Quesada</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
