<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EU - Mexico</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>73</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>65</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>1997-12-08</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2000-07-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2000-07-25</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2010-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">MEX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">AUT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BGR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CZE</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ESP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">EST</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FIN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">GRC</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">HRV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">HUN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">LTU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">LVA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">MEX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">MLT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="24">POL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="25">PRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="26">ROU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="27">SVK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="28">SVN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="29">SWE</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral; One Party is an RTA</composition>
    <region>Europe; North America</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="1">137</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="2">132</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="3">123</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="4">52</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="5">6</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="6">145</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="7">120</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <related_agreement_wto_id n="8">869</related_agreement_wto_id>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399390562230&amp;uri=CELEX:22001D0153</source>
    <source lang="es" type="full text">http://www.sice.oas.org/Trade/MEX_EU/Spanish/index_s.asp</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1399390562230&amp;uri=CELEX:22001D0153</source>
    <source lang="es" type="annex">http://www.sice.oas.org/Trade/MEX_EU/Spanish/index_s.asp</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="889">
      <article article_identifier="7444">THE JOINT COUNCIL,

  Having regard to the Economic Partnership, Political Coordination and
  Cooperation Agreement between the European Community and its Member
  States, of the one part, and the United Mexican States, of the other
  part (hereinafter "the Agreement"), and in particular
  articles 6, 9, 12 and 50 in conjunction with Article 47 thereof.

  Mindful of their rights and obligations under the Marrakesh Agreement
  establishing the World Trade Organisation (hereinafter "the
  WTO").

  Whereas:

  (1) Article 4 and 6 of the Agreement provide that the Joint Council
  shall decide on the arrangements for a progressive and reciprocal
  liberalisation of trade in services, in accordance with Article V of
  the General Agreement on Trade in Services (hereinafter
  "GATS").

  (2) Article 9 of the Agreement provides that the Joint Council shall
  adopt measures for the progressive liberalisation of investment and
  related payments between the Parties.

  (3) Article 12 of the Agreement stipulates that the Joint Council
  shall adopt measures with a view to ensure an adequate and effective
  protection of intellectual property rights.

  (4) Article 50 of the Agreement provides that the Joint Council shall
  establish a specific trade or trade related dispute settlement
  procedure.

  (5) In accordance with Article 60 of the Agreement, upon entry into
  force of that Agreement, the Decision 2/2000 of the Joint Council
  established by the Interim Agreement on trade and trade-related
  matters between the European Community, of the one part, and the
  United Mexican States, of the other part, is deemed to have been
  adopted by the Joint Council established by the Agreement. That
  decision implements the objectives laid down in Articles 5, 10, 11 and
  12(2)(a) of the Agreement,

  HAS DECIDED AS FOLLOWS:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="890">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" name="Scope Of The Decision" article_identifier="7445">The Joint Council hereby lays down the necessary arrangements for
  implementing the following objectives of the Agreement:

  (a) the progressive and reciprocal liberalisation of trade in
  services, in conformity with Article V of GATS;

  (b) the progressive liberalisation of investment and related payments;

  (c) ensuring an adequate and effective protection of the intellectual
  property rights, in accordance with the highest international
  standards; and

  (d) establishing a dispute settlement mechanism.

  TRADE IN SERVICES</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" name="Coverage" article_identifier="7446">1. For the purposes of this Title, trade in services is defined as the
  supply of a service:

  (a) from the territory of a Party into the territory of the other
  Party;

  (b) in the territory of a Party to the service consumer of the other
  Party;

  (c) by a service supplier of a Party, through commercial presence in
  the territory of the other Party;

  (d) by a service supplier of a Party, through presence of natural
  persons in the territory of the other Party.

  2. This Title applies to trade in all services sectors with the
  exception of:

  (a) audio-visual services;

  (b) air services, including domestic and international air
  transportation services, whether scheduled or non-scheduled, and
  related services in support of air services, other than:

  (i) aircraft repair and maintenance services during which an aircraft
  is withdrawn from service,

  (ii) the selling and marketing of air transport services,

  (iii) computer reservation system (CRS) services, and

  (c) maritime cabotage.

  3. Maritime transport and financial services shall be governed by the
  provisions laid down in Chapters II and III, respectively, unless
  otherwise specified.

  4. Nothing in this Title shall be construed to impose any obligation
  with respect to government procurement.

  5. The provisions of this Title shall not apply to subsidies granted
  by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER I" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="891">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" name="Definitions" article_identifier="7447">For purposes of this Chapter:

  (a) A federal, central or subcentral government includes any
  non-governmental body in the exercise of any regulatory,
  administrative or other governmental authority delegated to it by that
  federal, central and sub-central government;

  (b) "service suppliers" of a Party means any person of a
  Party that seeks to provide or provides a service;

  (c) "commercial presence" means:

  (i) as regards nationals, the right to set up and manage undertakings,
  which they effectively control. This shall not extend to seeking or
  taking employment in the labour market or confer a right of access to
  the labour market of another Party,

  (ii) as regards juridical persons, the right to take up and pursue the
  economic activities covered by this Chapter by means of the setting up
  and management of subsidiaries, branches or any other form of
  secondary establishment,

  (d) "subsidiary" means a juridical person which is
  effectively controlled by another juridical person;

  (e) a "Community juridical person" or a "Mexican
  juridical person" means a juridical person set up in accordance
  with the laws of a Member State of the Community or of Mexico,
  respectively, and having its registered office, central
  administration, or principal place of business in the territory of the
  Community or of Mexico, respectively;

  Should the juridical person have only its registered office or central
  administration in the territory of the Community or Mexico,
  respectively, it shall not be considered as a Community or a Mexican
  juridical person, respectively, unless its operations possess a real
  and continuous link with the economy of the Community or Mexico,
  respectively;

  (f) a "national" means a natural person who is a national of
  one of the Member States or Mexico according to their respective
  national legislations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" name="Market Access" article_identifier="7448">In those sectors and modes of supply which shall be liberalised
  pursuant to the decision provided for in Article 7 (3), and subject to
  any reservations stipulated therein, the measures which a Party shall
  not maintain or adopt are defined as:

  (a) limitations on the number of services suppliers whether in the
  form of numerical quotas, monopolies, exclusive service suppliers or
  the requirements of an economic needs test;

  (b) limitations on the total value of service transactions or assets
  in the form of numerical quotas or the requirement of an economic
  needs test;

  (c) limitations on the total number of service operations or on the
  total quantity of service output expressed in the terms of designated
  numerical units in the form of quotas or the requirement of an
  economic needs test;

  (d) limitations on the total number of natural persons that may be
  employed in a particular service sector or that a service supplier may
  employ and who are necessary for, and directly related to, the supply
  of a specific service in the form of numerical quotas or a requirement
  of an economic needs test;

  (e) limitations on the participation of foreign capital in terms of
  maximum percentage limit on foreign shareholding or the total value of
  individual or aggregate foreign investment; and

  (f) measures which require specific types of legal entities or joint
  ventures through which a service supplier of the other Party may
  supply a service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" name="Most Favoured Nation Treatment" article_identifier="7449">1. Subject to exceptions that may derive from harmonisation of
  regulations based on agreements concluded by a Party with a third
  country providing for mutual recognition in accordance with Article
  VII of GATS, treatment accorded to services suppliers of the other
  Party shall be no less favourable than that accorded to like services
  suppliers of any third country.

  2. Treatment granted under other agreements concluded by one of the
  Parties with a third country which have been notified under Article V
  of GATS shall be excluded from this provision.

  3. If a Party enters into an agreement of the type referred to in
  paragraph 2, it shall afford adequate opportunity to the other Party
  to negotiate the benefits granted therein.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="7450">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with Article 7, grant to services
  and service suppliers of the other Party, in respect of all measures
  affecting the supply of services, treatment no less favourable than
  that it accords to its own like services and services suppliers.

  2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 by according to
  services and service suppliers of the other Party, either formally
  identical treatment or formally different treatment to that it accords
  to its own like services and service suppliers.

  3. Formally identical or formally different treatment shall be
  considered to be less favourable if it modifies the conditions of
  competition in favour of services or service suppliers of the Party
  compared to like services or service suppliers of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" name="Trade Liberalisation" article_identifier="7451">1. As provided for in paragraphs 2 to 4, the Parties shall liberalise
  trade in services between themselves, in conformity with Article V of
  GATS.

  2. From the entry into force of this Decision, neither Party shall
  adopt new, or more, discriminatory measures as regards services or
  service suppliers of the other Party, in comparison with the treatment
  accorded to its own like services or service suppliers.

  3. No later than three years following the entry into force of this
  Decision, the Joint Council shall adopt a decision providing for the
  elimination of substantially all remaining discrimination between the
  Parties in the sectors and modes of supply covered by this Chapter(1).
  That decision shall contain:

  (a) a list of commitments establishing the level of liberalisation
  which the Parties agree to grant each other at the end of a
  transitional period of ten years from the entry into force of this
  Decision;

  (b) a liberalisation calendar for each Party in order to reach at the
  end of the ten-year transitional period the level of liberalisation
  described in subparagraph (a).

  4. Except as provided for in paragraph 2, Articles 4, 5 and 6 shall
  become applicable in accordance with the calendar and subject to any
  reservations stipulated in the Parties' lists of commitments provided
  for in paragraph 3.

  5. The Joint Council may amend the liberalisation calendar and the
  list of commitments established in accordance with paragraph 3, with a
  view to remove or add exceptions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" name="Regulatory Carve-Out" article_identifier="7452">Each Party may regulate the supply of services in its territory, in so
  far as regulations do not discriminate against services and service
  suppliers of the other Party, in comparison to its own like services
  and service suppliers.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" name="Mutual Recognition" article_identifier="7453">1. In principle no later than three years following the entry into
  force of this Decision, the Joint Council shall establish the
  necessary steps for the negotiation of agreements providing for the
  mutual recognition of requirements, qualifications, licenses and other
  regulations, for the purpose of the fulfilment, in whole or in part,
  by service suppliers of the criteria applied by each Party for the
  authorisation, licensing, operation and certification of service
  suppliers and, in particular, professional services.

  2. Any such agreement shall be in conformity with the relevant
  provisions of the WTO Agreement and, in particular, Article VII of
  GATS.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER II" name="Maritime Transport" chapter_identifier="892">
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" name="International Maritime Transport" article_identifier="7454">1. This Chapter applies to international maritime transport, including
  door to door and intermodal transport operations involving a sea-leg.

  2. The Definitions contained in Article 3 apply to this Chapter(2).

  3. In view of the existing levels of liberalisation between the
  Parties in international maritime transport:

  (a) the Parties shall continue to effectively apply the principle of
  unrestricted access to the international maritime market and traffic
  on a commercial and non-discriminatory basis;

  (b) each Party shall continue to grant to ships operated by service
  suppliers of the other Party treatment no less favourable than that
  accorded to its own ships with regard to, inter alia, access to ports,
  use of infrastructure and auxiliary maritime services of the ports, as
  well as related fees and charges, customs facilities and the
  assignment of berths and facilities for loading and unloading.

  4. Each Party shall permit to service suppliers of the other Party to
  have a commercial presence in its territory under conditions of
  establishment and operation no less favourable than those accorded to
  its own service suppliers or those of any third country, whichever are
  the better, and this in conformity with the legislation and
  regulations applicable in each Party.

  5. Paragraph 4 shall become applicable in accordance with the calendar
  and subject to any reservation stipulated in the Parties' list of
  commitments provided for in Article 7(3).</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER III" name="Financial Services" chapter_identifier="893">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" name="Definitions" article_identifier="7455">In accordance with the terms of the Annex on Financial Services to the
  GATS and the GATS Understanding on Commitments in Financial Services,
  for purposes of this Chapter:

  (a) "Financial service" means any service of a financial
  nature offered by a financial service supplier of a Party. Financial
  services comprise the following activities:

  A. Insurance and insurance-related services:

  1. direct insurance (including co-insurance):

  (a) life;

  (b) non-life;

  2. reinsurance and retrocession;

  3. insurance inter-mediation, such as brokerage and agency; and

  4. services auxiliary to insurance, such as consultancy, actuarial,
  risk assessment and claim settlement services.

  B. Banking and other financial services (excluding insurance):

  1. acceptance of deposits and other repayable funds from the public;

  2. lending of all types, including consumer credit, mortgage credit,
  factoring and financing of commercial transaction;

  3. financial leasing;

  4. all payment and money transmission services, including credit,
  charge and debit cards, travellers cheques and bankers drafts;

  5. guarantees and commitments;

  6. trading for own account or for account of customers, whether on an
  exchange, in an over-the-counter market or otherwise, the following:

  (a) money market instruments (including cheques, bills, certificates
  of deposits);

  (b) foreign exchange;

  (c) derivative products including, but not limited to, futures and
  options;

  (d) exchange rate and interest rate instruments, including products
  such as swaps, forward rate agreements;

  (e) transferable securities;

  (f) other negotiable instruments and financial assets, including
  bullion;

  7. participation in issues of all kinds of securities, including
  underwriting and placement as agent (whether publicly or privately)
  and provision of services related to such issues;

  8. money broking;

  9. asset management, such as cash or portfolio management, all forms
  of collective investment management, pension fund management,
  custodial, depository and trust services;

  10. settlement and clearing services for financial assets, including
  securities, derivative products, and other negotiable instruments;

  11. provision and transfer of financial information, and financial
  data processing and related software by suppliers of other financial
  services;

  12. advisory, intermediation and other auxiliary financial services on
  all the activities listed in subparagraphs (1) through (11), including
  credit reference and analysis, investment and portfolio research and
  advice, advice on acquisitions and on corporate restructuring and
  strategy.

  (b) "Financial service supplier" means any juridical person
  of a Party authorised to supply financial services. The term
  "financial service supplier" does not include a public
  entity.

  (c) "New financial service" means a service of a financial
  nature, including services related to existing and new products or the
  manner in which a product is delivered, that is not supplied by any
  financial service supplier in the territory of a Party but which is
  supplied in the territory of the other Party.

  (d) "Public entity" means:

  1. A government, a central bank or a monetary authority, of a Party,
  or an entity owned or controlled by a Party, that is principally
  engaged in carrying out governmental functions or activities for
  governmental purposes, not including an entity principally engaged in
  supplying financial services on commercial terms; or

  2. A private entity, performing functions normally performed by a
  central bank or monetary authority, when exercising those functions.

  (e) "Commercial presence" means a juridical entity within a
  Party's territory for the supply of financial services and includes
  wholly or partly owned subsidiaries, joint ventures, partnerships,
  franchising operations, branches, agencies, representative offices or
  other organisations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" name="Establishment Of Financial Service Suppliers" article_identifier="7456">1. Each Party shall allow the financial service suppliers of the other
  Party to establish a commercial presence in its territory.

  2. Each Party may require a financial service supplier of the other
  Party to incorporate under its own law or impose terms and conditions
  on establishment that are consistent with the other provisions of this
  Chapter.

  3. No Party may adopt new measures as regards to the establishment and
  operation of financial service suppliers of the other Party, which are
  more discriminatory than those applied on the date of entry into force
  of this Decision.

  4. No Party shall maintain or adopt the following measures:

  (a) limitations on the number of financial service suppliers whether
  in the form of numerical quotas, monopolies, exclusive financial
  service suppliers or the requirements of an economic needs test;

  (b) limitations on the total value of financial service transactions
  or assets in the form of numerical quotas or the requirement of an
  economic test;

  (c) limitations on the total number of service operations or on the
  total quantity of service output expressed in the terms of designated
  numerical units in the form of quotas or the requirement of an
  economic needs test;

  (d) limitations on the total number of natural persons that may be
  employed in a particular financial service sector or that a financial
  service supplier may employ and who are necessary for, and directly
  related to, the supply of a specific financial service in the form of
  numerical quotas or a requirement of an economic needs test; and

  (e) limitations on the participation of foreign capital in the terms
  of maximum percentage limit on foreign shareholding or the total value
  of individual or aggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" name="Cross-Border Provision Of Financial Services" article_identifier="7457">1. Each party shall allow the cross-border provision of financial
  services.

  2. No Party may adopt new measures as regards to the cross-border
  provision of financial services by financial service suppliers of the
  other Party which are more discriminatory as compared to those applied
  on the date of entry into force of this Decision.

  3. Without prejudice to other means of prudential regulation of the
  cross-border provision of financial services, a Party may require the
  registration of cross-border financial service suppliers of the other
  Party.

  4. Each Party shall permit persons located in its territory to
  purchase financial services from financial service suppliers of the
  other Party located in the territory of that other Party. This
  obligation does not require a Party to permit such suppliers to do
  business or carry on commercial operations; or to solicit, market or
  advertise their activities in its territory. Each Party may define the
  meaning of "doing business", "carry on commercial
  operations", "solicit", "market" and
  "advertise" for purposes of this obligation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="7458">1. Each Party shall grant to the financial service suppliers of the
  other Party, including those already established in its territory on
  the date of entry into force of this Decision, treatment no less
  favourable than that it accords to its own like financial service
  suppliers with respect to the establishment, acquisition, expansion,
  management, conduct, operation and sale or other disposition of
  commercial operations of financial service suppliers in its territory.

  2. Where a Party permits the cross-border provision of a financial
  service it shall accord to the financial service suppliers of the
  other Party treatment no less favourable than that it accords to its
  own like financial service suppliers with respect to the provision of
  such a service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" name="Most Favoured Nation Treatment" article_identifier="7459">1. Each Party shall accord to financial service suppliers of the other
  Party treatment no less favourable than it accords to the like
  financial service suppliers of a non Party.

  2. Treatment granted under other agreements concluded by one of the
  Parties with a third country which have been notified under Article V
  of GATS shall be excluded from this provision.

  3. If a Party enters into an agreement of the type referred to in
  paragraph 2, it shall afford adequate opportunity to the other Party
  to negotiate the benefits granted therein.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" name="Key Personnel" article_identifier="7460">1. No Party may require a financial service supplier of the other
  Party to engage individuals of any particular nationality as senior
  managerial or other key personnel.

  2. No Party may require that more than a simple majority of the board
  of directors of a financial service supplier of the other Party be
  composed of nationals of the Party, persons residing in the territory
  of the Party, or a combination thereof.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" name="Commitments" article_identifier="7461">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent a Party to
  apply:

  (a) any existing measure inconsistent with Articles 12 to 16 which is
  listed on Annex I; or

  (b) an amendment to any discriminatory measure referred to in
  subparagraph (a) to the extent that the amendment does not increase
  the inconsistency of the measure with Articles 12 to 16, as it existed
  immediately before the amendment.

  2. The measures listed in Annex I shall be reviewed by the Special
  Committee on Financial Services established under Article 23, with a
  view to propose to the Joint Council their modification, suspension or
  elimination.

  3. No later than three years following the entry into force of this
  Decision, the Joint Council shall adopt a decision providing for the
  elimination of substantially all remaining discrimination. That
  decision shall contain a list of commitments establishing the level of
  liberalisation which the Parties agree to grant each other.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Regulatory Carve Out" article_identifier="7462">Each Party may regulate the supply of financial services, in so far as
  regulations do not discriminate against financial service or financial
  service suppliers of the other Party in comparison to its own like
  financial services and financial service suppliers.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" name="Prudential Carve Out" article_identifier="7463">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent a Party from
  adopting or maintaining reasonable measures for prudential reasons,
  such as:

  (a) the protection of investors, depositors, financial market
  participants, policy-holders, policy-claimants, or persons to whom a
  fiduciary duty is owed by a financial service supplier;

  (b) the maintenance of the safety, soundness, integrity or financial
  responsibility of financial service suppliers; or

  (c) ensuring the integrity and stability of a Party's financial
  system.

  2. These measures shall not be more burdensome than necessary to
  achieve their aim, and shall not discriminate against financial
  service suppliers of the other Party in comparison to its own like
  financial service suppliers.

  3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to require a Party to
  disclose information relating to the affairs and accounts of
  individual consumers or any confidential or proprietary information in
  the possession of public entities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" name="Effective And Transparent Regulation" article_identifier="7464">1. Each Party shall make its best endeavours to provide in advance to
  all interested persons any measure of general application that the
  Party proposes to adopt in order to allow an opportunity for such
  persons to comment on the measure. Such measure shall be provided:

  (a) by means of an official publication; or

  (b) in other written or electronic form.

  2. Each Party's appropriate financial authority shall make available
  to interested persons its requirements for completing applications
  relating to the supply of financial services.

  3. On the request of an applicant, the appropriate financial authority
  shall inform the applicant of the status of its application. If such
  authority requires additional information from the applicant, it shall
  notify the applicant without undue delay.

  4. Each Party shall make its best endeavours to ensure that the Basle
  Committee's "Core Principles for Effective Banking
  Supervision", the International Association of Insurance
  Supervisors' "Key Standards for Insurance Supervision" and
  the International Organisation of Securities Commissions'
  "Objectives and Principles of Securities Regulation" are
  implemented and applied in its territory.

  5. The Parties also take note of the "Ten Key Principles for
  Information Exchange" promulgated by the Finance Ministers of the
  G7 Nations, and undertake to consider to what extent they may be
  applied in bilateral contacts.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" name="New Financial Services" article_identifier="7465">Each Party shall permit a financial service supplier of the other
  Party to provide any new financial service of a type similar to those
  services that the Party permits its own financial service suppliers to
  provide under its domestic law in like circumstances. A Party may
  determine the juridical form through which the service may be provided
  and may require authorisation for the provision of the service. Where
  such authorisation is required, a decision shall be made within a
  reasonable time and the authorisation may only be refused for
  prudential reasons.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" name="Data Processing" article_identifier="7466">1. Each Party shall permit a financial service supplier of the other
  Party to transfer information in electronic or other form, into and
  out of its territory, for data processing where such processing is
  required in the ordinary course of business of such financial service
  supplier.

  2. As far as the transfer of personal data is concerned, each Party
  shall adopt adequate safeguards to the protection of privacy and
  fundamental rights, and freedom of individuals in accordance with
  Article 41 of the Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" name="Special Committee On Financial Services" article_identifier="7467">1. The Joint Council hereby establishes a Special Committee on
  Financial Services. The Special Committee shall be composed of
  representatives of the Parties. The principal representative of each
  Party shall be an official of the Party's authority responsible for
  financial services set out in Annex II.

  2. The functions of the Special Committee shall include:

  (a) supervising the implementation of this Chapter;

  (b) considering issues regarding financial services that are referred
  to it by a Party;

  (c) considering the application of measures listed by either Party in
  Annex I in order to propose to the Joint Council its modification,
  suspension or elimination, as appropriate;

  (d) reviewing the provisions contained in this Chapter at such a time
  as either of the Parties may grant a third party more favourable
  access to its financial services market pursuant to the conclusion of
  a regional economic integration agreement compatible with Article V of
  GATS, with a view to proposing consequent modifications to this
  Chapter to the Joint Council; and

  (e) considering implementation of Article 16 of the Agreement.

  3. The Special Committee shall meet once a year on a date and with an
  agenda agreed in advance by the Parties. The office of chairman shall
  be held alternately. The Special Committee shall report to the Joint
  Committee the results of each annual meeting.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" name="Consultations" article_identifier="7468">1. A Party may request consultations with the other Party regarding
  any matter arising under this Chapter. The other Party shall give
  sympathetic consideration to the request. The Parties shall report the
  results of their consultations to the Special Committee on Financial
  Services at its annual meeting.

  2. Consultations under this Article shall include officials of the
  authorities specified in Annex II.

  3. Nothing in this Article shall be construed to require financial
  authorities participating in consultations to disclose information or
  take any action that would interfere with individual regulatory,
  supervisory, administrative or enforcement matters.

  4. Where a Party requires information for supervisory purposes
  concerning a financial service supplier in the other Party's
  territory, the Party may approach the competent financial authority in
  the other Party's territory to seek the information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="7469">Arbitrators appointed to panels established in accordance with Title V
  for disputes on prudential issues and other financial matters shall
  have the necessary expertise relevant to the specific financial
  service under dispute, as well as expertise or experience in financial
  services law or practice, which may include the regulation of
  financial institutions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" name="Specific Exceptions" article_identifier="7470">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent a Party,
  including its public entities, from exclusively conducting or
  providing in its territory activities or services forming part of a
  public retirement plan or statutory system of social security, except
  when those activities may be carried out by financial service
  suppliers in competition with public entities or private institutions.

  2. Nothing in this Chapter applies to activities conducted by a
  central bank or monetary authority or by any other public entity in
  pursuit of monetary or exchange rate policies.

  3. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent a Party,
  including its public entities, from exclusively conducting or
  providing in its territory activities or services for the account or
  with the guarantee or using the financial resources of the Party, or
  its public entities.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER IV" name="General Exceptions" chapter_identifier="894">
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="7471">1. The provisions of this Title are subject to the exceptions
  contained in this Article.

  2. Subject to the requirement that such measures are not applied in a
  manner which would constitute a means of arbitrary or unjustifiable
  discrimination between countries where like conditions prevail, or a
  disguised restriction on trade in services, nothing in this Title
  shall be construed to prevent the adoption or enforcement by any Party
  of measures:

  (a) necessary to protect public morals or to maintain public order and
  public security;

  (b) necessary to protect human, animal or plant life or health;

  (c) necessary to secure compliance with laws or regulations which are
  not inconsistent with the provisions of this Title including those
  relating to:

  (i) the prevention of deceptive and fraudulent practices or to deal
  with the effects of a default on services contracts;

  (ii) the protection of the privacy of individuals in relation to the
  processing and dissemination of personal data and the protection of
  confidentiality of individual records and accounts;

  (iii) safety;

  (d) inconsistent with the objective of Article 6 and 14, provided that
  the difference in treatment is aimed at ensuring the effective or
  equitable imposition or collection of direct taxes in respect of
  services or service suppliers of the other Party.

  3. The provisions of this Title shall not apply to the Parties'
  respective social security systems or to activities in the territory
  of each Party, which are connected, even occasionally, with the
  exercise of official authority.

  4. Nothing in this Title shall prevent a Party from applying its laws,
  regulations and requirements regarding entry and stay, work, labour
  conditions, and establishment of natural persons(3) provided that, in
  so doing, it does not apply them in a manner as to nullify or impair
  the benefits accruing to the other Party under the terms of a specific
  provision of this Title.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE III" name="Investment And Related Payments" chapter_identifier="895">
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" name="Definitions" article_identifier="7472">1. For the purpose of this Title, investment made in accordance with
  the laws of the Parties means direct investment, investment in real
  estate and purchase and sale of any kind of securities, as defined in
  the OECD Codes of Liberalisation.

  2. Payments covered by this Title are those related to an investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" name="Payments Related To Investment" article_identifier="7473">1. Without prejudice to Articles 30 and 31, restrictions on payments
  related to investment between the Parties shall be progressively
  eliminated. The Parties undertake not to introduce any new
  restrictions on payments related to direct investment from the entry
  into force of this Decision.

  2. Restrictions on payments related to investments in the services
  sector which have been liberalised in accordance with Title II of this
  Decision shall be eliminated according to the same timetable.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" name="Exchange Rate Policy And Monetary Policy Difficulties" article_identifier="7474">1. Where, in exceptional circumstances, payments related to investment
  between the Parties cause, or threaten to cause, serious difficulties
  for the operation of the exchange rate policy or monetary policy of a
  Party, that Party may take safeguard measures that are strictly
  necessary for a period not exceeding six months. The application of
  safeguard measures may be extended through their formal
  reintroduction.

  2. The Party adopting the safeguard measure shall inform the other
  Party forthwith and present, as soon as possible, a time schedule for
  their removal.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" name="Balance Of Payments Difficulties" article_identifier="7475">1. Where one or more Member States or Mexico is in serious balance of
  payments difficulties, or under imminent threat thereof, the Community
  or the Member State concerned, or Mexico, as the case may be, may
  adopt restrictive measures with regard to payments, including
  transfers of proceeds from the total or partial liquidation of direct
  investment. Such measures shall be equitable, non-discriminatory, in
  good faith, of limited duration and may not go beyond what is
  necessary to remedy the balance of payments situation.

  2. The Community or the Member State concerned, or Mexico, as the case
  may be, shall inform the other Party forthwith and present, as soon as
  possible, a time schedule for their removal. Such measures shall be
  taken in accordance with other international obligations of the Party
  concerned, including those under the WTO Agreement and the Articles of
  Agreement of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" name="Transfers" article_identifier="7476">The liquidation and transfer abroad of any direct investment made in
  Mexico by Community residents or in the Community by Mexican
  residents, and of any profits stemming therefrom, shall not be
  affected by the provisions of Article 30.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" name="Investment Promotion Between The Parties" article_identifier="7477">The Community and its Member States, within the scope of their
  respective competences, and Mexico shall aim to promote an attractive
  and stable environment for reciprocal investment. Such promotion
  should take the form, in particular, of:

  (a) mechanisms for information about and identification and
  dissemination of investment legislation and opportunities;

  (b) development of a legal framework favourable to investment on both
  sides, particularly through the conclusion, where appropriate, by the
  Member States of the Community and Mexico of bilateral agreements
  promoting and protecting investment and preventing double taxation;

  (c) development of uniform and simplified administrative procedures;
  and

  (d) development of mechanisms for joint investments, in particular
  with the small and medium enterprises of both Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" name="International Commitments On Investment" article_identifier="7478">The Community and its Member States, within the scope of their
  respective competences, and Mexico recall their international
  commitments with regard to investment, and especially the OECD Codes
  of Liberalisation and OECD National Treatment Instrument.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" name="Review Clause" article_identifier="7479">With the view of the objective of progressive liberalisation of
  investment, the Community and its Member States, and Mexico affirm
  their commitment to review the investment legal framework, the
  investment climate and the flow of investment between their
  territories consistent with their commitments in international
  investment agreements not later than three years after the entry into
  force of this Decision.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IV" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="896">
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" name="Multilateral Conventions On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="7480">1. The Community and its Member States, on the one hand, and Mexico on
  the other hand, confirm their obligations arising from the following
  multilateral conventions:

  (a) Agreement on Trade-related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights
  (TRIPs Agreement, 1994);

  (b) Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property
  (Stockholm Act, 1967);

  (c) Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works
  (Paris Act, 1971);

  (d) International Convention for the Protection of Performers,
  Producers of Phonograms and Broadcasting Organisations (Rome, 1961);
  and

  (e) Patent Cooperation Treaty (Washington, 1970, amended in 1979 and
  modified in 1984).

  2. The Parties confirm the importance they attach to the obligations
  arising from the International Convention for the Protection of New
  Varieties of Plants, 1978 (1978 UPOV Convention), or the International
  Convention for the Protection of New Varieties of Plants, 1991 (1991
  UPOV Convention).

  3. At the entry into force of this Decision, the Member States of the
  Community and Mexico will have acceded to the Nice Agreement
  concerning the International Classification of Goods and Services for
  the purposes of the Registration of Marks (Geneva, 1977 and amended in
  1979).

  4. Within 3 years of the entry into force of this Decision the Members
  States of the Community and Mexico will have acceded to the Budapest
  Treaty of the International Recognition of the Deposit of
  Microorganisms for the Purposes of Patent Procedure (1977, modified in
  1980).

  5. The Parties shall make every effort to complete the necessary
  procedures for their accession to the following multilateral
  conventions at the earliest possible opportunity:

  (a) the WIPO Copyright Treaty (Geneva, 1996); and

  (b) the WIPO Performances and Phonogram Treaty (Geneva, 1996).

  DISPUTE SETTLEMENT</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER I" name="Scope And Coverage" chapter_identifier="897">
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" name="Scope And Coverage" article_identifier="7481">1. The provisions of this Title shall apply with respect to any matter
  arising from this Decision or from Articles 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and
  11 of the Agreement (hereinafter the "covered legal
  instruments").

  2. By way of exception, the arbitration procedure laid down in Chapter
  III shall not be applicable in the case of disputes concerning Article
  9(2), 31(2) last sentence, 34 and 36 of this Decision.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER II" name="Consultation" chapter_identifier="898">
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" name="Consultation" article_identifier="7482">1. The Parties shall at all times endeavour to agree on the
  interpretation and application of the covered legal instruments and
  shall make every attempt through cooperation and consultations to
  arrive to a mutually satisfactory resolution of any matter that might
  affect their operation.

  2. Each Party may request consultations within the Joint Committee
  with respect to any matter relating to the application or
  interpretation of the covered legal instruments or any other matter
  that it considers might affect their operation.

  3. The Joint Committee shall convene within 30 days of delivery of the
  request and shall endeavour to resolve the dispute promptly by means
  of a decision. That decision shall specify the implementing measures
  to be taken by the Party concerned, and the period of time to do so.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER III" name="Arbitration Procedure" chapter_identifier="899">
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" name="Establishment Of An Arbitration Panel" article_identifier="7483">1. In case a Party considers that a measure applied by the other Party
  violates the covered legal instruments and such matter has not been
  resolved within 15 days after the Joint Committee has convened
  pursuant to Article 38(3) or 45 days after the delivery of the request
  for a Joint Committee meeting, either Party may request in writing the
  establishment of an arbitration panel.

  2. The requesting Party shall state in the request the measure and
  indicate the provisions of the covered legal instruments that it
  considers relevant, and shall deliver the request to the other Party
  and to the Joint Committee.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" name="Appointment Of Arbitrators" article_identifier="7484">1. The requesting Party shall notify the other Party of the
  appointment of an arbitrator, and propose up to 3 candidates to serve
  as a chair. The other Party must then appoint a second arbitrator
  within 15 days, and propose up to 3 candidates to serve as a chair.

  2. Both Parties shall endeavour to agree on the chair within 15 days
  after the second arbitrator has been appointed.

  3. The date of establishment of the arbitration panel shall be the
  date on which the chair is appointed.

  4. If a Party fails to appoint its arbitrator pursuant to paragraph 1,
  such arbitrator shall be selected by lot from the candidates proposed.
  If the Parties are unable to agree on the chair within the time period
  referred to in paragraph 2, it shall be selected by lot within one
  week from the candidates proposed.

  5. If an arbitrator dies, withdraws or is removed, a replacement shall
  be selected within 15 days in accordance with the selection procedure
  followed to select him or her. In such a case, any time period
  applicable to the arbitration panel proceeding shall be suspended for
  a period beginning on the date the arbitrator dies, withdraws or is
  removed and ending on the date the replacement is selected.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" name="Panel Reports" article_identifier="7485">1. The arbitration panel should, as a general rule, submit an initial
  report containing its findings and conclusions to the Parties not
  later than three months from the date of establishment of the
  arbitration panel. In no case should it do so later than five months
  from this date. Any Party may submit written comments to the
  arbitration panel on its initial report within 15 days of presentation
  of the report.

  2. The arbitration panel shall present to the Parties a final report
  within 30 days of presentation of the initial report.

  3. In cases of urgency, including those involving perishable goods,
  the arbitration panel shall make every effort to issue its final
  report to the Parties within three months from the date of
  establishment of the arbitration panel. In no case should it do so
  later than four months. The arbitration panel may give a preliminary
  ruling on whether a case is urgent.

  4. All decisions of the arbitration panel, including the adoption of
  the final report and of any preliminary ruling, shall be taken by
  majority vote, each arbitrator having one vote.

  5. The complaining Party may withdraw its complaint at any time before
  the final report has been issued. Such withdrawal is without prejudice
  to its right to introduce a new complaint regarding the same issue at
  a later point in time.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" name="Implementation Of Panel Reports" article_identifier="7486">1. Each Party shall be bound to take the measures involved in carrying
  out the final report referred to in Article 41(2).

  2. The Party concerned shall inform the other Party within 30 days
  after the final report has been issued of its intentions in respect of
  its implementation.

  3. The Parties shall endeavour to agree on the specific measures that
  are required for implementing the final report.

  4. The Party concerned shall promptly comply with the final report. If
  it is impracticable to comply immediately, the Parties shall endeavour
  to agree on a reasonable period of time to do so. In the absence of
  such agreement, either Party may request the original arbitration
  panel to determine the length of the reasonable period of time, in
  light of the particular circumstances of the case. The ruling of the
  arbitration panel shall be given within 15 days from that request.

  5. The Party concerned shall notify to the other Party the measures
  adopted in order to implement the final report before the expiry of
  the reasonable period of time determined in accordance with paragraph
  4. Upon that notification, any of the Parties may request the original
  arbitration panel to rule on the conformity of those measures with the
  final report. The ruling of the arbitration panel shall be given
  within 60 days from that request.

  6. If the Party concerned fails to notify the implementing measures
  before the expiry of the reasonable period of time determined in
  accordance with paragraph 4, or if the arbitration panel rules that
  the implementing measures notified by the Party concerned are
  inconsistent with the final report, such Party shall, if so requested
  by the complaining Party, enter into consultations with a view to
  agree on a mutually acceptable compensation. If no such agreement has
  been reached within 20 days from the request, the complaining Party
  shall be entitled to suspend only the application of benefits granted
  under the covered legal instruments equivalent to those affected by
  the measure found to violate the covered legal instruments.

  7. In considering what benefits to suspend, a complaining Party should
  first seek to suspend benefits in the same sector or sectors as that
  affected by the measure that the panel has found to violate the
  covered legal instruments. A complaining Party that considers it is
  not practicable or effective to suspend benefits in the same sector or
  sectors may suspend benefits in other sectors.

  8. The complaining Party shall notify the other Party of the benefits
  which it intends to suspend no later than 60 days before the date on
  which the suspension is due to take effect. Within 15 days from that
  notification, any of the Parties may request the original arbitration
  panel to rule on whether the benefits which the complaining Party
  intends to suspend are equivalent to those affected by the measure
  found to violate the covered legal instruments, and whether the
  proposed suspension is in accordance with paragraphs 6 and 7. The
  ruling of the arbitration panel shall be given within 45 days from
  that request. Benefits shall not be suspended until the arbitration
  Panel has issued its ruling.

  9. The suspension of benefits shall be temporary and shall only be
  applied by the complaining Party until the measure found to violate
  the covered legal instruments has been withdrawn or amended so as to
  bring it into conformity with the covered legal instruments, or the
  Parties have reached agreement on a resolution of the dispute.

  10. At the request of any of the Parties, the original arbitration
  panel shall rule on the conformity with the final report of any
  implementing measures adopted after the suspension of benefits and, in
  light of such ruling, whether the suspension of benefits should be
  terminated or modified. The ruling of the arbitration panel shall be
  given within 30 days from the date of that request.

  11. The rulings provided for in paragraphs 4, 5, 8 and 10 shall be
  binding.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="7487">1. Any time period mentioned in this Title may be extended by mutual
  agreement of the Parties.

  2. Unless the Parties otherwise agree, the arbitration panel
  proceedings shall be conducted in accordance with the Model Rules of
  Procedure set out in Annex III. The Joint Committee may amend the
  Model Rules of Procedure.

  3. Arbitration proceedings established under this Title will not
  consider issues relating to each Party's rights and obligations under
  the WTO.

  4. Recourse to the dispute settlement provisions of this Title shall
  be without prejudice to any possible action in the WTO framework,
  including dispute settlement action. However, where a Party has, with
  regard to a particular matter, instituted a dispute settlement
  proceeding under either Article 39(1) of this Title or the WTO
  Agreement, it shall not institute a dispute settlement proceeding
  regarding the same matter under the other forum until such time as the
  first proceeding has ended. For purposes of this paragraph, dispute
  settlement proceedings under the WTO Agreement are deemed to be
  initiated by a Party's request for a panel under Article 6 of the
  Understanding on Rules and Procedures Governing the Settlement of
  Disputes of the WTO.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VI" name="Specific Duties Of The Joint Committee With Respect To Trade And Other Trade Related Matters" chapter_identifier="900">
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" article_identifier="7488">1. The Joint Committee shall:

  (a) supervise the implementation and proper operation of this
  Decision, as well as of any other decision concerning trade and other
  trade related matters(4);

  (b) oversee the further elaboration of the provisions of this
  Decision;

  (c) undertake consultations pursuant to Article 38(2) and (3);

  (d) carry out any functions assigned to it under this Decision or
  under any other decision concerning trade or trade related matters;

  (e) assist the Joint Council in the performance of its functions
  regarding trade and other trade related matters;

  (f) supervise the work of all the special committees established under
  this Decision; and

  (g) report annually to the Joint Council.

  2. The Joint Committee may:

  (a) set up any special committees or bodies to deal with matters
  falling within its competence, and determine their composition and
  duties, and how they shall function;

  (b) meet at any time by agreement of the Parties;

  (c) consider any issues regarding trade and other trade related
  matters, and take appropriate action in the exercise of its functions;
  and

  (d) take decisions or make recommendations on trade and other trade
  related matters, in accordance with Article 48(2) of the Agreement.

  3. When the Joint Committee meets in order to perform any of the tasks
  conferred upon it by this Decision, it shall be composed of
  representatives of the members of the Council of the European Union
  and of the European Commission, on the one hand, and of
  representatives of the Government of Mexico, on the other, with a
  responsibility for trade and trade related matters, normally at senior
  civil servant level.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE VII" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="901">
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="7489">This Decision shall enter into force on the first day of the month
  following that in which it is adopted by the Joint Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" name="Annexes" article_identifier="7490">The Annexes to this Decision, including the Appendixes to those
  Annexes, are an integral part thereof.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="902">
      <article article_identifier="7491">Done at Brussels, 27 February 2001.

  For the Joint Council

  The President

  J. Castaeda

  (1) The Joint Council may decide to postpone the adoption of the
  decision provided for in this paragraph. Should this occur, the
  decision shall be adopted not later than one year after the conclusion
  of the negotiations mandated by Article XIX of GATS and in any event
  within a reasonable timeframe before the end of the ten-year
  transitional period.

  (2) Notwithstanding Article 3(e), shipping companies established
  outside the Community or Mexico and controlled by nationals of a
  Member State of the Community or Mexico, respectively, shall also be
  beneficiaries of the provisions of this Chapter, if their vessels are
  registered in accordance with their respective legislation, in that
  Member State or in Mexico and carry the flag of a Member State or
  Mexico.

  (3) In particular, a Party may require that natural persons must
  possess the necessary academic qualifications and/or professional
  experience specified in the territory where the service is supplied,
  for the sector of activity concerned.

  (4) The Parties understand that "trade and other trade related
  matters" includes any matter arising under this Decision and
  Titles III through V of the Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
