<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Yaoundé I</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>366</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>316</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1963-07-20</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1964-01-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1964-03-31</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>1971-01-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BDI</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">BEN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">BFA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">CAF</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">CIV</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">CMR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">COG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="11">GAB</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="12">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="13">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="14">MDG</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="15">MLI</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="16">MRT</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="17">NER</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="18">NLD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="19">RWA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="20">SEN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="21">SOM</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="22">TCD</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="23">TGO</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe; Africa</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>Yes</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=90770102&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="2709">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="22525">With a view to promoting an increase of trade between the Associated 
States and the Member States, strengthening their economic relations and the 
economic independence of the Associated States and thereby contributing to 
the development of international trade, the High Contracting Parties have 
agreed upon the following provisions which shall regulate their mutual trade 
relations.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="Customs Duties And Quantitative Restrictions" chapter_identifier="2710">
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="22526">1. Goods originating in Associated States shall, when imported into Member 
States, benefit from the progressive abolition of customs duties and charges 
having an effect equivalent to such duties, resulting between Member States 
under the provisions of Articles 12, 13, 14, 15 and 17 of the Treaty and the 
decisions which have been or may be adopted to accelerate the rate of achieving 
the aims of the Treaty. 



2. Nevertheless, upon the entry into force of the Convention, Member States 
shall abolish the customs duties and charges having an effect equivalent to such 
duties which they apply to the goods originating in Associated States which are 
listed in the Annex to this Convention. 

At the same time Member States shall apply the common customs tariff duties 
of the Community to imports of these goods from third countries. 



3. Imports from third countries of unroasted coffee into the Benelux countries 
on the one hand, and of bananas into the Federal Republic of Germany on the other 
hand, shall be subject to the terms set out respectively, as to unroasted coffee, 
in the Protocol this day concluded between the Member States and, as to bananas, 
in the Protocol concluded on 25 March 1957 between the Member States and in 
the Declaration annexed to this Convention. 



4. Application of the provisions of this Article shall not predetermine the 
treatment to be applied to certain agricultural products under the provisions 
of Article 11 of this Convention. 



5. At the request of an Associatezed State, there shall be consultations within 
the Association Council regarding the conditions of application of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="22527">1. Each Associated State shall accord identical tariff treatment to goods 
originating in any of the Member States; Associated States not applying this 
rule on the entry into force of this Convention shall do so within the following 
six months. 



2. In each Associated State goods originating in Member States shall benefit, 
under the terms set out in Protocol No. 1 annexed to this Convention, from the 
progressive abolition of customs duties and charges having an effect equivalent 
to such duties which that Associated State applies to imports of these goods-
into its territory. 

Provided always that, each Associated State may retain or introduce customs 
duties and charges having an effect equivalent to such duties which correspond 
to its development needs or its industrialization requirements or which are 
intended to contribute to its budget. 


The customs duties and charges having an effect equivalent to such duties 
levied by Associated States in accordance with the foregoing sub-paragraph, as 
also any alteration which they may make in these duties and charges under the 
provisions of Protocol No. 1, may not either de jure or de facto give rise to 
any direct or indirect discrimination between Member States. 


3. At the request of the Community and in accordance with the procedures laid 
down in Protocol No. 1, there shall be consultations within the Association 
Council regarding the conditions of application of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="22528">1. Insofar as an Associated State levies export duties on exports of its 
products to Member States, these duties may not give rise, de jure or de facto, 
to any direct or indirect discrimination between Member States and may not be 
granted than those applied to products exported to the most favoured third 
country. 



2. Without prejudice to the application of Article 13, paragraph 2 of this 
Convention, the Association Council shall take suitable measures if the 
application of such duties leads to serious disturbances in the conditions 
of competition.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="22529">1. With regard to the abolition of quantitative restrictions, Member States 
shall apply to imports of goods originating in the Associated States the relevant 
provisions of the Treaty, and of the decisions which have been or may be adopted 


-to accelerate the rate of achieving the..aims of the Treaty, which they apply in 
their relations with each other. 


2. At the request of an Associated State, there shall be consultations within 
the Association Council regarding the conditions of application of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="22530">1. Associated States shall, not later than four years after the entry into 
force of the Convention, abolish all quantitative restrictions on imports of 
goods originating in Member States and all measures having equivalent effect. 
This abolition shall be carried out progressively under the conditions set out 


in Protocol No. 2 annexed to this Convention. 



2. Associated States shall refrain from introducing any new quantitative 
restrictions or measures having equivalent effect on imports of goods originating 
in Member States. 



3. Should the measures provided for in Article 3 prove insufficient to meet 
their development needs and their industrialization requirements, or in the 
event of difficulties in their balance of payments, or, where agricultural 
products are concerned, in connection with the requirements arising from 
existing regional market organizations, Associated States may, notwithstanding 
the provisions of. the two foregoing paragraphs and subject to the terms of 
Protocol No. 2, retain or introduce quantitative restrictions on imports of 
goods originating in Member States. 



4. Associated States in which imports come within the province of a State 
trading monopoly or of any body which, de jure or de facto, either directly 
or indirectly limits, controls, directs or influences them, shall take any 
steps necessary to attain the objectives defined in this Title and to abolish 
progressively any discrimination in conditions. of supply and marketing of 
goods. 

Without prejudice to the application of Article 7 below, foreign trade 
plans drawn up by the Associated States shall not contain or bring about, 
de jure or de facto, any direct or indirect discrimination between Member 
States. 


The Associated States concerned shall inform the Association Council of 
the steps taken to implement the provisions of this paragraph. 


5. At .the request of the Community, there shall be consultations within the 
Association Council regarding the conditions of application of this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="22531">Without prejudice to the special provisions for border trade, the treatment 


that the Associated States apply by virtue of this Title to goods originating 


in Member States shall in no case be less favourable than that applied to goods 


originating in the most favoured: third country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="22532">This Convention shall not preclude the maintenance or establishment of 
customs unions or free-trade areas among Associated States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="22533">This Convention shall not preclude the maintenance or establishment of 
customs unions or free-trade areas between one or more Associated States and 
one or more third countries insofar as they neither are nor prove to be incompatible with the principles and provisions of the said Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="22534">The provisions of the foregoing Articles 3, 4 and 6 shall not preclude 
prohibitions or restrictions on imports, exports or goods in transit justified 
on grounds of public morality, public policy, public security, the protection 
of human, animal or plant life or health, the protection of national treasures 
possessing artistic, historic or archaeological value, or the protection of 
industrial and commercial property. Provided always that such prohibitions 
or restrictions shall not be used as a means of arbitrary discrimination nor as 
a disguised restriction on trade.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Provisions Concerning Certain Agricultural Products" chapter_identifier="2711">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="22535">When drawing up its common agricultural policy, the Community shall take 
the interests of the Associated States into consideration as regards products 
similar to and competitive with European products. The Community and the 
Associated States concerned shall consult together for this purpose. 


The treatment applicable to imports into the Community of these products, 
if they have originated in the Associated States, shall be determined by the 
Community in the course of defining its common agricultural policy, after 
consultation within the Association Council.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Provisions Concerning Commercial Policy" chapter_identifier="2712">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="22536">1. On matters of commercial policy, the Contracting Parties agree to keep each 
other informed and, should one of them so request, to consult together for the 
purpose of giving good effect to this Convention. 



2. Such consultation shall bear on measures concerning trade with third 
countries if these measures are likely to harm the interests of one or more 
Contracting Parties, with particular reference to: 

(a). 	the suspension, alteration or abolition of customs duties, 



(b) 	the granting of tariff quotas at reduced or zero duties, other than 
the quotas referred to in Article 2, paragraph 3, above, 



(c) 	the introduction, reduction or abolition of quantitative restrictions, 
without prejudice to the obligations incumbent upon certain 
Contracting Parties by reason of their membership of GATT. 

3. Upon the entry into force of this Convention, the Association Council shall 
define the procedure for consultation and exchange of information in respect of 
the implementation of this Article.:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Safeguard Clauses" chapter_identifier="2713">
      <article article_identifier="22537">1. If serious disturbances occur in one sector of the economy of an Associated 
State or jeopardize its external financial: stability, that State may take the 
necessary protective measures, notwithstanding the provisions of Article 3, 
paragraph 2, sub-paragraph1 and Article 6, paragraphs 1, 2 and 4.. 


These measures and the methods of applying them shall be notified 
immediately to the Association Council. 


2. If serious disturbances occur in one sector of the economy of the Community 


or of one or more Member States, or jeopardize their external financial stability, 
and if difficulties arise which may result in a region suffering grave economic 
hardship, the Community may take, or may authorize the Member State or States 
concerned to take such measures as may prove necessary in their relations with 
the Associated States, notwithstanding the provisions of Articles 2 and 5. 


These measures and -the methods of applying them shall be notified immediately 
to the Association Council. 



3. For the purpose of implementing paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, 
priority shall be given to such measures as will least disturb the functioning 
of the Association. These measures shall not exceed the limits strictly 
necessary to remedy the difficulties that have arisen. 



4. There shall be consultations within the Association Council regarding the 
measures taken under paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article. 

Such consultations shall be held at the request of the Community in respect 
of measures under paragraph 1 and at the request of one or more Associated 
States in respect of those under paragraph 2.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="2714">
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="22538">Without prejudice to the special provisions laid down in this Convention, 
and particularly those of Article 3 above, each Contracting Party shall refrain 
from any measure or practice of an internal fiscal nature that directly or 
indirectly sets up any discrimination between its own products and similar 
products originating in the territories of the other Contracting Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE II" name="Financial And Technical Co-Operation" chapter_identifier="2715">
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="22539">Under the conditions determined below the Community shall participate in 
measures calculated to promote the economic and social development of the 
Associated States, by supplementing the efforts achieved by those States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="22540">For the purposes set out in Article 15, and for the duration of this 
Convention, an aggregate amount of 730 million units of account shall be 
provided as follows: 



(a) 	666 million units of account by the Member States;. this amount, 
to be paid into the European Development Fund, hereinafter 
referred to as "the Fund", shall be employed up to 620 million 
units of account in the form of grants and the balance in the form 
of loans on special terms. 



(b) 	up to 64 million units of account by the European Investment Bank, 
hereinafter referred to as "the Bank",

in the form of loans granted 
by it under the terms set out in Protocol No. 5 concerning the 
administration of the financial aids, annexed to this Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="22541">Under the terms laid down by this Convention and by Protocol No. 5, the 
amount fixed in Article 16 above shall be employed as. follows: 


1. in the field of economic and social investments, 


-for basic economic and social schemes, 


-for production schemes of general interest, 
-for production schems providing normal financial returns, 
-for relevant technical assistance before, during and after such 


investments; 


2. 	in the field of general technical co-operation, 
-for surveying the.-development prospects of the economies of the 


Associated States, 
-for staff training and vocational training programmes; 


3. 	in the field of aids for diversification and production, 


-	for measures essentially intended to make marketing possible at 
competitive prices on the Community's markets as a whole, by 
encouraging, in particular, rationalization of cropping and sales 
methods, and by aiding producers to make the necessary adaptations; 


4. 	in the field of price stabilization, 


-	for advances for the purpose of helping to alleviate the .effects of 
temporary fluctuations in world prices.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" name="Grants And Loans Shall Be Assigned As Follows:" article_identifier="22542">(a) 	up to 500 million units of account for financing the measures 
referred to in Article 17, paragraphs 1 and 2, 



(b) 	up to 230 million units of account for financing the measures 
referred to in Article 17, paragraph 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="22543">The Bank loans referred to in Article 16(b) may carry a rebate on the 
interest. The rate of such rebates may be up to 3% on loans of a maximum 
duration of 25 years. 


The amounts required to pay such rebates shall, so long as the Fund 
exists, be charged to the amount of the grants provided for in Article 16(a).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 20" article_identifier="22544">1. The Community may grant advances from the liquid assets of the Fund up to 
a ceiling of 50 million units of account for the operations provided for in 
Article 17, paragraph 4. 



2. Such advances shall be granted according to the terms set out in 
Protocol No. 5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 21" article_identifier="22545">In order to finance the measures referred to in Article 17, the Associated 
State or group of Associated States concerned shall, as prescribed in Protocol No. 5 
open a file for each scheme or programme for which it is requesting financial 
assistance. It shall send this file to the Community, addressed to the Commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 22" article_identifier="22546">The Community shall examine the requests for financing that are brought 
before it by virtue of the provisions of the foregoing Article. It shall 
maintain such contacts with the Associated States concerned as it may require 
in order that its decisions on the schemes or programmes submitted to it may 
be formulated in full knowledge of the facts. The Associated State or group of 
Associated States concerned shall be informed of the decision taken regarding 
its request.:</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 23" article_identifier="22547">Aid contributed by the Community for the purpose of carrying out certain 
schemes or programmes may take the form of participation in financing in which, 
in particular, third countries, international finance organizations, or credit 
and development institutions and authorities, whether of the Associated States 
or the Member States, may take part.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 24" article_identifier="22548">1. The following shall be entitled to benefit from aids from the Fund: 


(a) as regards grants: 


-for economic and social investment schemes: either the.Associated 
States, or legal persons who are non-profit-making in their main 
capacity, who have a status of general or social interest, and 
who are subject in those States to government inspection; 


-for staff training and vocational training programmes and for 
economic surveys: the Governments of the Associated States 
specialized bodies and institutions, or on exceptional grounds, 
scholars and trainees; 


-for aid towards production: producers; 


-for aid towards diversification: the Associated States, producer 
groups or-similar bodies approved by the Community; or, failing 
these, producers themselves,; 


(b) as regards loans on special terms and rebates on interest: 


-for economic and social investment schemes: either the Associated 
States, or legal persons who are non-profit-making in their main 
capacity, who have a status of general or social interest, and 
who are subject in those States to government inspection, or, 


possibly, private enterprises by special decision of the Community; 


-for aid towards diversification: the Associated States, producer 
groups or similar bodies approved by the Community, or, failing 
these, producers themselves and, possibly, private enterprises by 
special decision of the Community, 


2. Financial aids may not be used to cover current administrative, maintenance 
and operating expenses.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 25" article_identifier="22549">As regards operations financed by the Fund or by the Bank, participation 
in the letting out of contracts, invitations for tenders, purchasing and other 
contracts shall be open, on equal terms, to all natural and legal persons who 
are nationals of the Member States or the Associated States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 26" article_identifier="22550">The amounts allocated for financing schemes or programmes under the 
provisions of this Title, shall be utilized in accordance with the purposes 
decided upon and shall be expended to the best economic advantage.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 27" article_identifier="22551">The Association Council shall lay down the general pattern for financial 
and technical co-operation within the framework of association, more particularly 
in the light of an annual report to be submitted to it by the organ responsible 


for administering the Community's financial and technical aid.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 28" article_identifier="22552">If any Associated State should fail to ratify the Convention, under the 


terms set out in Article 57, or denounce the Convention in accordance with 
Article 60, it shall then be obligatory upon the Contracting Parties to adjust 
the amount of financial aid fixed in Articles 16 and 18.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE III" name="Right Of Establishment, Services, Payments And Capital" chapter_identifier="2716">
      <article number="ARTICLE 29" article_identifier="22553">Without prejudice to measures adopted in implementation of the Treaty, in 
each Associated State nationals and companies of every Member State shall be 
placed on an equal footing as regards the right of establishment and provision 
of services, progressively and not later than three years after the entry into 
force of this Convention. 


The Association Council may authorize an Associated State, at its request, 
to suspend implementation of the provisions of the foregoing sub-paragraph over 
a given period and for a given activity. 


Nevertheless, in an Associated State nationals and companies of a Member 
State may benefit from the provisions of the first sub-paragraph, in respect 
of a given activity, only in so far as the State to which they belong grants 
similar advantages for the same activity to the nationals and companies of 
the Associated State in question.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 30" article_identifier="22554">Should an Associated State grant nationals or companies of a State which 
is neither a Member State of the Community nor an Associated State within the 
meaning of this Convention, more favourable treatment than that which implementation of the provisions of this Title afford to nationals, such treatment 
shall be extended to nationals or companies of the Member States, excepting 
where it arises out of regional agreements.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 31" article_identifier="22555">Subject to the provisions relating to movements of capital, the right of 
establishment within the meaning of this Convention shall include the right to 
engage in and carry on non-wage-earning activities, to set up and manage 
undertakings and in particular companies, and to set up agencies, branches or 
subsidiaries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 32" article_identifier="22556">Services within the meaning of this Convention shall be deemed to be services 
normally provided against remuneration, in so far as they are not governed by 
the provisions relating to trade, the right of establishment and movements of, 
capital. Services shall include in particular activities ofan industrial. 
.character, activities of a commercial character, artisan activities and 
activities of the liberal professions, excluding wage-earning activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 33" article_identifier="22557">Companies within the meaning of this Convention shall be deemed to be 
companies under civil or commercial law, including co-operative societies and 
other legal persons under public or private law, but not including non-profitmaking companies. 


Companies of a Member State or an Associated State shall be companies 
constituted in accordance with the law of a Member State or an Associated 
State, and having their registered office, central administration, or main 
establishment in a Member State or an Associated State; nevertheless", should 
they have only their registered office in a Member State or an Associated 
State, their business must be actively and continuously linked with the economy 
of that Member State or Associated State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 34" article_identifier="22558">The Association Council shall take any decisions required to further the 
implementation of Articles 29 to 35 above.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 35" article_identifier="22559">Each Signatory State undertakes, to the full extent of its powers, to 
authorize payments relating to trade in goods, services and capital and to 
wages, as also the transfer of such payments to the Member State or Associated 
State in which the creditor or the beneficiary is resident, in so far as the 
movement of such goods, services, capital or persons has been liberalized in 
implementation of this Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 36" article_identifier="22560">Throughout the whole duration of the loans and advances referred to in 
Chapters III, IV and V of Protocol No. 5, the Associated States undertake to 
make available to debtors the foreign currency necessary for the repayment of 
capital and interest on loans granted for schemes to be carried out in their 
territory and for repayment of advances granted to the stabilization funds.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 37" article_identifier="22561">1. Associated States shall make every endeavour not to introduce any new 
exchange restriction that would affect the treatment applied to investments and 
to current payments connected with the movements of capital resulting therefrom, 
where these are effected by persons residing in the Member States, and not to 
make the existing controls more restrictive. 



2. To the extent necessary for achieving the objectives of this Convention, 
the Associated States undertake to treat nationals and companies of Member 
States on an equal footing, not later than 1 January 1965, in respect of 
investments made by them as from the date of the entry into force of the 
Convention, as also of movements of capital resulting therefrom.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 38" article_identifier="22562">The Association Council shall formulate any appropriate recommendations to 
the Contracting Parties concerning the implementation of Articles 35, 36 and 
37 above.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE IV" name="Institutions Of The Association" chapter_identifier="2717">
      <article number="ARTICLE 39" article_identifier="22563">The Institutions of the Association shall be: 


-the Association Council assisted by the Association Committee, 


-the Parliamentary Conference of the Association, 


-t.e Court of Arbitration of the Association.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 40" article_identifier="22564">The Association Council shall be composed, on the one hand, of the members 


of the Council of the European Economic Community and members of the Commission 


of the European Economic Community and, on the other hand, of one member of the 


Government of each Associated State. 


Any member of the Association Council prevented from attending may be represented. The representative shall exercise all the rights of the accredited 
member. 


Proceedings of the Association Council shall only be valid if half the 
members of the Council of the Community, one member of the Commission and half 
the accredited members representing the Governments of the Associated States 


are present.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 41" article_identifier="22565">The office of the President of the Association Council shall be exercised 
alternately by a member of the Council of the European Economic Community and a 
member of the Government of an Associated State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 42" article_identifier="22566">Meetings of the Association Council shall be called once a year by the 
President. 


Furthermore it shall meet whenever necessary, in accordance with the 
conditions laid down in its rules of procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 43" article_identifier="22567">The Association Council shall express itself by mutual agreement between 
the Community on the one hand and the Associated States on the other. 


The Community on the one hand and the Associated States on the other shall 
each by means of an internal Protocol determine their procedure for arriving 
at their respective positions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 44" article_identifier="22568">In cases covered by this Convention, the Association Council shall dispose 


of the power of decision; such decisions shall be binding upon the Contracting 
Parties, who shall be under the obligation to take all necessary measures to 


carry them out. 


The Association Council may likewise formulate such resolutions, recommendations or opinions as it may deem necessary to achieve the common objectives 
and to ensure that the Association system works efficiently. 


The Association Council shall periodically study the results of the 
Association system in the light of that system's objectives. 


The Association Council shall lay down its rules of procedure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 45" article_identifier="22569">The Association Council shall be assisted in the performance of its task 
by an Association Committee composed on the one hand of one representative of 
each Member State and one representative of the Commission and, on the other, 
of one representative of each Associated State.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 46" article_identifier="22570">The Office of the Chairman of the Association Committee shall be filled 
by the State which is presiding over the Association Council. 


The Association Committee shall lay down its rules of procedure, which 
shall be submitted to the Association Council for approval.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 47" article_identifier="22571">1. In its rules of procedure the Association Council shall define the duties 
and powers of the Association Committee, with the object, in particular, of 
ensuring the continuity of co-operation essential to the satisfactory operation 
of the Association. 


2. The Association Council may when necessary delegate to the Association 
Committee the exercise of the powers entrusted to it by this Convention, under 
the terms and within the limits laid down by the Council. 


In that event, the Committee shall give its decisions in accordance with 
the terms of Article 43.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 48" article_identifier="22572">The Association Committce shall account for its actions to the Association 
Council, particularly in matters which have been the subject of a delegation of 
powers. 


It shall also submit any useful proposal to the Association Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 49" article_identifier="22573">The duties of the Secretariat of the Association Council and the Association 
Committee shall be carried out on a basis of parity and in accordance with the 
rules of procedure of the Association Council.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 50" article_identifier="22574">The Parliamentary Conference of the Association shall meet once a year. It 
shall be composed, on a basis of parity, of members of the Assembly and members 
of the Parliaments of the Associated States. 


Each year the Association Council shall submit a report on its activities 
to the Parliamentary Conference. 


The Parliamentary Conference may vote resolutions on matters concerning the 
Association. It shall appoint its President and its officers and shall adopt 
its own rules of procedure. 


The Parliamentary Conference shall be prepared by a Joint Committee set up 
on a basis of parity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 51" article_identifier="22575">1. Disputes concerning the interpretation or the application of the present 
Convention which might arise between one Member State, several Member States or: 
the Community on the one hand, and one or more Associated States on the other, 
shall be submitted by one of the parties to the dispute to the Association 
Council which shall seek an amicable settlement at its next meeting. If this 
cannot be achieved and if the parties to the dispute fail to agree upon an 
appropriate solution, the dispute shall, at the request of the earliest 
petitioner, be submitted to the Court of Arbitration of the Association. 



2. The Court of Arbitration shall be composed of five members: a President 
who shall be appointed by the Association Council and four' judges chosen from 
among persons whose independence and competence can be fully guaranteed. The 
Judges shall be appointed by the Association Council within three months after 
the entry into force of the Convention and for the duration thereof'. Two of. 
the judges shall be appointed by the Council of the European Economic Community 
and the other two by the Associated States. For each judge, following the same 
procedure, the Association Council shall appoint a deputy who shall sit in the 
event of the accredited judge being unable to do so. 



3. The Court of Arbitration shall act by majority vote. 



4. The decisions of the Court of Arbitration shall be binding on the parties 
to the dispute who shall be under the obligation to take all necessary measures 
to carry them out. 



5. Within three months after the judges are appointed, the Association Council 
shall lay down the Statute of the Court of Arbitration, on a proposal of that 
Court. 



6. The Court of Arbitration shall adopt its rules of procedure within the 
same period.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 52" article_identifier="22576">The Association Council may make any useful recommendations for the purpose 
of facilitating contacts between the Community and the representatives of the 
various trades and professions of the Associated States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 53" article_identifier="22577">The administrative expenses of the Institutions of the Association shall 
be defrayed in accordance with the terms set out in Protocol No. 6 annexed to 
this Convention.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE V" name="General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="2718">
      <article number="ARTICLE 54" article_identifier="22578">No treaties, conventions, agreements or arrangements of whatever form or 
nature between one or more Member States and one or more Associated States shall 
preclude the implementation of the provisions of this Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 55" article_identifier="22579">This Convention shall apply to the European territory of the Member States 
of the Community on the one hand, and to the territory of the Associated States 
on the other. 


The First Title of this Convention shall also apply to the relations 
between the French Overseas Territories and the Associated States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 56" article_identifier="22580">As far as the Community is concerned, this Convention shall be validly 
concluded by a decision of the Council of the Community taken in conformity 
with the provisions of the Treaty and notified to the Parties. It shall be 
ratified by the Signatory States in conformity with their respective 
constitutional requirements. 


The instruments of ratification and the act of notification of the 
conclusion of the Convention shall be deposited with the Secretariat of the 
Councils of the European Communities, who shall give notice thereof to the 
Signatory States.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 57" article_identifier="22581">1. This Convention shall enter into force on the first day of the month 
following the date on which the instruments of ratification of the Member 
States and of at least fifteen of the Associated States and the instrument 
notifying the conclusion of the Convention by the Community have been deposited. 



2. Any Associated State which has not ratified the Convention by the date of 
its entry into force as provided for in the previous paragraph, shall be able 
to proceed with this ratification only during the twelve months following such 
entry into force, unless before the expiry of this period it gives notice to 
the Association Council of its intention to ratify the Convention not later than 
six months after this period, and on condition that it deposits its instruments 
of ratification within the same time limit. 

3. As regards those States which have not ratified the Convention by the date 
of its entry into force as laid down in paragraph 1, the provisions of the 
Convention shall become applicable on the first day of the month following the 
deposit of their respective instruments of ratification. 


Signatory States who ratify the Convention in accordance with the terms of 
paragraph 2 shall recognize the validity-of-all measures taken in implementation 
of the said Convention between the date of its entry into force and the date 
when its provisions become applicable to them. Without prejudice to any delay 
which might be granted to them by the Association Council, they shall, not later 
than six months after depositing their instruments of ratification, carry out all 
the obligations which devolve upon them under the terms of this Convention or 
of implementing decisions adopted by the-Association Council. 


4. The rules of procedure of the organs of the Association shall lay down if 
and under what conditions the representatives of Signatory States which, on the 
date of entry into force of the Convention, have not yet ratified it, shall sit 
in the organs of the Association as observers. The arrangements thus adopted 
shall only be effective until the date on which the Convention becomes applicable 
to these States; in any case, they shall cease to apply on the date on which, 
according to the terms of paragraph 2 above, the State concerned shall no longer 
be able to proceed with the ratification of the Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 58" article_identifier="22582">1. The Association Council shall be informed of any request made by a State 
for accession to or association with the Community. 



2. There shall be consultations within the Association Council on any request 
for association with the Community made by a State which has an economic 
structure and production comparable to those of the Associated States if the 
Community, after examining the said request, has laid it before the Association 
Council. 



3. The agreement of association between the Community and any State covered by 
the previous paragraph may provide for the accession of that State to the present 
Convention. That State shall then enjoy the same rights and be subject to the 
same obligations as the Associated States. Provided always that the agreement 
which associates it with the Community may determine the date on which certain of 
these rights and obligations shall become applicable to it. 

Such accession shall not adversely affect the advantages accruing to the 
Associated States which are signatories to this Convention from the provisions 
relating to financial and technical co-operation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 59" article_identifier="22583">This Convention shall be concluded for a period of five years from the 
date of its entry into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 60" article_identifier="22584">One year before the expiry of this Convention, the Contracting Parties 
shall examine the provisions which might be made for a further period. 


The Association Council shall if necessary take any transitional measures 
required until the new Convention enters into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 61" article_identifier="22585">The Comnmunity and the Member States shall undertake the obligations set 
out in Articles 2, 5 and 11 of the Convention with respect to Associated States 
which, on the grounds of international obligations applying at the time of the 
entry into force of the Treaty establishing the European Economic Community art 
subjecting them to a particular customs treatment, may consider themselves not 
yet able to offer the Community the reciprocity provided for by Article , 
paragraph 2 of the Convention. 


The Contracting Parties concerned shall re-examine the situation not later 
than three years after the entry into force of the Convention.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 62" article_identifier="22586">This Convention may be dedenounced by the Community in respect of any 
Associated State and by any Associated State in respect of the Community by 
means of six months' notice.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 63" article_identifier="22587">The Protocols annexed to this Convention shall form an integral part 
thereof.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 64" article_identifier="22588">The present Convention, drawn up in a single original in the German, 
French, Italian and Netherlands languages, each of these texts being equally 
authentic, shall be deposited in the archives af the Secretariat of the Councils 
of the European Comrnunities which shall transmit a certified copy to the 
Government of each of the Signatory States.</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
