<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Russian Federation - Turkmenistan</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>862</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>432</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1992-11-11</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1993-04-06</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2013-01-18</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>1993-12-31</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">TKM</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">RUS</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">TKM</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS)</region>
    <parties_wto>No</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://rtais.wto.org/rtadocs/862/TOA/English/Text of Agreement RF-Turkmenistan.docx</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4373">
      <article article_identifier="37886">AGREEMENTBetween the Government of THE Russian
  Federation and the Government of Turkmenistan on Free Trade
  (Moscow, 11 November, 1992)

  The Government of the Russian Federation and the Government of
  Turkmenistan, hereafter referred to as the Contracting Parties,

  Guided by the provisions of the Treaty on Friendship and Co-operation
  between the Russian Federation and Turkmenistan signed on 31 July
  1992,

  Taking into consideration the multilateral Agreement on customs policy
  principles of 13 March 1992,

  Striving to develop trade and economic cooperation between the Russian
  Federation and Turkmenistan on the basis of equality and mutual
  benefit,

  On the assumption of the sovereign right of each State to conduct its
  independent foreign economic policy and enforce relevant international
  obligations and realization of proclaimed intentions,

  Intending to promote the establishment of common market for goods,
  services, capital and labour,

  Desiring to promote the establishment of proper conditions for the
  Customs union,

  HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4374">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="37887">1. Contracting Parties shall not apply customs duties, taxes and charges having equivalent impact on exportation and importation of goods originating from the customs territory of one of Contracting Parties and destined for the customs territory of the other Contracting Party. 
Exceptions from this trade regime on the basis of the agreed nomenclature of goods shall be formalized by annual documents, which shall be an integral part of this Agreement. 
2. For the purposes of this Agreement, and for its effective term, goods originating from the territories of Contracting Parties shall be deemed to be:
Completely produced in the territory of Contracting Parties; 
Having been processed on the territory of Contracting Parties by utilizing raw materials and components of third country origin, and, with this regard, have been changed its classification under the Goods Nomenclature of International Trade, based under the Harmonized System of Commodity Description and Coding of Goods and Combined tariff-statistical nomenclature of the European economic community, on the basis of the first four digits; 
Produced with the use of raw materials and components listed in "b" above, provided that its total cost shall not exceed fixed proportion of export price of goods sold. 
Detailed rules on establishing origin of goods shall be formulated by the Contracting Parties in a separate document, which will become an integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="37888">Contracting Parties shall not:

  directly or indirectly impose on goods, covered by this Agreement, any
  internal taxes or charges in excess of corresponding taxes and
  charges, imposed on domestically produced similar goods or goods of
  third country origin;

  apply with regard to import or export of goods, covered by this
  Agreement, any special limitations or requirements, which are not
  applied in a similar situation to domestically produced similar goods
  or goods of third country origin;

  apply with regard to warehousing, reloading, storage, transportation
  of goods, originated from the territory of the other Contracting
  Party, as well as to payments and payment transfers, rules other than
  those applied in similar situations to goods of domestic production or
  of third country origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="37889">Contracting Parties shall refrain from imposing quantitative
      restrictions or equivalent to them measures on export and/or
      import of goods within the frames of this Agreement.
    
      Quantitative restrictions, referred to in Paragraph 1 of this
      Article, may be introduced unilaterally within reasonable reasons
      and on a strictly defined period only in case of:
    
      Quantitative restrictions, referred to in Paragraph 1 of this
      Article, may also be introduced by mutual agreement of the Parties
      and shall be included in the annual documents, as referred to in
      Paragraph 1 Article 1 of this Agreement.
    
      A Contracting Party, which applies quantitative restrictions in
      accordance with Paragraph 2 of this Article, shall, upon request
      of the other Contracting Party, provide necessary information on
      reasons, forms and possible time frames for using the
      abovementioned restrictions.
    
      Contracting Parties shall endeavour to solve all issues arising in
      relation to application of quantitative restrictions under
      Paragraph 2 of this Article by means of consultations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="37890">Neither Contracting Party shall permit re-export of goods in relation
  to export of which the other Contracting Party, on which territory
  these goods originate from, applies measures of tariff or non-tariff
  regulation. Contracting Parties shall define a list of goods, which
  are forbidden for re-export, and also exchange lists of goods, to
  which measures of tariff and non-tariff regulation are applied.

  Re-export of such goods into third countries is permitted only upon
  written consent and on conditions stipulated by an authorized state
  agency of the country of origin of these goods. In case of
  non-compliance with this provision, the Contracting Party, whose
  interests have been violated, has the right for unilateral
  introduction of measures to regulate export of goods into the
  territory of the Contracting Party that permitted the non-sanctioned
  re-export. Currency gain from such re-export shall be repaid to the
  country of origin of relevant goods.

  For the purposes of this Article the term "re-export" refers
  to the export of goods originating from the customs territory of one
  Contracting Party, by the other Contracting Party outside the customs
  territory of the latter, for the purpose of exporting it into a third
  country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="37891">Contracting Parties will exchange information on customs issues on a
  regular basis, including customs statistics. Relevant authorized
  bodies of Contracting Parties shall formulate in a relevant document
  an order of exchanging such information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="37892">Contracting Parties will apply measures to converge levels of
      customs duties, which are imposed in trade with third countries,
      and for this purpose will hold regular consultations.
    
      Contracting Parties will inform each other of all exceptions from
      the existing in its states rules on customs tariffs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="37893">Contracting Parties shall recognize incompatible with the purposes of
  this Agreement unfair business practices, which are expressed, in
  particular, in the following:

  concluding agreements between enterprises, its divisions, which
  purpose is to prevent or limit competition or violate conditions for
  it on the territories of Contracting Parties;

  performing actions, by which means one or several enterprises use
  their dominant position, limiting competition within the entire or
  considerable part of the territory of Contracting Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="37894">At applying measures of tariff and non-tariff regulation in bilateral
  economic relationships, for statistical information exchange, for
  carrying out customs procedures, Contracting Parties have agreed to
  use the unified nine-digit Commodity Nomenclature of Foreign Economic
  Activitiy (CN FEA), based upon the Harmonized Commodity Description
  and Coding System and Combined Tariffs and Statistics Nomenclature of
  the European Economic Community. At the same time for the own needs of
  its states Contracting Parties exercise the development of Commodity
  Nomenclature beyond the nine digits if necessary.

  Conduct of the standard specimen of the Commodity Nomenclature is
  carried out by the Russian Federation through the existing
  representations in relevant international organizations during the
  period of time, until Turkmenistan declares its independent conduct of
  such standard specimen.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="37895">Contracting Parties agree that compliance with the principle of
  freedom of transit is the major condition for achieving goals of this
  Agreement and a substantial element in the process of its integration
  to the system of international specialization of labour and
  cooperation.

  Thereupon each Contracting Party shall provide unimpeded transit
  through its territory for goods originating from the customs territory
  of the other Contracting Party and/or third countries and destined for
  the customs territory of the other Contracting Party or any third
  country, and shall provide exporters, importers and carriers with all
  available and necessary for ensuring transit facilities and services
  on terms not worse than these facilities and services are granted to
  national exporters, importers or carriers, or exporters, importers or
  carriers of any other third state.

  Transit tariffs for all types of transportation, including tariffs for
  loading and unloading operations, shall be economically justified and
  shall not exceed normal operational expenses, including reasonable
  profit rates. Contracting Parties shall not request payment for
  warehousing, reloading, storage and transportation of goods in
  currency of any third state.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="37896">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent any of the Contracting Parties
  to take measures, which it considers necessary for protecting its
  vital interests or which undoubtedly are necessary for compliance with
  international agreements, which it is or intends to become parties to,
  if these measures relate to:

  
    information affecting the interests of national security;
  
    trade in arms, ammunitions and military equipment;
  
    research or production related to security needs;
  
    supply of materials and equipment used in nuclear industry;
  
    protection of public morality, public order;
  
    protection of industrial and intellectual property;
  
    gold, silver and other precious metals and stones;
  
    protection of human, animal and plant life.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="37897">Provisions of this Agreement shall replace the provisions of
  agreements concluded earlier between Contracting Parties insofar as
  the latter are either incompatible with the former or identical to it.
  Contracting Parties shall instruct its competent authorities to
  prepare an appropriate protocol on this matter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="37898">This Agreement shall not affect other Agreements, concluded earlier by
  Contracting Parties with third countries.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="37899">Nothing in this Agreement shall prevent Contracting Parties from
  establishing relationships, which do not contradict goals and terms of
  this Agreement, with third countries, as well as with its associations
  and international organizations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="37900">Disputes between Contracting Parties, which are related to
  interpretation or application of provisions of this Agreement, shall
  be settled by means of negotiations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="37901">To achieve the goals of this Agreement and to elaborate
  recommendations for improvement of trade-economic cooperation between
  the two countries, Contracting Parties have agreed to establish a
  joint Russian-Turkmenistan commission.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="37902">Contracting Parties have agreed that the Russian Federation may
  establish its trade representation in Turkmenistan, and Turkmenistan
  may establish its trade representation in the Russian Federation. The
  legal status of trade representations, its functions and residence
  shall be formulated in a separate agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="37903">Any state may accede to this Agreement on terms, which will be agreed
  between the acceding state and Contracting Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" article_identifier="37904">An integral part of this Agreement shall be a Protocol on exceptions
  to free trade regime, which Contracting Parties shall sign in by the
  end of 1992.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="37905">This Agreement shall become effective upon exchange of notices of
  completion by Contracting Parties of intra-state procedures necessary
  for its entry into force and will remain in force upon the expiry of
  twelve months from the date, when one of Contracting Parties notifies
  the other Contracting Party in writing of its desire to terminate its
  action.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter chapter_identifier="4375">
      <article article_identifier="37906">Done in the City of Moscow, on November 11, two originals, each in
  Russian and Turkmen, both texts are being equally authentic.

  (Signature)</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
