<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>EC - Cyprus Association Agreement</name>
    <type>Customs Union</type>
    <wto_rta_id>237</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>210</treaty_identifier>
    <status>Inactive</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV</notification>
    <date_signed>1972-12-19</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>1973-06-01</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>1973-06-13</date_notification>
    <end_implementation/>
    <date_inactive>2004-05-01</date_inactive>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">BEL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">CYP</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="3">DEU</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="4">DNK</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="5">FRA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="6">GBR</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="7">IRL</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="8">ITA</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="9">LUX</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="10">NLD</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1"/>
    </parties>
    <composition>Plurilateral</composition>
    <region>Europe</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://sul-derivatives.stanford.edu/derivative?CSNID=90880152&amp;mediaType=application/pdf</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="2150">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1" article_identifier="17969">By this Agrcement, an Association is established 
between the European Economic Community and the 
Republic of Cyprus.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2" article_identifier="17970">1. The aim of the Agreement is progressively to 
eliminate obstacles as regards the main body of trade 
between the European Economic Community and 
Cyprus and thus to contribute to the development of 


international trade. 



2. The Agreement provides for two successive 
stages, the first terminating on 30 June 1977 and the 
second of a duration, in principle, of five years. 



3. Negotiations are provided for during the 
eighteen months preceding the expiry of the first 
stage, with a view to defining the content of the 
second stage, providing for a further elimnination of 
obstacles to trade between the European Economic 
Community and Cyprus and the adoption by the 
Republic of Cyprus of the Common Customs Tariff. 



4. The first stage shall be governed by the 

provisions set forth hereinafter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE I" name="Trade" chapter_identifier="2151">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3" article_identifier="17971">1. Products originating in Cyprus, shall, on 
importation into the Community, benefit from the 
provisions set forth in Annex I. 


2. Products originating in the Community shall, on 


importation into Cyprus, benefit from the provisions 


set forth in Annex II. 


3. The Contracting Parties shall take all 
appropriate measures, whether general or particular, 


to ensure fulfilment of the obligations arising out of 
the Agreement. 


They shall refrain from any measure likely to 
jeopardize the achievement of the aims of the 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4" article_identifier="17972">Any measure or practice of an internal fiscal nature establishing, whether directly or indirectly, a
discrimination between the products of one Contracting Party and like products originating in the other Contracting Party shall be forbidden.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5" article_identifier="17973">The rules governing trade between the Contracting
Parties may not give rise to any discrimination 
between the Member States, or between nationals or 


companies of these States, nor nationals or 
companies of Cyprus.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6" article_identifier="17974">To the extent that export duties are levied on 
products of one Contracting Party exported to the 
other Contracting Party, such duties shall not be 
higher than those applicable to products exported to 


the most favoured third country.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7" article_identifier="17975">The provisions set forth in the Protocol shall 
determine the rules of origin to be applied to the 


products covered by the Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8" article_identifier="17976">1. If one of the Contracting Parties finds that 
dumping is being practised in its relations with the 
other Contracting Party, it may, following
consultations within the Association Council, have 
recourse to protective measures against such 
practices, in accordance with the Agreement relating 


to the application of Article VI of the General 
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. 


In case of urgency, such Contracting Party may, after 
having informed the Association Council, take the 
provisional measures provided for in the said 


Agreement. Consultations shall be held on such 
measures not later than two weeks after their 
implementation. 


2. I; the event of measures being taken against


bounties and subsidies, the Contracting Parties 


undertake to comply with the provisions of Article VI 


of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. 


3. Any dumping practices, bounties or subsidies 
Article 4 which have been ascertained, and any measures taken 
against them, shall, at the request of one of the 


Any measure or practice of an internal fiscal nature Contracting Parties, give rise to consultation within 
establishing, whether directly or indirectly, a the Association Council at three-monthly intervals.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9" article_identifier="17977">Payments relating to trade in goods, and the transfer 


of such payments to the Member State in which the 


creditor is resident, or to Cyprus, shall be free from 


any restrictions, to the extent that such transactions 


fall within the provisions of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10" article_identifier="17978">1. If serious disturbances occur in a sector of 
Cyprus' economic activity or jeopardize its external 
financial stability, or if difficulties arise which result 


in the deterioration of the economic situation of any 
area of Cyprus, the Republic of Cyprus may take the 
necessary protective measures. 


Such measures and the procedures for applying them 


shall be notified to the Association Council without 


delay. 


2. If serious disturbances occur in a sector of the 
economic activity of the Community or of one or 
more of its Member States, or jeopardize their 
external financial stability, or if difficulties arise 
which result in the deterioration of the economic 
situation of any area of the Community, the latter 
may take, or may authorize the Member State or 
States concerned to take, the necessary protective 


measures. 


Such measures and the procedures for applying them 


shall be notified to the Association Council without 
delay. 


3. For the purpose of implementing paragraphs 1 
and 2, the measures selected must, as a matter of 
priority, be such as would least disturb the 
functioning of the regime established by this 
Agreement. Such measures shall not exceed the limits 
of what is strictly necessary to remedy the difficulties 


that have arisen. 


4. ConsultationsmaybeheldwithintheAssociation 
Council concerning measures taken pursuant to 
paragraphs 1 and 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11" article_identifier="17979">commercial property. However, such prohibitions or 


restrictions shall not constitute a means of arbitrary


discrimination or a disguised restriction on trade.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="TITLE II" name="General And Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="2152">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12" article_identifier="17980">1. An Association Council is hereby established,
which shall be responsible for the administration of 
this Agreement and shall supervise its proper


implementation. For this purpose, it shall make 
recommendations. It shall take decisions in the cases 
provided for under Title II. 


2. The Contracting Parties shall keep each other 
informed and, at the request of either Party, shall 
hold consultations within the Association Council 
with a view to the proper implementation of this 


Agreement. 


3. The Association Council shall lay down its rules 
of procedure in a Decision.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13" article_identifier="17981">1. The Association Council shall consist of the 
members of the Council and members of the 
Commission of the European Communities, on the 
one hand, and of members of the Government of the 
Republic of Cyprus, on the other. 


Members of the Association Council may arrange to 
be represented, in accordance with the conditions to 
be laid down in the rules of procedure. 


2. The Association Council shall take its decisions 
by common agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14" article_identifier="17982">1. The Association Council shall be presided in 
turn by each of the Contracting Parties, in 
accordance with the provisions to be adopted in the 
rules of procedure of the Association Council. 


This Agreement shall not preclude prohibitions or 
restrictions on imports, exports or goods in transit 
justified on grounds of public morality, public policy,
public security, the protection of health and life of 
humans, animals or plants, the protection of national 
treasures possessing artistic, historic, or archaeological value, or the protection of industrial or 


2. Meetings of the Association Council shall be 
convened once a year by its President. 


The Association Council shall, in addition, meet 
whenever circumstances so require, at the request of 
either of the Contracting Parties, in accordance with 
the conditions to be laid down in its rules of 
procedure. 


3. The Association Council may decide to set up 
any committee that can assist it in the discharge of its 
rasks. 


In its rules of procedure, the Association Council 
shall determine the composition and duties of such 
committees and how they shall function.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15" article_identifier="17983">This Agreement may be denounced by either 
Contracting Party, subject to six months' notice in 
advance being given.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16" article_identifier="17984">This Agreement shall apply on the one hand, to the 


territories to which the Treaty establishing the 
European Economic Community applies, and, on the 
other hand, to the territory of the Republic of 
Cyprus.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17" article_identifier="17985">Annexes I and II and the Protocol on originating
products shall form an integral part of this 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 18" article_identifier="17986">This Agreement shall come into force on the first day 
of the month following the date on which the 
Contracting Parties have notified each other that the 
necessary procedures to this end have been 
completed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 19" article_identifier="17987">This Agreement is drawn up in duplicate, in the 
Dutch, English, French, German and Italian 
languages, each of these texts being equally authentic.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter name="Conclusion" chapter_identifier="2153">
      <article article_identifier="17988">Zu Urkund dessen haben die unterzeichneten Bevollmichtigten ihre Unterschriften unter 
dieses Abkommen gesetzt. 


En foi de quoi, les plénipotentiaires soussignés ont apposé leurs signatures au bas du 
present accord. 


In fede di che, i plenipotenziari sottoscritri hanno apposto le loro firme in calce al 
presente accordo. 


Ten blijke waarvan de ondergetekende gevolmachtigden hun handtekening onder deze 


Overeenkomst hebben gesteld. 


In witness whereof, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures 
below this Agreement. 


Geschehen zu Brussel am neunzehnten Dezember neunzehnhundertzweiundsiebzig. 


Fait a Bruxelles, le dix-neuf décembre mil neuf cent soixante-douze. 


Fatto a Bruxelles, addi diciannove dicembre millenovecentosettantadue. 


Gedaan te Brussel, de negentiende december negentienhonderdtweeEnzeventig. 


Done at Brussels on this nineteenth day of December in the year one thousand nine 


hundred and seventy-two. 


Im Namen des Rates der Europaischen Gemeinschaften 
Pour le Conseil des Communautés européennes, 
Per iI Consiglio delle Comunità europee, 
Voor de Raad der Europese Gemeenschappen, 
For the Council of the European Communities, 


Mit dem Vorbehalt, daß für die Europäische Wirtschaftsgemeinschaft erst dann end

gültig eine Verpflichtung besteht, wenn sie der anderen Vertragspartei notifiziert hat, 


daß die dutch den Vertrag zur Gründung der Europäischen Wirtschaftsgemeinschaft 
vorgeschriebenen Verfahren, namentlich die Anhörung des Europäischen Parlaments, 


starrgefunden haben. 


Sous reserve que la Communauté économique européenne ne sera définitivement engagée
qu'après notification à l'autre partie contractante de l'accomplissement des procedures 
requises par le trait instituant la Communauté économique europeenne et notamment 
la consultation de l'Assemblee. 


Con riserva che la Comunita economic europea sara definitivamente vincolata soltanto 
dopo la notifica all'altra parte contraente dell'espletamento delle procedure richieste 


dal trattato che istituisce la Comunita economica europea e, in particolare, dell'avvenuta 
consultazione del Parlamento europeo. 


Onder voorbehoud dat de Europese Economische Gemeenschap eerst definitief gebonden 


zal zijn na kennisgeving aan de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij van de vervulling 


der door het Verdrag tot oprichting van de Europese Economische Gemeenschap vereiste 
procedures, met name van de raadpleging van het Europese Parlement. 


Provided that the Community shall be finally bound only after the other Contracting 
Party has been notified that the procedures required by the Treaty establishing the 
European Economic Community, and, in particular, consultation of the European 


Parliament, have been completed. 


Im Namen der Regierung der Republik Zypern, 
Pour le gouvernement de la répubiique de Chypre, 
Per il governo della Repubblica di Cipro, 
Voor de Regering van de Republiek Cyprus, 
For the Government of the Republic of Cyprus, 


'4 Anj. W</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
