<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treaty>
  <meta>
    <name>Japan - Mongolia</name>
    <type>Free Trade Agreement &amp; Economic Integration Agreement</type>
    <wto_rta_id>835</wto_rta_id>
    <treaty_identifier>425</treaty_identifier>
    <status>In Force</status>
    <notification>GATT Art. XXIV &amp; GATS Art. V</notification>
    <date_signed>2015-02-10</date_signed>
    <date_into_force>2016-06-07</date_into_force>
    <date_notification>2016-06-01</date_notification>
    <end_implementation>2036-12-30</end_implementation>
    <date_inactive/>
    <parties_original>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MNG</partyisocode>
    </parties_original>
    <parties>
      <partyisocode n="1">JPN</partyisocode>
      <partyisocode n="2">MNG</partyisocode>
    </parties>
    <composition>Bilateral</composition>
    <region>East Asia</region>
    <parties_wto>Yes</parties_wto>
    <crossregional>No</crossregional>
    <language>en</language>
    <source lang="en" type="full text">http://www.mofa.go.jp/a_o/c_m2/mn/page3e_000298.html</source>
    <source lang="en" type="annex">http://www.mofa.go.jp/a_o/c_m2/mn/page3e_000298.html</source>
  </meta>
  <body>
    <chapter name="Preamble" chapter_identifier="4241">
      <article article_identifier="36719">Preamble 


Japan and Mongolia, 


Conscious of their warm relationship and strong 
economic and political ties that have developed through
growing trade and investment and mutually beneficial
cooperation between the Parties; 


Realizing that a dynamic and rapidly changing global 
environment brought about by globalization and closer
integration among economies in the world presents many new
economic challenges and opportunities to the Parties; 


Recognizing that the economies of the Parties are 
endowed with conditions to complement each other and that
this complementarity should contribute to further promoting
the sustainable economic development in the Parties, by
making use of their respective economic strengths through
bilateral trade and investment activities; 


Realizing the differences between the Parties in terms 
of their level of economic development; 


Seeking to create a clearly established and secured 
trade and investment framework through mutually
advantageous rules to govern trade and investment between
the Parties; 


Further seeking to enhance the competitiveness and
supply capacity of the economies of the Parties, make their
markets more efficient and vibrant, ensure predictable
commercial environment for further expansion of trade and
investment between them, and contribute to further economic
efficiency and growth of the Parties; 


Noting the important roles of private sectors for 
further enhancing commercial and economic relations between
the Parties and believing that this Agreement will create
new trade and investment opportunities for such private
sectors; 


Believing that the implementation of this Agreement 
will contribute to creating new and better employment
opportunities through human resource development and thus
will improve living standard, including consumer welfares,
of the peoples of the Parties; 


Reaffirming the view that this Agreement will not only 
contribute to strengthening the existing political and
economic ties between the Parties but also become one of 
the significant steps in building Japan-Mongolia “Strategic
Partnership”; 


Recalling Article XXIV of the GATT 1994 and Article V 
of the GATS; 


Convinced that this Agreement would open a new era for 
the relationship between the Parties; and 


Determined to establish a legal framework for 
strengthening the economic partnership between the Parties; 


HAVE AGREED as follows:</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 1" name="General Provisions" chapter_identifier="4242">
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.1" name="Objective" article_identifier="36720">The objective of this Agreement is to create a new
economic dynamism between the Parties by means of the
following, taking into account the stage of development and
economic needs of the Parties: 



(a) liberalizing and facilitating trade in goods and
services between the Parties; 



(b) facilitating movement of natural persons between
the Parties; 



(c) increasing investment opportunities and
strengthening protection for investments and
investment activities in the Parties; 



(d) enhancing protection of intellectual property; 



(e) promoting cooperation and coordination for the
effective enforcement of competition laws in each
Party; 



(f) establishing a framework for further reinforcing,
broadening and deepening bilateral cooperation in
all fields relevant to trade and investment and 
improvement of the business environment; and 



(g) creating effective procedures for the
implementation and operation of this Agreement
and for the prevention and resolution of
disputes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.2" name="General Definitions" article_identifier="36721">For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise
specified: 



(a) the term “Agreement on Customs Valuation” means
the Agreement on Implementation of Article VII of
the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994
in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 



(b) 	the term “Area” means: 

(i) 	for Japan, the territory of Japan, and the 
exclusive economic zone and the continental 
shelf with respect to which Japan exercises
sovereign rights or jurisdiction in
accordance with international law; and 


(ii) 	for Mongolia, the territory of Mongolia; 


Note: 	Nothing in this subparagraph shall affect
the rights and obligations of the Parties
under international law, including those
under the UNCLOS. 


(c) the term “commercial presence” means any type of
business or professional establishment, including
through: 


(i) the constitution, acquisition or maintenance
of a juridical person; or 


(ii) 	the creation or maintenance of a branch or a 
representative office, 


within the Area of a Party for the purposes of
supplying a service; 



(d) 	the term “customs authority” means the authority 
that, according to the legislation of each Party
or a non-Party, is responsible for the
administration and enforcement of customs laws 
and regulations: 


(i) for Japan, the Ministry of Finance, or its
successor; and 


(ii) 	for Mongolia, the Customs General 
Administration, or its successor; 


(e) the term “days” means calendar days, including
weekends and holidays; 



(f) the term “enterprise” means any juridical person
or any other entity duly constituted or organized
under the applicable laws and regulations,
whether or not for profit, and whether private or
government owned or controlled, including any
corporation, trust, partnership, sole
proprietorship, joint venture, association,
organization or company; 



(g) the term “enterprise of a Party” means an
enterprise constituted or organized under the
applicable laws and regulations of that Party; 



(h) the term “GATS” means the General Agreement on
Trade in Services in Annex 1B to the WTO 
Agreement; 



(i) the term “GATT 1994” means the General Agreement
on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO 
Agreement. For the purposes of this Agreement,
references to articles in the GATT 1994 include 
the interpretative notes; 



(j) the term “Harmonized System” or “HS” means the
Harmonized Commodity Description and Coding
System set out in the Annex to the International
Convention on the Harmonized Commodity
Description and Coding System, and adopted and
implemented by the Parties in their respective
laws; 



(k) the term “investment” means every kind of asset
owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by
an investor, including: 

(i) an enterprise and a branch of an enterprise; 


(ii) shares, stocks or other forms of equity
participation in an enterprise, including
rights derived therefrom; 


(iii) bonds, debentures, loans and other forms of
debt, including rights derived therefrom; 



(iv) rights under contracts, including turnkey,
construction, management, production or
revenue-sharing contracts; 


(v) claims to money and to any performance under
contract having a financial value; 


(vi) intellectual property;

 

Note: 	Intellectual property means that set
out in Article 12.2. 


 

(vii) rights conferred pursuant to laws and
regulations or contracts such as
concessions, licenses, authorizations and
permits, including, but not limited to,
those for the supply of financial services,
the supply of telecommunications services,
the production of nuclear energy and the
exploration and exploitation of natural
resources; and 


(viii) any other tangible and intangible, movable
and immovable property, and any related
property rights, such as leases, mortgages,
liens and pledges; 


Note: 	An investment includes the amount yielded 
by an investment, in particular, profit,
interest, capital gains, dividends,
royalties and fees. A change in the form
in which assets are invested does not 
affect their character as an investment. 


(l) the term “investor of a Party” means: 


(i) a natural person who is a national of a
Party under the law of the Party; or 


(ii) an enterprise of that Party, 


that seeks to make, is making or has made
investments in the Area of the other Party; 



(m) the term “juridical person” means any legal
entity duly constituted or otherwise organized
under applicable law, whether for profit or
otherwise, and whether private or government
owned, including any corporation, trust,
partnership, joint venture, sole proprietorship
or association; 



(n) a juridical person is: 


(i) “owned” by persons if more than 50 percent
of the equity interest in it is beneficially
owned by the persons; and 


(ii) “controlled” by persons if the persons have
the power to name a majority of its
directors or otherwise to legally direct its
actions; 


(o) the term “originating good” means a good which
qualifies as an originating good under the
provisions of Chapter 3; 



(p) the term “Parties” means Japan and Mongolia and
the term “Party” means either Japan or Mongolia; 



(q) the term “person” means a natural person or an
enterprise/juridical person, as the case may be; 



(r) the term “service supplier” means any person that
supplies or seeks to supply a service; 


Note: 	Where the service is not supplied or
sought to be supplied directly by a
juridical person but through other forms
of commercial presence such as a branch or
a representative office, the service
supplier (i.e. the juridical person)
shall, nonetheless, through such
commercial presence be accorded the
treatment provided for service suppliers
under Chapter 7. Such treatment shall be
extended to the commercial presence
through which the service is supplied or
sought to be supplied and need not be
extended to any other parts of the service
supplier located outside the Area of a
Party where the service is supplied or
sought to be supplied. 


(s) the term “SPS Agreement” means the Agreement on
the Application of Sanitary and Phytosanitary
Measures in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 



(t) the term “state enterprise” means a juridical
person owned or controlled by a Party; 



(u) the term “TRIPS Agreement” means the Agreement on
Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property
Rights in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement; 



(v) 	the term “UNCLOS” means the United Nations 
Convention on the Law of the Sea, done at Montego
Bay, December 10, 1982; and 



(w) the term “WTO Agreement” means the Marrakesh
Agreement Establishing the World Trade
Organization, done at Marrakesh, April 15, 1994.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.3" name="Transparency" article_identifier="36722">1. Each Party shall promptly publish, or otherwise make 
publicly available, its laws, regulations and judicial
decisions of general application as well as international
agreements to which the Party is a party, with respect to
any matter covered by this Agreement. 



2. Each Party shall make easily available to the public
the names and addresses of the competent authorities
responsible for the laws and regulations referred to in
paragraph 1. 



3. Each Party shall, upon request of the other Party,
within a reasonable period of time, respond to specific
questions from, and provide information to, the other Party
with respect to matters referred to in paragraph 1, in the
English language to the extent possible. 



4. When introducing or changing its laws or regulations
that significantly affect the implementation and operation
of this Agreement, each Party shall endeavor to provide,
except in emergency situations and to the extent covered by
its domestic laws, a reasonable interval between the time
when such laws or regulations are published or made
publicly available and the time when they enter into force.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.4" name="Public Comment Procedures" article_identifier="36723">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations and to the extent practicable, maintain public
comment procedures with respect to any matter covered by
this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.5" name="Administrative Procedures" article_identifier="36724">1. Upon receiving an application submitted by a person
who seeks an administrative decision which pertains to or
affects the implementation and operation of this Agreement,
the competent authorities of a Party shall, in accordance
with the laws and regulations of the Party: 



(a) inform the applicant of the decision within a
reasonable period of time after the submission of
the application considered complete in accordance
with the laws and regulations of the Party,
taking into account the established standard
period of time referred to in paragraph 3; and 



(b) provide, within a reasonable period of time,
information concerning the status of the
application, upon request of the applicant. 

2. The competent authorities of a Party shall, in
accordance with the laws and regulations of the Party,
establish criteria for reviewing the application referred
to in paragraph 1. The competent authorities shall make
such criteria: 



(a) as specific as possible; and 



(b) publicly available except when it would
extraordinarily raise administrative difficulties
for the Party. 

3. For the purposes of reviewing the applications
referred to in paragraph 1, the competent authorities of a
Party shall, in accordance with the laws and regulations of
the Party: 



(a) endeavor to establish standard periods of time
between the receipt of the applications and the
administrative decisions taken in response to the
applications; and 



(b) make publicly available such periods of time, if
established. 

4. The competent authorities of a Party shall endeavor
to, in accordance with the laws and regulations of the
Party, prior to any final decision which imposes
obligations on or restricts legal rights of a person,
provide that person with: 



(a) a reasonable notice, including a description of
the nature of the measure, specific provisions
upon which such measure will be based, and the
facts which may be a cause of taking such
measure; and 



(b) a reasonable opportunity to present facts and
arguments in support of position of such person, 

provided that time, nature of the measure and public
interest permit.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.6" name="Review And Appeal" article_identifier="36725">1. Each Party shall maintain courts or procedures for the 
purpose of prompt review and, where warranted, correction
of administrative actions regarding matters covered by this
Agreement. Such courts or procedures shall be impartial and
independent of the authorities entrusted with the
administrative enforcement of such actions. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that the parties in any such
courts or procedures are provided with the right to: 



(a) a reasonable opportunity to support or defend
their respective positions; and 



(b) 	a decision based on the evidence and submissions 
of record. 


3. Each Party shall ensure, subject to appeal or further
review as provided in its laws and regulations, that such
decision is implemented by the relevant authorities with
respect to the administrative action at issue.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.7" name="Measures Against Corruption" article_identifier="36726">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take appropriate measures to prevent and
combat corruption of its public officials regarding matters
covered by this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.8" name="Confidential Information" article_identifier="36727">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, maintain the confidentiality of information
provided in confidence by the other Party in accordance
with this Agreement. 



2. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement,
nothing in this Agreement shall require a Party to provide
confidential information, the disclosure of which would
impede the enforcement of its laws and regulations, or
otherwise be contrary to the public interest, or which
would prejudice legitimate commercial interests of
particular enterprises, public or private.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.9" name="Taxation" article_identifier="36728">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, the
provisions of this Agreement shall not apply to any
taxation measures. 



2. Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rights and
obligations of either Party under any tax convention. In
the event of any inconsistency between this Agreement and
any such convention, that convention shall prevail to the
extent of the inconsistency. 



3. Articles 1.3 and 1.8 shall apply to taxation measures,
to the extent that the provisions of this Agreement are
applicable to such taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.10" name="Exceptions" article_identifier="36729">1. For the purposes of this Agreement except Chapters 7,
8 and 12, Articles XX and XXI of the GATT 1994 are
incorporated into and form part of this Agreement, PXWDWLV 
PXWDQGLV. 



2. For the purposes of Chapters 7, 8, 9 and 10, Articles
XIV and XIV ELV of the GATS are incorporated into and form
part of this Agreement, PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV. 



3. The Parties may consult with each other on issues
related to the situation where: 



(a) the export earnings of a Party the economy of
which depend on exports of a small number of
primary commodities may be seriously reduced by a
decline in the sales or the world prices of such
commodities; or 



(b) promoting the establishment of a particular
industry of a Party may be required with a view
to raising the general standard of living of its
people. 

Note: For the purposes of this Article, it is understood 
that subparagraph (b) of Article XX of the GATT 1994
and subparagraph (b) of Article XIV of the GATS
include environmental measures necessary to protect
human, animal or plant life or health, and that
subparagraph (g) of Article XX of the GATT 1994
applies to measures related to the conservation of
living and non-living exhaustible natural resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.11" name="Relation To Other Agreements" article_identifier="36730">1. The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
under the WTO Agreement or any other agreements to which
both Parties are party. 



2. In the event of any inconsistency between this
Agreement and the WTO Agreement, the WTO Agreement shall
prevail to the extent of the inconsistency. 



3. In the event of any inconsistency between this
Agreement and any agreement other than the WTO Agreement to
which both Parties are party, the Parties shall immediately
consult with each other with a view to finding a mutually
satisfactory solution, taking into consideration general
principles of international law.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.12" name="Implementing Agreement" article_identifier="36731">The Governments of the Parties shall conclude a 
separate agreement setting forth the details and procedures
for the implementation of this Agreement, which thereby
shall be complementary to this Agreement (hereinafter
referred to as “Implementing Agreement”).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.13" name="Joint Committee" article_identifier="36732">1. The Parties hereby establish a Joint Committee under
this Agreement. 



2. The functions of the Joint Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Agreement and, when necessary,
making appropriate recommendations to the
Parties; 



(b) considering and recommending to the Parties any
amendments to this Agreement; 



(c) supervising and coordinating the work of all Sub-
Committees established under this Agreement; 



(d) adopting: 


(i) the Operational Procedures for Trade in
Goods and the Operational Procedures for
Rules of Origin referred to in Article 2.20 
and Article 3.26, respectively; and 


(ii) any necessary decisions; and 


(e) carrying out other functions as the Parties may
agree. 


3. 	The Joint Committee: 



(a) shall be composed of representatives of the
Governments of the Parties; 



(b) 	may establish other Sub-Committees than those 
provided for in Article 1.14; and 



(c) may delegate its responsibilities to Sub-
Committees. 


4. The Joint Committee shall establish its rules and 
procedures. 



5. The Joint Committee shall hold the first meeting on
the date of entry into force of this Agreement, and
thereafter, meet at such times and venues or by means, as
may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.14" name="Sub-Committees" article_identifier="36733">1. The following Sub-Committees shall be established on
the date of entry into force of this Agreement: 



(a) 	Sub-Committee on Trade in Goods, as provided for 
in Article 2.19; 



(b) 	Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin, as provided for 
in Article 3.25; 



(c) 	Sub-Committee on Customs Procedures and Trade 
Facilitation, as provided for in Article 4.8; 



(d) 	Sub-Committee on Sanitary and Phytosanitary 
Measures, as provided for in Article 5.6; 



(e) 	Sub-Committee on Technical Regulations, Standards 
and Conformity Assessment Procedures, as provided
for in Article 6.9; 



(f) 	Sub-Committee on Trade in Services, as provided 
for in Article 7.16; 



(g) 	Sub-Committee on Movement of Natural Persons, as 
provided for in Article 8.6; 



(h) 	Sub-Committee on Electronic Commerce, as provided 
for in Article 9.13; 



(i) 	Sub-Committee on Investment, as provided for in 
Article 10.18; 



(j) 	Sub-Committee on Intellectual Property, as 
provided for in Article 12.18; 



(k) 	Sub-Committee on Government Procurement, as 
provided for in Article 13.5; 



(l) 	Sub-Committee on Improvement of the Business 
Environment, as provided for in Article 14.2; and 



(m) 	Sub-Committee on Cooperation, as provided for in 
Article 15.4. 

2. The Sub-Committees shall carry out the functions
specified in the corresponding Articles referred to in
paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 1.15" name="Communications" article_identifier="36734">Each Party shall designate a contact point to
facilitate communications between the Parties on any matter
related to this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 2" name="Trade In Goods" chapter_identifier="4243">
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.1" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36735">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “Agreement on Agriculture” means the
Agreement on Agriculture in Annex 1A to the WTO
Agreement; 



(b) the term “Agreement on Anti-Dumping” means the
Agreement on Implementation of Article VI of the
General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade 1994 in
Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement; 



(c) the term “Agreement on Safeguards” means the
Agreement on Safeguards in Annex 1A to the WTO
Agreement; 



(d) the term “Agreement on Subsidies and
Countervailing Measures” means the Agreement on
Subsidies and Countervailing Measures in Annex 1A
to the WTO Agreement; 



(e) the term “bilateral safeguard measure” means a
bilateral safeguard measure provided for in
paragraph 2 of Article 2.8; 



(f) the term “customs duty” means any customs or
import duty imposed in connection with the
importation of a good, but does not include any: 


(i) charge equivalent to an internal tax imposed
consistently with the provisions of
paragraph 2 of Article II and paragraph 2 of
Article III of the GATT 1994; 


(ii) 	anti-dumping or countervailing duty applied 
pursuant to a Party’s law and applied
consistently with the provisions of Article
VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on Anti-
Dumping and the Agreement on Subsidies and
Countervailing Measures; or 


(iii) fees or other charges commensurate with the
cost of services rendered; 


(g) the term “customs value of goods” means the value
of goods for the purposes of levying DGYDORUHP 
customs duties on imported goods; 



(h) the term “domestic industry” means the producers
as a whole of the like or directly competitive
goods operating in a Party, or those whose
collective output of the like or directly
competitive goods constitutes a major proportion
of the total domestic production of those goods; 



(i) the term “provisional bilateral safeguard
measure” means a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure provided for in paragraph 1 of Article
2.13; 



(j) the term “serious injury” means a significant
overall impairment in the position of a domestic
industry; and 



(k) the term “threat of serious injury” means serious
injury that, on the basis of facts and not merely
on allegation, conjecture or remote possibility,
is clearly imminent.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.2" name="Classification Of Goods" article_identifier="36736">The classification of goods in trade between the
Parties shall be in conformity with the Harmonized System.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.3" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="36737">Each Party shall accord national treatment to the
goods of the other Party in accordance with Article III of
the GATT 1994, and to this end Article III of the GATT 1994
is incorporated into and forms part of this Agreement,
PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.4" name="Elimination Or Reduction Of Customs Duties" article_identifier="36738">1. Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, each 
Party shall eliminate or reduce its customs duties on
originating goods of the other Party in accordance with its
Schedule in Annex 1. 



2. Upon request of either Party, the Parties shall
negotiate on issues such as improving market access for 
originating goods designated for negotiation in the
Schedules in Annex 1, in accordance with the terms and
conditions set out in such Schedules. 



3. In accordance with subparagraph 1(b) of Article II of
the GATT 1994, the goods traded between the Parties shall
be exempt from other duties or charges of any kind imposed
on or in connection with the importation. 



4. Nothing in this Article shall prevent a Party from
imposing, at any time, a charge equivalent to an internal
tax, any anti-dumping or countervailing duty, or fees or
other charges referred to in subparagraphs (f)(i) through

(iii) of Article 2.1, respectively, on the importation of
any good of the other Party. 



5. If, as a result of the elimination or reduction of its
customs duty on a particular good on a most-favored-nation
basis, the most-favored-nation applied rate for the good
becomes equal to, or lower than, the rate of customs duty
to be applied in accordance with paragraph 1 on the
originating good which is classified under the same tariff
line as that particular good, each Party shall notify the
other Party of such elimination or reduction without delay. 



6. In cases where its most-favored-nation applied rate of
customs duty on a particular good becomes lower than the
rate of customs duty to be applied in accordance with
paragraph 1 on the originating good which is classified
under the same tariff line as that particular good, each
Party shall apply the lower rate with respect to that
originating good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.5" name="Customs Valuation" article_identifier="36739">For the purposes of determining the customs value of
goods traded between the Parties, the provisions of Part I
of the Agreement on Customs Valuation shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.6" name="Export Subsidies" article_identifier="36740">Neither Party shall introduce or maintain any export
subsidies, which are inconsistent with its obligations
under the WTO Agreement, on any agricultural good, which is
listed in Annex 1 to the Agreement on Agriculture.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.7" name="Import And Export Restrictions" article_identifier="36741">1. Neither Party shall introduce or maintain any
prohibition or restriction other than customs duties on the
importation of any good of the other Party or on the
exportation or sale for export of any good destined to the
other Party, which is inconsistent with its obligations
under the relevant provisions of the WTO Agreement. 



2. In the case that a Party introduces a prohibition or
restriction other than customs duties taken consistently
with the provisions of the WTO Agreement with respect to
the importation from, or the exportation to, the other
Party of a good upon which the Parties agree, the former
Party shall make available, and endeavor to notify,
relevant information to the other Party, prior to the
introduction of such prohibition or restriction, or as soon
as possible thereafter, in a manner consistent with the
laws and regulations of the former Party. This paragraph
shall apply unless the sharing of such information is
considered by the former Party as prejudicial to public
interest. 

Note: A Party may comply with this paragraph by 
providing the relevant information to the other
Party through the relevant procedures under the
WTO Agreement.
Safeguard Measures</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.8" name="Application Of Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="36742">1. Subject to the provisions of this Section, a Party may 
apply a bilateral safeguard measure, to the minimum extent
necessary to prevent or remedy the serious injury to its
domestic industry and to facilitate adjustment thereof, if
an originating good of the other Party, as a result of the
elimination or reduction of a customs duty in accordance
with Article 2.4, is being imported into the former Party
in such increased quantities, in absolute terms or relative
to domestic production, and under such conditions that the
imports of that originating good constitute cause of 
serious injury, or threat of serious injury, to a domestic
industry of the former Party. 



2. A Party may, as a bilateral safeguard measure: 



(a) suspend the further reduction of any rate of
customs duty on the originating good provided for
in this Chapter; or 



(b) increase the rate of customs duty on the
originating good to a level not to exceed the
lesser of: 

(i) the most-favored-nation applied rate of
customs duty in effect on the day when the
bilateral safeguard measure is applied; and 


(ii) the most-favored-nation applied rate of
customs duty in effect on the day
immediately preceding the date of entry into
force of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.9" name="Conditions And Limitations" article_identifier="36743">1. No bilateral safeguard measure shall be maintained
except to the extent and for such period of time as may be
necessary to prevent or remedy serious injury and to
facilitate adjustment, provided that such period of time
shall not exceed a period of three years. However, in
highly exceptional circumstances, a bilateral safeguard
measure may be extended, provided that the total duration
of the bilateral safeguard measure, including such
extensions, shall not exceed six years. In order to
facilitate adjustment in a situation where the expected
duration of a bilateral safeguard measure is over one year,
the Party maintaining the bilateral safeguard measure shall
progressively liberalize the bilateral safeguard measure at
regular intervals during the period of application. 



2. No bilateral safeguard measure shall be applied again 
to the import of a particular originating good which has
been subject to such a bilateral safeguard measure, for a
period of time equal to the duration of the previous
bilateral safeguard measure or one year, whichever is
longer. 



3. Upon the termination of a bilateral safeguard measure,
the rate of customs duty for the originating good subject
to the measure shall be the rate which would have been in 
effect if the bilateral safeguard measure had never been
applied. 



4. A bilateral safeguard measure shall not be applied
against an originating good of the exporting Party as long
as its share of imports of the good concerned in the
importing Party does not exceed three percent. 



5. Each Party shall adopt or maintain equitable, timely,
transparent and effective procedures relating to bilateral
safeguard measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.10" name="Investigation" article_identifier="36744">1. A Party may apply a bilateral safeguard measure only
after an investigation has been carried out by the
competent authorities of that Party in accordance with the
same procedures as those provided for in Article 3 and
paragraph 2 of Article 4 of the Agreement on Safeguards. 



2. The investigation referred to in paragraph 1 shall,
except in special circumstances, be completed within one 
year, and in no case more than 18 months, following its
date of initiation.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.11" name="Notification And Consultations" article_identifier="36745">1. A Party shall immediately make a written notice to the
other Party upon: 



(a) initiating an investigation referred to in
paragraph 1 of Article 2.10 related to serious
injury, or threat of serious injury, and the
reasons therefor; and 



(b) taking a decision to apply or extend a bilateral
safeguard measure. 

2. The Party making the written notice referred to in
paragraph 1 shall provide the other Party with all
pertinent information, which shall include: 



(a) in the written notice referred to in subparagraph
1(a), the reason for the initiation of the
investigation, a precise description of the
originating good subject to the investigation and
its subheading under the Harmonized System, the
period subject to the investigation and the date
of initiation of the investigation; and 



(b) in the written notice referred to in subparagraph
1(b), evidence of serious injury or threat of
serious injury caused by the increased imports of
the originating good, a precise description of
the originating good subject to the proposed
bilateral safeguard measure and its subheading
under the Harmonized System, a precise
description of the proposed bilateral safeguard
measure, and the proposed date of the
introduction and expected duration of the
bilateral safeguard measure. 

3. A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral
safeguard measure shall provide adequate opportunity for
prior consultations with the other Party with a view to
reviewing the information arising from the investigation
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 2.10, exchanging
views on the bilateral safeguard measure and reaching an
agreement on compensation set out in Article 2.12.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.12" name="Compensation" article_identifier="36746">1. A Party proposing to apply or extend a bilateral
safeguard measure may agree on adequate means of trade
compensation in the form of concessions of customs duties
whose value is substantially equivalent to that of the
additional customs duties expected to result from the
bilateral safeguard measure. 



2. If the Parties are unable to agree on the compensation
within 30 days after the commencement of the consultations
in accordance with paragraph 3 of Article 2.11, the Party
to whose originating good the bilateral safeguard measure
is applied shall be free to suspend the application of
concessions of customs duties under this Agreement, which
are substantially equivalent to the bilateral safeguard
measure. The Party exercising the right of suspension may
suspend the application of concessions of customs duties
only for the minimum period necessary to achieve the
substantially equivalent effects and only while the
bilateral safeguard measure is maintained.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.13" name="Provisional Bilateral Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="36747">1. In critical circumstances, where delay would cause
damage which it would be difficult to repair, a Party may
apply a provisional bilateral safeguard measure, which
shall take the form of the measure set out in subparagraph
2(a) or 2(b) of Article 2.8, pursuant to a preliminary
determination that there is clear evidence that increased 
imports of an originating good of the other Party have
caused or are threatening to cause serious injury to a
domestic industry of the former Party. 



2. A Party shall make a written notice to the other Party
prior to applying a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure. Consultations between the Parties on the 
application of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure
shall be initiated immediately after the provisional
bilateral safeguard measure is applied. 



3. The duration of a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure shall not exceed 200 days. During that period, the
pertinent requirements of Article 2.10 shall be met. The
duration of the provisional bilateral safeguard measure
shall be counted as a part of the period referred to in
paragraph 1 of Article 2.9. 



4. Paragraphs 3 through 5 of Article 2.9 shall apply,
PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV, to a provisional bilateral safeguard
measure. The customs duty imposed as a result of the
provisional bilateral safeguard measure shall be refunded
if the subsequent investigation referred to in paragraph 1
of Article 2.10 does not determine that increased imports
of an originating good of the other Party have caused or
threatened to cause serious injury to a domestic industry.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.14" name="Relation To Safeguard Measures Under The Wto Agreement" article_identifier="36748">1. Nothing in this Section shall prevent a Party from
applying a safeguard measure to an originating good of the
other Party in accordance with: 



(a) Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
Safeguards; or 



(b) Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture. 


2. A Party applying a safeguard measure to the
importation of an originating good of the other Party in
accordance with Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the 
Agreement on Safeguards, or Article 5 of the Agreement on
Agriculture, shall not apply at the same time a bilateral
safeguard measure under this Section to that importation. 



3. In the case that a Party has applied a bilateral
safeguard measure under this Section to the importation of
an originating good of the other Party prior to the
application of a safeguard measure in accordance with
Article XIX of the GATT 1994 and the Agreement on
Safeguards, or Article 5 of the Agreement on Agriculture,
the duration of the latter safeguard measure shall be
counted as a part of the total duration of the bilateral
safeguard measure. The Party may resume the application of
the bilateral safeguard measure to that importation upon
the termination of the latter safeguard measure up to the
remaining period of the bilateral safeguard measure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.15" name="Communications" article_identifier="36749">A written notice referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 


2.11 and paragraph 2 of Article 2.13 and any other
communication between the Parties in accordance with this 
Section shall be made in the English language.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.16" name="Review" article_identifier="36750">The Parties shall review the provisions of this
Section, if necessary, 10 years after the date of entry
into force of this Agreement.
Other Provisions</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.17" name="Anti-Dumping And Countervailing Measures" article_identifier="36751">Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent
a Party from taking any measure in accordance with the
provisions of Article VI of the GATT 1994, the Agreement on
Anti-Dumping and the Agreement on Subsidies and
Countervailing Measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.18" name="Measures To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="36752">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall be construed to prevent
a Party from taking any measure for balance-of-payments
purposes. A Party taking such measure shall do so in
accordance with the conditions established under Article 
XII of the GATT 1994 and the Understanding on the Balance-
of-Payments Provisions of the General Agreement on Tariffs
and Trade 1994 in Annex 1A to the WTO Agreement. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall preclude the use by a
Party of exchange controls or exchange restrictions in
accordance with the Articles of Agreement of the
International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.19" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Goods" article_identifier="36753">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Trade in Goods (hereinafter referred to in
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) considering any other matter related to this
Chapter as the Parties may agree; 



(c) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,
as necessary, to the Joint Committee on the
Operational Procedures for Trade in Goods
referred to in Article 2.20; 



(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.20" name="Operational Procedures For Trade In Goods" article_identifier="36754">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement,
the Joint Committee shall adopt the Operational Procedures
for Trade in Goods that provide detailed regulations
pursuant to which the relevant authorities of the Parties
shall implement their functions under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 2.21" name="Cooperation With Respect To Exports" article_identifier="36755">The Parties shall, in accordance with the provisions
of Chapter 15, cooperate with each other in the field of
used four-wheeled motor vehicles exported from the
exporting Party.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 3" name="Rules Of Origin" chapter_identifier="4244">
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.1" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36756">For the purposes of this Chapter:


 

(a) the term “competent governmental authority” means
the authority that, according to the legislation
of each Party, is responsible for the issuing of
a Certificate of Origin or for the designation of
certification entities or bodies;


 


(b) the term “exporter” means a person located in an
exporting Party who exports a good from the
exporting Party; 



(c) the term “factory ships of the Party” or “vessels
of the Party” respectively means factory ships or
vessels: 

 

(i) which are registered in the Party; 


(ii) which sail under the flag of the Party; and 


(iii) which meet one of the following conditions:


 


(A) they are at least 50 percent owned by
nationals of the Parties; or 



(B) they are owned by a juridical person
which has its head office and its 
principal place of business in either
Party and which does not own any vessel
or ship registered in a non-Party;

 


(d) the term “fungible originating goods of a Party”
or “fungible originating materials of a Party”
respectively means originating goods or materials
of a Party that are interchangeable for
commercial purposes, whose properties are
essentially identical; 



(e) the term “Generally Accepted Accounting
Principles” means the recognized consensus or
substantial authoritative support within a Party
at a particular time as to which economic
resources and obligations should be recorded as
assets and liabilities, which changes in assets
and liabilities should be recorded, how the
assets and liabilities and changes in them should
be measured, what information should be disclosed
and how it should be disclosed, and which
financial statements should be prepared. These
standards may be broad guidelines of general
application as well as detailed practices and
procedures; 



(f) the term “importer” means a person who imports a
good into the importing Party; 



(g) the term “indirect materials” means goods used in
the production, testing or inspection of another
good but not physically incorporated into the
good, or goods used in the maintenance of
buildings or the operation of equipment
associated with the production of another good,
including: 


(i) fuel and energy; 


(ii) tools, dies and molds; 


(iii) spare parts and goods used in the
maintenance of equipment and buildings; 



(iv) lubricants, greases, compounding materials
and other goods used in production or used
to operate equipment and buildings; 


(v) gloves, glasses, footwear, clothing, safety
equipment and supplies; 


(vi) equipment, devices and supplies used for
testing or inspecting the good; 

(vii) catalysts and solvents; and 


(viii) any other goods that are not incorporated
into another good but whose use in the
production of the good can reasonably be
demonstrated to be a part of that
production; 


(h) the term “material” means a good that is used in
the production of another good; 



(i) the term “non-originating material” means a
material which does not qualify as originating
under this Chapter; 



(j) 	the term “originating material” means a material 
which qualifies as originating under this
Chapter; 



(k) the term “packing materials and containers for
transportation and shipment” means goods that are
used to protect a good during transportation,
other than packaging materials and containers for
retail sale referred to in Article 3.13; 



(l) the term “preferential tariff treatment” means
the rate of customs duties applicable to an
originating good of the exporting Party in
accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 2.4; 



(m) the term “producer” means a person who engages in
the production of goods or materials; and 



(n) the term “production” means a method of obtaining
goods including manufacturing, assembling,
processing, raising, growing, breeding, mining,
extracting, harvesting, fishing, trapping,
gathering, collecting, hunting and capturing.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.2" name="Originating Goods" article_identifier="36757">Unless otherwise provided for in this Chapter, a good
shall qualify as an originating good of a Party where: 



(a) the good is wholly obtained or produced entirely
in the Party, as defined in Article 3.3; 



(b) the good is produced entirely in the Party
exclusively from originating materials of the
Party; or 



(c) the good satisfies the product specific rules
(change in tariff classification, qualifying
value content or specific manufacturing or
processing operation) set out in Annex 2, as
well as all other applicable requirements of
this Chapter, when the good is produced entirely
in the Party using non-originating materials.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.3" name="Wholly Obtained Goods" article_identifier="36758">For the purposes of subparagraph (a) of Article 3.2,
the following goods shall be considered as being wholly
obtained or produced entirely in a Party: 



(a) live animals born and raised in the Party; 



(b) animals obtained by hunting, trapping, fishing,
gathering or capturing in the Party; 



(c) goods obtained from live animals in the Party; 



(d) plants and plant products harvested, picked or
gathered in the Party; 



(e) minerals and other naturally occurring
substances, not included in subparagraphs (a)
through (d), extracted or taken in the Party; 



(f) goods of sea-fishing and other goods taken by
vessels of the Party from the sea outside the
territorial seas of the Parties; 



(g) goods produced on board factory ships of the
Party outside the territorial seas of the Parties
from the goods referred to in subparagraph (f); 



(h) goods taken from the seabed or subsoil thereof
outside the territorial sea of the Party,
provided that the Party has rights to exploit
such seabed or subsoil in accordance with the 
provisions of the UNCLOS; 



(i) articles collected in the Party which can no
longer perform their original purpose in the
Party nor are capable of being restored or
repaired and which are fit only for disposal or
for the recovery of parts or raw materials; 



(j) scrap and waste derived from manufacturing or
processing operations or from consumption in the
Party and fit only for disposal or for the
recovery of raw materials; 



(k) parts or raw materials recovered in the Party
from articles which can no longer perform their
original purpose nor are capable of being
restored or repaired; and 



(l) goods obtained or produced in the Party
exclusively from the goods referred to in
subparagraphs (a) through (k).</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.4" name="Qualifying Value Content" article_identifier="36759">1. For the purposes of subparagraph (c) of Article 3.2,
the qualifying value content of a good shall be calculated
on the basis of one or the other of the following methods: 


(a) Method based on value of non-originating
materials (“Build-down method”) 


F.O.B. – V.N.M. 


Q.V.C. = ----------------------------- x 100 


F.O.B. 


 

(b) Method based on value of originating materials


(“Build-up method”) 
 


V.O.M. + Direct Labor Cost 


+ Direct Overhead Cost + Profit 


Q.V.C. = -------------------------------- x 100 


F.O.B. 


 

Where: 


Q.V.C. is the qualifying value content of a good, expressed
as a percentage; 


F.O.B. is, except as provided for in paragraph 2, the free-
on-board value of the good payable by the buyer of the good
to the seller of the good, regardless of the mode of
shipment, not including any internal excise taxes reduced,
exempted or repaid when the good is exported; 


V.N.M. is the value of non-originating materials used in
the production of the good; and 


V.O.M. is the value of originating materials used in the
production of the good. 


Note: For the purposes of calculating the qualifying 
value content of a good, the Generally Accepted
Accounting Principles in the exporting Party
shall apply. 


2. 	F.O.B. referred to in paragraph 1 shall be the value: 



(a) adjusted to the first ascertainable price paid
for a good from the buyer to the producer of the
good, if there is free-on-board value of the
good, but it is unknown and cannot be
ascertained; or 



(b) determined in accordance with Articles 1 through
8 of the Agreement on Customs Valuation, if there
is no free-on-board value of a good. 

3. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value
content of a good in accordance with paragraph 1, the value
of material used in the production of the good in a Party: 



(a) 	shall be determined in accordance with the 
Agreement on Customs Valuation, and shall include
freight, insurance where appropriate, packing and
all the other costs incurred in transporting the
material to the importation port in the Party
where the producer of the good is located; or 



(b) 	if such value is unknown and cannot be 
ascertained, shall be the first ascertainable
price paid for the material in the Party, but may
exclude all the costs incurred in the Party in
transporting the material from the warehouse of
the supplier of the material to the place where
the producer is located such as freight,
insurance and packing as well as any other known
and ascertainable cost incurred in the Party. 

4. For the purposes of calculating the qualifying value
content of a good to determine whether the good qualifies
as an originating good of a Party: 



(a) V.N.M. of the good under subparagraph 1(a) shall
not include the value of non-originating
materials used in the production of originating
materials of the Party which are used in the
production of the good; and 



(b) V.O.M. of the good under subparagraph 1(b) shall
include the value of non-originating materials
used in the production of originating materials
of the Party which are used in the production of
the good. 

5. For the purposes of subparagraph 2(b) or 3(a), in
applying the Agreement on Customs Valuation to determine
the value of a good or a material, the Agreement on Customs
Valuation shall apply PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV to domestic 
transactions or to the cases where there is no transaction 
of the good or the material.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.5" name="Accumulation" article_identifier="36760">For the purposes of determining whether a good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party: 



(a) an originating good of the other Party which is
used as a material in the production of the good
in the former Party may be considered as an
originating material of the former Party; 



(b) the production in the other Party may be
considered as that in the former Party; and 



(c) the production carried out at different stages by
one or more producers within the Party or in the
other Party may be taken into account, when the
good is produced using non-originating materials, 

provided that such good has undergone its last production
process in the exporting Party and such production process
goes beyond the operations provided for in Article 3.7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.6" name="De Minimis" article_identifier="36761">1. For the application of the product specific rules set
out in Annex 2, non-originating materials used in the
production of a good that do not satisfy an applicable rule
for the good shall be disregarded, provided that the
totality of such materials does not exceed specific
percentage in value, weight or volume of the good and such
percentage is set out in the applicable product specific
rule for the good. 



2. Paragraph 1 shall not apply to a non-originating
material used in the production of a good provided for in
Chapters 1 through 24 of the Harmonized System, except
where such non-originating material is provided for in a
subheading which is different from that of the good for
which the origin is being determined under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.7" name="Non-Qualifying Operations" article_identifier="36762">1. A good shall not be considered as an originating good
of a Party merely by reason of: 



(a) operations to ensure the preservation of products
in good condition during transport and storage
(such as drying, freezing, keeping in brine) and
other similar operations; 



(b) changes of packaging and breaking-up and assembly
of packages; 



(c) disassembly; 



(d) placing in bottles, cases, boxes and other simple
packaging operations; 



(e) collection of parts and components classified as
a good in accordance with Rule 2(a) of the
General Rules for the Interpretation of the
Harmonized System; 



(f) mere making-up of sets of articles; or 



(g) any combination of operations referred to in
subparagraphs (a) through (f). 

2. Paragraph 1 shall prevail over the product specific
rules set out in Annex 2.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.8" name="Consignment Criteria" article_identifier="36763">1. An originating good of the other Party shall be deemed
to meet the consignment criteria when it is transported: 



(a) directly from the other Party; or 



(b) through one or more non-Parties for the purpose
of transit or temporary storage in warehouses in
such non-Parties, provided that it does not
undergo operations other than unloading,
reloading and any other operation to preserve it
in good condition. 

2. If an originating good of the other Party does not
meet the consignment criteria referred to in paragraph 1,
the good shall not be considered as an originating good of
the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.9" name="Unassembled Or Disassembled Goods" article_identifier="36764">1. Where a good satisfies the requirements of the
relevant provisions of Articles 3.2 through 3.7 and is
imported into a Party from the other Party in an
unassembled or disassembled form but is classified as an 
assembled good in accordance with Rule 2(a) of the General
Rules for the Interpretation of the Harmonized System, such
a good shall be considered as an originating good of the
other Party. 



2. A good assembled in a Party from unassembled or
disassembled materials, which were imported into the Party
and classified as an assembled good in accordance with Rule
2(a) of the General Rules for the Interpretation of the
Harmonized System, shall be considered as an originating
good of the Party, provided that the good would have
satisfied the applicable requirements of the relevant
provisions of Articles 3.2 through 3.7 if each of the non-
originating materials among the unassembled or disassembled
materials had been imported into the Party separately and
not as an unassembled or disassembled form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.10" name="Fungible Goods And Materials" article_identifier="36765">1. For the purposes of determining whether a good
qualifies as an originating good of a Party, where fungible
originating materials of the Party and fungible non-
originating materials that are commingled in an inventory
are used in the production of the good, the origin of the
materials may be determined in accordance with an inventory
management method under the Generally Accepted Accounting
Principles in the Party. 



2. Where fungible originating goods of a Party and
fungible non-originating goods are commingled in an
inventory and, prior to exportation, do not undergo any
production process or any operation in the Party where they
were commingled other than unloading, reloading and any
other operation to preserve them in good condition, the
origin of the good may be determined in accordance with an
inventory management method under the Generally Accepted
Accounting Principles in the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.11" name="Indirect Materials" article_identifier="36766">Indirect materials shall be, without regard to where
they are produced, considered as originating materials of a
Party where the good is produced.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.12" name="Accessories, Spare Parts And Tools" article_identifier="36767">1. In determining whether all the non-originating
materials used in the production of a good undergo the
applicable change in tariff classification or a specific
manufacturing or processing operation set out in Annex 2,
accessories, spare parts or tools delivered with the good
that form part of the good’s standard accessories, spare
parts or tools, shall be disregarded, provided that: 



(a) the accessories, spare parts or tools are not 
invoiced separately from the good, without regard
to whether they are separately described in the
invoice; and 



(b) the quantities and value of the accessories, 
spare parts or tools are customary for the good.

 

2. If a good is subject to a qualifying value content
requirement, the value of the accessories, spare parts or
tools shall be taken into account as the value of 
originating materials of a Party where the good is produced
or non-originating materials, as the case may be, in
calculating the qualifying value content of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.13" name="Packaging Materials And Containers For Retail Sale" article_identifier="36768">1㸬 Packaging materials and containers for retail sale,which are classified with the good in accordance with Rule5 of the General Rules for the Interpretation of theHarmonized System, shall be disregarded in determining theorigin of the good, provided that:

 


(a) the good is wholly obtained or entirely produced 
as defined in subparagraph (a) of Article 3.2; 



(b) the good is produced exclusively from originating
materials, as defined in subparagraph (b) of
Article 3.2; or 



(c) the good has undergone the applicable change in
tariff classification or a specific manufacturing
or processing operation set out in Annex 2. 

2. If a good is subject to a qualifying value content
requirement, the value of packaging materials and
containers for retail sale shall be taken into account as 
the value of originating materials of a Party where the
good is produced or non-originating materials, as the case
may be, in calculating the qualifying value content of the
good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.14" name="Packing Materials And Containers For Transportation And Shipment" article_identifier="36769">Packing materials and containers for transportation
and shipment of a good shall not be taken into account in
determining the origin of the good.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.15" name="Claim For Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="36770">1. The importing Party shall grant preferential tariff
treatment in accordance with this Agreement to an
originating good of the exporting Party on the basis of a
Certificate of Origin.



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1: 

 

(a) the importing Party shall not require a
Certificate of Origin from the importer for an
importation of an originating good of the
exporting Party whose aggregate customs value
does not exceed 1,500 United States dollars or
its equivalent amount in the importing Party’s
currency, or such higher amount as may be
established by the importing Party, provided that
the importation does not form part of
importations that may reasonably be considered to
have been made separately for the purpose of
avoiding the requirement for a Certificate of
Origin; and


 

(b) the importing Party may waive the requirement for
a Certificate of Origin in accordance with its
laws and regulations.


 


3. The importing Party may require, where appropriate,
the importer to submit other evidence that the good
qualifies as an originating good of the exporting Party. 



4. Where an originating good of the exporting Party is
imported through one or more non-Parties, the importing
Party may require the importer who claims preferential
tariff treatment for that good to submit: 



(a) a copy of the through bill of lading; or 



(b) a certificate or any other information given by
the customs authorities of such non-Parties or 
other relevant entities, which evidences that the
good has not undergone operations other than
unloading, reloading and any other operation to
preserve it in good condition in those non-
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.16" name="Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="36771">1. A Certificate of Origin referred to in paragraph 1 of
Article 3.15 shall be issued by the competent governmental
authority of the exporting Party upon request having been
made by the exporter or its authorized agent. Such
Certificate of Origin shall include minimum data specified
in Annex 3. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party may designate
other entities or bodies to be responsible for the issuance
of Certificate of Origin, under the authorization given in
accordance with the applicable laws and regulations of the
exporting Party. 



3. Where the competent governmental authority of the
exporting Party designates other entities or bodies to
carry out the issuance of Certificate of Origin, the
exporting Party shall notify in writing the other Party of
its designees.


 

4. For the purposes of this Chapter, upon the entry into
force of this Agreement, the Parties shall establish each
Party’s format of Certificate of Origin in the English
language in the Operational Procedures for Rules of Origin
referred to in Article 3.26. 



5. A Certificate of Origin shall be completed in the
English language. 



6. A Certificate of Origin shall be in a printed format
or such other medium agreed upon by the Parties. 



7. An issued Certificate of Origin shall be applicable to
a single importation of originating goods of the exporting
Party into the importing Party and be valid for 12 months
from the date of issuance. 



8. Where the exporter of a good is not the producer of
the good in the exporting Party, the exporter may request a
Certificate of Origin on the basis of: 



(a) a declaration provided by the exporter to the
competent governmental authority or its designees
based on the information provided by the producer
of the good to that exporter; or 



(b) a declaration voluntarily provided by the
producer of the good directly to the competent
governmental authority or its designees by the
request of the exporter. 


9. A Certificate of Origin shall be issued only after the
exporter who requests the Certificate of Origin, or the
producer of a good in the exporting Party referred to in
subparagraph 8(b), proves to the competent governmental
authority of the exporting Party or its designees that the
good to be exported qualifies as an originating good of the
exporting Party. 



10. The competent governmental authority of the exporting
Party shall provide the importing Party with specimen
signatures and impressions of stamps used in the offices of
the competent governmental authority or its designees. 



11. Each Partyin accordance with its laws and 
regulations, shall ensure that the competent governmental
authority or its designees shall keep a record of issued
Certificate of Origin for a period of five years after the
date on which the Certificate was issued. Such record 
includes all supporting documents presented to prove the
qualification as an originating good of the exporting
Party. 



12. The competent governmental authority of the exporting
Party shall, when it cancels the decision to issue a
Certificate of Origin, promptly notify the cancellation to
the exporter to whom the Certificate of Origin has been
issued, and to the customs authority of the importing
Party, except where the Certificate of Origin has been
returned to the competent governmental authority.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.17" name="Obligations Regarding Exportations" article_identifier="36772">Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, ensure that an exporter to whom a Certificate
of Origin has been issued, or the producer of a good in the
exporting Party referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of Article


3.16 shall: 



(a) notify in writing the competent governmental
authority of the exporting Party or its designees
without delay, when such exporter or producer
knows that the good for which the Certificate of
Origin has been issued does not qualify as an
originating good of the exporting Party; and



(b) keep the records related to the origin of the
good for five years after the date on which the
Certificate of Origin was issued.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.18" name="Request For Checking Of Certificate Of Origin" article_identifier="36773">1. In order to ensure the proper application of this
Chapter, the Parties shall assist each other to check the
information related to a Certificate of Origin, in
accordance with this Agreement and their respective laws
and regulations. 



2. For the purposes of determining whether a good
imported from the exporting Party under preferential tariff
treatment qualifies as an originating good of the exporting
Party, the customs authority of the importing Party may
request information related to the origin of the good from
the competent governmental authority of the exporting Party
on the basis of a Certificate of Origin. 



3. For the purposes of paragraph 2, the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party shall, in
accordance with the laws and regulations of the exporting
Party, provide the requested information in a period not
exceeding four months after the date of receipt of the
request. If the customs authority of the importing Party
considers necessary, it may require additional information
related to the origin of the good. If additional
information is requested by the customs authority of the
importing Party, the competent governmental authority of
the exporting Party shall, in accordance with the laws and
regulations of the exporting Party, provide the requested
information in a period not exceeding two months after the
date of receipt of the request. 



4. For the purposes of paragraph 3, the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party may request
the exporter to whom the Certificate of Origin has been
issued, or the producer of the good in the exporting Party
referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of Article 3.16, to
provide the former with the requested information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.19" name="Verification Visit" article_identifier="36774">1. If the customs authority of the importing Party is not
satisfied with the outcome of the request for checking in
accordance with Article 3.18, it may request the exporting
Party to: 



(a) collect and provide information related to the
origin of a good, and check, for that purpose,
the facilities used in the production of the
good, through a visit by the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party
along with the customs authority of the importing
Party to the premises of the exporter to whom the
Certificate of Origin has been issued, or the
producer of the good in the exporting Party
referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of Article 3.16;
and 



(b) provide information related to the origin of the
good in the possession of the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party or
its designee, during or after the visit referred
to in subparagraph (a). 


2. When requesting the exporting Party to conduct a visit
in accordance with paragraph 1, the customs authority of
the importing Party shall deliver a written communication
with such request to the exporting Party at least 40 days
in advance of the proposed date of the visit, the receipt
of which is to be confirmed by the exporting Party. The
competent governmental authority of the exporting Party
shall request the written consent of the exporter, or the
producer of the good in the exporting Party, whose premises
are to be visited. 



3. The communication referred to in paragraph 2 shall
include: 



(a) the identity of the customs authority issuing the
communication; 



(b) the name of the exporter, or the producer of the
good in the exporting Party, whose premises are
requested to be visited; 



(c) the proposed date and place of the visit; 



(d) the objective and scope of the proposed visit,
including specific reference to the good subject
of the verification referred to in the 
Certificate of Origin; and 



(e) 	the names and titles of the officials of the 
customs authority of the importing Party to be
present during the visit. 


4. The exporting Party shall respond in writing to the
importing Party, within 30 days after the receipt of the
communication referred to in paragraph 2, whether it
accepts or refuses to conduct the visit requested in
accordance with paragraph 1. 



5. The competent governmental authority of the exporting
Party shall, in accordance with the laws and regulations of
the exporting Party, provide within 45 days or any other
mutually agreed period after the last day of the visit, to
the customs authority of the importing Party the
information obtained in accordance with paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.20" name="Determination Of Origin And Preferential Tariff Treatment" article_identifier="36775">1. The customs authority of the importing Party may deny
preferential tariff treatment to a good for which an
importer claims preferential tariff treatment where the
good does not qualify as an originating good of the
exporting Party or where the importer fails to comply with
any of the relevant requirements of this Chapter. 



2. The customs authority of the importing Party may
determine that a good does not qualify as an originating
good of the exporting Party and may deny preferential
tariff treatment where it receives the notification from 
the competent governmental authority of the exporting Party
to cancel the decision to issue the Certificate of Origin
for the good in accordance with paragraph 12 of Article

3.16. 



3. The customs authority of the importing Party may
determine that a good does not qualify as an originating
good of the exporting Party and may deny preferential
tariff treatment, and a written determination thereof shall
be sent to the competent governmental authority of the
exporting Party where: 



(a) the competent governmental authority of the
exporting Party fails to provide the information
within the period referred to in paragraph 3 of
Article 3.18 or paragraph 5 of Article 3.19; 



(b) the exporting Party refuses to conduct a visit,
or that Party fails to respond to the
communication referred to in paragraph 2 of
Article 3.19 within the period referred to in
paragraph 4 of Article 3.19; or 



(c) the information provided to the customs authority
of the importing Party in accordance with Article

3.18 or 3.19 is not sufficient to prove that the
good qualifies as an originating good of the
exporting Party. 


4. After carrying out the procedures outlined in Article

3.18 or 3.19 as the case may be, the customs authority of
the importing Party shall provide the competent
governmental authority of the exporting Party with a
written determination of whether or not the good qualifies
as an originating good of the exporting Party, including
findings of fact and the legal basis for the determination.
The competent governmental authority of the exporting Party
shall inform such determination by the customs authority of
the importing Party to the exporter, or the producer of the
good in the exporting Party, whose premises were subject of
the visit referred to in Article 3.19.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.21" name="Confidentiality" article_identifier="36776">1. Each Party shall maintain, in accordance with its laws
and regulations, the confidentiality of information
provided to it as confidential in accordance with this
Chapter, and shall protect that information from disclosure
that could prejudice the competitive position of the
persons providing the information. 



2. Information obtained by the customs authority of the
importing Party in accordance with this Chapter: 



(a) may only be used by such authority for the
purposes of this Chapter; and 



(b) shall not be used by the importing Party in any
criminal proceedings carried out by a court or a
judge, unless the information is requested to the
exporting Party and provided to the importing
Party through the diplomatic channels or other
channels established in accordance with the 
applicable laws and regulations of the exporting
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.22" name="Minor Errors" article_identifier="36777">The customs authority of the importing Party shall
disregard minor errors, such as slight discrepancies or
omissions, typing errors or protruding from the designated
field, provided that these minor errors are not such as to
create doubts concerning the accuracy of the information
included in the Certificate of Origin.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.23" name="Penalties And Measures Against False Declaration" article_identifier="36778">1. Each Party shall establish or maintain, in accordance
with its laws and regulations, appropriate penalties or
other sanctions against its exporters to whom a Certificate
of Origin has been issued and the producers of a good in
the exporting Party referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of
Article 3.16, for providing false declaration or documents
to the competent governmental authority of the exporting
Party or its designees prior to the issuance of Certificate
of Origin. 



2. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate
against its exporters to whom a Certificate of Origin has
been issued and the producers of a good in the exporting
Party referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of Article 3.16, for
failing to notify in writing to the competent governmental
authority of the exporting Party or its designees without
delay after having known, after the issuance of Certificate
of Origin, that the good for which the Certificate of
Origin has been issued does not qualify as an originating
good of the exporting Party. 

Note: For greater certainty, the exporters to whom a 
Certificate of Origin has been issued and the
producers of a good in the exporting Party
referred to in subparagraph 8(b) of Article 3.16
are not subject to the measures referred to in
this paragraph, in accordance with the laws and
regulations of each Party, provided that they
notify in writing to the competent governmental
authority of the exporting Party or its
designees without delay after having known,
after the issuance of Certificate of Origin,
that the good for which the Certificate of
Origin has been issued does not qualify as an
originating good of the exporting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.24" name="Miscellaneous" article_identifier="36779">Communications between the importing Party and the
exporting Party shall be conducted in the English language.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.25" name="Sub-Committee On Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="36780">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Rules of Origin (hereinafter referred to
in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 

(a) reviewing and making appropriate recommendations,
as necessary, to the Joint Committee on: 


(i) the implementation and operation of this
Chapter; 


(ii) any amendments to Annex 2 or 3, proposed by
either Party; and 


(iii) the Operational Procedures for Rules of
Origin referred to in Article 3.26;


 


(b) considering any other matter as the Parties may
agree related to this Chapter; 



(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 3.26" name="Operational Procedures For Rules Of Origin" article_identifier="36781">Upon the date of entry into force of this Agreement, 
the Joint Committee shall adopt the Operational Procedures
for Rules of Origin that provide detailed regulations
pursuant to which the customs authorities, the competent
governmental authorities and other relevant authorities of
the Parties shall implement their functions under this
Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 4" name="Customs Procedures And Trade Facilitation" chapter_identifier="4245">
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.1" name="Scope And Objectives" article_identifier="36782">1. This Chapter shall apply to customs procedures
required for the clearance of goods traded between the
Parties. 



2. This Chapter shall be implemented by the Parties in
accordance with the laws and regulations of each Party and
within the available resources of their respective customs
authorities. 


 


3. The objectives of this Chapter are to establish a
framework to ensure transparency, proper application of
customs laws and prompt clearance of goods and to promote
cooperation in the field of customs procedures, with a view
to facilitating trade in goods between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.2" name="Definition" article_identifier="36783">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “customs
laws” means such laws and regulations administered and
enforced by the customs authority of each Party concerning
the importation, exportation and transit of goods, as they
relate to customs duties, charges and other taxes, or to
prohibitions, restrictions and other similar controls with
respect to the movement of controlled items across the
boundary of the customs territory of each Party</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.3" name="Transparency" article_identifier="36784">1. Each Party shall ensure that all relevant information
of general application pertaining to its customs laws is
readily available to any interested person. 



2. When information that has been made available must be 
revised due to changes in its customs laws, each Party
shall make the revised information readily available,
whenever possible in advance of the entry into force of the
changes, to enable interested persons to take account of
them. 



3. Upon request of any interested person of the Parties,
each Party shall provide, as quickly and accurately as
possible, information related to the specific customs
matters raised by the interested person and pertaining to
its customs laws. Each Party shall supply not only the
information specifically requested but also any other
pertinent information which it considers the interested
person should be made aware of. 



4. Each Party shall designate one or more enquiry points
to answer reasonable enquiries from any interested person
of the Parties concerning customs matters, and shall make
publicly available, includingthrough its website, the
names and addresses of such enquiry points.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.4" name="Customs Clearance" article_identifier="36785">1. The Parties shall apply their respective customs 
procedures in a predictable, consistent and transparent
manner. 



2. For prompt customs clearance of goods traded between
the Parties, each Partyshall: 



(a) 	make use of information and communications 
technology; 



(b) simplify its customs procedures; 



(c) harmonize its customs procedures, to the extent
possible, with relevant international standards
and recommended practices such as those made
under the auspices of the Customs Co-operation
Council; and 



(d) 	promote cooperation, where appropriate, between 
its customs authority and: 

(i) other national authorities of the Party; 


(ii) the trading communities of the Party; and 


(iii) the customs authorities of non-Parties. 


3. Each Party shall provide affected parties with easily
accessible processes of judicial or administrative review
related to the action on the customs matters taken by the
Party. Such review shall be independent of the authorities
entrusted with the administrative enforcement of such 
actions and shall be carried out in an impartial and fair
manner.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.5" name="Temporary Admission And Goods In Transit" article_identifier="36786">1. Each Party shall continue to facilitate the procedures
for the temporary admission of goods traded between the
Parties in accordance with its laws, regulations and
international obligations. 



2. Each Party shall continue to facilitate customs
clearance of goods in transit from or to the other Party in
accordance with paragraph 3 of Article V of the GATT 1994. 



3. The Parties shall endeavor to promote, through
arrangements such as seminars and courses, the use of

A.T.A. carnets in accordance with the international 
obligations and the facilitation of customs clearance of
goods in transit in the Parties or non-Parties. 


4. 	For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) 	the term “A.T.A. carnet” shall have the same 
meaning as in: 


(i) for Japan, the Customs Convention on A.T.A.
Carnet for the Temporary Admission of Goods,
done at Brussels on December 6, 1961; and 


(ii) for Mongolia, the Convention on Temporary
Admission, done at Istanbul on June 26,
1990; and 


(b) the term “temporary admission” means customs
procedures under which certain goods may be
brought into a customs territory conditionally,
relieved totally or partially from the payment of
customs duties. Such goods shall beimported for
a specific purposeand shall be intended for reexportationwithin a specified period and without
having undergone any change except normal
depreciation due to the use made of them.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.6" name="Advance Rulings" article_identifier="36787">Where a written application is made in accordance with
relevant laws, regulations or procedures adopted or
maintained by theimporting Party and the importing Party
has no reasonable grounds to deny the issuance, the
importing Party shall endeavor to, prior to the importation
of the good, issue a written advance ruling on: 



(a) the tariff classification; 



(b) the customs valuation; and


 


(c) the qualification of the good as an originating
good of the exporting Party under the provisions
of Chapter 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.7" name="Cooperation And Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="36788">1. The Parties shall cooperate and exchange information
with each other in the field of customs procedures,
including combating the trafficking of prohibited goods and
the importation and exportation of goods suspected of
infringing intellectual property rights. 



2. Such cooperation and exchange of information shall be
implemented as provided for in the Implementing Agreement. 



3. Paragraph 2 of Article 1.8 shall not apply to the
exchange of information under this Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 4.8" name="Sub-Committee On Customs Procedures And Trade Facilitation" article_identifier="36789">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Customs Procedures and Trade Facilitation 
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the Sub-
Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) identifying areas, related to this Chapter, to be 
improved for facilitating trade between the
Parties; 



(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee 


3. The composition of the Sub-Committee shall be
specified in the Implementing Agreement. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 5" name="Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" chapter_identifier="4246">
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="36790">This Chapter shall apply to all sanitary and
phytosanitary (hereinafter referred to as “SPS”) measures
of the Parties under the SPS Agreement, that may, directly
or indirectly, affect trade in goods between the Parties. 


Article 5.2 
Reaffirmation of Rights and Obligations


 

The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
related to SPS measures under the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.3" name="Harmonization" article_identifier="36791">The Parties shall endeavor to cooperate on the matters
related to the harmonization of SPS measures, on as wide a
basis as possible, as prescribed under Article 3 of the SPS
Agreement. Such cooperation shall be conducted without
requiring either Party to change its appropriate level of
protection of human, animal or plant life or health that
the Party has determined in accordance with Article 5 of
the SPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.4" name="Equivalence" article_identifier="36792">1. An importing Party shall accept an exporting Party’s 
SPS measures as equivalent, if the exporting Party
objectively demonstrates to the importing Party that its
measures achieve the importing Party’s appropriate level of
SPS protection. 



2. Each Party shall, upon request of the other Party,enter into consultations with the aim of achievingbilateral arrangements related to recognition of theequivalence of specified SPS measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.5" name="Enquiry Point" article_identifier="36793">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point to answer
all reasonable enquiries from the other Party regarding SPS
measures and, where appropriate, to provide the other Party
with relevant information.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.6" name="Sub-Committee On Sanitary And Phytosanitary Measures" article_identifier="36794">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on SPS Measures (hereinafter referred to in
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) exchanging information on such matters as change
or introduction of SPS-related regulations and
standards of the Parties and occurrences of SPS 
incidents in the Areas of the Parties, which may,
directly or indirectly, affect trade in goods
between the Parties; 



(c) undertaking science-based technical consultations
to address matters related to harmonization,
equivalence, adaptation to regional conditions,
and control, inspection and approval procedures
as referred to in the SPS Agreement with the
objective to achieve mutually acceptable
solutions; 



(d) discussing technical cooperation between the
Parties on SPS measures including capacity
building, technical assistance and exchange of
experts; 



(e) discussing any other issues related to this
Chapter; 



(f) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the relevant bodies; and 



(g) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee.

 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties with appropriate
participation of relevant experts. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 5.7" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="36795">Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 6" name="Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" chapter_identifier="4247">
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="36796">1. This Chapter shall apply to technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures as defined
in the TBT Agreement, that may affect trade in goods
between the Parties. 



2. 	This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) purchasing specifications prepared by
governmental bodies for production or consumption
requirements of such bodies; or 



(b) 	SPS measures as defined in Annex A of the SPS 
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.2" name="Objectives" article_identifier="36797">The objectives of this Chapter are to: 



(a) 	increase and facilitate trade between the 
Parties, through the improvement of the
implementation of the TBT Agreement; 



(b) ensure that technical regulations, standards and
conformity assessment procedures do not create
unnecessary obstacles to trade; and 



(c) enhance joint cooperation between the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.3" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36798">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “TBT Agreement” means the Agreement on
Technical Barriers to Trade in Annex 1A to the 
WTO Agreement; and 



(b) 	the terms and definitions set out in Annex 1 of 
the TBT Agreement shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.4" name="Reaffirmation Of Rights And Obligations" article_identifier="36799">The Parties reaffirm their rights and obligations
related to technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures under the TBT Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.5" name="International Standards" article_identifier="36800">1. Each Party shall use relevant international standards
and guides or recommendations to the extent provided in
paragraph 4 of Article 2 and paragraph 4 of Article 5 of
the TBT Agreement, as a basis for its technical regulations
and conformity assessment procedures. 



2. Each Party shall encourage its national standardizing
bodies to cooperate with the relevant national
standardizing bodies of the other Party in international
standardizing activities. Such cooperation may take place
in regional and international standardizing bodies of which
they are both members.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.6" name="Technical Regulations" article_identifier="36801">1. Upon request of a Party that has an interest in
developing a technical regulation similar to a technical
regulation of the other Party, such other Party shall
provide, to the extent practicable, relevant information,
including studies or documents, except for confidential
information, on which it has relied in its development. 



2. Each Party shall give positive consideration to
accepting as equivalent technical regulations of the other
Party, even if these regulations differ from its own,
provided it is satisfied that these regulations adequately
fulfill the objectives of its own regulations. 



3. Where a Party does not accept a technical regulation
of the other Party as equivalent to its own, it shall, upon
request of the other Party, explain the reasons therefor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.7" name="Acceptance Of Results Of Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="36802">1. The Parties recognize that a broad range of mechanisms 
exists to facilitate the acceptance in a Party of the
results of conformity assessment procedures conducted in
the other Party. Each Party shall, upon request of the
other Party, provide information on the range of such
mechanisms used in its Area. 



2. Each Party shall ensure, whenever possible, that
results of the conformity assessment procedures in the
other Party are accepted, even when those procedures differ
from its own, provided it is satisfied that the procedures
offer an assurance of conformity with applicable technical
regulations or standards equivalent to its own procedures. 



3. Where a Party does not accept the results of a
conformity assessment procedure conducted in the other
Party, it shall, upon request of the other Party and
subject to the laws and regulations of that Party, explain
the reasons therefor so that corrective action may be taken
by the other Party where appropriate. 



4. Each Party shall, whenever possible, accredit,
designate or recognize conformity assessment bodies in the
other Party on terms no less favorable than those it
accords to conformity assessment bodies in its Area. If a
Party accredits, designates or recognizes a body assessing
conformity with a particular technical regulation or
standard in its Area and it refuses to accredit, designate
or recognize a body in the other Party assessing conformity
with that technical regulation or standard, it shall, upon
request, explain the reasons therefor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.8" name="Enquiry Point" article_identifier="36803">Each Party shall designate an enquiry point to answer
all reasonable enquiries from the other Party regarding
technical regulations, standards and conformity assessment
procedures and, where appropriate, to provide the other
Party with other relevant information which it considers
the other Party should be made aware of.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.9" name="Sub-Committee On Technical Regulations, Standards And Conformity Assessment Procedures" article_identifier="36804">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Technical Regulations, Standards and
Conformity Assessment Procedures (hereinafter referred to
in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. 	The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) 	reviewing and monitoring the implementation and 
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) enhancing joint cooperation in the development
and improvement of technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures; 



(c) exchanging information on technical regulations,
standards and conformity assessment procedures; 



(d) undertaking consultations on issues related to
technical regulations, standards and conformity
assessment procedures; 



(e) exchanging information on the work in regional
and multilateral fora engaged in activities
related to technical regulations, standards and
conformity assessment procedures; 



(f) discussing technical cooperation between the
Parties on matters related to this Chapter; 



(g) discussing any issues including those which may
cause disputes between the Parties related to
this Chapter with the objective of finding
mutually acceptable solutions; 



(h) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the relevant bodies; and 



(i) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties. 



5. For the purposes of this Article, the Sub-Committee
shall be coordinated by: 



(a) 	for Japan, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, or 
its successor; and 



(b) 	for Mongolia, the Ministry of Industry, or its 
successor.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 6.10" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="36805">Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 7" name="Trade In Services" chapter_identifier="4248">
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="36806">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or
maintained by a Party affecting trade in services. 



2. 	This Chapter shall not apply to: 



(a) cabotage in maritime transport services; 



(b) with respect to air transport services, measures
affecting traffic rights, however granted, or
measures affecting services directly related to
the exercise of traffic rights; 



(c) government procurement; 



(d) 	subsidies provided by a Party or a state 
enterprise, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance; 



(e) measures pursuant to immigration laws and
regulations; 



(f) measures affecting natural persons of a Party
seeking access to the employment market of the
other Party, or measures regarding nationality or
citizenship, or residence or employment on a
permanent basis; and 



(g) services supplied in the exercise of governmental
authority. 


3. Notwithstanding subparagraph 2(b), this Chapter shall
apply to measures affecting: 



(a) aircraft repair and maintenance services; 



(b) the selling and marketing of air transport
services; and 



(c) computer reservation system services. 


4. Annex 4 provides supplementary provisions to this 
Chapter on financial services, including scope and
definitions. 



5. Annex 5 provides supplementary provisions to this
definitions.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36807">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) 	the term “aircraft repair and maintenance 
services” means such activities when undertaken 
on an aircraft or a part thereof while it is
withdrawn from services and does not include so-
called line maintenance; 



(b) the term “computer reservation system services”
means services provided by computerized systems
that contain information about air carriers’ 
schedules, availability, fares and fare rules,
through which reservations may be made or tickets
may be issued; 



(c) the term “existing” means in effect on the date
of entry into force of this Agreement; 



(d) the term “juridical person of the other Party”
means a juridical person which is either: 


(i) constituted or otherwise organized under the
law of the other Party; or 


(ii) in the case of the supply of a service
through commercial presence, owned or
controlled by: 



(A) natural persons of the other Party; or 



(B) juridical persons of the other Party
identified under subparagraph (i); 


(e) the term “measure” means any measure, whether in
the form of a law, regulation, rule, procedure,
decision, administrative action or any other
form; 


Note: 	The term “measure” shall include taxation 
measures to the extent covered by the
GATS. 


(f) the term “measure adopted or maintained by a
Party” means any measure adopted or maintained
by: 


(i) any level of government or authority of a
Party; and 


(ii) 	non-governmental bodies in the exercise of 
powers delegated by any level of government
or authority of a Party; 


(g) the term “measures by a Party affecting trade in
services” includes measures with respect to: 


(i) the purchase, payment or use of a service; 


(ii) the access to and use of, in connection with
the supply of a service, services which are
required by the Party to be offered to the
public generally; and 


(iii) the presence, including commercial presence,
of persons of the other Party for the supply
of a service in the Area of the former 
Party; 


(h) the term “monopoly supplier of a service” means
any person, public or private, which in the
relevant market of the Party, is authorized or
established formally or in effect by that Party
as the sole supplier of that service; 



(i) the term “natural person of a Party” means a
national of a Party under the law of the Party; 



(j) the term “selling and marketing of air transport
services” means opportunities for the air carrier
concerned to sell and market freely its air
transport services including all aspects of
marketing such as market research, advertising
and distribution. These activities do not include 
the pricing of air transport services nor the
applicable conditions; 



(k) the term “service supplied in the exercise of
governmental authority” means any service which
is supplied neither on a commercial basis nor in
competition with one or more service suppliers; 



(l) the term “supply of a service” includes the
production, distribution, marketing, sale and
delivery of a service; 



(m) the term “trade in services” means the supply of
a service: 


(i) from the Area of a Party into the Area of
the other Party (“cross-border supply
mode”); 


(ii) in the Area of a Party to the service
consumer of the other Party (“consumption
abroad mode”); 


(iii) by a service supplier of a Party, through
commercial presence in the Area of the other
Party (“commercial presence mode”); or 


(iv) by a service supplier of a Party, through
presence of natural persons of that Party in
the Area of the other Party (“presence of
natural persons mode”); and 


(n) the term “traffic rights” means the rights for
scheduled and non-scheduled services to operate
and/or to carry passengers, cargo and mail for
remuneration or hire from, to, within, or over a
Party, including points to be served, routes to
be operated, types of traffic to be carried,
capacity to be provided, tariffs to be charged
and their conditions, and criteria for
designation of airlines, including such criteria
as number, ownership and control.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.3" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="36808">1. In the sectors inscribed in its Schedule of Specific
Commitments in Annex 6, and subject to any conditions and
qualifications set out therein, each Party shall accord to
services and service suppliers of the other Party, with
respect to all measures affecting the supply of services,
treatment no less favorable than that it accords to its own 
like services and service suppliers. 


Note: Specific commitments assumed under this Article 
shall not be construed to require either Party
to compensate for any inherent competitive
disadvantages which result from the foreign
character of the relevant services or service 
suppliers. 


2. A Party may meet the requirement of paragraph 1 by
according to services and service suppliers of the other
Party, either formally identical treatment or formally
different treatment to that it accords to its own like 
services and service suppliers. 



3. Formally identical or formally different treatment
shall be considered to be less favorable if it modifies the 
conditions of competition in favor of services or service
suppliers of a Party compared to like services or service
suppliers of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.4" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="36809">1. Each Party shall accord to services and service
suppliers of the other Party treatment no less favorable
than that it accords to like services and service suppliers
of any non-Party. 



2. Each Party may maintain measures inconsistent with 
paragraph 1 provided that such measures are listed in, and
meet the conditions of, the List of Most-Favored-Nation
Treatment Exemptions in Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.5" name="Market Access" article_identifier="36810">1. With respect to market access through the modes of
supply identified in subparagraph (m) of Article 7.2, a
Party shall accord services and service suppliers of the
other Party treatment no less favorable than that provided
for under the terms, limitations and conditions agreed and
specified in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in
Annex 6. 


Note: If a Party undertakes a market-access commitment 
in relation to the supply of a service through
the mode of supply referred to in subparagraph
(m)(i) of Article 7.2 and if the cross-border
movement of capital is an essential part of the
service itself, that Party is thereby committed
to allow such movement of capital. If a Party
undertakes a market-access commitment in 
relation to the supply of a service through the
mode of supply referred to in subparagraph
(m)(iii) of Article 7.2, it is thereby committed
to allow related transfers of capital into its
Area. 


2. In sectors where market-access commitments are 
undertaken, the measures which a Party shall not maintain
or adopt either on the basis of a regional subdivision or
on the basis of its entire Area, unless otherwise specified
in its Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6, are
defined as: 


(a) limitations on the number of service suppliers
whether in the form of numerical quotas,
monopolies, exclusive service suppliers or the
requirements of an economic needs test; 



(b) 	limitations on the total value of service 
transactions or assets in the form of numerical 
quotas or the requirement of an economic needs
test; 



(c) 	limitations on the total number of service 
operations or on the total quantity of service
output expressed in terms of designated numerical
units in the form of quotas or the requirement of
an economic needs test; 


Note: 	This subparagraph does not cover measures
of a Party which limit inputs for the
supply of services. 


(d) 	limitations on the total number of natural 
persons that may be employed in a particular
service sector or that a service supplier may
employ and who are necessary for, and directly
related to, the supply of a specific service in
the form of numerical quotas or the requirement
of an economic needs test; 



(e) measures which restrict or require specific types
of legal entity or joint venture through which a
service supplier may supply a service; and 



(f) 	limitations on the participation of foreign 
capital in terms of maximum percentage limit on
foreign shareholding or the total value of
individual or aggregate foreign investment.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.6" name="Additional Commitments" article_identifier="36811">The Parties may negotiate commitments with respect to
measures affecting trade in services not subject to
scheduling under Articles 7.3 and 7.5, including those
regarding qualifications, standards or licensing matters.
Such commitments shall be inscribed in a Party’s Schedule
of Specific Commitments in Annex 6.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.7" name="Schedule Of Specific Commitments" article_identifier="36812">1. Each Party shall set out in a schedule the specific
commitments it undertakes under Articles 7.3, 7.5 and 7.6.
With respect to sectors or sub-sectors where such
commitments are undertaken, each Schedule of Specific
Commitments in Annex 6 shall specify: 



(a) 	terms, limitations and conditions on market 
access; 



(b) conditions and qualifications on national
treatment; 



(c) undertakings related to additional commitments; 
and 



(d) where appropriate, the time-frame for
implementation of such commitments. 


2. With respect to sectors or sub-sectors where the
specific commitments are undertaken and which are indicated
with “SS”, any terms, limitations, conditions and
qualifications, referred to in subparagraphs 1(a) and 1(b),
other than those based on measures pursuant to immigration
laws and regulations, shall be limited to those based on
existing non-conforming measures. 



3. Measures inconsistent with both Articles 7.3 and 7.5 
shall be inscribed in the column related to Article 7.5. In 
this case the inscription will be considered to provide a
condition or qualification to Article 7.3 as well.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.8" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="36813">1. Each Party shall ensure that all measures of general
application affecting trade in services are administered in
a reasonable, objective and impartial manner. 



2. Where authorization is required by a Party for the
supply of a service, the competent authorities of that
Party shall, within a reasonable period of time after the
submission of an application is considered complete under
the laws and regulations of that Party, inform the
applicant of the decision concerning the application. Upon
request of the applicant, the competent authorities of that
Party shall provide, without undue delay, information
concerning the status of the application. 



3. With a view to ensuring that any measure adopted or
maintained by a Party in any services sector related to the
authorization, qualification requirements and procedures,
technical standards and licensing requirements of service
suppliers of the other Party does not constitute an
unnecessary barrier to trade in services, each Party shall
ensure that such measure: 



(a) is based on objective and transparent criteria,
such as the competence and ability to supply the
service; 



(b) 	is not more burdensome than necessary to ensure 
the quality of the service; and 



(c) does not constitute a disguised restriction on
the supply of the service.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.9" name="Recognition" article_identifier="36814">1. A Party may recognize the education or experience
obtained, requirements met, or licenses or certifications
granted in the other Party for the purposes of the
fulfillment, in whole or in part, of its standards or
criteria for the authorization, licensing or certification
of service suppliers of the other Party. 



2. Recognition referred to in paragraph 1, which may be
achieved through harmonization or otherwise, may be based
upon an agreement or arrangement between the Parties or may
be accorded unilaterally. 



3. Where a Party recognizes, by agreement or arrangement
between the Party and a non-Party or unilaterally, the
education or experience obtained, requirements met, or
licenses or certifications granted in the non-Party: 



(a) nothing in Article 7.4 shall be construed to
require the Party to accord such recognition to
the education or experience obtained,
requirements met, or licenses or certifications
granted in the other Party; 



(b) the Party shall accord the other Party an
adequate opportunity to negotiate the accession
of that other Party to such an agreement or
arrangement or to negotiate a comparable one with
it between the Parties; and 



(c) where the Party accords such recognition
unilaterally, the Party shall accord the other
Party an adequate opportunity to demonstrate that
the education or experience obtained,
requirements met, or licenses or certifications
granted in the other Party should also be
recognized.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.10" name="Monopolies And Exclusive Service Suppliers" article_identifier="36815">1. A Party shall ensure that any monopoly supplier of a
service in its Area does not, in the supply of the monopoly
service in the relevant market, act in a manner
inconsistent with that Party’s obligations under Articles
7.3, 7.4 and 7.5. 



2. Where a Party’s monopoly supplier competes, either
directly or through an affiliated company, in the supply of
a service outside the scope of its monopoly rights, in an
area subject to its Specific Commitments, that Party shall
ensure that such a supplier does not abuse its monopoly
position to act in the Area of that Party in a manner
inconsistent with such commitments under Articles 7.3 and 

7.5. 



3. If a Party has a reason to believe that a monopoly
supplier of a service of the other Party is acting in a
manner inconsistent with paragraph 1 or 2, the former Party
may request the other Party to provide specific information
concerning the relevant operations. 



4. This Article shall also apply to cases of exclusive
service suppliers, where a Party, formally or in effect: 



(a) 	authorizes or establishes a small number of 
service suppliers; and 



(b) substantially prevents competition among those
suppliers in its Area.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.11" name="Business Practices" article_identifier="36816">1. The Parties recognize that certain business practices
of service suppliers, other than those falling under
Article 7.10, may restrain competition and thereby restrict
trade in services. 



2. A Party shall, upon request of the other Party, enter
into consultations with a view to eliminating practices
referred to in paragraph 1. The Party addressed shall
accord full and sympathetic consideration to such a request
and shall cooperate through the supply of publicly
available non-confidential information of relevance to the 
matter in question. The Party addressed shall also provide
other information available to the requesting Party,
subject to its laws and regulations and to the conclusion
of a satisfactory agreement concerning the safeguarding of
its confidentiality by the requesting Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.12" name="Payments And Transfers" article_identifier="36817">1. Except under the circumstances envisaged in Article
7.13, a Party shall not apply restrictions on international
transfers and payments for current transactions related to
trade in services. 



2. Nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and
obligations of the Parties as members of the International
Monetary Fund under the Articles of Agreement of the
International Monetary Fund, including the use of exchange
actions which are in conformity with the Articles of
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund. However, a
Party shall not impose restrictions on any capital
transactions inconsistently with its Specific Commitments
regarding such transactions, except under Article 7.13 or
upon request of the International Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.13" name="Restrictions To Safeguard The Balance Of Payments" article_identifier="36818">1. In the event of serious balance-of-payments and
external financial difficulties or threat thereof, a Party
may adopt or maintain restrictions on trade in services,
including on payments or transfers for transactions. 



2. 	The restrictions referred to in paragraph 1 shall: 



(a) 	be applied on the basis of national treatment and 
most-favored-nation treatment; 



(b) be consistent with the Articles of Agreement of
the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other 
Party; 



(d) not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances described in paragraph 1; and 



(e) be temporary and be phased out progressively as
the situation specified in paragraph 1 improves. 


3. In determining the incidence of such restrictions, a
Party may give priority to the supply of services which are
more essential to its economic or development programs.
However, such restrictions shall not be adopted or
maintained for the purposes of protecting a particular
service sector. 



4. Any restrictions adopted or maintained under
paragraph 1, or any changes therein, shall be promptly
notified to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.14" name="Transparency" article_identifier="36819">Each Party shall prepare a non-legally binding list
providing all relevant measures affecting the obligations
under Articles 7.3, 7.4 and 7.5 in all sectors. The list
shall be exchanged with the other Party and made publicly
available within five years from the date of entry into
force of this Agreement and shall also be subject to future 
review and revision where necessary or as agreed between
the Parties. The list shall include the following elements: 



(a) sector and sub-sector or matter; 



(b) type of inconsistency (i.e. national treatment,
most-favored-nation treatment and/or market
access); 



(c) legal source or authority of the measure; and 



(d) brief description of the measure. 

Note: The list under this Article is made solely for the 
purposes of transparency, and shall not be construed
to affect the rights and obligations of a Party under
this Chapter. Any review or revision under this
Article is solely for the purposes of updating such
list.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.15" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="36820">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a
service supplier of the other Party that is a juridical
person of the other Party, where the denying Party
establishes that the juridical person is owned or
controlled by persons of a non-Party, and the denying
Party: 



(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with the
non-Party; or 



(b) adopts or maintains measures regarding the non-
Party that: 

(i) prohibit transactions with the juridical
person; or 


(ii) 	would be violated or circumvented if the 
benefits of this Chapter were accorded to
the juridical person. 


2. Subject to prior notification and consultation, a
Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to a service
supplier of the other Party that is a juridical person of
the other Party, where the denying Party establishes that
the juridical person is owned or controlled by persons of a
non-Party and has no substantial business activities in the
Area of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.16" name="Sub-Committee On Trade In Services" article_identifier="36821">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Trade in Services (hereinafter referred to
in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(c) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 7.17" name="Review Of Commitments" article_identifier="36822">1. With the objective of further liberalizing trade in
services between the Parties, including the possibility of
renegotiating the format of schedules, the Parties shall
consider in due course undertaking a review of this Chapter
and the Annexes referred to therein on occasions as may be
agreed by the Parties. 



2. If, after the entry into force of this Agreement, a
Party has undertaken further liberalization autonomously in
any of the services sectors, sub-sectors or activities, it
shall consider in due course requests from the other Party
to incorporate such liberalization into this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 8" name="Movement Of Natural Persons" chapter_identifier="4249">
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.1" name="General Principles" article_identifier="36823">1. This Chapter reflects the preferential trading
relationship between the Parties, the desire of the Parties
to facilitate entry and temporary stay of natural persons
on a mutually beneficial basis and to establish transparent
criteria and procedures for entry and temporary stay, and
the need to ensure border security and to protect the
domestic labor force and permanent employment in each
Party. 



2. Each Party shall apply its measures related to the
provisions of this Chapter in accordance with the general
principles referred to in paragraph 1, and, in particular,
shall apply those measures expeditiously so as to avoid
unduly impairing or delaying trade in goods or services or
investment activities under this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.2" name="Scope" article_identifier="36824">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures affecting the
entry and temporary stay of natural persons of a Party who
enter the other Party and fall under one of the categories
referred to in paragraph 1 of Article 8.4. 



2. This Chapter shall not apply to measures affecting
natural persons of a Party seeking access to the employment
market of the other Party, nor shall it apply to measures
regarding nationality or citizenship, or residence or
employment on a permanent basis. 



3. This Chapter shall not prevent a Party from applying
measures to regulate the entry and temporary stay of
natural persons of the other Party, including those
measures necessary to protect the integrity of, and to
ensure the orderly movement of natural persons across, its
borders, provided that such measures are not applied in
such a manner as to nullify or impair the benefits accruing
to the other Party under the terms of specific commitments
set out in Annex 7. 

Note: The sole fact of requiring a visa for natural 
persons of the other Party and not for those of
certain non-Parties shall not be regarded as
nullifying or impairing benefits under the terms
of specific commitments set out in Annex 7.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.3" name="Definition" article_identifier="36825">For the purposes of this Chapter, the term “naturalperson of a Party” means a natural person who resides in aParty or elsewhere and who under the law of the Party is anational of the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.4" name="Specific Commitments" article_identifier="36826">1. Each Party shall set out in Annex 7 the specific
commitments it undertakes for: 



(a) short-term business visitors of the other Party; 



(b) intra-corporate transferees of the other Party; 



(c) investors of the other Party; 



(d) natural persons of the other Party who engage in
professional services; 



(e) natural persons of the other Party who engage in
supplying services, which require technology or
knowledge at an advanced level on the basis of a
contract with public or private organizations in
the former Party; and 



(f) spouse and children accompanying those natural
persons set out in subparagraphs (b) through (e). 


2. Natural persons covered by the categories referred to 
in paragraph 1 shall be granted entry and temporary stay in
accordance with the terms and conditions set out in Annex 
7, provided that the natural persons comply with
immigration laws and regulations applicable to entry and
temporary stay which are not inconsistent with the
provisions of this Chapter. 



3. Neither Party shall impose or maintain any limitation 
on the number of natural persons to be granted entry and
temporary stay under paragraph 1.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.5" name="Requirements And Procedures" article_identifier="36827">1. Each Party shall publish or otherwise make available
to the other Party upon the date of entry into force of
this Agreement, with respect to natural persons covered by
that Party’s specific commitments set out in Annex 7,
information on requirements and procedures necessary for an
effective application by natural persons of the other Party
for the grant of: 



(a) entry into the former Party; 



(b) initial temporary stay in the former Party; 



(c) renewal of temporary stay in the former Party; 



(d) where applicable, permission to work in the
former Party; and 



(e) change of status of temporary stay in the former
Party. 


2. Each Party shall endeavor to provide, upon request by
a natural person of the other Party, information on
requirements and procedures referred to in paragraph 1. 



3. Each Party shall endeavor to promptly inform the other
Party of the introduction of any new requirements and
procedures, or changes in any existing requirements and
procedures referred to in paragraph 1 that affect the
effective application by natural persons of the other Party
for the grant of entry, temporary stay or permission
referred to in subparagraphs 1(a) through (e). 



4. Each Party shall ensure that fees charged by its
competent authorities on application referred to in
paragraph 1 do not in themselves represent an unjustifiable
impediment to entry and temporary stay of natural persons
of the other Party under this Chapter. 



5. Each Party shall endeavor, to the maximum extent
possible, to take measures to simplify the requirements and
to facilitate and expedite the procedures related to the
entry and temporary stay of natural persons of the other
Party subject to its laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.6" name="Sub-Committee On Movement Of Natural Persons" article_identifier="36828">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Movement of Natural Persons (hereinafter
referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) considering the development of measures to 
further facilitate the entry and temporary stay
of natural persons on a reciprocal basis; 



(c) exchanging information on measures affecting
entry and temporary stay of natural persons
referred to in Annex 7; 



(d) discussing any issues related to this Chapter as 
may be agreed upon; 



(e) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(f) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 8.7" name="Dispute Settlement" article_identifier="36829">1. The dispute settlement procedures provided for in
Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter unless: 



(a) the matter involves a pattern of practice; and 



(b) the natural persons of a Party affected by that
matter have exhausted the available domestic 
administrative remedies of the other Party. 

2. The remedies referred to in subparagraph 1(b) shall be
deemed to be exhausted if a final determination in the 
matter has not been issued by the competent authority of
the other Party within one year after the date of the
institution of the administrative remedy, and the failure
to issue such a determination is not attributable to the 
delay caused by the natural persons.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 9" name="Electronic Commerce" chapter_identifier="4250">
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.1" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="36830">1. The Parties recognize the economic growth and
opportunities provided by electronic commerce, and the
importance of avoiding unnecessary barriers to its use and
development. 



2. The objective of this Chapter is to contribute to
creating an environment of trust and confidence in the use
of electronic commerce and to promote electronic commerce
between the Parties and the wider use of electronic 
commerce globally. 



3. The Parties recognize the principle of technological
neutrality in electronic commerce. 



4. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter
and Chapter 2, 7, 10 or 12, the Chapter other than this
Chapter shall prevail to the extent of the inconsistency.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36831">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “digital products” means computer
programs, text, video, images, sound recordings
and other products, that are digitally encoded,
regardless of whether they are fixed on a carrier
medium or transmitted electronically; 



(b) 	the term “electronic certificate” means an 
electromagnetic record prepared for certifying
that matters used to confirm that the user has 
performed the electronic signature are pertaining
to such user; 



(c) the term “electronic signature” means a measure
taken with respect to information that can be
recorded in an electromagnetic record and which
fulfills both of the following requirements: 


(i) 	that the measure indicates that such 
information has been approved by a person
who has taken such measure; and 


(ii) 	that the measure confirms that such 
information has not been altered; and 


(d) 	the term “trade administration documents” means 
forms that a Party issues or controls and that
must be completed by or for an importer or
exporter in connection with the importation or
exportation of goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.3" name="Customs Duties" article_identifier="36832">Each Party shall maintain its practice of not imposing
customs duties on electronic transmissions between the 
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.4" name="Non-Discriminatory Treatment Of Digital Products" article_identifier="36833">1. 	Neither Party shall adopt or maintain: 



(a) 	measures that accord less favorable treatment to 
digital products of the other Party than it
accords to its own like digital products; and 



(b) 	measures that accord less favorable treatment to 
digital products of the other Party than it
accords to like digital products of a non-Party. 

2. 	Paragraph 1 shall not apply to: 



(a) government procurement; 



(b) subsidies provided by a Party or a state
enterprise, including grants, government-
supported loans, guarantees and insurance; 



(c) measures maintained by a Party in accordance with
paragraph 2 of Article 7.4; 



(d) measures adopted or maintained by a Party within
the scope of Article 7.3 or 7.5 which are: 


(i) 	related to the sectors not committed in its 
Schedule of Specific Commitments in Annex 6;
or 


(ii) not inconsistent with the terms,
limitations, conditions and qualifications
agreed and specified in its Schedule of
Specific Commitments in Annex 6; and 


(e) 	non-conforming measures adopted or maintained by 
a Party in accordance with Article 10.8.

 


3. In implementing its obligations under paragraph 1,
each Party shall, where necessary, determine in good faith
whether a digital product is a digital product of a Party,
of the other Party or of a non-Party. Such determination
shall be made in a transparent, objective, reasonable and
fair manner. 



4. Each Party shall, upon request of the other Party,
explain how it determines the origin of a digital product
where it determines such origin in implementing its
obligations under paragraph 1. 



5. The Parties shall cooperate in internationalorganizations and fora to foster the development ofcriteria for the determination of the origin of a digitalproduct, with a view to considering the incorporation ofsuch criteria into this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.5" name="Electronic Signature" article_identifier="36834">1. Neither Party shall adopt or maintain measures
regulating electronic signature that would: 



(a) prohibit parties to an electronic transaction
from mutually determining the appropriate
electronic signature methods for their
transaction; or 



(b) prevent parties to an electronic transaction from
having the opportunity to prove in court that
their electronic transactions comply with any
legal requirements. 

2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, each Party may require 
that, for a particular category of electronic transactions,
the electronic signatures meet certain performance
standards or are based on a specific electronic certificate
issued by a supplier of certification services accredited
or recognized in accordance with the laws and regulations
of the Party, provided that the requirement: 



(a) serves a legitimate policy objective; and 



(b) is substantially related to achieving that
objective.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.6" name="Consumer Protection" article_identifier="36835">1. The Parties recognize the importance of adopting and
maintaining transparent and effective consumer protection
measures for electronic commerce as well as measures 
conducive to the development of consumer confidence. 



2. The Parties recognize the importance of cooperation
between their respective competent authorities in charge of
consumer protection on activities related to electronic
commerce in order to enhance consumer protection. 



3. The Parties shall adopt or maintain measures, in
accordance with their respective laws and regulations, to
protect the personal data of electronic commerce users.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.7" name="Unsolicited Commercial E-Mail" article_identifier="36836">Each Party shall endeavor to take appropriate and
necessary measures to regulate unsolicited commercial
e-mail for advertising purposes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.8" name="Paperless Trade Administration" article_identifier="36837">1. Each Party shall endeavor to make all trade
administration documents available to the public in
electronic form. 



2. Each Party shall endeavor to accept trade
administration documents submitted electronically as the
legal equivalent of the paper version of such documents. 



3. The Parties shall cooperate bilaterally and in
international fora to enhance the acceptance of electronic
versions of trade administration documents.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.9" name="Domestic Regulation" article_identifier="36838">Each Party shall ensure that all its measures
affecting electronic commerce are administered in a
transparent, objective, reasonable and impartial manner,
and are not more burdensome than necessary to meet
legitimate policy objectives.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.10" name="Prohibition On Requirement Concerning The Location Of Computing Facilities" article_identifier="36839">1. Neither Party shall require: 



(a) a service supplier of the other Party; 



(b) an investor of the other Party; or 



(c) an investment of an investor of the other Party
in the Area of the former Party, 

as a condition for conducting its business in the Area of
the former Party, to use or locate computing facilities in
that Area. 


2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, nothing in this Article
shall be construed to prevent a Party from adopting or
maintaining measures affecting the use or location of
computing facilities necessary to achieve a legitimate
public policy objective, provided that such measures are
not applied in a manner which would constitute a means of
arbitrary or unjustifiable discrimination or a disguised
restriction on trade.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.11" name="Source Code" article_identifier="36840">1. Neither Party shall require the transfer of, or access
to, source code of software owned by a person of the other
Party, as a condition of the import, distribution, sale or
use of such software, or of products containing such
software, in its Area. 



2. For the purposes of this Article, software subject to
paragraph 1 is limited to mass-market software or products
containing such software, and does not include software
used for critical infrastructure.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.12" name="Cooperation" article_identifier="36841">1. The Parties shall, where appropriate, cooperate
bilaterally and participate actively in regional and
multilateral fora to promote the development of electronic
commerce. 



2. The Parties shall, where appropriate, share
information and experiences, including on related laws,
regulations and best practices with respect to electronic
commerce, related to, LQWHUDOLD, consumer confidence,
cyber-security, combatting unsolicited commercial e-mail,
intellectual property, electronic government and personal
data protection. 



3. The Parties shall cooperate to overcome obstacles
encountered by small and medium enterprises in the use of
electronic commerce. 



4. Each Party shall encourage, through existing means
available to it, the activities of non-profit organizations
in that Party aimed at promoting electronic commerce,
including the exchange of information and views. 



5. The Parties recognize the importance of working to
maintain cross-border flows of information as an essential 
element for a vibrant electronic commerce environment. 



6. The Parties recognize the importance of further
enhancement of trade in digital products.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 9.13" name="Sub-Committee On Electronic Commerce" article_identifier="36842">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Electronic Commerce (hereinafter referred
to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) discussing any issues related to this Chapter
including, where appropriate, the possible review
of Article 9.4; 



(c) seeking new opportunities to further enhance
trade in digital products; 



(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 10" name="Investment" chapter_identifier="4251">
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="36843">1. This Chapter shall apply to measures adopted or
maintained by a Party related to: 



(a) investors of the other Party; 



(b) investments of investors of the other Party in
the Area of the former Party; and 



(c) with respect to Articles 10.7 and 10.17, all
investments in the Area of the former Party. 

Note 1: For greater certainty, this Chapter shall also 
apply to measures adopted or maintained by a
Party related to investments made by investors
of the other Party in the Area of the former
Party prior to the entry into force of this
Agreement. 


Note 2: For greater certainty, this Chapter shall not 
apply to claims arising out of events which
occurred prior to the entry into force of this
Agreement. 


2. In the event of any inconsistency between this Chapter
and Chapter 7: 



(a) with respect to matters covered by Articles 10.3,


10.4 and 10.7, Chapter 7 shall prevail to the
extent of the inconsistency; and 


(b) with respect to matters not falling under
subparagraph (a), this Chapter shall prevail to
the extent of the inconsistency. 

3. Nothing in this Chapter shall impose any obligation on
either Party regarding measures pursuant to immigration
laws and regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.2" name="Definitions" article_identifier="36844">For the purposes of this Chapter: 



(a) the term “Bilateral Investment Agreement” means
the Agreement between Japan and Mongolia
concerning the Promotion and Protection of
Investment signed at Tokyo on February 15, 2001; 



(b) an enterprise is: 


(i) “owned” by an investor if more than 50
percent of the equity interest in it is
owned by the investor; and 


(ii) “controlled” by an investor if the investor
has the power to name a majority of its
directors or otherwise to legally direct its
actions; 


(c) the term “existing” means in effect on the date
of entry into force of this Agreement; 



(d) the term “freely usable currency” means freely
usable currency as defined under the Articles of
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(e) 	the term “investment activities” means 
establishment, acquisition, expansion, operation,
management, maintenance, use, enjoyment and sale
or other disposal of an investment; and 



(f) the term “measure” means any measure, whether in
the form of a law, regulation, rule, procedure,
decision, administrative action or any other
form.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.3" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="36845">1. Each Party shall in its Area accord to investors of
the other Party and to their investments treatment no less
favorable than the treatment it accords in like 
circumstances to its own investors and to their investments 
with respect to investment activities. 



2. Paragraph 1 shall not be construed to prevent a Party
from adopting or maintaining a measure that prescribes
special formalities in connection with investment
activities of investors of the other Party in its Area,
provided that such special formalities do not impair the
substance of the rights of such investors under this
Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.4" name="Most-Favored-Nation Treatment" article_identifier="36846">Each Party shall in its Area accord to investors of


the other Party and to their investments treatment no less


favorable than the treatment it accords in like 


circumstances to investors of a non-Party and to their


investments with respect to investment activities.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.5" name="General Treatment" article_identifier="36847">1. Each Party shall in its Area accord to investments of
investors of the other Party treatment in accordance with
international law, including fair and equitable treatment
and full protection and security. 


Note 1: This paragraph prescribes the customary 
international law minimum standard of 
treatment of aliens as the minimum standard of 
treatment to be afforded to investments of 
investors of the other Party. The concepts of
“fair and equitable treatment” and “full
protection and security” do not require
treatment in addition to or beyond that which
is required by the customary international law
minimum standard of treatment of aliens. A 
determination that there has been a breach of 
another provision of this Agreement, or of a
separate international agreement, does not
establish that there has been a breach of this 
paragraph. 


Note 2: “Fair and equitable treatment” includes the 
obligation of the Party not to deny justice in
criminal, civil or administrative adjudicatory
proceedings in accordance with the principle
of due process of law. 



2. Each Party shall observe any written obligation it may
have entered into with respect to a specific investment by
an investor of the other Party, which the investor could
have relied on at the time of establishment, acquisition or
expansion of such investment. 



3. This Article shall apply to taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.6" name="Access To The Courts" article_identifier="36848">1. Each Party shall in its Area accord to investors of
the other Party treatment no less favorable than the
treatment it accords in like circumstances to its own 
investors or to investors of a non-Party with respect to
access to the courts and administrative agencies in all
degrees of jurisdiction, both in pursuit and in defense of
such investors’ rights. 



2. This Article shall apply to taxation measures.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.7" name="Prohibition Of Performance Requirements" article_identifier="36849">1. Neither Party shall impose or enforce any of the
following requirements, or enforce any commitment or
undertaking, in connection with investment activities of an
investor of a Party or of a non-Party in its Area to: 



(a) export a given level or percentage of goods or
services; 



(b) achieve a given level or percentage of domestic
content; 



(c) purchase, use or accord a preference to goods
produced or services provided in its Area, or to
purchase goods or services from persons in its
Area; 



(d) relate in any way the volume or value of imports
to the volume or value of exports or to the
amount of foreign exchange inflows associated
with an investment of the investor; 



(e) restrict sales of goods or services in its Area
that an investment of the investor produces or
provides by relating such sales in any way to the
volume or value of its exports or foreign
exchange earnings; 



(f) restrict the exportation or sale for export; 



(g) appoint, as executives, managers or members of
boards of directors, individuals of any
particular nationality; 



(h) locate the headquarters of that investor for a
specific region or the world market in its Area; 



(i) hire a given number or percentage of its
nationals; 



(j) supply one or more of the goods that the investor
produces or the services that the investor
provides to a specific region or the world
market, exclusively from the Area of the former
Party; or 



(k) adopt: 

(i) given rate or amount of royalty under a
license contract; or 


(ii) a given duration of the term of a license
contract, 


with respect to any license contract freely
entered into between the investor and a person in
its Area, whether it has been entered into or
not, provided that the requirement is imposed or
the commitment or undertaking is enforced by an
exercise of governmental authority of the Party. 


Note: 	A “license contract” referred to in this 
subparagraph means any license contract
concerning transfer of technology, a
production process, or other proprietary
knowledge. 


2. Neither Party shall condition the receipt or continued
receipt of an advantage, in connection with investment
activities of an investor of a Party or of a non-Party in
its Area, on compliance with any of the following
requirements to: 



(a) achieve a given level or percentage of domestic
content; 



(b) purchase, use or accord a preference to goods
produced or services provided in its Area, or to
purchase goods or services from persons in its
Area; 



(c) relate in any way the volume or value of imports
to the volume or value of exports or to the
amount of foreign exchange inflows associated
with an investment of the investor; 



(d) restrict sales of goods or services in its Area
that an investment of the investor produces or
provides by relating such sales in any way to the
volume or value of its exports or foreign
exchange earnings; or 



(e) restrict the exportation or sale for export. 

3. 	(a) Nothing in paragraph 2 shall be construed to 
prevent a Party from conditioning the receipt or
continued receipt of an advantage, in connection
with investment activities of an investor of a 
Party or of a non-Party in its Area, on
compliance with a requirement to locate
production, supply a service, train or employ
workers, construct or expand particular
facilities, or carry out research and
development, in its Area. 



(b) Subparagraph 1(k) shall not apply when the 
requirement is imposed or the commitment or
undertaking is enforced by a court or competition
authority to remedy an alleged violation of laws
controlling the anti-competitive activities. 



(c) Subparagraphs 1(a), 1(b), 1(c), 2(a) and 2(b)
shall not apply to qualification requirements for
goods or services with respect to foreign aid
programs. 



(d) Subparagraphs 2(a) and 2(b) shall not apply to
requirements imposed by an importing Party
related to the content of goods necessary to
qualify for preferential tariffs or preferential
quotas. 

4. Paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply to any requirement
other than the requirements set out in those paragraphs.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.8" name="Non-Conforming Measures" article_identifier="36850">1. Articles 10.3, 10.4 and 10.7 shall not apply to: 



(a) any existing non-conforming measure that is
maintained by the central government of a Party,
as set out in its Schedule in Annex 8; 



(b) any existing non-conforming measure that is
maintained by a local government of a Party; 



(c) the continuation or prompt renewal of any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs


(a) and (b); or 


(d) an amendment or modification to any nonconforming measure referred to in subparagraphs

(a) and (b), to the extent that the amendment or
modification does not decrease the conformity of
the measure, as it existed immediately before the
amendment or modification, with Articles 10.3,


10.4 and 10.7. 



2. If a Party considers that the non-conforming measure 
referred to in subparagraph 1(b) and adopted or maintained
by a prefecture or the city of Ulaanbaatar or a province of
the other Party creates an impediment to investment
activities of an investor of the former Party, that former
Party may request consultations with respect to the
application of that measure with a view to achieving
mutually satisfactory solution. 



3. Articles 10.3, 10.4 and 10.7 shall not apply to any 
measure that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to
sectors, sub-sectors or activities, as set out in its
Schedule in Annex 9. 



4. Neither Party shall, under any measure adopted after
the date of entry into force of this Agreement and covered
by its Schedule in Annex 9, require an investor of the
other Party, by reason of its nationality, to sell or
otherwise dispose of an investment that exists at the time
when the measure becomes effective. 



5. In cases where a Party makes an amendment or a
modification to any existing non-conforming measure set out
in its Schedule in Annex 8 or where a Party adopts any new
or more restrictive measure with respect to sectors, sub-
sectors or activities set out in its Schedule in Annex 9 
after the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the
Party shall, prior to the implementation of the amendment
or modification or the new or more restrictive measure, or
in exceptional circumstances, as soon as possible
thereafter: 



(a) notify the other Party of detailed information on
such amendment, modification or measure; and 



(b) hold, upon request of the other Party,
consultations in good-faith with the other Party
with a view to achieving mutual satisfaction. 


6. Each Party shall endeavor, where appropriate, to
reduce or eliminate the non-conforming measures specified
in its Schedules in Annexes 8 and 9 respectively. 



7. Articles 10.3 and 10.4 shall not apply to any measure
covered by the exceptions to, or derogations from,
obligations under Articles 3 and 4 of the TRIPS Agreement,
as specifically provided in Articles 3 through 5 of the
TRIPS Agreement. 



8. Articles 10.3, 10.4 and 10.7 shall not apply to any 
measure that a Party adopts or maintains with respect to
government procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.9" name="Expropriation And Compensation" article_identifier="36851">1. Neither Party shall expropriate or nationalize an
investment in its Area of investors of the other Party or
take any measure equivalent to expropriation or
nationalization (hereinafter referred to as
“expropriation”) except: 



(a) for a public purpose; 



(b) in a non-discriminatory manner; 



(c) upon payment of prompt, adequate and effective
compensation in accordance with paragraphs 2
through 4; and 



(d) in accordance with due process of law and Article

10.5. 



2. The compensation shall be equivalent to the fair
market value of the expropriated investment at the time
when the expropriation was publicly announced or when the
expropriation took place, whichever is earlier. The fair
market value shall not reflect any change in value
occurring because the intended expropriation had become
publicly known earlier. 



3. The compensation shall be paid without delay and shall
include interest at a commercially reasonable rate, taking
into account the length of time until the time of payment.
It shall be effectively realizable and freely transferable,
and shall be freely convertible into the currency of the
Party of the investors concerned and into freely usable
currencies at the market exchange rate prevailing on the
date of expropriation. 



4. Without prejudice to the provisions of Article 10.13,
the investors affected by expropriation shall have a right
of access to the courts or administrative agencies of the
Party making the expropriation to seek a prompt review of
the investors’ case and the amount of compensation in
accordance with the principles set out in this Article. 



5. This Article shall apply to taxation measures, to the
extent that such taxation measures constitute 
expropriation. 



6. This Article shall be interpreted in accordance with
Annex 10.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.10" name="Protection From Strife" article_identifier="36852">1. Each Party shall accord to investors of the other
Party that have suffered loss or damage related to their
investments in the Area of the former Party due to armed
conflict or a state of emergency such as revolution,
insurrection, civil disturbance or any other similar event
in the Area of that former Party, treatment, as regards
restitution, indemnification, compensation or any other
settlement, that is no less favorable than the treatment it
accords to its own investors or to investors of a non-
Party, whichever is more favorable to the investors of the
other Party. 



2. Any payment as a means of settlement referred to in
paragraph 1 shall be effectively realizable, freely
transferable and freely convertible at the market exchange
rate into the currency of the Party of the investors
concerned and freely usable currencies. 



3. Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 1.10,
neither Party shall be relieved of its obligation under
paragraph 1 by reason of its measures taken in accordance
with that Article.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.11" name="Transfers" article_identifier="36853">1. Each Party shall ensure that all transfers related to
investments in its Area of an investor of the other Party
may be freely made into and out of its Area without delay.
Such transfers shall include, in particular, though not
exclusively: 



(a) the initial capital and additional amounts to
maintain or increase investments; 



(b) profits, interest, capital gains, dividends,
royalties, fees and other current incomes
accruing from investments; 



(c) payments made under a contract including loan
payments in connection with investments; 



(d) 	proceeds of the total or partial sale or 
liquidation of investments; 



(e) earnings and remuneration of personnel from the
other Party engaged in activities in connection
with investments in the Area of the former Party; 



(f) payments made in accordance with Articles 10.9
and 10.10; and 



(g) payments arising out of the settlement of a
dispute under Article 10.13. 


2. Each Party shall further ensure that such transfers
may be made without delay in freely usable currencies at
the market exchange rate prevailing on the date of the
transfer. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraphs 1 and 2, a Party may delay
or prevent a transfer through the equitable, nondiscriminatory and good-faith application of its laws and
regulations related to: 



(a) bankruptcy, insolvency or the protection of the
rights of creditors; 



(b) issuing, trading or dealing in securities; 



(c) criminal or penal offenses; or 



(d) ensuring compliance with orders or judgments in
adjudicatory proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.12" name="Subrogation" article_identifier="36854">If a Party or its designated agency makes a payment to
any investor of that Party under an indemnity, guarantee or
insurance contract, pertaining to an investment of such
investor in the Area of the other Party, the latter Party
shall recognize the assignment to the former Party or its
designated agency of any right or claim of such investor on
account of which such payment is made and shall recognize
the right of the former Party or its designated agency to
exercise by virtue of subrogation any such right or claim
to the same extent as the original right or claim of the
investor. As regards payment to be made to that former
Party or its designated agency by virtue of such assignment
of right or claim and the transfer of such payment, the
provisions of Articles 10.9, 10.10 and 10.11 shall apply.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.13" name="Settlement Of Investment Disputes Between A Party And An Investor Of The Other Party" article_identifier="36855">1. 	For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) the term “disputing investor” means an investor
who is a party to an investment dispute; 



(b) the term “disputing Party” means a Party that is
a party to an investment dispute; 



(c) the term “disputing parties” means the disputing
investor and the disputing Party; 



(d) 	the term “ICSID Convention” means the Convention 
on the Settlement of Investment Disputes between
States and Nationals of Other States, done at
Washington, March 18, 1965; 



(e) 	the term “ICSID Additional Facility Rules” means 
the Rules Governing the Additional Facility for
the Administration of Proceedings by the
Secretariat of the International Centre for 
Settlement of Investment Disputes; 



(f) 	the term “investment dispute” means a dispute 
between a Party and an investor of the other
Party that has incurred loss or damage by reason
of, or arising out of, an alleged breach of any
obligation of the former Party under this Chapter
with respect to the investor of that other Party
or its investment in the Area of the former 
Party; and 



(g) 	the term “New York Convention” means the 
Convention on the Recognition and Enforcement of
Foreign Arbitral Awards, done at New York, June
10, 1958. 


2. Subject to subparagraph 6(a)(i), nothing in this
Article shall be construed to prevent a disputing investor
from seeking administrative or judicial settlement within
the Area of the disputing Party. 



3. An investment dispute shall, as far as possible, be
settled amicably through consultations between the
disputing parties. 



4. If the investment dispute cannot be settled through
such consultations within 120 days from the date on which
the disputing investor requested in writing the disputing
Party for the consultations, the disputing investor may,
subject to paragraph 6, submit the investment dispute to
one of the following international arbitrations: 



(a) 	arbitration in accordance with the ICSID 
Convention, so long as the ICSID Convention is in
force between the Parties; 



(b) arbitration under the ICSID Additional Facility
Rules, provided that either Party, but not both,
is a party to the ICSID Convention; 



(c) 	arbitration under the Arbitration Rules of the 
United Nations Commission on International Trade 
Law; and 



(d) if agreed with the disputing Party, any
arbitration in accordance with other arbitration 
rules. 


5. The applicable arbitration rules shall govern the
arbitration set forth in paragraph 4 except to the extent
modified in this Article. 



6. 	(a) Notwithstanding paragraphs 4 and 8, no claim may 
be submitted to the arbitration set forth in 
paragraph 4 unless: 


(i) the disputing investor gives the disputing
Party written waiver of any right to
initiate before any court under the law of
either Party or other dispute settlement
procedures including the investment dispute
settlement procedures under the Bilateral
Investment Agreement, any proceedings with
respect to any measure of the disputing
Party alleged to constitute a breach
referred to in subparagraph 1(f); and 


(ii) the disputing investor has not initiated
before the investment dispute settlement
procedures under the Bilateral Investment
Agreement, any proceedings with respect to
any measure of the disputing Party alleged
to constitute a breach referred to in 
subparagraph 1(f). 


(b) Notwithstanding subparagraph (a), the disputing
investor may initiate or continue an action that
seeks interim injunctive relief that does not
involve the payment of monetary damages before
any competent court of the disputing Party. 


7. The disputing investor who intends to submit the
investment dispute to arbitration in accordance with
paragraph 4 shall give to the disputing Party written
notice of intent to do so at least 90 days before the
investment dispute is submitted. The notice of intent shall
specify: 



(a) the name and address of the disputing investor; 



(b) the specific measures of the disputing Party at
issue and a brief summary of the factual and
legal basis of the investment dispute sufficient
to present the problem clearly, including the
obligations under this Chapter alleged to have
been breached; 



(c) arbitration set forth in paragraph 4 which the
disputing investor chooses to invoke; and 



(d) the relief sought and the approximate amount of
damages claimed. 


8. 	(a) Each Party hereby consents to the submission of 
investment disputes by a disputing investor to
arbitration set forth in paragraph 4 chosen by
the disputing investor. 


(b) The consent given under subparagraph (a) and the
submission by a disputing investor of an
investment dispute to arbitration shall satisfy
the requirements of: 


(i) Chapter II of the ICSID Convention or the
ICSID Additional Facility Rules, for written
consent of the parties to a dispute; and 


(ii) 	Article II of the New York Convention for an 
agreement in writing. 


9. Notwithstanding paragraph 8, no investment disputes
may be submitted to arbitration set forth in paragraph 4,
if more than three years have elapsed since the date on
which the disputing investor acquired or should have first
acquired, whichever is the earlier, the knowledge that the
disputing investor had incurred loss or damage referred to
in subparagraph 1(f). 



10. Unless the disputing parties otherwise agree, an
arbitral tribunal established under paragraph 4 shall
comprise three arbitrators, one arbitrator appointed by
each of the disputing parties and the third, who shall be
the presiding arbitrator, appointed by agreement of the
disputing parties. If the disputing investor or the
disputing Party fails to appoint an arbitrator or
arbitrators within 60 days from the date on which the
investment dispute was submitted to arbitration, the
Secretary-General of the International Centre for
Settlement of Investment Disputes in the case of
arbitration referred to in subparagraph 4(a) or 4(b), or
the Secretary-General of the Permanent Court of
Arbitration, at The Hague in the case of arbitration
referred to in subparagraph 4(c) or 4(d), may be requested
by either of the disputing parties, to appoint the
arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed, subject to the
requirements of paragraph 11. 



11. Unless the disputing parties otherwise agree, the
third arbitrator shall not be a national of either Party,
nor have his or her usual place of residence in either
Party, nor be employed by either of the disputing parties,
nor have dealt with the investment dispute in any capacity. 



12. Unless the disputing parties otherwise agree, the
arbitration shall be held in a country that is a party to
the New York Convention. 



13. An arbitral tribunal established under paragraph 4
shall decide the issues in dispute in accordance with this
Chapter and other provisions of this Agreement as
applicable and applicable rules of international law. 



14. The disputing Party shall deliver to the other Party: 



(a) written notice of the investment dispute
submitted to the arbitration no later than 30 
days after the date on which the investment
dispute was submitted; and 



(b) copies of all pleadings filed in the arbitration. 


15. The Party which is not the disputing Party may, upon
written notice to the disputing parties, make submissions
to the arbitral tribunal on a question of interpretation of
this Chapter and other provisions of this Agreement as
applicable. 



16. The arbitral tribunal may order an interim measure of
protection to preserve the rights of the disputing
investor, or to facilitate the conduct of arbitral
proceedings, including an order to preserve evidence in the
possession or control of either of the disputing parties.
The arbitral tribunal shall not order attachment or enjoin
the application of the measure alleged to constitute a
breach referred to in subparagraph 1(f). 



17. Before ruling on the merits, the arbitral tribunal
shall address and, if warranted, decide as a preliminary
question any objection by the disputing Party to the
jurisdiction of the arbitral tribunal and to the
admissibility of the claim of the disputing investor. When
the arbitral tribunal decides such an objection as a
preliminary question, it may, if warranted, award to the
prevailing disputing party reasonable costs and attorney’s
fees incurred in submitting or opposing the objection. In
determining whether such an award is warranted, the
arbitral tribunal shall consider whether either the 
disputing investor’s claim or the disputing Party’s
objection was frivolous. In doing so, the arbitral tribunal
shall provide the disputing parties a reasonable
opportunity to comment. 



18. The arbitral tribunal may award only: 



(a) a judgment whether or not there has been a breach
by the disputing Party of any obligation under
this Chapter with respect to the disputing
investor and its investment; and 



(b) one or both of the following remedies, only if
there has been such a breach: 

(i) monetary damages and applicable interest;
and 


(ii) restitution of property, in which case the
award shall provide that the disputing Party
may pay monetary damages and any applicable
interest, in lieu of restitution. 


The arbitral tribunal may also award costs and
attorneys’ fees in accordance with this Article and the
applicable arbitration rules. 


19. The disputing Party may make available to the public
in a timely manner all documents, including an award,
submitted to, or issued by, an arbitral tribunal
established under paragraph 4, subject to redaction of: 



(a) 	confidential business information; 



(b) information which is privileged or otherwise
protected from disclosure under the applicable
laws and regulations of either Party; and 



(c) 	information which shall be withheld in accordance 
with the relevant arbitration rules. 


20. The award rendered by the arbitral tribunal shall be
final and binding upon the disputing parties. This award
shall be executed in accordance with the applicable laws
and regulations, as well as relevant international law
including the ICSID Convention and the New York Convention,
concerning the execution of award in force in the country
where such execution is sought. 



21. Neither Party shall give diplomatic protection, or
bring an international claim, with respect to an investment
dispute which the other Party and an investor of the former
Party have consented to submit or submitted to arbitration
set forth in paragraph 4, unless the other Party has failed
to abide by and comply with the award rendered in such
investment dispute. Diplomatic protection, for the purposes
of this paragraph, shall not include informal diplomatic
exchanges for the sole purpose of facilitating a settlement
of the investment dispute. 



22. This Article shall apply to disputes regarding
taxation measures to the extent covered by Article 10.5,

10.6 or 10.9.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.14" name="Temporary Safeguard Measures" article_identifier="36856">1. A Party may adopt or maintain restrictive measures
with respect to cross-border capital transactions as well
as payment and transfers related to investments: 



(a) in the event of serious balance-of-payments and
external financial difficulties or threat 
thereof; or 



(b) in exceptional cases where movements of capital
cause or threaten to cause serious difficulties 
for macroeconomic management, in particular
monetary and exchange rate policies. 

2. 	Restrictive measures referred to in paragraph 1: 



(a) 	shall be applied on the basis of national 
treatment and most-favored-nation treatment; 



(b) 	shall be consistent with the Articles of 
Agreement of the International Monetary Fund; 



(c) shall avoid unnecessary damage to the commercial,
economic and financial interests of the other 
Party; 



(d) shall not exceed those necessary to deal with the
circumstances described in paragraph 1; and 



(e) shall be temporary and be phased out
progressively as the situation specified in
paragraph 1 improves. 


3. Any restrictions adopted or maintained in accordance
with paragraph 1, or any changes therein, shall be promptly
notified to the other Party. 



4. Nothing in this Article shall be construed to alter
the rights enjoyed and obligations undertaken by a Party as
a party to the Articles of Agreement of the International
Monetary Fund.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.15" name="Prudential Measures" article_identifier="36857">1. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this Chapter,
a Party shall not be prevented from adopting or maintaining
measures related to financial services for prudential
reasons, including measures for the protection of
investors, depositors, policy holders or persons to whom a
fiduciary duty is owed by an enterprise supplying financial
services, or to ensure the integrity and stability of its
financial system. 



2. Where the measures adopted or maintained by a Party in
accordance with paragraph 1 do not conform with this
Chapter, they shall not be used as a means of avoiding the
obligations of the Party under this Chapter.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.16" name="Denial Of Benefits" article_identifier="36858">1. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an
investor of the other Party that is an enterprise of the
other Party and to its investment if the enterprise is
owned or controlled by an investor of a non-Party and the
denying Party: 



(a) does not maintain diplomatic relations with the
non-Party; or 



(b) adopts or maintains measures with respect to the
non-Party that prohibit transactions with the
enterprise or that would be violated or
circumvented if the benefits of this Chapter were
accorded to the enterprise or to its investment. 

2. A Party may deny the benefits of this Chapter to an
investor of the other Party that is an enterprise of the
other Party and to its investment if the enterprise is
owned or controlled by an investor of a non-Party and the
enterprise has no substantial business activities in the
Area of the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.17" name="Health, Safety And Environmental Measures And Labor Standards" article_identifier="36859">The Parties shall refrain from encouraging investment
by investors of each Party or of a non-Party by relaxing
their respective health, safety or environmental measures
or by lowering its labor standards. To this effect each
Party should not waive or otherwise derogate from such
measures or standards as an encouragement for the
establishment, acquisition or expansion in its Area of
investments by investors of each Party or of a non-Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.18" name="Sub-Committee On Investment" article_identifier="36860">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Investment (hereinafter referred to in
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) exchanging information on any matters related to
this Chapter; 



(c) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(d) reporting the findings and the outcome of
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee may invite representatives of 
relevant entities other than the Governments of the Parties 
with the necessary expertise relevant to the issues to be
discussed. 



5. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties. 



6. This Article shall apply to matters regarding taxation 
measures to the extent covered by Article 10.5, 10.6 or

10.9.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.19" name="Relation To The Bilateral Investment Agreement" article_identifier="36861">1. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of Article 17 of the
Bilateral Investment Agreement, the Bilateral Investment
Agreement shall be terminated upon the date of entry into
force of this Agreement. 



2. The Parties confirm that with respect to investments
and returns acquired prior to the date of termination of
the Bilateral Investment Agreement, the provisions of
Articles 1 through 16 of the Bilateral Investment Agreement
shall continue to be effective for a further period of 15
years from that date in accordance with paragraph 3 of
Article 17 of the Bilateral Investment Agreement. 



3. For the purposes of paragraph 2, nothing in this 
Agreement shall affect the rights and obligations of a
Party under the relevant provisions of the Bilateral
Investment Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 10.20" name="Duration And Termination" article_identifier="36862">With respect to investments acquired prior to the date
of termination of this Agreement, the provisions of this
Chapter, as well as provisions of this Agreement which are
directly related to this Chapter, shall continue to be
effective for a period of 10 years from the date of
termination of this Agreement.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 11" name="Competition" chapter_identifier="4252">
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.1" name="Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="36863">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take measures which it considers appropriate
against anticompetitive activities, in order to facilitate
trade and investment flows between the Parties through the
efficient functioning of its markets. 



2. For the purposes of this Chapter, the term
“anticompetitive activities” means any conduct or
transaction that may be subject to penalties or relief
under the competition laws and regulations of the
respective Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.2" name="Cooperation On Controlling Anticompetitive Activities" article_identifier="36864">1. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, cooperate and assist each other for
controlling anticompetitive activitieswithin their 
respective available resources. 



2. The details and procedures concerning the
implementation of cooperation under this Article shall be
specified in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.3" name="Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="36865">Each Party shall apply its competition laws and
regulations in a manner which does not discriminate between
persons in like circumstances on the basis of their
nationality.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.4" name="Procedural Fairness" article_identifier="36866">Each Party shall implement administrative and judicial
procedures in a fair manner to control anticompetitive
activities, in accordance with its relevant laws and
regulations.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.5" name="Transparency" article_identifier="36867">Each Party shall promote transparency of the
implementation of its competition laws and regulations and
its competition policy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 11.6" name="Non-Application Of Paragraph 2 Of Article 1.8 And Chapter 16" article_identifier="36868">Paragraph 2 of Article 1.8 and Chapter 16 shall not
apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 12" name="Intellectual Property" chapter_identifier="4253">
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.1" name="General Provisions" article_identifier="36869">1. The Parties shall grant and ensure adequate, effective
and non-discriminatory protection of intellectual property
and provide for measures for the enforcement of
intellectual property rights against infringement thereof,
in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and the
international agreements related to intellectual property
to which both Parties are party. 



2. The Parties shall also promote efficiency and
transparency in the administration of intellectual property
system. 



3. Nothing in this Chapter shall derogate from existing
rights and obligations that the Parties have under the
TRIPS Agreement or other international agreements related
to intellectual property to which both Parties are party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.2" name="Definition" article_identifier="36870">The term “intellectual property” referred to in this

that are under the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.3" name="National Treatment" article_identifier="36871">Each Party shall accord to nationals of the other
Party treatment no less favorable than the treatment it
accords to its own nationals with regard to the protection
of intellectual property in accordance with Articles 3 and
5 of the TRIPS Agreement. 


Note: For the purposes of this Article: 



(a) the term “nationals” shall have the same meaning
as in the TRIPS Agreement; 



(b) the term “protection” shall include matters
affecting the availability, acquisition, scope,
maintenance and enforcement of intellectual 
property rights as well as those matters
affecting the use of intellectual property
rights specifically addressed in this Chapter;
and 



(c) for greater certainty, the term “protection of
intellectual property” shall include the
repression of unfair competition as provided for
in Article 12.12.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.4" name="Procedural Matters" article_identifier="36872">1. For the purposes of providing efficient administration
of intellectual property system, each Party shall take
appropriate measures to improve its administrative
procedures concerning intellectual property rights. 



2. Neither Party shall require the authentication of
signatures or other means of self-identification on
documents to be submitted to the competent authority of the
Party, including applications, translations into a language
accepted by such authority of any earlier application whose
priority is claimed, powers of attorney and certifications
of assignment, in the course of application procedure or
other administrative procedures on patents, utility models,
industrial designs or trademarks. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, a Party may require: 



(a) the authentication of signatures or other means
of self-identification, if the law of the Party
so provides, where the signatures or other means
of self-identification concern the surrender of a 
patent or a registration of utility models,
industrial designs or trademarks; and 



(b) 	the submission of evidence if there is reasonable 
doubt as to the authenticity of signatures or
other means of self-identification on documents 
submitted to the competent authority of the
Party. Where the competent authority notifies the
person that the submission of evidence is
required, the notification shall state the reason
for requiring the submission. 


4. Neither Party shall require that the submission of a
power of attorney be completed together with the filing of
the application as a condition for according a filing date
to the application. 



5. Each Party shall endeavor to improve patent attorney
or registered intellectual property rights authorized
representative system. 



6. Where the acquisition of an intellectual property
right is subject to the right being granted or registered,
each Party shall ensure that, irrespective of whether an
application for the granting or registration of an
intellectual property right is filed as a national or as an
international application in accordance with the applicable
international agreement, the procedures for granting or
registration of the right, subject to compliance with the
substantive conditions for acquisition of the right,
provide the granting or registration within a reasonable
period of time so as to avoid undue curtailment of the
period of protection. 



7. Each Party shall provide a system for the registration
of trademarks, industrial designs and patents which shall
include: 



(a) a requirement to provide to the applicant a
communication in writing, which may be
electronic, of the decision with reasons for a
refusal of the application; 



(b) an opportunity for the applicant to appeal
against administrative refusal; 



(c) an opportunity for the applicant to ask for
judicial review of the final administrative
refusal; and 



(d) 	an opportunity for interested parties, if so 
provided in its laws and regulations: 

(i) to petition to oppose an application or a
registration; and 


(ii) 	to seek cancellation or invalidation of the 
registration.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.5" name="Transparency" article_identifier="36873">For the purposes of further promoting transparency in
the administration of its intellectual property system,
each Party shall take appropriate measures available to the
extent possible in accordance with its laws and regulations
to: 


(a) publish information on, at least: 


(i) intention to grant patents, or applications
for and grant of patents; 


(ii) registrations of utility models; 


(iii) intention to grant rights of industrial
designs, or registrations of industrial
designs; and 


(iv) registrations of trademarks and/or 
applications therefor, 


and provide the relevant information contained in
the files thereof at least to interested persons
upon request; and 


(b) make available to the public information on its
efforts to ensure effective enforcement of 
intellectual property rights and other
information with respect to its intellectual
property system.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.6" name="Promotion Of Public Awareness Concerning Protection Of Intellectual Property" article_identifier="36874">The Parties shall take necessary measures to enhance
public awareness of protection of intellectual property
including educational and dissemination projects on the use
of intellectual property as well as on the enforcement of
intellectual property rights.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.7" name="Patents" article_identifier="36875">1. Each Party shall ensure that any patent application is
not rejected solely on the ground that the subject matter
claimed in the application is related to a computer
program. Nevertheless, the provision of this Article shall
not prejudice the autonomy of each Party to exclude from
patentability computer programs as such in accordance with
the laws and regulations of each Party. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that an applicant may, on its
own initiative, divide a patent application containing more
than one invention into a certain number of divisional 
patent applications within the time limit provided for in
the laws and regulations of the Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.8" name="Industrial Designs" article_identifier="36876">Each Party shall provide adequate and effective
protection of industrial designs of an article as a whole,
and, where appropriate, of a part thereof.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.9" name="Trademarks" article_identifier="36877">1. Each Party shall refuse or cancel the registration of
a trademark, which is identical or similar to a trademark
well-known in either Party as indicating the goods or
services of the owner of the well-known trademark, if use
of that trademark is for unfair intentions, LQWHUDOLD,
intention to gain an unfair profit or intention to cause
damage to the owner of the well-known trademark, and/or if
such use would result in a likelihood of confusion. 


Note: Each Party may determine in accordance with its 
laws and regulations whether a trademark is a
well-known trademark. 


 

2. Each Party shall ensure that an applicant may file a
request to the competent authority that examination of its
application for registration of a trademark be accelerated,
subject to reasonable grounds and procedural requirements.
Where such a request has been filed, the competent
authority shall, where appropriate, accelerate the
examination of the application.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.10" name="Copyright And Related Rights" article_identifier="36878">1. Each Party shall provide to authors, performers and
producers of phonograms the right to authorize the making
available to the public of their works, performances fixed
in phonograms and phonograms respectively, by wire or
wireless means, in such a way that members of the public
may access them from a place and at a time individually
chosen by them. 



2. Each Party shall provide to broadcasting organizations
the right to prohibit the following acts when undertaken
without their consent: 



(a) the rebroadcasting of their broadcasts; 



(b) the fixation of their broadcasts; or 



(c) the reproduction of fixations of their
broadcasts. 


3. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws and
regulations, take appropriate measures to facilitate the
activities to be conducted by the collective management
organizations for copyright and related rights in that
Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.11" name="Geographical Indications" article_identifier="36879">Each Party shall ensure adequate and effective
protection of geographical indications in accordance with
its laws and regulations and with the TRIPS Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.12" name="Unfair Competition" article_identifier="36880">1. Each Party shall provide for effective protection
against acts of unfair competition in accordance with
Article 10 ELV of the Paris Convention. 



2. Each Party shall ensure that provisions of Article 10
ELV of the Paris Convention shall apply PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV 
with respect to services. 



3. For the purposes of this Article, the term “Paris
Convention” means the Paris Convention for the Protection 
of Industrial Property of March 20, 1883, as revised at
Brussels on December 14, 1900, at Washington on June 2,
1911, at The Hague on November 6, 1925, at London on June
2, 1934, at Lisbon on October 31, 1958, and at Stockholm on
July 14, 1967 and as amended on September 28, 1979.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.13" name="Protection Of Undisclosed Information" article_identifier="36881">Each Party shall ensure, in its laws and regulations,
adequate and effective protection of undisclosed
information in accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 39 of
the TRIPS Agreement including not taking measures that
limit the duration of protection of the undisclosed
information stipulated in private contracts, or measures
that force the disclosure of undisclosed information 
without legitimate reasons.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.14" name="Enforcement – Border Measures" article_identifier="36882">1. Each Party shall adopt or maintain procedures with
respect to import shipments under which: 



(a) its customs authorities may act upon their own
initiative to suspend the release of goods
suspected of infringing rights to trademarks
and/or copyrights and related rights (hereinafter
referred to in this Article as “suspected
goods”); and 



(b) a right holder may request that Party’s competent
authorities to suspend the release of suspected
goods. 


2. Each Party shall adopt or maintain procedures by which
its competent authorities may determine, within a
reasonable period after the initiation of the procedures
described in paragraph 1, whether the suspected goods
infringe rights to trademarks and/or copyrights and related
rights. 



3. In the case of the suspension with respect to import
shipments in accordance with paragraph 1, the importer and
the right holder shall be promptly notified of the
suspension and shall be provided with all the information
available about suspected goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.15" name="Enforcement – Civil Remedies" article_identifier="36883">Each Party shall ensure that a right holder of
intellectual property has the right to claim against the
infringer damages adequate to compensate for the injury the
right holder has suffered because of an infringement of
that person’s intellectual property right by an infringer
who knowingly, or with reasonable grounds to know, engaged
in infringing activity.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.16" name="Enforcement – Criminal Remedies" article_identifier="36884">1. Each Party shall provide for criminal procedures and
penalties to be applied at least in cases of willful
trademark counterfeiting or copyright piracy on a
commercial scale in accordance with Article 61 of the TRIPS 
Agreement. 



2. With respect to the offences specified in paragraph 1,
each Party shall provide that its competent authorities
have the authority in accordance with its laws and
regulations to order the forfeiture or destruction of all
infringing goods.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.17" name="Enforcement – In The Digital Environment" article_identifier="36885">Each Party’s enforcement procedures shall apply to
infringement of copyright or related rights over digital
networks, which may include the unlawful use of means of
widespread distribution for infringing purposes. These
procedures shall be implemented in a manner that avoids the
creation of barriers to legitimate activity, including
electronic commerce, and, consistent with the laws and
regulations of that Party, preserves fundamental principles
such as freedom of expression, fair process and privacy.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.18" name="Sub-Committee On Intellectual Property" article_identifier="36886">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Intellectual Property (hereinafter
referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) discussing any issues related to intellectual
property with a view to enhancing protection of
intellectual property and enforcement of
intellectual property rights in accordance with
the provisions of this Chapter and to promoting
efficient and transparent administration of
intellectual property system; 



(c) reporting the findings and the outcome of
discussions of the Sub-Committee to the Joint 
Committee; and 



(d) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 12.19" name="Security Exceptions" article_identifier="36887">For the purposes of this Chapter, Article 73 of the
TRIPS Agreement is incorporated into and forms part of this
Agreement, PXWDWLVPXWDQGLV.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 13" name="Government Procurement" chapter_identifier="4254">
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.1" name="Procurement Principle" article_identifier="36888">Recognizing the importance of government procurement
in furthering the expansion of production and trade so as
to promote growth and employment, each Party shall ensure
transparency of the measures regarding government
procurement in accordance with its laws and regulations.
The Parties also recognize the need to take into account
the development, financial and trade needs of the Parties.
Each Party shall ensure a fair and effective implementation
of the measures regarding government procurement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.2" name="Exchange Of Information" article_identifier="36889">The Parties shall at the central government level,
subject to their respective laws and regulations, exchange
information, to the extent possible in the English language
and in a timely manner, on their respective laws and
regulations, policies and practices on government
procurement, as well as on any reforms to their existing
government procurement regimes.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.3" name="Further Negotiations" article_identifier="36890">The Parties shall enter into negotiations to review
this Chapter with a view to achieving a comprehensive
Chapter on Government Procurement, when Mongolia expresses
its intention to become a party to the Agreement on
Government Procurement in Annex 4 to the WTO Agreement
(hereinafter referred to in this Article as “the GPA”). 


Note: If the GPA is amended or is superseded by another 


agreement, “the GPA”, for the purposes of this


Article, shall refer to the GPA as amended or such


other agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.4" name="Negotiation On Non-Discrimination" article_identifier="36891">In the event that, after the entry into force of this
Agreement, a Party offers a non-Party any advantages of
access to its government procurement market or any
advantageous treatment concerning the measures regarding
government procurement, the former Party shall, upon
request of the other Party, afford adequate opportunity to
enter into negotiations with the other Party with a view to
extending these advantages or advantageous treatment to the
other Party on a reciprocal basis.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 13.5" name="Sub-Committee On Government Procurement" article_identifier="36892">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Government Procurement (hereinafter
referred to in this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the implementation and
operation of this Chapter; 



(b) analyzing available information on each Party’s
government procurement market; 



(c) cooperating on e-procurement and human resource
development; 



(d) reporting the findings of the Sub-Committee to
the Joint Committee; and 



(e) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 14" name="Improvement Of The Business Environment" chapter_identifier="4255">
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.1" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="36893">1. Each Party shall, in accordance with its laws andregulations㸪take appropriate measures to further improvethe business environment for the persons of the other Party

conducting their business activities in the former Party. 


2. The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, promote cooperation to further
improve the business environment in the respective Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.2" name="Sub-Committee On Improvement Of The Business Environment" article_identifier="36894">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Improvement of the Business Environment
(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “the Sub-
Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing findings reported by a Liaison Office 
on Improvement of the Business Environment
(hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as “the
Liaison Office”) to be designated by each Party
in accordance with Article 14.3; 



(b) addressing, and seeking ways to promptly resolve, 
issues related to the business environment on its 
own initiative or based on the findings reported
by the Liaison Office; 



(c) reporting its findings and making 
recommendations, including those on measures that
should be taken by the Parties, to the Parties; 



(d) reviewing, where appropriate, the measures taken 
by the Parties related to such recommendations
referred to in subparagraph (c); 



(e) making available to the public, in an appropriate
manner, the recommendations referred to in
subparagraph (c) and the results of the review
referred to in subparagraph (d); 



(f) cooperating, in an appropriate manner, with other
Sub-Committees established under this Agreement,
with a view to avoiding unnecessary duplication
of works. The forms of such cooperation may
include: 


(i) informing the results of its consideration
to such other Sub-Committees; 


(ii) seeking opinions from such other Sub-
Committees; 


(iii) inviting to the Sub-Committee the members of
such other Sub-Committees; and 


(iv) where appropriate, transferring the relevant
issues to such other Sub-Committees; 


(g) reporting promptly the findings and
recommendations referred to in subparagraph (c)
to the Joint Committee; and 



(h) carrying out other functions as may be delegated 
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties including officials of
relevant Ministries or Agencies in charge of the issues to
be addressed. The Sub-Committee may invite representatives
of relevant entities other than the Governments of the 
Parties with the necessary expertise relevant to the issues
to be addressed. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.3" name="Liaison Office" article_identifier="36895">1. Each Party shall designate and maintain a Liaison
Office for the purposes of this Chapter. 



2. The functions and other details of the Liaison Office 
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 14.4" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="36896">Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 15" name="Cooperation" chapter_identifier="4256">
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.1" name="Basic Principles" article_identifier="36897">The Parties shall, in accordance with their respective
laws and regulations, promote cooperation under this
Agreement for their mutual benefit, in order to further
liberalize and facilitate trade in goods and services as
well as investment between the Parties and to promote the
well-being of the people and sustainable development of the
Parties. For this purpose, the Parties shall enhance
further cooperation between their Governments, and
encourage and facilitate mutual cooperation between
relevant entities of the Parties, one or both of whom are
entities other than the Governments of the Parties, in the
following fields: 



(a) agriculture, forestry and fisheries, including
matters related to SPS measures referred to in 
Chapter 5; 



(b) manufacturing industry, including matters related
to technical regulations, standards and
conformity assessment procedures referred to in
Chapter 6; 



(c) small and medium enterprises; 



(d) 	trade and investment; 



(e) 	infrastructure, construction and urban
development; 



(f) science and technology and intellectual property; 



(g) 	financial services; 



(h) education and human resource development; 



(i) 	tourism; 



(j) 	environment; 



(k) mining and energy; 



(l) healthcare; 



(m) competition; 



(n) information and communications technology; and 



(o) other fields to be mutually agreed upon by the
Governments of the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.2" name="Areas And Forms Of Cooperation" article_identifier="36898">The areas and forms of cooperation under this Chapter
shall be set forth in the Implementing Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.3" name="Costs Of Cooperation" article_identifier="36899">1. The Parties shall initiate discussion, after the entry
into force of this Agreement, to explore potential
cooperation activities in the fields referred to in Article


15.1 and to ensure timely, efficient and effective
implementation of cooperation activities under this
Chapter.



 



2. The Parties shall endeavor to make available the 
necessary funds and other resources for the implementation
of cooperation under this Chapter in accordance with their
respective laws and regulations. 



3. Costs for cooperation under this Chapter shall be
borne in such a manner to be mutually agreed upon by the
Parties through efficient and effective utilization of
funds and resources.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.4" name="Sub-Committee On Cooperation" article_identifier="36900">1. For the purposes of the effective implementation and
operation of this Chapter, the Parties hereby establish a
Sub-Committee on Cooperation (hereinafter referred to in
this Article as “the Sub-Committee”). 



2. The functions of the Sub-Committee shall be: 



(a) reviewing and monitoring the effective
implementation and operation of this Chapter; 



(b) exchanging information on cooperation in each of
the fields referred to in Article 15.1; 



(c) identifying ways for further cooperation between
the Parties; 



(d) discussing any issues related to this Chapter; 



(e) discussing proposals on cooperation presented by
other Sub-Committees established under this 
Agreement; 



(f) making recommendations to the Joint Committee,
where appropriate, on cooperation activities
under this Chapter; 



(g) reporting to the Joint Committee the findings and
outcome of discussions of the Sub-Committee 
regarding the implementation of this Chapter,
including the measures to be taken by the
Parties; and 



(h) carrying out other functions as may be delegated
by the Joint Committee. 


3. The Sub-Committee shall, where appropriate, recognize 
and share information with the Parties’ existing
consultation mechanisms for Official Development Assistance
and other cooperation schemes to ensure timely, effective
and efficient implementation of cooperation activities
under this Agreement. 



4. The Sub-Committee shall be composed of representatives 
of the Governments of the Parties. The Sub-Committee may
invite representatives of relevant entities other than the
Governments of the Parties with the necessary expertise
relevant to the issues to be discussed. 



5. The Sub-Committee shall hold meetings at such times 
and venues or by means, as may be agreed by the Parties.
The Sub-Committee shall endeavor to hold the first meeting
within one year after the entry into force of this
Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 15.5" name="Non-Application Of Chapter 16" article_identifier="36901">Chapter 16 shall not apply to this Chapter.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 16" name="Dispute Settlement" chapter_identifier="4257">
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.1" name="Scope" article_identifier="36902">Unless otherwise provided for in this Agreement, the
dispute settlement procedure of this Chapter shall apply
with respect to the avoidance and the settlement of
disputes between the Parties arising out of the
interpretation and/or application of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.2" name="General Principle" article_identifier="36903">The Parties shall at all times endeavor to agree on
the interpretation and application of this Agreement. They
shall make every attempt through cooperation, consultations
or other means to arrive at a prompt and mutually
satisfactory resolution of any matter concerning the
interpretation and/or application of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.3" name="Choice Of Forum" article_identifier="36904">1. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights of
the Parties to have recourse to dispute settlement
procedures available under any other international
agreement to which both Parties are party, including the
WTO Agreement. The complaining Party may select the forum
in which to settle the dispute. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1, once the complaining
Party has requested the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal under this Chapter or any other international
agreement to which both Parties are party, including a
panel under the Understanding on Rules and Procedures
Governing the Settlement of Disputes in Annex 2 to the WTO
Agreement with respect to a particular dispute, the
arbitral tribunal or panel selected shall be used to the
exclusion of any other procedure for that particular
dispute.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.4" name="Consultations" article_identifier="36905">1. Either Party may request in writing consultations to
the other Party with respect to any matter on the
interpretation and/or application of this Agreement. 



2. In the request for consultations referred to in
paragraph 1, the complaining Party shall set out the
reasons for the request, including identification of the
measure at issue and an indication of the legal and factual
basis of the complaint. 



3. The Party complained against shall promptly respond in
writing to such request and enter into consultations with
the complaining Party in good faith within 40 days after
the date of receipt of the request. In cases of urgency,
including those which concern perishable goods, the Party
complained against shall enter into consultations within 20
days after the date of receipt of the request. 



4. The Parties shall make every effort to arrive at a
mutually satisfactory resolution of the matter through
consultations under this Article. During the consultations
the Parties shall provide to each other sufficient
information to enable a full examination of the matter. 



5. During the consultations under this Article, the
Parties shall endeavor to make available personnel of their
relevant agencies and organizations with expertise in the
matter subject to the consultations. 



6. The consultations under this Article shall be 
confidential and without prejudice to the rights of either
Party in any further proceedings. 



7. The consultations under this Article may be held in
person or by any technological means available to the
Parties upon agreement by the Parties. If the Parties agree
to hold consultations in person, the consultations shall be
held in a venue agreed upon by the Parties, or if there is
no agreement on the venue, in the capital of the Party
complained against.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.5" name="Good Offices, Conciliation Or Mediation" article_identifier="36906">1. Good offices, conciliation or mediation may be
requested at any time by either Party. They may begin at
any time by agreement of the Parties, and be terminated at
any time upon request of either Party. 



2. If the Parties agree, good offices, conciliation or
mediation may continue while procedures of the arbitral
tribunal provided for in this Chapter are in progress. 



3. Proceedings involving good offices, conciliation or
mediation and positions taken by the Parties during these
proceedings shall be confidential and without prejudice to
the rights of either Party in any further proceedings.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.6" name="Establishment Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="36907">1. The complaining Party may request in writing the
establishment of an arbitral tribunal to the Party
complained against if: 



(a) the Party complained against does not enter into
consultations under Article 16.4 within 40 days,
or within 20 days in cases of urgency, including
those which concern perishable goods, after the
date of receipt of the request for such
consultations; or 



(b) the Parties fail to resolve the dispute through
consultations under Article 16.4 within 60 days,
or within 30 days in cases of urgency, including
those which concern perishable goods, after the
date of receipt of the request for such
consultations, 

provided that the complaining Party considers that any
benefit accruing to it directly or indirectly under this
Agreement is being nullified or impaired as a result of the
failure of the Party complained against to carry out its
obligations under this Agreement, or as a result of the
application by the Party complained against of measures
which are in conflict with its obligations under this
Agreement. 


2. Any request to establish an arbitral tribunal in
accordance with this Article shall identify the reasons for
the request including: 



(a) the legal basis of the complaint including the
provisions of this Agreement alleged to have been
breached and any other relevant provisions of the
applicable international law; and 



(b) the factual basis of the complaint.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.7" name="Composition Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="36908">1. An arbitral tribunal shall comprise three arbitrators,
who should have relevant technical or legal expertise. 



2. Each Party shall, within 30 days after the date of
receipt of the request for the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal, appoint one arbitrator who may be its national
and propose up to three candidates to serve as the third
arbitrator who shall be the chair of the arbitral tribunal. 
The third arbitrator shall not be a national of either 
Party, nor have his or her usual place of residence in
either Party, nor be employed by either Party, nor have
dealt with the dispute in any capacity. 



3. The Parties shall endeavor to agree on and appoint the
third arbitrator within 45 days after the date of receipt
of the request for the establishment of an arbitral
tribunal, taking into account the candidates proposed in
accordance with paragraph 2. 



4. If a Party has not appointed the one arbitrator in
accordance with paragraph 2, or if the Parties fail to
agree on the third arbitrator in accordance with paragraph
3, the arbitrator or arbitrators not yet appointed shall be
chosen within 10 days by lot from the candidates proposed
in accordance with paragraph 2. 



5. The date of the establishment of an arbitral tribunal 
shall be the date on which the chair is appointed. 



6. If an arbitrator appointed under this Article resigns,
dies or otherwise becomes unable to act, a replacement
arbitrator shall be appointed in the same manner as
prescribed for the appointment of the original arbitrator.
The replacement arbitrator shall have all the powers and
duties of the original arbitrator. The work of the arbitral
tribunal shall be suspended until the replacement
arbitrator is appointed.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.8" name="Functions Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="36909">1. The functions of the arbitral tribunal established in 
accordance with Articles 16.6 and 16.7 shall be to: 



(a) make an objective assessment of the matter before
it, including an objective assessment of the
facts of the case and the applicability of and
conformity with this Agreement; 



(b) consult regularly with the Parties offering them
equal opportunities for such consultations and
provide adequate opportunities for the
development of a mutually satisfactory
resolution; 



(c) 	make its award in accordance with this Agreement 
and applicable rules of international law; 



(d) 	include in its award, its findings of law and 
fact, together with the reasons for the findings;
and 



(e) attach to its award suggested implementation
options including suggested period of time for
implementing the award, for the Parties to
consider in conjunction with Article 16.11, if
requested by either Party.

 


2. The arbitral tribunal may seek, from the Parties, such
relevant information as it considers necessary and
appropriate. The Parties shall respond promptly and fully
to any request by the arbitral tribunal for such
information as the arbitral tribunal considers necessary
and appropriate. 



3. The arbitral tribunal may seek information from any
relevant source and may consult experts to obtain their
opinion on certain aspects of the matter. With respect to
factual issues concerning a scientific or other technical
matter raised by a Party, the arbitral tribunal may request
advisory reports in writing from experts. 



4. Any information obtained by the arbitral tribunal in
accordance with paragraph 3 shall be made available to the
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.9" name="Proceedings Of Arbitral Tribunals" article_identifier="36910">1. The arbitral tribunal shall meet in closed session. 
The Parties shall be present at the meetings only when
invited by the arbitral tribunal to appear before it. 



2. The venue for the proceedings of the arbitral tribunal
shall be decided by mutual consent of the Parties, failing
which it shall alternate between the Parties with the first 
meeting of the arbitral tribunal proceedings to be held in
the capital of the Party complained against. 



3. The deliberations of the arbitral tribunal and the 
documents submitted to it shall be kept confidential. 



4. Notwithstanding paragraph 3, either Party may make
public statements as to its views regarding the dispute,
but shall treat as confidential, information and written
submissions submitted by the other Party to the arbitral
tribunal which that other Party has designated as
confidential. Where a Party has provided information or
written submissions designated as confidential, the other
Party may request a non-confidential summary of the
information or written submission which may be disclosed
publicly. The Party to which such a request is made may
agree to the request and submit such a summary, or refuse
the request without needing to ascribe any reasons or
justification. 



5. The Parties shall be given the opportunity to attend
any of the presentations, statements or rebuttals in the
proceedings. Any information or written submissions
submitted by a Party to the arbitral tribunal, including
any comments on the descriptive part of the draft award and
responses to questions put by the arbitral tribunal, shall
be made available to the other Party. 



6. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be drafted 
without the presence of the Parties. 



7. The arbitral tribunal shall, within 120 days, or
within 60 days in cases of urgency including those which
concern perishable goods, after the date of its
establishment, submit to the Parties its draft award,
including both the descriptive part and its findings and
conclusions, for the purposes of enabling the Parties to
review it. When the arbitral tribunal considers that it 
cannot submit its draft award within the aforementioned 120 
days or 60 days period, it may extend that period with the
consent of the Parties. However, in no case should the
period from the establishment of the arbitral tribunal to
the submission of the draft award to the Parties exceed 150 
days. Either Party may submit comments in writing to the
arbitral tribunal on the draft award within 30 days after
the date of submission of the draft award. 



8. The arbitral tribunal shall present its award to the
Parties within 45 days after the date of submission of the
draft award. 



9. The arbitral tribunal shall attempt to make its
decisions, including its award, by consensus, but may also
make its decisions, including its award, by majority vote. 



10. The award of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and 
binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.10" name="Termination Of The Proceedings" article_identifier="36911">The Parties may agree to terminate the proceedings of
the arbitral tribunal by jointly so notifying the chair of
the arbitral tribunal at any time before the issuance of
the award to the Parties, in which case the chair shall
terminate the proceedings of the arbitral tribunal without
delay.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.11" name="Implementation Of Award" article_identifier="36912">1. Unless the Parties otherwise agree, the Party
complained against shall promptly comply with the award of
the arbitral tribunal issued in accordance with Articles 


16.8 and 16.9. If this is not practicable, the Party
complained against shall comply with the award within a
reasonable period of time. 



2. The reasonable period of time referred to in paragraph
1 shall be mutually determined by the Parties, taking into
account, where appropriate, the suggested period of time
attached to the award by the arbitral tribunal. Where the
Parties fail to agree on the reasonable period of time
within 45 days after the date of issuance of the award of
the arbitral tribunal, either Party may refer the matter to
an arbitral tribunal, which shall determine the reasonable
period of time. 



3. 	(a) If the Party complained against considers it 
impracticable to comply with the award within the
reasonable period of time, the Party complained
against shall, no later than the expiry of that
period, enter into consultations with the
complaining Party, with a view to developing
mutually satisfactory compensation or any
alternative arrangement. 


(b) If no satisfactory compensation or any
alternative arrangement has been agreed within 30
days after the date of expiry of the reasonable
period of time, the complaining Party may suspend
the application to the Party complained against
of concessions or other obligations under this
Agreement, after giving notification of such
suspension 30 days in advance. 


4. If the complaining Party considers that the Party
complained against has failed to comply with the award
within the reasonable period of time and if the Party
complained against has not entered into consultations in
accordance with subparagraph 3(a), the complaining Party
may suspend the application to the Party complained against
of concessions or other obligations under this Agreement,
after giving notification of such suspension 30 days in
advance. 



5. The suspension of the application of concessions or
other obligations under paragraph 3 or 4 shall: 



(a) not be effected if, with respect to the dispute
to which the suspension relates, consultations or
proceedings before the arbitral tribunal are in
progress; 



(b) be temporary, and be discontinued when the
Parties reach a mutually satisfactory resolution
or where compliance with the award is effected; 



(c) 	be restricted to the same level of nullification 
or impairment that is attributable to the failure
to comply with the award; and 



(d) 	be restricted to the same sector or sectors to 
which the nullification or impairment relates,
unless it is not practicable or effective to
suspend the application of concessions or other
obligations in such sector or sectors. 


6. If the Party complained against considers that the
requirements for the suspension of the application of
concessions or other obligations under this Agreement by
the complaining Party set out in paragraph 3, 4 or 5 have
not been met, it may request consultations with the
complaining Party. The complaining Party shall enter into
consultations within 10 days after the date of receipt of
the request. If the Parties fail to resolve the matter
within 30 days after the date of receipt of the request for
consultations in accordance with this paragraph, the Party
complained against may refer the matter to an arbitral
tribunal, which then shall determine whether the said
requirements have been met. 



7. The arbitral tribunal that is established for the 
purposes of this Article shall, whenever possible, have as
its arbitrators, the arbitrators of the original arbitral
tribunal. If this is not possible, then the arbitrators to
the arbitral tribunal that is established for the purposes
of this Article shall be appointed in accordance with
paragraphs 2, 3 and 4 of Article 16.7. Unless the Parties
agree on a different period, the arbitral tribunal
established under this Article shall make its 
determinations within 60 days after the date when the
matter is referred to it. Such determinations shall be 
final and binding on the Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.12" name="Modification Of Time Periods" article_identifier="36913">Any time period provided for in this Chapter may be
modified for a particular dispute by mutual consent of the
Parties.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.13" name="Expenses" article_identifier="36914">Each Party shall bear the costs of the arbitrator
appointed by it and its representation in the proceedings
of the arbitral tribunal. The other costs of the arbitral 
tribunal shall be borne by the Parties in equal shares,
unless the Parties otherwise agree.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 16.14" name="Language" article_identifier="36915">All proceedings of the arbitral tribunal and all
documents and information submitted to the arbitral 
tribunal shall be in the English language.</article>
    </chapter>
    <chapter number="CHAPTER 17" name="Final Provisions" chapter_identifier="4258">
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.1" name="Table Of Contents And Headings" article_identifier="36916">The table of contents and headings of the Chapters,
Sections and Articles of this Agreement are inserted for
convenience of reference only and shall not affect the
interpretation of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.2" name="Annexes And Notes" article_identifier="36917">The Annexes and Notes to this Agreement shall form an
integral part of this Agreement.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.3" name="Amendment" article_identifier="36918">1. This Agreement may be amended by written agreement
between the Parties. 



2. Such amendment shall be approved by the Parties in
accordance with their respective legal procedures, and
shall enter into force on the date to be agreed upon by the
Parties and by means of diplomatic notes exchanged between
the Governments of the Parties informing each other that
their respective legal procedures necessary for its entry
into force have been completed. 



3. Notwithstanding paragraph 2, amendments related only
to the following may be made by diplomatic notes exchanged
between the Governments of the Parties: 



(a) Annex 1, provided that the amendments are made in
accordance with the amendment of the Harmonized 
System, and include no change on the rates of
customs duty to be applied by a Party to the
originating goods of the other Party in
accordance with Annex 1; 



(b) Annex 2; and 



(c) Annex 3.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.4" name="Entry Into Force" article_identifier="36919">This Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth
day after the date on which the Governments of the Parties
exchange diplomatic notes informing each other that their
respective legal procedures necessary for entry into force
of this Agreement have been completed. It shall remain in
force unless terminated as provided for in Article 17.5.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.5" name="Termination" article_identifier="36920">Either Party may terminate this Agreement by giving
one year’s advance notice in writing through the diplomatic
channel to the other Party.</article>
      <article number="ARTICLE 17.6" name="Authentic Texts" article_identifier="36921">1. The texts of this Agreement in the Japanese, Mongolian
and English languages shall be equally authentic. 



2. Notwithstanding paragraph 1: 



(a) (i) 	Part 2 of Annex 1 is in the Japanese and 
English languages, such texts being equally
authentic; and 


(ii) 	Part 3 of Annex 1 is in the Mongolian and 
English languages, such texts being equally
authentic; 


(b) (i) 	Part 1A and Part 2 of Annex 6 are in the 
Japanese and English languages, such texts
being equally authentic; and 


(ii) 	Part 1B of Annex 6 is in the Mongolian and 
English languages, such texts being equally
authentic; 


(c) (i) 	Part 1 of Annex 7 is in the Japanese and 
English languages, such texts being equally
authentic; and 


(ii) 	Part 2 of Annex 7 is in the Mongolian and 
English languages, such texts being equally
authentic; and 


(d) (i) 	Part 1 of Annex 8 and Part 1 of Annex 9 are 
in the Japanese and English languages, such
texts being equally authentic; and 

(ii) 	Part 2 of Annex 8 and Part 2 of Annex 9 are 
in the Mongolian and English languages, such
texts being equally authentic. 


3. In the event of any divergence among the texts, the
English text shall prevail. 

IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly 
authorized by their respective Governments, have signed
this Agreement. 


DONE at Tokyo on this tenth day of February in the
year 2015 in duplicate in the Japanese, Mongolian and
English languages. 


 

For Japan: 	For Mongolia: 


Ᏻಸ᫴୕Chimed Saikhanbileg</article>
    </chapter>
  </body>
</treaty>
